<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4358973</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25768726</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119438</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-48318</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Favorable Alleles for Stem Water-Soluble Carbohydrates Identified by Association Analysis Contribute to Grain Weight under Drought Stress Conditions in Wheat</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">WSC Enhances Grain Weight under Drought Stress Conditions</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Weiyu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Bin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Runzhi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chang</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaoping</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jing</surname>
            <given-names>Ruilian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff001">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>National Key Facility for Crop Gene Resources and Genetic Improvement / Institute of Crop Science, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing 100081, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff002">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Agronomy College, Shanxi Agricultural University, Taigu 030801, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Guangxiao</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Academic Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Huazhong University of Science &amp; Technology(HUST), CHINA</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: RJ RL. Performed the experiments: WL BZ XC. Analyzed the data: BZ WL. Wrote the paper: BZ RJ.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>jingrl@caas.net.cn</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <elocation-id>e0119438</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Li et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0119438.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Drought is a major environmental constraint to crop distribution and productivity. Stem water-soluble carbohydrates (WSC) buffer wheat grain yield against conditions unfavorable for photosynthesis during the grain filling stage. In this study, 262 winter wheat accessions and 209 genome-wide SSR markers were collected and used to undertake association analysis based on a mixed linear model (MLM). The WSC in different internodes at three growth stages and 1000-grain weight (TGW) were investigated under four environmental regimes (well-watered, drought stress during the whole growth period, and two levels of terminal drought stress imposed by chemical desiccation under the well-watered and drought stress during the whole growth period conditions). Under diverse drought stress conditions, WSC in lower internodes showed significant positive correlations with TGW, especially at the flowering stage under well-watered conditions and at grain filling under drought stress. Sixteen novel WSC-favorable alleles were identified, and five of them contributed to significantly higher TGW. In addition, pyramiding WSC favorable alleles was not only effective for obtaining accessions with higher WSC, but also for enhancing TGW under different water regimes. During the past fifty years of wheat breeding, WSC was selected incidentally. The average number of favorable WSC alleles increased from 1.13 in the pre-1960 period to 4.41 in the post-2000 period. The results indicate a high potential for using marker-assisted selection to pyramid WSC favorable alleles in improving WSC and TGW in wheat.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This study was supported by the National High-tech R&amp;D Program (2011AA100501), and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31271720). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="7"/>
        <table-count count="3"/>
        <page-count count="15"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta id="data-availability">
          <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
          <meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability</title>
      <p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Drought, defined as water deficit, is one of the major environmental factors determining crop distribution and productivity. Plants exposed to drought undergo dramatic losses in productivity if they are not adapted to cope with such conditions [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) is one of the most important crops in the world and any loss of yield has serious consequences, both locally and worldwide. For dryland wheat grown in arid and semiarid areas, such as the semi-arid regions of northwest China and the Mediterranean region, low and erratic rainfall can greatly reduce grain yield and yield stability [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Terminal drought stress from unrelieved water deficit that may occur during and after flowering impairs photosynthesis, enhances plant senescence and influences the duration of grain filling [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Understanding plant tolerance to drought is therefore of fundamental importance and forms one of the major research topics in agronomy [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p>
      <p>It was suggested that yield should be taken as an important index of crop drought resistance [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Water-soluble carbohydrates (WSC; composed mainly of fructans, sucrose, glucose, and fructose, with the main reserve as fructans at the late stages of WSC accumulation) deposited in wheat stems are important carbon sources for grain filling [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Moreover, fructans can act as compatible solutes in cells under osmotic stress [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Stem water-soluble carbohydrates (WSC) can be an important contributor to buffer grain yields against unfavorable conditions for photosynthesis during grain-filling period [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Mobilization of WSC during grain filling can potentially contribute about 20% of the final grain weight under non-stress conditions, and up to 70% or more of grain dry matter under drought stress in wheat [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The amount of WSC accumulation and remobilization reportedly differs between internodes [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p>
      <p>WSC, which mainly occurs as fructans, increased in response to water deficit, and WSC were higher in drought tolerant genotypes than those in sensitive ones [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Grains of sensitive cultivars reached maturity much earlier than tolerant ones under both control and stress conditions [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Therefore, it may be concluded that drought tolerant wheat cultivars have a high capability of WSC accumulation, coupled with higher mobilization efficiency, stronger sink activity and longer duration of grain filling. The ability to store and remobilize large amounts of WSC to grain has been suggested as a selection criterion for wheat breeding due to its high heritability and positive linear relationship with grain yield [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. However, unpredictable water deficits from year to year make reliable selection difficult in dryland breeding programs. Nicolas and Turner [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] developed a technique, involving use of a leaf spray of potassium iodide as a mild treatment on wheat for revealing genotypic differences in the absence of photosynthesis under terminal stress (post-anthesis stress) in wheat. Blum [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and Regan et al. [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] found a highly significant relationship between the rates of grain weight reduction caused by chemical desiccation and by drought stress. In wheat breeding, chemical desiccation can be used to assess advanced lines or used in mass selection.</p>
      <p>Studies on WSC QTL have been reported in rice [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], wheat [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], maize [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], barley [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and perennial ryegrass [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. QTL studies using three wheat mapping populations showed that WSC accumulation was controlled by many genes, and plays an important role in assuring stable yield and grain size [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. With the rapid increases in number of molecular markers, association analysis has become an important tool for dissection of complex traits [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. It makes full use of existing diversity and provides a high-resolution platform for mapping QTL [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In wheat, loci influencing various traits, such as stem rust resistance, plant height and grain weight, were identified by association analysis [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p>
      <p>A few loci for WSC were reported through association analysis. In previous research on WSC in genetic populations most attention was given to whole stem WSC. However, such work did not provide sufficient information on the genetics of WSC, because 1) WSC in different internodes responds differently to drought; and 2) family-based genetic populations possess limited favorable alleles because they are derived from two parents. In the present study, a diverse population of 262 winter wheat accessions was tested with 209 SSR markers distributed on all 21 chromosomes by association analysis aimed at gaining further genetic insight into the genetic mechanism of WSC under various drought treatments. We investigated WSC in different internodes at three growth stages and 1000-grain weight (TGW) at two growth stages in four environments (well-watered, drought stress during the whole growth period, and two levels of terminal drought stress imposed by chemical desiccation under the well-watered and drought stress during the whole growth period conditions). Our objectives were to: 1) further describe the effect of various drought conditions on WSC in different internodes; 2) assess the relationship between WSC and TGW at three growth stages; 3) identify elite alleles significantly associated with WSC under various drought conditions; and 4) confirm the close genetic relationships between WSC and TGW.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="sec003">
        <title>Ethics Statement</title>
        <p>Two locations, Changping (116&#xB0;13&#xB4;E; 40&#xB0;13&#xB4;N) and Shunyi (116&#xB0;56&#xB4;E; 40&#xB0;23&#xB4;N) in Beijing, are the experiment stations of the Institute of Crop Science, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences. We have obtained the relevant permission for our field studies for growing our plant materials in the field from the corresponding institutions. There was no specific permissions required for these locations/activities. Our field studies did not involve endangered or protected species.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec004">
        <title>Plant materials and field experiments</title>
        <p>A total of 262 common wheat accessions collected as a diverse population for this research (<xref rid="pone.0119438.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). Of them, 254 were from China, 3 from USA, 2 from Australia, 2 from Italy, and 1 from Romania. The cultivars from China were mainly planted in the Northern Winter Wheat Zone, and Yellow and Huai River Valleys Facultative Wheat Zone [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The population was sown in Changping, Beijing (116&#xB0;13&#xB4;E; 40&#xB0;13&#xB4;N), at the beginning of October 2010 and harvested in mid-June 2011. The experimental unit was a 2 m four-row plot, with 30 cm between the rows. Forty seeds were planted per row. The field was managed under separate rain-fed (drought stress, CK-DS) and well-watered (CK-WW) conditions. The rainfall from sowing to harvest was 131 mm. The WW treatment was watered with 750 m<sup>3</sup>/ha (75 mm) at the pre-overwintering, booting, flowering and grain filling stages, respectively. The 0.8% chemical desiccant KI (Potassium Iodide, AR, Sinopharm Chemical Reagent Co., Ltd) was sprayed on the leaves of each plot separately at the third day after flowering to simulate the terminal drought stress [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. There were four water regimes including well-watered as a control (CK-WW), drought stress during the whole growth period (CK-DS) and two levels of terminal drought stress imposed under the well-watered and drought stress during the whole growth period conditions (KI-WW; KI-DS).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec005">
        <title>Phenotyping of WSC and TGW</title>
        <p>Methods of collecting data on stem water-soluble carbohydrates (WSC)-related and TGW were reported earlier [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. For each accession under the four water regimes, five main stems with the same heading date were selected as samples. The main stem was cut from the soil surface at three morphological stages, viz., flowering, mid-grain filling (14 days after flowering, DAF), and maturity. Leaf blades were removed, and the stems with leaf sheaths were cut into three parts, the upmost internode (peduncle, Ped), the lower internode (the remainder segments of stem except for peduncle, Low) and the spike. Stem samples for each accession were chipped into 2&#x2013;5 mm lengths. The WSC of the three sections, i.e. peduncle, the lower internode and whole stem (Ste), were determined by different near-infrared reflectance spectroscopy (NIRS) regression models, which were developed for quantitative determination of WSC using modeling samples of 150 DH (Hanxuan 10 &#xD7; Lumai 14) lines [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Briefly, at the first step, partial least square regression models for predicting WSC in the target parts of wheat were developed using selected wavelength regions, spectroscopic pretreatments and the latent variables included in each model. The total amounts of WSC (mg WSC / g dry weight, mg / g dw) in each modeling sample of 150 DH lines were also measured by chemical assay (anthrone colorimetric assay), and used for the cross validation. The NIRS regression models were highly accurate in determination of the true values of WSC measured by chemical assay in the wheat organs tested, according to high coefficients of determination (R<sup>2</sup> &gt;0.992) and low root mean square errors of prediction (RMSEP &lt;0.228). An additional 40 samples per model (i.e. not included in the modeling samples) were used to verify the accuracy of outer predictions of models. Paired <italic>t</italic>-tests were also conducted using the outer samples to assess the models. The results showed the high accuracy of the models in predicting WSC. We obtained WSC at the flowering (WSCF), mid-grain filling (WSCG), and maturity (WSCM) stages.</p>
        <p>Spikes corresponding to main stem samples were collected at the mid-grain filling and maturity stages for each accession to obtain 1000-grain weight (TGWG, TGWM). The grain-filling efficiency (GFE, %) at an early period (before 14 DAF) and a late period (from 14 DAF prior to maturity) were assessed by [TGWG / TGWM] &#xD7; 100% and [(TGWM &#x2212; TGWG) / TGWM] &#xD7; 100%, respectively [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec006">
        <title>SSR genotyping and association mapping</title>
        <p>Two hundred and nine SSR markers, evenly spaced along the 21 wheat chromosomes, were selected for evaluating population structure, relative kinship, and association mapping. The genetic positions of these SSR markers were from the consensus map Ta-SSR-2004 [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and the Komugi wheat genetic resources database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp/wheat/komugi&#x200B;/top/top.jsp">http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp/wheat/komugi&#x200B;/top/top.jsp</ext-link>). Molecular data were obtained by a fluorescence detection system [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Amplification products were separated on an ABI3730 DNA Analyzer, and fragment sizes were calculated by GeneMapper software (Applied Biosystems).</p>
        <p>Allele number, allele frequency and polymorphism information content (PIC) were calculated by PowerMarker V3.25 (Lui and Muse, 2005). Population structure was estimated by STRUCTURE v2.3.2 using data from 209 SSR markers. Ten subpopulations (<italic>k</italic> = 1 to 10) were set with a burn-in period of 50,000 iterations and a run of 500,000 replications of Markov Chain Monte Carlo after burn in. The &#x25B3;<italic>k</italic> method was applied according to LnP(D) in the STRUCTURE, and the output and result were estimated [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The <italic>Q</italic> data of five replicate runs were integrated by CLUMPP software [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Principal coordinate analysis based on genetic distances was also used to confirm the results of STRUCTURE by NTSYSpc analysis [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The relative kinship coefficient (<italic>K</italic>) was calculated by the SPAGeDi software package [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Finally, the <italic>Q</italic> + <italic>K</italic> models were performed using mixed linear model (MLM) in tassel V2.1 for association of WSC and TGW [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="sec007">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="sec008">
        <title>Trait variation</title>
        <p>A total of 262 common wheat accessions with similar flowering time were collected as a diverse population for our research. The average values of 262 wheat accessions for WSC, TGW and grain-filling efficiency (GFE) were presented in <xref rid="pone.0119438.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0119438.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref> Tables, <xref rid="pone.0119438.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0119438.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>. There was considerable phenotypic variability for WSC and TGW in the natural population with coefficients of variation (<italic>CV</italic>) ranging from 16.11 to 50.51% and from 14.65 to 43.64%, respectively. The WSC at the mid-grain filling were higher than those at flowering and maturity stages. Before maturity, the WSC was overall much higher in lower internodes than that in the peduncles in every water regime (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0119438.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0119438.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119438.g001</object-id>
          <label>Fig 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Stem water-soluble carbohydrates (WSC, mg / g dw) of 262 winter wheat accessions in different internodes at three growth stages under well-watered and drought stress environments.</title>
            <p>Bars indicate 2&#xD7;SE. CK-DS-Ped, peduncle under drought stress; CK-DS-Low, lower internode, drought stressed; CK-DS-Ste, whole stem, drought stressed; CK-WW-Ped, peduncle, well-watered; CK-WW-Low, lower internode, well-watered; CK-WW-Ste, whole stem, well-watered; KI-DS-Ped, peduncle treated with KI, drought stressed; KI-DS-Low, lower internode treated with KI, drought stressed; KI-DS-Ste, whole stem treated with KI, drought stressed; KI-WW-Ped, peduncle treated with KI, well-watered; KI-WW-Low, lower internode treated with KI, well-watered; KI-WW-Ste, whole stem treated with KI, well-watered.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0119438.g001"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone.0119438.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119438.g002</object-id>
          <label>Fig 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>1000-grain weight (TGW, a) and grain-filling efficiency (GFE, b) based on 262 winter wheat accessions.</title>
            <p>Bars indicate 2&#xD7;SE.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0119438.g002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec009">
        <title>Correlations between WSC and TGW</title>
        <p>Pearson correlation coefficients were calculated to further understand the relationships between WSC of internodes and TGW under diverse water regimes. There were significant correlations between WSC and TGW at flowering and mid-grain filling stages. Compared to WSC in the peduncle, a higher correlation existed between WSC in lower internodes and TGW (data not presented). Under diverse drought stress, WSC of lower internodes at the mid-grain filling (WSCG) showed significant correlations with TGW at the mid-grain filling (r = 0.313*** and 0.302*** under CK-DS and KI-DS) and those at maturity (0.358***, 0.382*** and 0.257** under CK-DS, KI-DS and KI-WW) (<xref rid="pone.0119438.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). However, under well-watered condition (CK-WW), a significant positive correlation (r = 0.197**) between WSC of the lower internode and TGW at maturity was detected at the flowering stage, but there were no significant correlations at other growth stages (<xref rid="pone.0119438.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0119438.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119438.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Pearson correlation coefficients of WSC of lower internodes and TGW under various water conditions.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0119438.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0119438.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">WSC</th>
                  <th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">1000-grain weight (TGW)</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK-DS</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK-WW</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KI-DS</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KI-WW</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSCF</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.249<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref>/0.216<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058/0.197<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.113/0.157<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105/0.028</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSCG</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.313<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref>/0.358<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045/0.085</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.302<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref>/0.382<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127/0.257<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSCM</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088/0.054</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010/0.057</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.126<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>/-0.157<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.034/0.065</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t001fn001">
              <p>* Significant at <italic>P</italic> = 0.05</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn002">
              <p>** Significant at <italic>P</italic> = 0.01</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn003">
              <p>*** Significant at <italic>P</italic> = 0.001. Numbers at the left of the &#x201C;/&#x201D; were 1000-grain weight measured at the mid-grain filling and those at the right were measured at maturity. WSCF, stem water-soluble carbohydrates at flowering; WSCG, stem water-soluble carbohydrates at the mid-grain-filling; WSCM, stem water-soluble carbohydrates at maturity; CK-DS, drought stress condition; CK-WW, well-watered condition; KI-DS, treated with KI (potassium iodide) under drought stress condition; KI-WW, treated with KI under well-watered condition.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec010">
        <title>Allelic diversity and population structure</title>
        <p>A total of 2,748 alleles were identified at the 209 SSR loci in our population (262 accessions), an average of 13/locus. The average percentage of missing data for all markers and genotypes was 3.36%. The polymorphism information content (PIC) of the SSR loci ranged from 0.0175 to 0.932 with an average of 0.619. Population structure was assessed by STRUCTURE v2.3.2 using all markers. The most significant change of the LnP(D) value was observed at <italic>k</italic> = 2, and there was also a sharp peak of &#x25B3;<italic>k</italic>, indicating that <italic>k</italic> = 2 was the best separator (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). This was further supported by principal coordinate analysis based on Nei&#x2019;s genetic distances [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The top two principal components clearly separated the 262 wheat accessions into two sub-populations, comprising 126 and 136 accessions, respectively, and agreeing the with the STRUCTURE analysis (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0119438.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119438.g003</object-id>
          <label>Fig 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Population structure analysis of 262 wheat accessions based on 209 SSR markers.</title>
            <p>(A) Estimated LnP(D) and &#x25B3;<italic>k</italic> over five repeats of STRUCTURE analysis; (B) Two sub-populations inferred by structure analysis. Each of the 262 individuals is represented by a vertical line and different colors indicate different sub-populations. Asterisk in (A) indicates the point of the most significant change in the LnP(D) value.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0119438.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone.0119438.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119438.g004</object-id>
          <label>Fig 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Principal coordinate analysis of 262 wheat accessions based on 209 SSR markers reveals two sub-populations.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0119438.g004"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec011">
        <title>Association studies for WSC and TGW</title>
        <p>According to the correlation results, WSC of the lower internode (WSCF under CK-WW, WSCG under CK-DS, KI-WW and KI-DS) and TGW at maturity under four water regimes were used for association mapping. Moreover, WSC of the whole stem were also included to further identify associated loci. A mixed linear model (MLM) was used; it accounted for population structure (<italic>Q</italic>) and unequal relatedness among individuals (<italic>K</italic> matrix) [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Thirty-three novel loci were significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01) associated with WSC (<xref rid="pone.0119438.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Table</xref>). Sixteen loci were significantly associated with TGW at maturity (<xref rid="pone.0119438.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5 Table</xref>). In regard to WSC, <italic>Xgwm186&#x2013;5A</italic> was detected under both KI-WW and KI-DS; <italic>Xgwm413&#x2013;1B</italic>, <italic>Xbarc324&#x2013;3A</italic>, <italic>Xgwm566&#x2013;3B</italic> and <italic>Xbarc175&#x2013;6D</italic> were associated with both WSC in lower internodes and in the whole stems under KI-DS, CK-DS, CK-DS and CK-WW, respectively (<xref rid="pone.0119438.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Table</xref>). <italic>Xbarc24&#x2013;6B</italic>, near QTL <italic>QWSCm</italic>.<italic>cgb-6B</italic>.<italic>1</italic> (flanking marker region: <italic>Xgwm219</italic>&#x2013;<italic>Xwmc341</italic>) controlling WSC was also detected in a DH population [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In Ta-SSR-2004 [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], the genetic distance between <italic>Xbarc24&#x2013;6B</italic> and <italic>Xgwm219&#x2013;6B</italic> is 4 cM. <italic>Xbarc324&#x2013;3A</italic> and <italic>Xgwm361&#x2013;6B</italic> were simultaneously associated with both WSC and TGW under CK-DS and KI-DS, respectively. These results provided further genetic insight into the significant correlations between WSC and TGW.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec012">
        <title>Favorable WSC alleles enhance TGW under diverse water conditions</title>
        <p>For each locus associated with WSC, differences in WSC between accessions with the favorable allele and those carrying other alleles were estimated by ANOVA (SAS 8.01). Sixteen of the 33 associated loci had significant favorable allelic effect; that is, the difference between the favorable allele and others was significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05). There were 4, 3, 7 and 2 favorable alleles under CK-DS, CK-WW, KI-DS and KI-WW, respectively (<xref rid="pone.0119438.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). <italic>Xgwm566&#x2013;3B</italic><sub><italic>124</italic></sub> was simultaneously associated with both WSCG-Low and WSCG-Ste under CK-DS. Moreover, the WSC of accessions combining larger numbers of favorable alleles were higher than those with lower numbers of favorable alleles, showing that the accumulation of favorable alleles leads to better phenotypes (<xref rid="pone.0119438.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0119438.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119438.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Phenotypic values of favorable marker alleles significantly associated with WSC.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0119438.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0119438.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water regime</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trait</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locus</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Favorable allele (bp)</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Freq. (%)</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#xB1; SE (mg / g dw)</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK-DS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSCG-Low</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xgwm403&#x2013;1B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.76</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">277.3 &#xB1; 9.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.24</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230.3 &#xB1; 2.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xgwm566&#x2013;3B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.82</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256.4 &#xB1; 7.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0045<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.18</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">231.1 &#xB1; 2.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSCG-Ste</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xbarc181&#x2013;1B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>187</underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.75</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223.6 &#xB1; 4.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0027<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.25</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208.6 &#xB1; 4.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xgwm566&#x2013;3B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.82</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233.2 &#xB1; 7.0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0069<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.18</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210.8 &#xB1; 2.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xgwm537&#x2013;7B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.76</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">231.9 &#xB1; 8.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0321<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.24</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211.4 &#xB1; 2.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK-WW</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSCF-Low</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xgwm358&#x2013;5D</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>162</underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.72</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.7 &#xB1; 5.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.28</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.9 &#xB1; 2.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xgwm131&#x2013;7B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 and 118</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.64</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.5 &#xB1; 8.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0004<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.36</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.3 &#xB1; 2.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSCF-Ste</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xgwm148&#x2013;2B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>165</underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.02</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.9 &#xB1; 4.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.98</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.9 &#xB1; 2.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KI-DS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSCG-Low</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xgwm259&#x2013;1B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225.4 &#xB1; 8.8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206.6 &#xB1; 3.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xgwm261&#x2013;2D</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>203</underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232.3 &#xB1; 7.8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0493<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.65</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207.3 &#xB1; 3.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xbarc314&#x2013;3A</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">257</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221.1 &#xB1; 3.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.87</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191.2 &#xB1; 5.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xcfd23&#x2013;4D</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.51</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214.2 &#xB1; 3.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0288<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.49</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200.3 &#xB1; 5.8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSCG-Ste</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xgwm374&#x2013;2B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">217</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.91</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209.6 &#xB1; 6.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0138<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.09</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188.2 &#xB1; 2.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xgwm149&#x2013;4B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>153</underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.92</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197.8 &#xB1; 2.8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.81</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178.7 &#xB1; 4.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xbarc216&#x2013;5B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.24</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204.9 &#xB1; 4.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0024<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.76</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186.4 &#xB1; 2.8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KI-WW</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSCG-Low</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xbarc176&#x2013;7B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">282</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.67</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.7 &#xB1; 9.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0003<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.33</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.5 &#xB1; 2.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSCF-Ste</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xgwm186&#x2013;5A</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.52</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124.6 &#xB1; 8.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0042<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x3000;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x3000;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>&#x3000;</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.48</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.9 &#xB1; 3.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x3000;</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t002fn001">
              <p><italic>P</italic> values are for comparison between phenotypic values of favorable allele and others.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t002fn002">
              <p>*, **, *** indicate significance at <italic>P</italic> = 0.05, 0.01 and 0.001, respectively. Underlined values indicate that lines with the single favorable WSC allele produced significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) higher TGW at maturity than accessions with other alleles.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0119438.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119438.t003</object-id>
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Pyramiding of favorable WSC alleles enhanced WSC and TGW under various water conditions.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0119438.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0119438.t003"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water condition</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Favorable allele</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of alleles</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (%)</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSC Mean &#xB1; SE (mg / g dw)</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGW Mean &#xB1; SE (g)</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK-DS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2265;2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.98</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">258.0&#xB1;6.4(a)<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>1</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.75&#xB1;1.02(a) <xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>1</sup></xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.90</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247.0&#xB1;4.5(a)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.17&#xB1;0.72(ab)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222.6&#xB1;2.8(b)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.21&#xB1;0.49(b)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK-WW</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2265;2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108.6&#xB1;6.2(a)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.28&#xB1;1.01(a)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.2&#xB1;4.5(b)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.62&#xB1;0.62(a)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.2&#xB1;3.0(b)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.73&#xB1;0.53(b)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KI-DS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2265;3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226.7&#xB1;3.8(a)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.00&#xB1;0.57(a)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209.1&#xB1;5.0(b)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.46&#xB1;0.93(ab)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2264;1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181.6&#xB1;6.8(c)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.61&#xB1;0.91(b)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KI-WW</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2265;1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.6&#xB1;7.4(a)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.54&#xB1;1.24(a)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108.0&#xB1;2.4(b)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.15&#xB1;0.60(a)</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t003fn001">
              <p><sup>1</sup> Values with different letters in columns are significantly different (P &lt;0.05).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>In accordance with the significant positive correlations between WSC and TGW, the TGW of accessions carrying favorable WSC alleles were overall much higher than those of others. Only five of the 16 favorable WSC alleles, individually contributed to significantly higher TGW; they were <italic>Xbarc181&#x2013;1B</italic><sub><italic>187</italic></sub>, <italic>Xgwm148&#x2013;2B</italic><sub><italic>165</italic></sub>, <italic>Xgwm261&#x2013;2D</italic><sub><italic>203</italic></sub>, <italic>Xgwm149&#x2013;4B</italic><sub><italic>153</italic></sub> and <italic>Xgwm358&#x2013;5D</italic><sub><italic>162</italic></sub> (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). We also analyzed the TGW of accessions containing different numbers of favorable WSC alleles under diverse water conditions (CK-WW, CK-DS, KI-WW, KI-DS, <xref rid="pone.0119438.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Under CK-DS, accessions combining more than two favorable WSC alleles had significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05) higher TGW (43.75 g) than those without favorable alleles (41.21 g). Except for KI-WW, the pyramiding of favorable WSC alleles was also effective under CK-WW and KI-DS. There were only 4 accessions carrying 2 favorable alleles where significant differences under KI-WW were not detected.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0119438.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119438.g005</object-id>
          <label>Fig 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Single WSC favorable allele contributed to significantly higher 1000-grain weight (TGW).</title>
            <p>Bars indicate 2&#xD7;SE. WSC corresponding to <italic>Xbarc181&#x2013;1B</italic>, <italic>Xgwm261&#x2013;2D</italic> and <italic>Xgwm149&#x2013;4B</italic> represent WSC at the mid-grain filling under CK-DS, KI-DS and KI-DS, respectively; WSC corresponding to <italic>Xgwm148&#x2013;2B</italic> and <italic>Xgwm358&#x2013;5D</italic> represent WSC at flowering under CK-WW. TGW was measured at maturity. *, ** indicate significance at <italic>P</italic> = 0.05 and <italic>P</italic> = 0.01, respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0119438.g005"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec013">
        <title>WSC was selected with TGW during the past fifty years of wheat breeding</title>
        <p>WSC in lower internodes increased from means of 34.3, 206.6, 101.9, 146.6 before 1960 (pre-1960) to 90.7, 247.2, 118.9, 230.1 after 2000 (post-2000) under CK-WW, CK-DS, KI-WW, KI-DS, respectively; the trend for WSC of whole stems was the same (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0119438.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6 Table</xref>). Overall, the TGW and WSC of modern varieties gradually increased from pre-1960 to post-2000 under all four water regimes (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0119438.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119438.g006</object-id>
          <label>Fig 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>TGW and WSC of modern varieties from different decades under four water regimes.</title>
            <p>Pre-1960, before 1960; Post-2000, after 2000; There were 8, 27, 54, 39, 58 and 51 accessions released in Pre-1960, during the 1960s, 1970s, 1980s, 1990s, and Post-2000, respectively. Ten landraces and 15 accessions with unknown released decades were excluded. Bars indicate 2&#xD7;SE.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0119438.g006"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Breeding leaves a strong footprint at the genome level [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. A number of important genes (alleles) were positively selected, as implicated by changes in numbers and frequency [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. We estimated the accumulation and frequency distribution of 16 favorable alleles identified in our research in modern varieties from different decades. The average number of favorable WSC alleles increased from 1.13 in the pre-1960 period to 4.41 in the post-2000 period (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7A</xref>). Most modern varieties carried one or two favorable alleles before 1970, whereas modern varieties after 1990 have as many as eight favorable alleles (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7B</xref>). The obvious positive selection of the 16 favorable alleles identified here proves their value in breeding programs over past decades. However, compared with the 16 favorable alleles, the average number (4.41) in post-2000 varieties is relatively lower and indicates considerable potential for further improvement.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0119438.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0119438.g007</object-id>
          <label>Fig 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Accumulation (A) and frequency distribution (B) of 16 favorable alleles in modern varieties from different decades.</title>
            <p>Bars indicate 2&#xD7;SE.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0119438.g007"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec014">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="sec015">
        <title>Drought stress induces higher remobilization efficiency of stem water-soluble carbohydrates</title>
        <p>Extensive studies have demonstrated that remobilization of stem water-soluble carbohydrates to grain in wheat require initiation of whole-plant senescence [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. While drought stress induces early senescence by increasing abscisic acid (ABA) and reducing cytokinins in wheat and rice, it also leads to more and faster remobilization of stem water-soluble carbohydrates from vegetative tissues to the grains and increases the grain filling rate, but shortens the grain filling period [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. In this study, 1000-grain weight and grain-filling efficiency under drought stress conditions was clearly higher compared to those under well-watered condition during the early grain filling period (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). However, the remobilization efficiency of stem water-soluble carbohydrates was not sufficient to compensate for the reduction in grain filling period during most kinds of drought conditions [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The final values of TGW and grain-filling efficiency in our study were still lower under drought stress conditions than those under well-watered conditions (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). However, 1000-grain weight at maturity under well-watered condition is only slightly higher than that those under drought stress conditions. The reasons for this may be (1) early drought stress decreases tiller number, and (2) water deficit at grain filling induces carbon mobilization from tillers to the main stem ear [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]; therefore, the limited photosynthetic products are almost enough to ensure a good performance for grains of the main stem ear. Furthermore, grain size is greatly decreased by terminal drought [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. TGW were drastically lower compared to materials not sprayed with desiccant (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0119438.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec016">
        <title>Genetic basis of the relationship between stem water-soluble carbohydrates in lower internodes and TGW under various drought stress conditions</title>
        <p>Under various drought stress conditions, stem water-soluble carbohydrates are destined to have an inseparable relationship with drought stress, and are recognized as an important source for grain filling when current photosynthesis is inhibited by drought stress. It was also reported that accumulation and remobilization efficiencies of stem water-soluble carbohydrates differed between internodes, and that each internode responds differently to drought [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. We found that the stem water-soluble carbohydrate in lower internodes were higher than those in peduncles (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Under diverse drought stress conditions, stem water-soluble carbohydrates in lower internodes had extremely significant correlations with TGW, especially at flowering under well-watered conditions and at the mid-grain filling under drought stress (<xref rid="pone.0119438.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Thus, lower internodes should have sufficient length to store enough stem water-soluble carbohydrates and become a major source during the grain filling period [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec017">
        <title>Pyramiding favorable alleles for stem water-soluble carbohydrates are effective for high and stable yield under various water conditions</title>
        <p>Stem water-soluble carbohydrate in drought tolerant cultivars were observed to be higher than that in sensitive genotypes, both under control and stress conditions [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Among the 16 favorable alleles for stem water-soluble carbohydrates, five loci individually contributed to significantly higher 1000-grain weight (<xref rid="pone.0119438.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0119438.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Pyramiding of favorable alleles for accumulation efficiency led to higher stem water-soluble carbohydrates and higher 1000-grain weight (<xref rid="pone.0119438.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Because stem water-soluble carbohydrate and TGW are quantitative traits, individual loci among the numerous candidate genes are usually powerless to reveal the genetic basis and molecular relationships that underpin such complex traits. Perhaps this is the reason why only five of the 16 associated loci showed significant relationships between stem water-soluble carbohydrates and TGW. Our results indicated that 1) stem water-soluble carbohydrates can make a positive contribution to 1000-grain weight under variable water conditions; 2) pyramiding target favorable alleles is not only effective for obtaining genotypes with higher stem water-soluble carbohydrates, but also is effective for enhancing 1000-grain weight under drought conditions; and 3) the molecular relationships between stem water-soluble carbohydrates and 1000-grain weight are so complex that most of the single marker loci do not make measurable contributions. Our previous research identified seven novel favorable WSC alleles which exhibited positive individual contributions to 1000-grain weight, and were verified under 16 environments, including drought and heat stresses [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Among them, <italic>Xgwm358&#x2013;5D</italic> (162 bp) is a common favorable WSC allele identified in the present research.</p>
        <p>During the past 50 years, consistent gains in grain yield were made by empirical breeding. Stem water-soluble carbohydrates, as an important drought-tolerant related trait, was selected incidentally (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). Moreover, trait-based selection inevitably pyramided some of the 16 favorable alleles identified in our research (<xref rid="pone.0119438.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). In the absence of epistasis, it should be possible to generate genotypes with higher numbers of favorable alleles and hence with the capability of higher WSC storage [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Scientists consider that significant increases in stem water-soluble carbohydrates have contributed to the recent genetic gains in grain yield in wheat [<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0119438.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. High stem water-soluble carbohydrates has already been suggested as a criterion for wheat breeding under drought stress. With marker-assisted selection, accumulation of favorable alleles for water-soluble carbohydrates should play an important role in future wheat breeding programs.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec018">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0119438.s001">
        <label>S1 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>The 262 accessions and their origins.</title>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0119438.s001.xlsx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0119438.s002">
        <label>S2 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Statistical data for WSC in different internodes under various water conditions.</title>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0119438.s002.xlsx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0119438.s003">
        <label>S3 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Statistical data for 1000-grain weight (TGW) under various water conditions.</title>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0119438.s003.xlsx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0119438.s004">
        <label>S4 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Thirty-three loci significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01) associated with WSC.</title>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0119438.s004.xlsx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0119438.s005">
        <label>S5 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>SSR markers significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01) associated with TGW.</title>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0119438.s005.xlsx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0119438.s006">
        <label>S6 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Statistical data for WSC and TGW under four water regimes.</title>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0119438.s006.xlsx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Professor Robert A. McIntosh (Plant Breeding Institute, University of Sydney, NSW, Australia) for suggestions on the manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref001">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sunkar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Drought and salt tolerance in plants</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Plant Sci</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref002">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effects of drought on the yield and physiological characteristics of winter wheat during later growth stage</article-title>. <source>Chin J Soil Sci</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>908</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>912</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref003">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rosenow DT, Clark LE. Drought tolerance in sorghum. In &#x2018;Proceedings of the 36th annual corn and sorghum industry research conference, Chicago, IL&#x2019; (Eds HD Loden, D Wilkinson); 1981. pp. 18&#x2013;30.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref004">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Homayoun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Remobilization of stem reserves in wheat genotypes under normal and drought stress conditions</article-title>. <source>Adv Environ Biol</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1721</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1724</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref005">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Present situation and approach of study on crop drought resistance</article-title>. <source>Agricultural Research in Arid Areas</source>. <year>1999</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref006">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ruuska</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rebetzke</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Herwaarden</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fettell</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tabe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Genotypic variation in water-soluble carbohydrate accumulation in wheat</article-title>. <source>Funct Plant Biol</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>799</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>809</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref007">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goggin</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Setter</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fructosyltransferase activity and fructan accumulation during development in wheat exposed to terminal drought</article-title>. <source>Funct Plant Biol</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref008">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Biscoe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of drought on grain growth</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1976</year>; <volume>264</volume>: <fpage>541</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>542</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref009">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Improving wheat grain filling under stress by stem reserve mobilisation</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>83</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref010">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ehdaie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alloush</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waines</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genotypic variation for stem reserves and mobilization in wheat. I. Postanthesis changes in internode dry matter</article-title>. <source>Crop Sci</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>746</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref011">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wardlaw</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Willenbrink</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Carbohydrate storage and mobilisation by the culm of wheat between heading and grain maturity: the relation to sucrose synthase and sucrose-phosphate synthase</article-title>. <source>Funct Plant Biol</source>. <year>1994</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref012">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>XP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification of quantitative trait loci and environmental interactions for accumulation and remobilization of water-soluble carbohydrates in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) stems</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>176</volume>: <fpage>571</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>584</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17287530?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17287530</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref013">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stem reserve mobilization and sink activity in wheat under drought conditions</article-title>. <source>Am J Plant Sci</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref014">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dreccer</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Herwaarden</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Grain number and grain weight in wheat lines contrasting for stem water soluble carbohydrate concentration</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Res</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref015">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shearman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sylvester-Bradley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Foulkes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Physiological processes associated with wheat yield progress in the UK</article-title>. <source>Crop Sci</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>185</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref016">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Use of chemical desiccants and senescing agents to select wheat lines maintaining stable grain size during post-anthesis drought</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Res</source>. <year>1993</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>171</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref017">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Regan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluation of chemical desiccation as a selection technique for drought resistance in a dryland wheat breeding program</article-title>. <source>Aust J Agric Res</source>. <year>1993</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1683</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1691</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref018">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Terao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quantitative trait loci for nonstructural carbohydrate accumulation in leaf sheaths and culms of rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) and their effects on grain filling</article-title>. <source>Breed Sci</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>275</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>283</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref019">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fukuta</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shiraiwa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Horie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Time-related mapping of quantitative trait loci controlling grain-filling in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>2107</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2118</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15983016?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15983016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref020">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rebetzke</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Herwaarden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruuska</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Quantitative trait loci for water-soluble carbohydrates and associations with agronomic traits in wheat</article-title>. <source>Crop Pasture Sci</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>891</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>905</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref021">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thevenot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simond-Cote</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reyss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manicacci</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trouverie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Le Guilloux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>QTLs for enzyme activities and soluble carbohydrates involved in starch accumulation during grain filling in maize</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>945</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>958</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15710637?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15710637</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref022">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Teulat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borries</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>This</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>New QTLs identified for plant water status, water-soluble carbohydrate and osmotic adjustment in a barley population grown in a growth-chamber under two water regimes</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>170</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref023">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Armstead</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ashton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skot</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Dissecting the regulation of fructan metabolism in perennial ryegrass (<italic>Lolium perenne</italic> L.) with quantitative trait locus mapping</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>169</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>57</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16390418?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16390418</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref024">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kroon</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Casstevens</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramdoss</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buckler</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>. <article-title>TASSEL: software for association mapping of complex traits in diverse samples</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>2633</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2635</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17586829?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586829</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref025">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Flint-Garcia</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thuillet</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pressoir</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Maize association population: a high-resolution platform for quantitative trait locus dissection</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1054</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1064</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16359397?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16359397</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref026">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identifying loci influencing 1,000-kernel weight in wheat by microsatellite screening for evidence of selection during breeding</article-title>. <source>Plos One</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e29432</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0029432">10.1371/journal.pone.0029432</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22328917?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22328917</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref027">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morgounov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wanyera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification of Ug99 stem rust resistance loci in winter wheat germplasm using genome-wide association analysis</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>749</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>758</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00122-012-1867-x">10.1007/s00122-012-1867-x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22534791?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22534791</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref028">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Association mapping of dynamic developmental plant height in common wheat</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>234</volume>: <fpage>891</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>902</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00425-011-1434-8">10.1007/s00425-011-1434-8</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21647605?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21647605</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref029">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Exploring elite alleles for chlorophyII content of flag leaf in natural population of wheat by association analysis</article-title>. <source>Acta Agron Sin</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>962</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>970</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref030">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sinmena</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Golan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shpiler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stem reserve mobilisation supports wheat-grain filling under heat stress</article-title>. <source>Funct Plant Biol</source>. <year>1994</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>771</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>781</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref031">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De Vries</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Flowering biology of wheat, particularly in view of hybrid seed production&#x2014;a review</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source>. <year>1971</year>; <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>170</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref032">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Waines</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Intraspecific gene flow in bread wheat as affected by reproductive biology and pollination ecology of wheat flowers</article-title>. <source>Crop Sci</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>451</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>463</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref033">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Development of near-infrared reflectance spectroscopy models for quantitative determination of water-soluble carbohydrate content in wheat stem and glume</article-title>. <source>Anal Lett</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>2478</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2490</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref034">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Isaac</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>A high-density microsatellite consensus map for bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>1105</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1114</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15490101?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15490101</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref035">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genetic diversity and core collection evaluations in common wheat germplasm from the Northwestern Spring Wheat Region in China</article-title>. <source>Mol Breed</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref036">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Evanno</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Regnaut</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goudet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Detecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software STRUCTURE: a simulation study</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>2611</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2620</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15969739?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15969739</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref037">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jakobsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>. <article-title>CLUMPP: a cluster matching and permutation program for dealing with label switching and multimodality in analysis of population structure</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1801</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1806</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17485429?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17485429</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref038">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genetic distance between populations</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source>. <year>1972</year>; <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>292</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref039">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Rohlf</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <source>NTSYS-pc, Numerical Taxonomy and Multivariate Analysis, version 2.0</source>. <publisher-name>Exeter Software Setauket</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>; <year>1998</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref040">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vekemans</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <article-title>SPAGeDi: a versatile computer program to analyse spatial genetic structure at the individual or population levels</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Notes</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>618</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>620</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref041">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pressoir</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doebley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A unified mixed-model method for association mapping that accounts for multiple levels of relatedness</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>208</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16380716?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16380716</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref042">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barrero</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bellgard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <article-title>Diverse approaches to achieving grain yield in wheat</article-title>. <source>Funct Integr Genomics</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>48</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10142-010-0208-x">10.1007/s10142-010-0208-x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21221697?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21221697</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref043">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identifying loci influencing grain number by microsatellite screening in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>236</volume>: <fpage>1507</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1517</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00425-012-1708-9">10.1007/s00425-012-1708-9</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22820969?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22820969</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref044">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Grain filling of cereals under soil drying</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>169</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>236</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16411926?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16411926</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref045">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Involvement of abscisic acid and cytokinins in the senescence and remobilization of carbon reserves in wheat subjected to water stress during grain filling</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1621</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1631</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref046">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Hormonal changes in the grains of rice subjected to water stress during grain filling</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>323</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11553759?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11553759</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref047">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lawlor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Legg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Growth of spring barley under drought: crop development, photosynthesis, dry-matter accumulation and nutrient content</article-title>. <source>J Agric Sci</source>. <year>1981</year>; <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>186</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref048">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>An improved water-use efficiency for winter wheat grown under reduced irrigation</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Res</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref049">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ehdaie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waines</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alloush</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genotypic variation for stem reserves and mobilization in wheat: II. Postanthesis changes in internode water-soluble carbohydrates</article-title>. <source>Crop Sci</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>2093</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2103</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref050">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of favorable alleles for water-soluble carbohydrates at grain filling on grain weight under drought and heat stresses in wheat</article-title>. <source>Plos one</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e102917</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0102917">10.1371/journal.pone.0102917</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 25036550?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25036550</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0119438.ref051">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Genetic gains in grain yield and physiological traits of winter wheat in Shandong Province, China, from 1969 to 2006</article-title>. <source>Crop Sci</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>44</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
