<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4383415</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25837893</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121580</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-40075</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Variation in Susceptibility to <italic>Wheat dwarf virus</italic> among Wild and Domesticated Wheat</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">WDV Susceptibility in Wild and Domesticated Wheat</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nygren</surname>
            <given-names>Jim</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shad</surname>
            <given-names>Nadeem</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="currentaff001">
            <sup>&#xA4;</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kvarnheden</surname>
            <given-names>Anders</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Westerbergh</surname>
            <given-names>Anna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff001">
        <addr-line>Department of Plant Biology, Uppsala BioCenter, Linnean Centre for Plant Biology in Uppsala, Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, Uppsala, Sweden</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Olsen</surname>
            <given-names>Kenneth M</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Academic Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Washington University, UNITED STATES</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AW AK JN. Performed the experiments: JN NS. Analyzed the data: AW JN. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AW AK. Wrote the paper: AW JN AK.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="currentaff001">
          <label>&#xA4;</label>
          <p>Current Address: Institute of Agricultural Sciences, Faculty of Life Sciences, University of the Punjab, Lahore, Pakistan</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>anna.westerbergh@slu.se</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>2</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <elocation-id>e0121580</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Nygren et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0121580.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>We investigated the variation in plant response in host-pathogen interactions between wild (<italic>Aegilops</italic> spp., <italic>Triticum</italic> spp.) and domesticated wheat (<italic>Triticum</italic> spp.) and <italic>Wheat dwarf virus</italic> (WDV). The distribution of WDV and its wild host species overlaps in Western Asia in the Fertile Crescent, suggesting a coevolutionary relationship. Bread wheat originates from a natural hybridization between wild emmer wheat (carrying the A and B genomes) and the wild D genome donor <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>, followed by polyploidization and domestication. We studied whether the strong selection during these evolutionary processes, leading to genetic bottlenecks, may have resulted in a loss of resistance in domesticated wheat. In addition, we investigated whether putative fluctuations in intensity of selection imposed on the host-pathogen interactions have resulted in a variation in susceptibility to WDV. To test our hypotheses we evaluated eighteen wild and domesticated wheat taxa, directly or indirectly involved in wheat evolution, for traits associated with WDV disease such as leaf chlorosis, different growth traits and WDV content. The plants were exposed to viruliferous leafhoppers (<italic>Psammotettix alienus</italic>) in a greenhouse trial and evaluated at two time points. We found three different plant response patterns: <italic>i</italic>) continuous reduction in growth over time, <italic>ii</italic>) weak response at an early stage of plant development but a much stronger response at a later stage, and <italic>iii</italic>) remission of symptoms over time. Variation in susceptibility may be explained by differences in the intensity of natural selection, shaping the coevolutionary interaction between WDV and the wild relatives. However, genetic bottlenecks during wheat evolution have not had a strong impact on WDV resistance. Further, this study indicates that the variation in susceptibility may be associated with the genome type and that the ancestor <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic> may be useful as genetic resource for the improvement of WDV resistance in wheat.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This study has been funded by the Swedish Research Council Formas and the Royal Swedish Academy of Agriculture and Forestry. NS was supported by the Higher Education Commission, Pakistan through University of the Punjab. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="5"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <page-count count="24"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta id="data-availability">
          <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
          <meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability</title>
      <p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Wild plant populations are constantly influenced by abiotic and biotic factors. The biotic stresses caused by pathogenic infestations exert a selective pressure on the evolution of defense mechanisms in host plants. The selective forces act mutually and the plant defense triggers a response in the colonizing pathogens. An arms race between the development of virulence in the pathogen and resistance in the host plant evolves. The strong selection imposed upon the other partner in the pathogen-host plant interaction will shape the genetic diversity and evolution of both organisms. The arms race may reach a stable, balanced polymorphism in the host plant-pathogen interaction if there is a negative frequency-dependent selection on the plant, the pathogen or both [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This means that when a phenotype such as resistance or virulence is rare in the population, the phenotype is relatively favored by natural selection but when it becomes more common, the fitness decreases and the interaction has reached an equilibrium.</p>
      <p>The domesticated crops are often highly susceptible to many pathogens [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], whereas the wild crop relatives may be resistant to the same pathogens. The susceptibility in crops may be a consequence of a lack of selection for disease resistance during domestication. Other traits such as increased seed size, increased apical dominance, suppression of natural seed dispersal, loss of seed dormancy and synchronized growth seem to have been favored by the ancient farmers in seed crops and selected from the standing genetic variation in wild crop ancestors [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Due to early agricultural practices where farmers selectively collected seeds from plants with desirable traits and planted them in their fields, the phenotype of the plants changed over time and much of the genetic diversity was unconsciously left behind in the wild populations. Thus, the genetic bottleneck caused by domestication may have hampered the arms race between the pathogen and the crop, and instead increased the susceptibility in the host. Disease resistance is also widespread in natural plant populations [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and references therein]. However, diversity of susceptibility and resistance occur both within and among populations as a result of trade-offs (cost of resistance and virulence) and/or spatial variation in intensity of selection in coevolutionary plant-pathogen interactions [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. By evaluating a number of plant-pathogen interaction studies, Laine et al. [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] found that the diversity in resistance provided a higher protection against pathogens at the population level.</p>
      <p>For a better understanding of the response to pathogen infections in crops and their wild relatives as well as the effects of crop domestication on the pathogen resistance we are studying the response in wild and domesticated wheat to <italic>Wheat dwarf virus</italic> (WDV, family <italic>Geminiviridae</italic>, genus <italic>Mastrevirus</italic>).</p>
      <p>Bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> ssp. <italic>aestivum</italic>) is susceptible to WDV and no highly resistant cultivar is known. However, variation in susceptibility has been found among cultivars [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and recently two Hungarian winter wheat cultivars were found to display partial resistance to WDV [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. WDV disease outbreaks may occur periodically and cause yield losses in most of Europe and in parts of Africa and Asia [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Recently, WDV has also been detected in Syria [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and in Iran [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The incidence of WDV disease in Swedish bread wheat fields can be up to 90% in severe cases [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Like many other geminiviruses WDV causes severe symptoms on host plants including dwarfing, tufting, streaks of leaf chlorosis, and reduced number of spikes that are often sterile and stunted [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The virus is transmitted by the leafhopper vector <italic>Psammotettix alienus</italic> (family Cicadellidae). However, virus-free <italic>P</italic>. <italic>alienus</italic> feeding on wheat plants does not cause any visible symptoms [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The primary spread of WDV to winter wheat takes place in autumn, when the adult leafhoppers migrate into newly sown fields. <italic>P</italic>. <italic>alienus</italic> completes two to three generations per year. In central Sweden the first adult generation appears in June-July and the second one in August-September [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The leafhoppers overwinter as eggs and the first generation of nymphs appears in May. WDV is not transmitted to the eggs and the nymphs of the first instar [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. WDV may be considered as a grass generalist pathogen since its host range encompasses not only wheat but also several wild grasses and other cereals such as barley, oat and rye [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. For infection of wheat, wild grasses are of less importance as primary sources compared to cultivated wheat. However, the grasses growing in vicinity to cultivated cereal fields may act as reservoirs of WDV [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p>
      <p>WDV has a genome of single-stranded circular DNA [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Five strains of WDV have been described, WDV-A to WDV-E [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Wheat-infecting isolates of WDV are usually unable to infect barley and the other way around [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Most of the WDV isolates from wheat belong to the strain WDV-E, which has a very wide geographic distribution throughout Europe and Asia and with isolates sharing a high genome sequence identity [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. However, based on wheat-infecting isolates of WDV a high genetic diversity has been found to be concentrated in some regions of the WDV genome including introns, short and long intergenic regions and the coding region of the replication-association protein Rep A [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Interestingly, it has been shown in maize streak virus (<italic>Mastrevirus</italic>) that single nucleotide mutations can lead to major changes in severity of symptoms and host range [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Presence of genetic variation both within the virus and the host plants is fundamental for their coevolutionary relationship. Moreover, evidence has been found for a correlation between cereal host divergence times (<italic>Triticum</italic>, <italic>Hordeum</italic> and <italic>Aveneae</italic>) and WDV divergence times, indicating coevolutionary arms race between the virus and the host plants [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p>
      <p>WDV is transmitted to the wheat plants by the leafhopper in a persistent manner [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The virus is mixed with the saliva of the nymph or the adult leafhopper and is inserted to the phloem fluid when the leafhopper is penetrating the plant tissues with its stylet for feeding [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In non-immune plants, viruses move with the phloem stream first to the young leaves and root tips, and then to the older parts, until the plant is systematically infected [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The response of the plant is not only dependent on its genotype but also on the age of the plant when it is infected. As the wheat plants grow they gradually acquire resistance to the WDV and when the plant has developed its first node on the stem it has acquired mature resistance [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p>
      <p>Wheat is one of many crops with origin in the Fertile Crescent in Western Asia (Asian part of Turkey, Syria, Lebanon, Israel, Jordan, Iraq and western Iran [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The first two domesticated forms of wheat were diploid einkorn <italic>T</italic>. <italic>monococcum</italic> ssp. <italic>monococcum</italic>, derived from its wild form <italic>T</italic>. <italic>monococcum</italic> ssp. <italic>boeticum</italic>, and the cultivated tetraploid emmer wheat, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>turgidum</italic> ssp. <italic>dicoccon</italic> derived from wild emmer wheat <italic>T</italic>. <italic>turgidum</italic> ssp. <italic>dicoccoides</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). South Eastern Turkey is supposed to be the domestication site of einkorn and emmer wheat [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The wild emmer underwent previous to its domestication hybridization and polyploidization between two diploids: the A genome donor <italic>Triticum urartu</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] and the suggested B genome donor <italic>Aegilops speltoides</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). The tetraploid cultivated emmer wheat migrated eastward and hybridized with the wild diploid <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic>, the D genome donor [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] and formed the first hexaploid wheat carrying the A, B and D genomes [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Whether the first hexaploid wheat was a hulled or free-threshing form has been discussed and additional models for the evolution of hexaploid wheat are presented. In a new model, Dvor&#xE1;k et al. [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] proposed that the ancestral hexaploid wheat was hulled and resulted from a cross between a free-threshing tetraploid wheat, not hulled cultivated emmer wheat, and the <italic>strangulata</italic> subspecies of <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic>. Through a mutation in the <italic>Tg</italic> locus, which controls glume tenacity, the ancestral hexaploid wheat evolved into a free-threshing form. In addition to this evolutionary model, spelt is derived from a hybridization between a free-threshing hexaploid wheat and hulled tetraploid emmer wheat.</p>
      <fig id="pone.0121580.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121580.g001</object-id>
        <label>Fig 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Studied species and their role in the evolutionary history of bread wheat.</title>
          <p>The figure is based on information described in Zohary et al. [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], Kilian et al. [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], Chantret et al. [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] and Peng et al. [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Genome type and ploidy level are given in brackets, LIGHT GREY = wild species, GREY = domesticated wheat. Dashed lines show the most accepted model of the origin of hexaploid wheat where the ancestral species are tetraploid emmer wheat (<italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> ssp. <italic>dicoccon</italic>) and <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>. A more recent model is described in Dvorak et al. [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pone.0121580.g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Besides the domestication process other bottlenecks created by the natural hybridization and polyploidization events in wheat evolution have reduced the genetic diversity of the ancestral genomes in cultivated wheat [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].</p>
      <p>Like all domesticated wheat taxa, their wild relatives, <italic>Aegilops</italic> spp. (22 species), <italic>Triticum</italic> spp. (4 species) and <italic>Amblyopyrum muticum</italic>, are annuals. The wild relatives carry different genomes defined as A, B, C, D, G, M, N, S, T, and U types, and have three different ploidy levels (diploid, tetraploid and hexaploid; [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]). They are distributed along the Euro-Asian axis from the Mediterranean region into China and the largest species diversity of wild wheat relatives is found in Western Asia in the Fertile Crescent region [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). The wild relatives are adapted to a wide variety of habitats growing at 400 m.a.s.l. up to 2700 m.a.s.l. and with different annual rainfall varying from 75 to 1400 mm per year [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. They show high diversity in morphological traits such as plant height, tiller number and spike length, and physiological traits such as number of days to heading [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].</p>
      <fig id="pone.0121580.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121580.g002</object-id>
        <label>Fig 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Collection sites of wild and domesticated wheat.</title>
          <p>&#x25CF; = <italic>Aegilops</italic>, <italic>Amblyopyrum</italic> and <italic>Triticum</italic> accessions, except spelt and the winter wheat cultivar Tarso, based on SINGER data base, 2009, species richness of <italic>Aegilops</italic> and <italic>Triticum</italic> based on information in Zohary et al. [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and Van Slageren [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]; LIGHT GREEN = 1&#x2013;5 species, GREEN = 6&#x2013;10 species, DARK GREEN = &gt;10 species.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pone.0121580.g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The early diploid <italic>Aegilops</italic> species have most likely originated in Transcaucasia like the first hexaploid wheat [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Most <italic>Aegilops</italic> spread to the west except the species carrying the D-genome which spread into Eastern Asia [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The distribution of wild relatives in the Fertile Crescent partly overlaps with regions where WDV has been detected in Turkey, Syria and Iran [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p>
      <p>The wild relatives of the <italic>Aegilops</italic> genus carry many genes of resistance to fungi and other pathogens and have been used as genetic sources for improvement of rust and powdery mildew resistance in bread wheat ([<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and references therein). In addition, variation in resistance has also been found in <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>monococcum</italic> to <italic>Soil-borne wheat mosaic virus</italic> (SBWMV) [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] and in <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>geniculata</italic> to <italic>Barley yellow dwarf virus</italic> (BYDV) [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. It has also been shown that the <italic>Aegilops</italic> species <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>caudata</italic>, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>ovata</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>triuncialis</italic> responded with a milder form of symptoms to WDV infection in comparison to spring wheat [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p>
      <p>The host-pathogen system involving both wild and domesticated wheat provides a unique opportunity to investigate the effect of crop evolution on pathogen resistance. The overlap of the distribution of wild wheat relatives and WDV over a large geographical scale in the Fertile Crescent and adjacent areas suggests that the virus and the wild wheat populations are interacting and co-evolving. The intensity of selection may vary across sites and in time, which have been seen in a wide range of species interactions ([<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] and references therein). Among several factors, the virulence of WDV, the population density of the vector, and the physical environment (temperature) may strengthen or weaken the selection locally. We therefore hypothesize that there is a genetic variation in susceptibility to WDV among wild wheat relatives in the Fertile Crescent region. We are also testing the hypothesis that the domestication and human selection, and other genetic bottlenecks during wheat evolution such as natural hybridization and polyploidization events have had a negative impact on the resistance to WDV.</p>
      <p>To test our hypotheses we studied the response of one accession each of thirteen wild wheat relatives and five domesticated wheat taxa when exposed to WDV-carrying leafhoppers (<xref rid="pone.0121580.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0121580.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). These accessions are from the Fertile Crescent and adjacent areas (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). The different taxa have had a direct or indirect role in the evolution of wheat (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). Interestingly, when the plants were evaluated for various traits associated with WDV resistance, we found three different response patterns. The variation in response was, however, not associated with whether the plants were domesticated or wild. Thus, our findings do not support the assumption that evolutionary processes such as natural hybridization followed by polyploidization and domestication have had an influence on the resistance to WDV in wheat. Instead the variation in susceptibility found in this study may be explained by differences in intensity of natural selection in different geographical areas, shaping the coevolutionary interaction between WDV and the wild wheat relatives in the Fertile Crescent and adjacent areas.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone.0121580.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121580.t001</object-id>
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>WDV content in exposed plants within each species the wild and domesticated groups.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone.0121580.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0121580.t001"/>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Species</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Mean</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>95% CI</bold>
                  <xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Aegilops comosa</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Aegilops cylindrical</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Aegilops juvenalis</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Aegilops searsii</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Aegilops sharonensis</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Aegilops speltoides</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Aegilops triuncialis</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Aegilops umbellulata</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Amblyopyrum muticum</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Wild einkorn</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Wild emmer</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Triticum urartu</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Bread wheat</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Spelt wheat</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Einkorn wheat</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Emmer wheat</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Durum wheat</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Wild-domesticated status</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Domesticated</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Wild</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Controls</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Positive (WDV infected source plant)</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="t001fn001">
            <p>WDV content is measured as the absorbance at 405 nm using DAS-ELISA.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="t001fn002">
            <p><sup>a</sup>95% confidence interval.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>Thirteen wild and five domesticated wheat taxa were used (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). They were selected based on their direct or indirect role in the evolution history of wheat [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] and the co-occurrence with WDV mainly within the Fertile Crescent and adjacent areas. The wild relatives included <italic>Amblyopyrum muticum</italic>, nine <italic>Aegilops</italic> species and three <italic>Triticum</italic> species. These species have different genome types and ploidy levels. The domesticated wheat taxa were the diploid cultivated einkorn, the tetraploids cultivated emmer and durum, and the hexaploids spelta and bread wheat. Seeds of these taxa, except the bread wheat cultivar, were provided by the International Center for Agricultural Research in the Dry Areas (ICARDA), Aleppo, Syria. One accession of each taxon was studied. Their accession numbers and origins are given in <xref rid="pone.0121580.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>. The winter wheat cultivar Tarso is derived from crosses between the winter wheat cultivar Taras and the breeding line Hadmerslebener 13313&#x2013;80 and was released commercially by the breeding company Lantm&#xE4;nnen SW Seed AB in 1994.</p>
      <sec id="sec003">
        <title>Wheat dwarf virus</title>
        <p>The WDV sources used for inoculation in our study originate both from infected bread wheat plants and the leafhopper vector <italic>P</italic>. <italic>alienus</italic>. These WDV sources were collected in three wheat fields in central Sweden (N 60.0022, E 17.5383; N 59.8384, E 17.7914; N 59.7031, E 17.6994). Sequence analyses of complete genomes have verified that the WDV isolates in this culture are closely related to the WDV isolates previously identified in Sweden and belong to strain WDV-E [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec004">
        <title>Vector</title>
        <p>The leafhopper vectors were collected using sweep nets in June and July 2010. The species identification was done using 10 x magnifier glasses. <italic>P</italic>. <italic>alienus</italic> leafhoppers were reared in nylon mesh covered cages (17 cm x 13 cm x13 cm) on wheat source plants not used in the trial. The plants were grown in ordinary potting soil (Weibulls Horto AB) and the cages were kept in a greenhouse with 16/8 hrs day/night photoperiod and 20/18&#xB0;C day/night temperature. The first generation of source plants was collected in WDV affected wheat fields and was confirmed by double antibody sandwich enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (DAS-ELISA, see below) to contain the virus. New healthy wheat plants grown from seeds were regularly replacing old infected ones inside the cages. The new plants were infected by viruliferous leafhoppers and in turn newly hatched and virus-free nymphs acquired WDV from infected wheat plants while feeding on them. This regenerating host-vector-virus system was successfully developed and a population size of several hundred leafhoppers has been maintained since 2009.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec005">
        <title>Exposure to viruliferous leafhoppers</title>
        <p>Seeds of the different accessions were sown in a mixture of ordinary potting soil (Weibulls Horto AB) and sand of 0.5 mm grain size (R&#xE5;dasand AB, 1:5 proportions) in a growth chamber with 16/8 hrs day/night photoperiod and 22/20&#xB0;C day/night temperature. When the plants reached the 2<sup>nd</sup> leaf stage they were transferred to 2L pots with the same mixture of potting soil and sand and placed in a greenhouse (16/8 hrs day/night photoperiod and 20/18&#xB0;C day/night temperature). One plant was placed inside a cage (17 cm x 13 cm x 13 cm) covered by nylon fabric with fine mesh avoiding the escape of leafhoppers. When the plants were at the 3<sup>rd</sup> leaf stage, three nymphs and two adult leafhoppers were transferred to each of the exposed plants by aspirators (insect-collecting tool). After seven days we removed the insects from the cages using the same tool. To make sure that all insects were removed the plants were also treated by the insecticides Pirimor and Confidor (Imidacloprid) at the same time as the cages were dismantled. The number of living insects in each cage was counted in the middle of the inoculation period and if necessary additional insects were transferred to keep the number of insects the same for each exposed plant. Prior to the experiment the nymphs and adult leafhoppers were feeding on infected wheat source plants for a minimum of three days to acquire WDV. These plants were confirmed to carry a high level of WDV using DAS-ELISA.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec006">
        <title>Block trial</title>
        <p>The plants were grown in a complete randomized block design with 6 blocks. Each block consisted of two plants of each of the 18 accessions. One of the two plants was exposed to viruliferous leafhoppers for seven days as described above, while the other plant of the same accession was not. We randomized the exposed and non-exposed plants of the 18 accessions in each block using the software Research Randomizer (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.randomizer.org/">www.randomizer.org</ext-link>). The randomization of accessions and treatments in each of the six blocks enabled us to estimate the block effect and also to reduce the environmental effect on the variation of the studied phenotypes among accessions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec007">
        <title>Evaluated traits</title>
        <p>The exposed and non-exposed plants were studied for four traits associated with response to WDV infection. We measured the plant height (base of the stem to the leaf tip of the longest leaf), the total number of tillers, total number of leaves, and percentage of leaf chlorosis (ratio of chlorotic leaves and total number of leaves) 28 days after the end of the exposure to viruliferous leafhopper. A leaf was considered chlorotic if at least 50% of the leaf was yellow. Investigating all leaves on each plant for chlorosis made it possible to assess the whole plant response to WDV infection. The number of tillers and leaves were also measured at a second date, 98 and 112 days after the end of exposure. From now on, we refer to 28 dpi (days after post-inoculation) as the first time point, and 98 dpi and 112 dpi as the second time point for analysis of the different traits. At harvest, 16 weeks after the start of the experiment (112 dpi), each plant was checked for survival (scored as 0 = dead or 1 = alive). A plant was considered dead when most of the leaves where necrotic and/or wilted.</p>
        <p>As the study comprised accessions from both wild and domesticated taxa with different ploidy level, genome types and degrees of relatedness, variation in the constitutive developmental patterns and morphology was expected. We have therefore chosen to compare the performance of each accession in both exposed and non-exposed control conditions. The response was measured both as the absolute reduction<disp-formula id="pone.0121580.e001"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121580.e001.jpg" id="pone.0121580.e001g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#xA0;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>&#xA0;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#xA0;</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x2211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#xA0;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#xA0;</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>1</label></disp-formula>
and as the proportional reduction
<disp-formula id="pone.0121580.e002"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121580.e002.jpg" id="pone.0121580.e002g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#xA0;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#xA0;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#xA0;</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x2211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#xA0;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#xA0;</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#xA0;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives><label>2</label></disp-formula>
between the two treatments for each trait, where <inline-formula id="pone.0121580.e003"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121580.e003.jpg" id="pone.0121580.e003g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M3"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the average in the non-exposed control condition, <inline-formula id="pone.0121580.e004"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121580.e004.jpg" id="pone.0121580.e004g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M4"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> the average in the exposed condition and <inline-formula id="pone.0121580.e005"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121580.e005.jpg" id="pone.0121580.e005g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M5"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> the value for the exposed individual <italic>i</italic>. It is very important to distinguish between the two viewpoints since they can give very different results. For example, an accession may have a small absolute reduction in leaf number relative to other accessions, indicating a weak response to WDV. However, the same accession might show a larger proportional reduction for the same trait due to a small number of leaves formed in the control condition as seen for example in einkorn wheat for leaf number at 112 dpi and <italic>Am</italic>. <italic>muticum</italic> for shoot dry weight (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0121580.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121580.g003</object-id>
          <label>Fig 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Plant response in wild and domesticated species.</title>
            <p>BLUE = Mean values and 95% confidence interval (CI) of non-exposed, and RED = exposed plants, GREEN = absolute reduction, PURPLE = proportional reduction of the <italic>Aegilops</italic> and <italic>Triticum</italic> taxa for the studied traits. Pairwise comparison (t-test) between non-exposed and exposed plants with Bonferroni correction. dpi refers to days after the end of exposure to viruliferous leafhoppers. * = p&lt;0.05, N.S. = no significance, <sup>a</sup>Mean = -39.8%, 95% CI = 44.0, <sup>b</sup>Mean = -75.0%, 95% CI = 65.7%. <sup>c</sup>No surviving plants.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0121580.g003"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec008">
        <title>ELISA</title>
        <p>Virus infection of the exposed and non-exposed plants was analyzed by DAS-ELISA. This method has become the standard for detection and quantification of virus content in large number of samples, especially in agricultural crops. We sampled young leaves from all exposed and non-exposed plants at 28 dpi. Virus content was not analyzed at the later growth stage at 98 and 112 dpi due to large differences in plant morphology among wild and domesticated accessions and thereby difficulties in identifying the youngest leaves. Leaves sampled at 28 dpi were kept at -20&#xB0;C prior to the testing for WDV infection. The plant sap was extracted from 50 mg leaf tissue in 400 &#x3BC;l phosphate buffer (pH 7.4). The samples were diluted 20 times in extraction buffer and analyzed by DAS-ELISA according to Loewe Biochemica GmbH protocol No. 07082 [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. The plant sap samples were applied onto 96-well microplates of Microlon 600 type and with flat bottoms (Greiner Bio-One) precoated with anti-WDV IgG. The samples were analyzed at 405 nm wavelength in a Benchmark Microplate Reader (Bio-Rad) after 2 hours of incubation with alkaline phosphatase-conjugated anti-WDV IgG and substrate. To verify accuracy and comparison in the tests we included as positive controls 1:20 dilutions of plant sap from a WDV infected bread wheat source plant. Moreover, we used 1:20 dilutions of sap from the non-exposed plants in the trial, and samples only with extraction buffer as negative controls.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec009">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>Residuals for each trait were checked for deviations from normality. Traits with residuals showing normal distribution were analyzed with a mixed proc model for two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). Plant height, shoot dry weight, number of tillers at 28 dpi and 98 dpi, number of leaves at 28 dpi and 112 dpi, and percentage of chlorosis showed normally distributed residuals and were therefore analyzed with two-way ANOVA. However, only the absorbance values for WDV content in the exposed plants showed normally distributed residuals and thus analyzed with one-way ANOVA. In addition, difference in mortality, showing binominal distribution, was analyzed by Chi-square test. The plants were grouped in two ways, according to 1) species and 2) whether they are wild or domesticated accessions. These two groups were analyzed separately. We used block as a random factor, and species, wild-domesticated status and treatment (exposed or non-exposed) as fixed factors. We analyzed the following interactions: species, treatment and block, and wild-domesticated status, treatment and block. A t-test was used for pairwise comparisons between the two treatments in each species and correlation among traits was analyzed by simple linear regression. These analyses were done with the statistical software JMP ver. 9 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="sec010">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="sec011">
        <title>WDV content</title>
        <p>In DAS-ELISA tests, the non-exposed plants for all accessions showed low absorbance values (mean = 0.125, 95% CI = 0.002). All plants exposed to viruliferous leafhoppers, except one replicate of <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>umbellulata</italic>, showed at least twice the absorbance value of the negative control and the non-exposed plants of the corresponding species. These plants were considered positive and infected by WDV. Significant difference in absorbance values for infected plants was found among species (p&lt;0.0001, one-way ANOVA). <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>umbellulata</italic> showed the lowest mean value (one negative sample excluded), while the domesticated spelt and emmer wheat had the highest WDV content (<xref rid="pone.0121580.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <p>Based on pairwise comparisons of infected plants between species the domesticated spelt wheat had significantly higher mean absorbance value than seven of the wild species (Tukey&#x2019;s HSD test, <xref rid="pone.0121580.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). Comparing the wild and domesticated groups a significant difference in mean absorbance value between the groups (p&lt;0.05, t-test) was found, and the mean value was higher in the domesticated group (<xref rid="pone.0121580.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec012">
        <title>Trait variation among non-exposed plants</title>
        <p>The non-exposed plants showed a large variation among species for all growth traits (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). The wild species had a significantly lower plant height and shoot dry weight, but a higher number of tillers and leaves for both time points than the domesticated taxa (p&lt;0.05, t-test for all traits, <xref rid="pone.0121580.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). We found also a significant block effect for number of tillers at 28 dpi and number of leaves at 28 dpi (p&lt;0.05, one-way ANOVA), showing a variation of non-exposed plants within accessions. This variation could be a result of environmental variation in the greenhouse and/or the genetic variation within the accessions since the wild accessions, in particular, may not have gone through many generations of selfing. However, no significant block effect was found for exposed plants.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0121580.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121580.g004</object-id>
          <label>Fig 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Plant response in the wild and domesticated groups.</title>
            <p>BLUE = Mean values and 95% confidence interval (CI) of non-exposed, and RED = exposed plants, GREEN = absolute reduction, PURPLE = proportional reduction of the wild and domesticated groups for the studied traits. Pairwise comparison (t-test) between non-exposed and exposed plants with Bonferroni correction. dpi refers to days after the end of exposure to viruliferous leafhoppers. * = p&lt;0.05, N.S. = no significance.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0121580.g004"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec013">
        <title>Effect of treatment</title>
        <p>Treatment had a significant effect on all traits (<xref rid="pone.0121580.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The exposed plants showed significantly lower plant height, shoot dry weight and leaf and tiller number at the different time points than the virus-free plants within the domesticated and wild plant groups (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). The exposed plants within the wild group had also higher percentage of leaf chlorosis, while the exposed and non-exposed domesticated plants were not significantly different. However, pairwise comparisons between exposed and non-exposed plants within each species showed non-significant differences for several species (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). Most domesticated species showed non-significant differences for percentage of leaf chlorosis and number of leaves and tillers at the two time points, while a larger variation in response was found among the wild species. The mortality was significantly higher in the exposed plants than in the non-exposed plants (<xref rid="pone.0121580.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>; p&lt;0.05, &#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>-test,). However, only half of the species was affected. Notable is that all exposed plants of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>urartu</italic> and cultivated emmer died before the harvest at 112 dpi. Also <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>juvenalis</italic> and wild einkorn showed high mortality. No significant difference was found in mortality between the domesticated and wild groups (p&lt;0.58, &#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>-test).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0121580.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121580.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Two-way ANOVA results showing the effects of treatment (exposed or non-exposed), species and their interactions as well as the effect of treatment, wild/domesticated status and their interactions on the studied traits.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0121580.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0121580.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Trait</bold>
                  </th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Source</bold>
                  </th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>F</bold>
                  </th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Source</bold>
                  </th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>F</bold>
                  </th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Plant height (28 dpi)</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">341.3<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.8<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.7<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Leaf chlorosis (28 dpi)</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.8<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9<xref rid="t002fn003" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Number of leaves (28 dpi)</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.1<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.8<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Number of tillers (28 dpi)</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.8<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.9<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5<xref rid="t002fn003" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Number of leaves (112 dpi)</bold>
                    <xref rid="t002fn001" ref-type="table-fn">
                      <sup>
                        <bold>a</bold>
                      </sup>
                    </xref>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.0<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Number of tillers (98 dpi)</bold>
                    <xref rid="t002fn001" ref-type="table-fn">
                      <sup>
                        <bold>a</bold>
                      </sup>
                    </xref>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.2<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.2<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Shoot dry weight (112 dpi)</bold>
                    <xref rid="t002fn001" ref-type="table-fn">
                      <sup>
                        <bold>a</bold>
                      </sup>
                    </xref>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">236.1<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.6<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9<xref rid="t002fn003" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x species</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment x wild/domesticated</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t002fn001">
              <p><sup>a</sup>Dead plants were not included in the analysis.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t002fn002">
              <p>* = p&lt;0.05,</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t002fn003">
              <p>** = p&lt;0.01,</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t002fn004">
              <p>*** = p&lt;0.001.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0121580.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121580.t003</object-id>
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Plant mortality rate at 112 days after the end of exposure to virouferious leafhoppers.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0121580.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0121580.t003"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Species</bold>
                  </th>
                  <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">
                    <bold>Treatment</bold>
                  </th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Exposed</bold>
                  </th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Non-exposed</bold>
                  </th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Aegilops comosa</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Aegilops cylindrica</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Aegilops juvenalis</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Aegilops searsii</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Aegilops sharonensis</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Aegilops speltoides</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Aegilops triuncialis</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Aegilops umbellulata</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Amblyopyrum muticum</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Wild einkorn</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Triticum urartu</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Wild emmer</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Einkorn wheat</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Bread wheat</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Spelt wheat</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Emmer wheat</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Durum wheat</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec014">
        <title>Variation in response</title>
        <p>To determine if there is a variation in susceptibility and resistance to WDV among species as well as the domesticated and wild status groups, we were also focusing on the treatment x species interactions and the treatment x domesticated/wild status. Both the treatment x species and the treatment x domesticated/wild status interactions had significant effect on shoot dry weight, number of tillers at 28 and 98 dpi, number of leaves at 28 dpi, and percentage of chlorotic leaves (<xref rid="pone.0121580.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), showing that the species differed in the response to WDV infection. In addition, significant effect was found in the treatment x species interaction for number of leaves at 112 dpi, while no effect was found in the treatment x domesticated/wild status interactions. The variation in response among species is supported by the above pairwise comparisons between treatments. However, all taxa responded in a similar way regarding plant height since no significant interaction was found between treatment x species or between treatment x domesticated/wild status.</p>
        <sec id="sec015">
          <title>Leaf chlorosis</title>
          <p>Surprisingly, cultivated spelt and emmer wheat showed a lower percentage of chlorotic leaves in the WDV infected plants compared to the non-infected (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). All other species showed an increase in chlorosis. However, the increase was least severe in <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>juvenalis</italic> and wild emmer and the bread wheat cultivar Tarso. The highest increase in chlorosis was found in the wild <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>sharonensis</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>searsii</italic>. The wild plant group showed a significantly larger increase in percentage of chlorotic leaves in the infected plants compared to the domesticated group (p&lt;0.05, t-test; <xref rid="pone.0121580.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec016">
          <title>Leaf number at 28 dpi</title>
          <p>The leaf number in cultivated emmer and its ancestor wild emmer wheat was not negatively affected by the WDV infection considering both the absolute and proportional reduction (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). The WDV infection had also a minor effect on cultivated spelt and the bread wheat cultivar Tarso. The highest proportional reduction was found in three wild species <italic>T</italic>. <italic>urartu</italic>, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>triuncialis</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>searsii</italic>. In fact, the absolute and proportional reductions in leaf number were most severe in the wild plant group (p&lt;0.05, t-test; <xref rid="pone.0121580.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec017">
          <title>Leaf number at 112 dpi</title>
          <p>As expected most species were more severely affected at 112 dpi compared to 28 days (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). In fact, all plants of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>urartu</italic> and cultivated emmer wheat showed a very slow and stunted growth and died before 112 dpi. However, interestingly, the exposed plants of spelt showed an increase in leaf number. WDV infection had also a relatively small effect on <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>juvenalis</italic>. <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>triuncialis</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>searsii</italic>, which were among the most severely affected species at 28 dpi, differed in response at 112 dpi. <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>searsii</italic> showed a milder response to WDV at 112 dpi than at 28 dpi, while <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>triuncialis</italic> had a high absolute and proportional reduction also at 112 dpi. The wild plant group showed a higher absolute reduction also at 112 dpi than the domesticated plants (p&lt;0.05, t-test; <xref rid="pone.0121580.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). The proportional reduction was, however, about the same in both groups.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec018">
          <title>Tiller number at 28 dpi</title>
          <p>We found the largest proportional reduction in tiller number at 28 dpi in the wild species <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>searsii</italic>, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>cylindrica</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>urartu</italic>, and the wild einkorn (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). In addition, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>cylindrica</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>triuncalis</italic> showed a large absolute reduction. Wild emmer, the bread wheat cultivar Tarso and spelt wheat had the lowest absolute and proportional reduction.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec019">
          <title>Tiller number at 98 dpi</title>
          <p>Interestingly, the exposed plants of spelt showed a notable increase in tiller number (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). Considering both the absolute and the proportional reduction in tillers the wild species <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>searsii</italic> showed the weakest response. Based on the proportional reduction, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>umbellulata</italic> was among the most affected species. <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>umbellulata</italic> showed also a large absolute reduction together with <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>triuncalis</italic>. The domesticated plant group had significantly lower absolute reduction compared to the wild plants at both time points (p&lt;0.05, t-test; <xref rid="pone.0121580.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). However, the two groups did not differ significantly in the proportional reduction. The difference between the result of the absolute and proportional reductions is most likely due to the large difference in the total number of leaves between the wild and domesticated plants.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec020">
          <title>Shoot dry weight</title>
          <p>The proportional reduction in shoot dry weight was less than 50% in <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>cylindrica</italic>, while all the other accessions showed a reduction between 53% to 83% (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). Shoot dry weight of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>urartu</italic> and cultivated emmer was not analyzed since all plants of both species died before 112 dpi. The change in absolute values was noticeably large in the wild <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>triuncalis</italic> and cultivated einkorn. The absolute reduction was significantly higher in the domesticated plant group (p&lt;0.05, t-test; <xref rid="pone.0121580.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). No significant difference in the proportional reduction in shoot dry weight was shown between the two groups.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec021">
          <title>No correlation between response to WDV and growth habit</title>
          <p>The variation in response to WDV measured both as absolute and proportional reduction was independent of the variation among species in the non-exposed condition for all traits studied (R<sup>2</sup>&lt;0.16 for each of the studied traits). This indicates that the response measured as the absolute and proportional reduction is independent of the growth habit of the species under non-exposed condition.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec022">
          <title>Variation in response over time</title>
          <p>Comparing the different time points the response pattern in leaf number differed among species (<xref rid="pone.0121580.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0121580.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0121580.g005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). For example, the WDV infection had no effect on cultivated emmer at 28 dpi, whereas all emmer plants were dead at 112 dpi (<xref rid="pone.0121580.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). In addition, the exposed plants of wild emmer showed a small increase in leaf number at the first measurement, but an almost 50% reduction 12 weeks later. On the contrary, the <italic>Aegilops</italic> species such as <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>searsii</italic> showed a much less proportional reduction in leaf number at the second time point compared to the first. While WDV infection had a small reduced effect on cultivated spelt, at 28 dpi spelt showed a striking increase in leaf production at 112 dpi. Other species such as <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>triuncialis</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>umbellulata</italic> were highly affected by the WDV infection at both time points.</p>
          <fig id="pone.0121580.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121580.g005</object-id>
            <label>Fig 5</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Proportional reduction of leaf and tiller number between non-exposed and exposed plants of wild and domesticated species measured at two time points.</title>
              <p>All exposed plants of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>urartu</italic> and cultivated emmer were dead at the second time point and not included in the figure.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="pone.0121580.g005"/>
          </fig>
          <table-wrap id="pone.0121580.t004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121580.t004</object-id>
            <label>Table 4</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Ranking of the studied species based on their response to WDV infection.</title>
            </caption>
            <alternatives>
              <graphic id="pone.0121580.t004g" xlink:href="pone.0121580.t004"/>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <colgroup span="1">
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                  <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                </colgroup>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Chlorosis(28 dpi)</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">
                      <bold>Height(28 dpi)</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">
                      <bold>Leaves(28 dpi)</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">
                      <bold>Tillers(28 dpi)</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">
                      <bold>Leaves(112 dpi)</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">
                      <bold>Tillers(98 dpi)</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">
                      <bold>Weight(112 dpi)</bold>
                    </th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Species</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>A</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>P</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>A</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>P</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>A</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>P</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>A</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>P</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>A</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>P</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>A</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>P</bold>
                    </th>
                    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>A</bold>
                    </th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold><italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>comosa</italic></bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold><italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>cylindrica</italic></bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold><italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>juvenalis</italic></bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold><italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>searsii</italic></bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold><italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>sharonensis</italic></bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold><italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>speltoides</italic></bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold><italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic></bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold><italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>triuncialis</italic></bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold><italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>umbellulata</italic></bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold><italic>Am</italic>. <italic>muticum</italic></bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Wild einkorn</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Wild emmer</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>
                        <italic>Triticum urartu</italic>
                      </bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<sup>a</sup></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<sup>a</sup></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<sup>a</sup></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<sup>a</sup></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<sup>a</sup></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<sup>a</sup></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Bread wheat</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Spelt wheat</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Einkorn wheat</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Emmer wheat</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<sup>a</sup></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<sup>a</sup></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<sup>a</sup></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<sup>a</sup></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<sup>a</sup></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<sup>a</sup></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Durum wheat</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </alternatives>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="t004fn001">
                <p>Number 1 signifies the species with the lowest proportional (P) or absolute (A) reduction and number 18 the species with the largest reduction for each trait. dpi refers to the end of the exposure time to viruliferous leafhoppers.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p>As for the leaf number, we also observed a difference in response pattern in tiller number between the two time points. Most notable is the much weaker response at 98 dpi compared to 28 dpi for <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>searsii</italic>. Even though the bread wheat cultivar Tarso and wild emmer wheat were among the species with lowest proportional and absolute reduction in tiller number at the first measurement, they were much more severely affected at 98 dpi. <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>umbellulata</italic> and wild einkorn showed a strong response to WDV at both time points.</p>
          <p>Taking also chlorosis, plant height, shoot dry weight and mortality in consideration, cultivated spelt was among the least affected species for all studied traits and time points (<xref rid="pone.0121580.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). In contrary, the wild species <italic>T</italic>. <italic>urartu</italic>, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>triuncialis</italic>, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>umbellulata</italic> and wild einkorn showed a strong response. Interestingly, some of the wild species such as <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic>, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>searsii</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>comosa</italic> were severely affected in most traits measured at the first time point, while they were among the least affected species at the later measurements. The bread wheat cultivar Tarso, showed a different level of response for various traits and time points.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec023">
          <title>Correlation between traits, and between traits and ELISA-values</title>
          <p>Based on simple linear regression we found strong positive correlation between number of tillers at 98 dpi and leaves at 112 dpi considering both exposed and non-exposed plants together (<xref rid="pone.0121580.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>). A strong positive correlation was also found when the exposed and non-exposed plants were analyzed separately. The same traits also showed a positive correlation at 28 dpi, although weaker, for all the three plant groups analyzed (all plants, exposed plants, and non-exposed plants). However, no strong correlation was found between number of leaves and the other growth traits (height and weight), or between the number of tillers and the two growth traits. Interestingly, there was no evident correlation between any growth trait and ELISA-value. Moreover, chlorosis did not correlate strongly with ELISA-value or any of the growth traits.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec024">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Crops are constantly confronted with a wide variety of potential pathogens within their environment. Cultivation of monocultures with genetically uniform plants in dense stands allowing closer contact between plants and vectors has led to efficient transmission of pathogens and evolution of more aggressive strains [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. These strains cause substantial damage to crops but our knowledge to prevent the pathogen infestations is often limited to the use of pesticides, leading to environmental and ecological risks. Aiming for a sustainable agriculture, breeding for disease resistant cultivars is an important component in the process. As strong selection during crop domestication often resulted in loss of genetic diversity and traits not directly selected for such as resistance to pest and diseases, the wild relatives may be the most useful or only genetic sources for introgression of resistance into crops.</p>
      <p>We have compared the variation in response to WDV infections in wild and domesticated wheat taxa to test whether the interaction between wild wheat relatives and the virus has coevolved under divergent intensity of selection and led to varying degrees of susceptibility in the host plants. We have also investigated if the genetic bottlenecks created by natural hybridization and polyploidization followed by the domestication process have resulted in a loss of resistance to WDV in wheat.</p>
      <p>Aiming to increase the understanding of the variation in response to WDV in an evolutionary history context, one accession of each of thirteen wild and five domesticated species directly or indirectly involved in wheat evolution were selected rather than a larger number of accessions within a few species. The large genetic diversity among the studied species, with different genome type and ploidy level, and from different geographic locations, has most likely increased the chances of variation in intensity of selection and strength of coevolution between the virus and the host plants. The large diversity will therefore increase the ability to identify genetic resources, which are critical for effective breeding programs. Because the within-species variation has not been studied here our results may not be broadly applied to the species level.</p>
      <p>We have chosen a number of different traits for the experimental study of symptomatic response such as leaf chlorosis, plant height, shoot dry weight and leaf and tiller number. To our knowledge this is the first study which has investigated the response to WDV infection in wild and domesticated wheat by combining the analyses of leaf chlorosis, different growth traits and WDV content. Chlorosis and reduced growth are commonly associated with WDV infection in wheat and were therefore selected for the investigation of variation in response in wild and domesticated wheat. These symptoms are caused by large changes in cellular and developmental processes in the host plants, but the genetic and cellular mechanisms behind these changes are not well known. However, studies of geminiviruses have demonstrated that they interact with different plant proteins leading to a transition from normal host growth processes to altered metabolic pathways and defense responses ([<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] and references therein). These proteins are joined in different protein complexes. Some of these complexes are players in cellular processes known as RNA silencing. This antiviral response restricts the accumulation and movement of viruses within the plant. However, as a way to escape the RNA silencing defense the viruses have evolved RNA silencing suppressor proteins (RSS). Several RSSs have been described for geminiviruses [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], and recently two replication-associated proteins encoded by WDV were shown to suppress the RNA silencing system [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The RSSs are not only involved in antiviral defense, but are also affecting the growth and development of the plant by interfering with cellular processes regulated by RNA silencing [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. In another virus-plant interaction it was recently shown that the coat protein of the <italic>Cucumber mosaic virus</italic> (CMV; family <italic>Bromoviridae</italic>) and the encoded RNA silencing suppressor 2b protein repress the expression of chloroplast and photosynthesis related genes [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. This reduces the number of chloroplast thylakoid membranes and causes chlorosis in CMV infected tobacco leaves. A decrease of photosynthesis may in turn initiate respiration and other processes involved in the host plant defense [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Callose deposition of saccharide callose at the plasmodesmata channels in the cell walls is another defense response that restricts the cell-to-cell movement of viruses within the plant [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. At the same time the callose deposition may also delay photoassimilate export from the infected leaves and restrict phloem transportation followed by chlorophyll breakdown [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>].</p>
      <sec id="sec025">
        <title>Large variation in symptomatic response among accessions</title>
        <p>We found a large variation in response to WDV infection in the wild relatives of wheat in leaf chlorosis as well as the different growth traits. The response ranged from increased growth, to modest decrease of growth and no surviving plants. By combining the results from the various traits and time points with the analysis of WDV content we were able to obtain a more complete picture of the variation in response in the different wild and domesticated wheat taxa. Interestingly, the response also changed over time for some accessions, where the plants showed severe symptoms at an early developmental stage but milder symptoms at a later stage and continued to produce new leaves and tillers. We found three different plant response patterns over time (<xref rid="pone.0121580.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>). Several of the accessions of the wild species such as <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>umbellulata</italic>, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>triuncialis</italic>, <italic>Am</italic>. <italic>muticum</italic>, wild einkorn and durum wheat showed a continuous reduction in the number of tillers and leaves between the time points. The growth was also severely affected in <italic>T</italic>. <italic>urartu</italic> and no plants were alive at the second time point. Other accessions such as bread wheat, wild emmer and cultivated emmer wheat showed a weak response to the WDV infection at the first time point but a much stronger response at the end of the experiment. In fact, all plants of cultivated emmer wheat died before the end of the experiment. An opposite response was found in the accessions <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic>, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>cylindrica</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>searsii</italic>, where the plants were severely affected at the first measurement, but showed a relative increase in production of tillers and leaves at the later time point. This increase in production over time was even more pronounced in spelt wheat, where the number of leaves and tillers in exposed plants was higher in comparison with the production in the non-exposed plants. Increased growth of tillers has also been observed in WDV infected winter wheat [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and in BYDV infected oat and barley plants grown in field trials [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. It has been suggested that increased vegetative production in BYDV infected oat is the result from reduced grain sink strength [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], and reallocation of host resources [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Spike formation was noted in our study and a reduction in spike formation was found in almost all accessions infected with WDV (<xref rid="pone.0121580.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Table</xref>). However, the reduction was not more prominent in the accessions with no or less affected growth of leaves and shoots such as spelt wheat and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic>. The data of the spike formation have to, however, be treated with caution since some of the studied accessions, including winter bread wheat, may be vernalization-sensitive, producing fewer spikes when the seedlings of these accessions have not been exposed to lower temperatures.</p>
        <p>The remission of symptoms found in several <italic>Aegilops</italic> species and spelt wheat has also been observed in dicots infected with geminiviruses such as tobacco, cassava, <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, pepper, zucchini and melon [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. These decreases of symptoms are associated with a reduction of virus content triggered by the RNA silencing system. We observed medium to high levels of virus content in all studied accessions at 28 dpi. Due to large differences in plant morphology among wild and domesticated accessions and thereby difficulties in identifying the youngest leaves the WDV content was not investigated at the later time point. Sampling of leaves of different ages would most likely have caused a bias in the analysis. We could therefore not investigate if the decrease of symptoms in some <italic>Aegilops</italic> species was associated with a reduction in virus content in the plants. Interestingly, in a preliminary study of a collection of <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic> accessions kept at John Innes Centre, Norwich, UK, we observed a reduction of both symptoms and WDV content in some accessions between two different developmental stages. However, in the present study at 28 dpi the severity of symptoms in wild and domesticated wheat was not correlated with the WDV content. Plants with high virus content did not necessarily show strong reduction in growth or high levels of chlorosis. In fact, spelt wheat had the highest WDV content but showed the mildest symptoms among accessions, which may indicate some degree of tolerance against WDV. In addition, the remission of symptoms over time in <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic> and some other <italic>Aegilops</italic> species may likewise indicate tolerance. On the other hand, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>umbellulata</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>triuncialis</italic> showed very strong response in almost all traits even though they had the lowest WDV content among the studied accessions.</p>
        <p>The lack of correlation between WDV content and severity of symptoms in the different <italic>Aegilops</italic> and <italic>Triticum</italic> species may at first be surprising as one may expect that the rate and extent of the virus amplification and movement within the plant will influence the severity of symptoms. It has, however, been shown that even though the RSSs of plant-infecting viruses are involved in the induction of symptoms, symptom severity and virus accumulation are not necessarily correlated [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. The activity of the RSSs may have a stronger effect on the symptomatic responses than the virus content in the plant and may be one of the explanations to the lack of strong correlation between the severity of symptoms and WDV content in the <italic>Aegilop</italic>s and <italic>Triticum</italic> plants.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec026">
        <title>No impact of domestication on WDV resistance</title>
        <p>To test the hypothesis that domestication and human selection have had a negative impact on the resistance to WDV we compared the response between the two groups, domesticated wheats and their wild relatives. We found no strong evidence that the domesticated wheats suffered from more severe symptoms than the wild relatives. In fact, no significant difference in proportional reduction was found between wild and domesticated wheats for chlorosis and all growth traits except leaf number at dpi 28. These results suggest that the loss of genetic diversity expected by the domestication process and other bottlenecks such as natural hybridization and polyploidization events during wheat evolution have not resulted in a general increase in susceptibility to WDV infection. The reduced genetic diversity caused by these bottlenecks may have been compensated by the hybridization of the different ancestral genomes followed by duplication, resulting in new genetic diversity. In addition, the polyploid nature of tetraploid and hexaploid wheats enables buffering capacity and greater robustness against gene mutations. This allows for a rapid formation of new genetic variation and novel traits [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. However, the WDV content was significantly higher in the domesticated wheat group. This suggests that the virus amplification and/or movement within the plants in the domesticated group are higher than in the wild plant group. Virus encoded movement proteins (MPs) interact with host proteins to promote virus movement within the plant. Different host proteins have been identified at different subcellular locations and in different virus host-plant interactions ([<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] and references therein). In our study all plants have been infected with the same WDV strain. However, not much is known about host proteins interacting with plant virus MPs in grasses. The domesticated and wild wheat species studied differs in genome type and ploidy level. If this diverse plant material would harbor a variation in host proteins, one may ask if specific interactions between WDV and plant proteins could explain the difference in WDV content among the wild and domesticated species.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec027">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Our findings do not support the assumption that evolutionary processes such as natural hybridization followed by polyploidization and domestication have had a strong influence on the resistance to WDV in wheat. Instead other processes such as natural selection may have shaped the coevolutionary interaction between WDV and the wild wheat relatives in the Fertile Crescent and adjacent areas. The arms race involving differences in the intensity of selection imposed on the interaction between the virus and the different host plants has resulted in a variation in response to WDV. Variation in virulence and host susceptibility among populations, geographical regions and related species will create what Thompson [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>] has called geographic mosaics of coevolutionary hotspots with strong reciprocal selection and cold spots with relaxed selection. These selection mosaics have been seen in a wide range of species interactions [<xref rid="pone.0121580.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. The variation in susceptibility found among <italic>Aegilops</italic> and <italic>Triticum</italic> species is likely caused by an evolutionary response to variation in selection pressure on the interacting organisms&#x2014;host plants, virus and insect vector&#x2014;over time. The influence of the leafhopper vector on the evolution of this interaction is not known. However, the population density of the vector and its efficiency in transferring the virus to the different hosts may vary across sites and thereby further affect the intensity of selection.</p>
      <p>Moreover, we found that the accessions of the A genome donor, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>urartu</italic>, the putative B genome donor <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>speltoides</italic> and the D genome donor of bread wheat, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic>, showed different patterns of response to WDV. Both infected <italic>T</italic>. <italic>urartu</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>speltoides</italic> plants had a continuous reduction in growth, whereas <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic> displayed a remission of symptoms over time. Even though our results may not be broadly applied to a species level since only one accession of each ancestral species have been studied, our findings indicate that the susceptibility to WDV may be associated with the genome type and that <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic> may be useful as a genetic resource for the improvement of resistance to WDV in bread wheat. From the viewpoint of our results, we suggest further evaluation of different accessions of <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic>. In addition, it would be of interest to further investigate the potential of <italic>Aegilops</italic> species, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>cylindrica</italic>, <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>comosa</italic> and <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>searsii</italic>, as well as spelt wheat as genetic resources for the improvement of WDV resistance in wheat. For a more complete picture of the response to WDV, we propose that different traits associated to WDV infection will be investigated at different plant development stages.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec028">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121580.s001">
        <label>S1 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Studied accessions and their passport data.</title>
          <p>The passport data were obtained from the SINGER data base, 2009. <sup>a</sup>N/A = data not available</p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0121580.s001.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121580.s002">
        <label>S2 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Tukey&#x2019;s HDS test (pairwise comparisons) of WDV content in exposed plants in the studied species.</title>
          <p>Similar letters indicate no significant difference.</p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0121580.s002.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121580.s003">
        <label>S3 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Correlation between traits shown as coefficient of determination (R<sup>2</sup>).</title>
          <p>N-E = non-exposed plants, E = exposed plants, All = All samples (exposed and non-exposed plants).</p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0121580.s003.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121580.s004">
        <label>S4 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Average number of spikes in exposed and non-exposed plants of wild and domesticated species.</title>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0121580.s004.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank K. Lindsten and P. Waern for their advice and assistance during the leafhopper collection.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref001">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JKM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tellier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Plant-parasite coevolution: bridging the gap between genetics and ecology</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>367</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev-phyto-072910-095301">10.1146/annurev-phyto-072910-095301</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21513455?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21513455</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref002">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Strange</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Plant disease: a threat to global food security</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>116</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.phyto.43.113004.133839">10.1146/annurev.phyto.43.113004.133839</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 16078878?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16078878</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref003">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oerke</surname><given-names>E-C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Crop losses to pests</article-title>. <source>J Agric Sci</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>144</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>43</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S0021859605005708">10.1017/S0021859605005708</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref004">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henk</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madoff</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCraw</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Emerging fungal threats to animal, plant and ecosystem health</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>484</volume>: <fpage>186</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>194</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature10947">10.1038/nature10947</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22498624?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22498624</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref005">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Doebley</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaut</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>. <article-title>The molecular genetics of crop domestication</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>127</volume>: <fpage>1309</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1321</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2006.12.006">10.1016/j.cell.2006.12.006</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 17190597?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17190597</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref006">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sakuma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salomon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Komatsuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>The domestication syndrome genes responsible for the major changes in plant form in the Triticeae crops</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>738</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>749</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/pcp/pcr025">10.1093/pcp/pcr025</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21389058?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21389058</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref007">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DuVal</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Patterns and processes in crop domestication: an historical review and quantitative analysis of 203 global food crops</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>196</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>48</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2012.04253.x">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2012.04253.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22889076?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22889076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref008">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Laine</surname><given-names>A-L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burdon</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dodds</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thrall</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Spatial variation in disease resistance: from molecules to metapopulations</article-title>. <source>J Ecol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>99</volume>: <fpage>96</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>112</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2745.2010.01738.x">10.1111/j.1365-2745.2010.01738.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21243068?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21243068</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref009">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Laine</surname><given-names>A-L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Resistance variation within and among host populations in a plant&#x2013;pathogen metapopulation: implications for regional pathogen dynamics</article-title>. <source>J Ecol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>990</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1000</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.0022-0477.2004.00925.x">10.1111/j.0022-0477.2004.00925.x</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref010">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vacke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cibulka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Response of selected winter wheat varieties to wheat dwarf virus infection at an early growth stage</article-title>. <source>Czech J Genet Plant Breed</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref011">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vacke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cibulka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reactions of registered winter barley varieties to wheat dwarf virus infection</article-title>. <source>Czech J Genet Plant Breed</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>50</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref012">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lindblad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waern</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Correlation of wheat dwarf incidence to winter wheat cultivation practices</article-title>. <source>Agric Ecosyst Environ</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>122</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0167-8809(01)00302-4">10.1016/S0167-8809(01)00302-4</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref013">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sirlova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vacke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chaloupkov&#xE1;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reaction of selected winter wheat varieties to autumnal infection with <italic>Wheat dwarf virus</italic></article-title><source>Plant Protect Sci</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref014">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benkovics</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vida</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Veisz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bedford</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silhavy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Partial resistance to <italic>Wheat dwarf virus</italic> in winter wheat cultivars</article-title>. <source>Plant Pathol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>1144</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1151</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3059.2010.02318.x">10.1111/j.1365-3059.2010.02318.x</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref015">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>K&#xF6;kl&#xFC;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Occurrence of cereal viruses on wheat in Tekirdag, Turkey</article-title>. <source>Phytoprotection</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>85</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7202/008902ar">10.7202/008902ar</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref016">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ekzayez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>First report of <italic>Wheat dwarf virus</italic> and its vector (<italic>Psammotettix provincialis</italic>) affecting wheat and barley crops in Syria</article-title>. <source>Plant Dis</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>76</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1094/PDIS-09-10-0628">10.1094/PDIS-09-10-0628</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref017">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Behjatnia</surname><given-names>SAA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Afsharifar</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tahan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Motlagh</surname><given-names>MHA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gandomani</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Widespread occurrence and molecular characterization of <italic>Wheat dwarf virus</italic> in Iran</article-title>. <source>Australasian Plant Pathol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>12</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>19</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s13313-010-0008-8">10.1007/s13313-010-0008-8</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref018">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vacke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Host plants range and symptoms of wheat dwarf virus</article-title>. <source>V&#x11B;d Pr V&#xFD;z &#xDA;stav&#xFA; Rostl V&#xFD;roby Praha-Ruzyn&#x11B;</source><year>1972</year>;<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>162</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref019">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lindsten</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vacke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gerhardson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>A preliminary report on three cereal virus diseases new to Sweden spread by <italic>Macrosteles</italic>- and <italic>Psammotettix</italic> leafhoppers</article-title>. <source>Natl Swed Inst Plant Protect Contr</source>. <year>1970</year>;<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>297</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref020">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vacke J. Some new findings on wheat dwarf virus. In: Blattn&#xFD; C, editor. Proceedings of the 5th conference of the Czechoslovak plant virologists. Prague, Czechoslovakia: Publishing House of the Czechoslovak Academy of Sciences, Prague, Czechoslovakia; 1964 pp. 331&#x2013;334.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref021">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ramsell</surname><given-names>JNE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lemmetty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jonasson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sigvald</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kvarnheden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sequence analyses of <italic>Wheat dwarf virus</italic> isolates from different hosts reveal low genetic diversity within the wheat strain</article-title>. <source>Plant Pathol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>57</volume>: <fpage>834</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>841</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3059.2008.01862.x">10.1111/j.1365-3059.2008.01862.x</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref022">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lindsten K, Lindsten B, Abdelmoeti M, Junti N. Purification and some properties of wheat dwarf virus. Proceedings of the 3rd conference on virus diseases of Gramineae in Europe, Rothamsted; 1980. pp. 27&#x2013;31.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref023">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Muhire</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Navas-Castillo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moriones</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zerbini</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A genome-wide pairwise-identity-based proposal for the classification of viruses in the genus <italic>Mastrevirus</italic> (family Geminiviridae)</article-title>. <source>Arch Virol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>158</volume>: <fpage>1411</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1424</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00705-012-1601-7">10.1007/s00705-012-1601-7</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23340592?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23340592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref024">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lindsten</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vacke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>A possible barley adapted strain of wheat dwarf virus (WDV)</article-title>. <source>Acta Phytopathol Entomol Hung</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>180</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref025">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kvarnheden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lindblad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lindsten</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valkonen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genetic diversity of <italic>Wheat dwarf virus</italic></article-title>. <source>Arch Virol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>147</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>216</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s705-002-8313-x">10.1007/s705-002-8313-x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 11858231?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11858231</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref026">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>K&#xF6;kl&#xFC;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramsell</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kvarnheden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The complete genome sequence for a Turkish isolate of <italic>Wheat dwarf virus</italic> (WDV) from barley confirms the presence of two distinct WDV strains</article-title>. <source>Virus Genes</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>366</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11262-006-0029-0">10.1007/s11262-006-0029-0</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 16927119?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16927119</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref027">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Melcher</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assessment of codivergence of Mastreviruses with their plant hosts</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-8-335">10.1186/1471-2148-8-335</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 19094195?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19094195</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref028">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boulton</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>King</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Donson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Point substitution in a promoter-like region and the V1 gene affect the host range and symptoms of maize streak virus</article-title>. <source>Virology</source><year>1991</year>;<volume>183</volume>: <fpage>114</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>121</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0042-6822(91)90124-T">10.1016/0042-6822(91)90124-T</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 2053276?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2053276</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref029">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boulton</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>King</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Markham</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pinner</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Host range and symptoms are determined by specific domains of the maize streak virus genome</article-title>. <source>Virology</source><year>1991</year>;<volume>181</volume>: <fpage>312</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>318</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0042-6822(91)90497-Y">10.1016/0042-6822(91)90497-Y</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 1994579?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1994579</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref030">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vacke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Wheat dwarf virus disease</article-title>. <source>Biol Plant Praha</source><year>1961</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>228</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>233</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref031">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Localization and distribution of wheat dwarf virus in its vector leafhopper, <italic>Psammotettix alienus</italic></article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>104</volume>: <fpage>897</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>904</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1094/PHYTO-09-13-0251-R">10.1094/PHYTO-09-13-0251-R</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 24502202?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24502202</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref032">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vuorinen</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelloniemi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valkonen</surname><given-names>JPT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Why do viruses need phloem for systemic invasion of plants?</article-title><source>Plant Sci</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>181</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>363</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.plantsci.2011.06.008">10.1016/j.plantsci.2011.06.008</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21889041?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21889041</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref033">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lindblad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sigvald</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Temporal spread of wheat dwarf virus and mature plant resistance in winter wheat</article-title>. <source>Crop Prot</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>234</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cropro.2003.08.011">10.1016/j.cropro.2003.08.011</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref034">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#xE4;fer-Pregl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klawan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castagna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Accerbi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borghi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Site of einkorn wheat domestication identified by DNA fingerprinting</article-title>. <source>Science</source><year>1997</year>;<volume>278</volume>: <fpage>1312</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1314</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.278.5341.1312">10.1126/science.278.5341.1312</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref035">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dubcovsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dvorak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genome plasticity a key factor in the success of polyploid wheat under domestication</article-title>. <source>Science</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>316</volume>: <fpage>1862</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1866</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1143986">10.1126/science.1143986</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 17600208?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17600208</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref036">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Zohary</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hopf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <source>Domestication of Plants in the Old World: the Origin and Spread of DomesticatedPplants in Southwest Asia, Europe, and the Mediterranean Basin</source>. <edition>4th ed.</edition><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref037">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>&#xD6;zkan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandolini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#xE4;fer-Pregl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salamini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>AFLP analysis of a collection of tetraploid wheats indicates the origin of emmer and hard wheat domestication in southeast Turkey</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1797</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1801</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a004002">10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a004002</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 12270906?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12270906</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref038">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dvorak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Terlizzi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Resta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>The evolution of polyploid wheats: identification of the A genome donor species</article-title>. <source>Genome</source><year>1993</year>;<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1139/g93-004">10.1139/g93-004</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18469969?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18469969</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref039">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>Bailey L</given-names></name><article-title>The origin of the A genome donor of wheats (<italic>Triticum</italic>: Poaceae)&#x2014;a perspective based on the sequence variation of the 5S DNA gene units</article-title>. <source>Genet Resour Crop Evol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>196</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/b:gres.0000020861.96294.f4">10.1023/b:gres.0000020861.96294.f4</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref040">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Salse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chague</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bolot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Magdelenat</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huneau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pont</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>New insights into the origin of the B genome of hexaploid wheat: evolutionary relationships at the <italic>SPA</italic> genomic region with the S genome of the diploid relative <italic>Aegilops speltoides</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-9-555">10.1186/1471-2164-9-555</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 19032732?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19032732</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref041">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adderley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular evolution and nucleotide diversity of nuclear plastid phosphoglycerate kinase (PGK) gene in Triticeae (Poaceae)</article-title>. <source>Gene</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>533</volume>: <fpage>142</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>148</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.gene.2013.09.103">10.1016/j.gene.2013.09.103</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 24120623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24120623</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref042">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berthelsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships of <italic>Triticum</italic> and <italic>Aegilops</italic> and evidence for the origin of the A, B, and D genomes of common wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>82</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2006.01.023">10.1016/j.ympev.2006.01.023</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 16504543?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16504543</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref043">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dvorak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deal</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>You</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Borstel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dehghani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>The origin of spelt and free-threshing hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>J Hered</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>103</volume>: <fpage>426</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>441</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jhered/esr152">10.1093/jhered/esr152</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22378960?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22378960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref044">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Kilian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mammen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Graner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salamini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><chapter-title>Aegilops</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Kole</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Wild crop relatives: genomic and breeding resources</source>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-loc>; <year>2011</year> pp. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref045">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chantret</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sabot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bellec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laubin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Molecular basis of evolutionary events that shaped the hardness locus in diploid and polyploid wheat species (<italic>Triticum</italic> and <italic>Aegilops</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1033</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1045</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.104.029181">10.1105/tpc.104.029181</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 15749759?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15749759</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref046">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nevo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Domestication evolution, genetics and genomics in wheat</article-title>. <source>Molecular Breed</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>301</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11032-011-9608-4">10.1007/s11032-011-9608-4</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref047">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Haudry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cenci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ravel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bataillon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brunel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poncet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Grinding up wheat: a massive loss of nucleotide diversity since domestication</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1506</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1517</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msm077">10.1093/molbev/msm077</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 17443011?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17443011</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref048">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brenchley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spannagl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>GLA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>D'Amore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Analysis of the bread wheat genome using whole-genome shotgun sequencing</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>491</volume>: <fpage>705</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>710</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature11650">10.1038/nature11650</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23192148?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23192148</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref049">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Waines</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barnhart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biosystematic research in <italic>Aegilops</italic> and <italic>Triticum</italic></article-title>. <source>Hereditas</source><year>1992</year>;<volume>116</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>212</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1601-5223.1992.tb00143.x">10.1111/j.1601-5223.1992.tb00143.x</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref050">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Vorarbeiten zur monographischen Darstellung von Wildpflanzensortimenten: <italic>Aegilops</italic> L</article-title>. <source>Kulturpflanze</source><year>1980</year>;<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>180</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref051">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Van Slageren</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Wild Wheats: A monograph of <italic>Aegilops</italic> L. and <italic>Amblyopyrum</italic> (Jaub. &amp; Spach) Eig (Poaceae)</chapter-title><publisher-loc>Wageningen, The Netherlands</publisher-loc>; <publisher-name>Wageningen Agricultural University</publisher-name>; <year>1994</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref052">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karag&#xF6;z</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pilanali</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Polat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Agro-morphological characterization of some wild wheat (<italic>Aegilops</italic> L. and <italic>Triticum</italic> L.) species</article-title>. <source>Turk J Agric For</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>387</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>398</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref053">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moln&#xE1;r</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moln&#xE1;r-L&#xE1;ng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Utilisation of <italic>Aegilops</italic> (goatgrass) species to widen the genetic diversity of cultivated wheat</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>163</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>19</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10681-007-9624-y">10.1007/s10681-007-9624-y</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref054">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kanyuka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lovell</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mitrofanova</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>A controlled environment test for resistance to <italic>Soil-borne cereal mosaic virus</italic> (SBCMV) and its use to determine the mode of inheritance of resistance in wheat cv. Cadenza and for screening <italic>Triticum monococcum</italic> genotypes for sources of SBCMV resistance</article-title>. <source>Plant Pathol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>53</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>160</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.0032-0862.2004.01000.x">10.1111/j.0032-0862.2004.01000.x</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref055">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanyuka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Motteram</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kornyukhin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The use of conventional and quantitative real-time PCR assays for <italic>Polymyxa graminis</italic> to examine host plant resistance, inoculum levels and intraspecific variation</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>165</volume>: <fpage>875</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>885</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2004.01291.x">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2004.01291.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 15720699?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15720699</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref056">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown-Guedira</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klatt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genetic analysis of resistance to S<italic>oil-borne wheat mosaic virus</italic> derived from <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic></article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>169</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>176</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10681-009-9910-y">10.1007/s10681-009-9910-y</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref057">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zaharieva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monneveux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rivoal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valkoun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nachit</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluation of a collection of wild wheat relative <italic>Aegilops geniculata</italic> Roth and identification of potential sources for useful traits</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>119</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>38</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1017500728227">10.1023/A:1017500728227</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref058">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Laine</surname><given-names>A-L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Role of coevolution in generating biological diversity: spatially divergent selection trajectories</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>60</volume>: <fpage>2957</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2970</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jxb/erp168">10.1093/jxb/erp168</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 19528527?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19528527</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref059">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yazdkhasti E. <italic>Wheat dwarf virus</italic> interaction with ancestors of wheat. M. Sc. Thesis, Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, Uppsala, Sweden. 2012. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://stud.epsilon.slu.se/5117/1/Yazdkhasti_E_121204.pdf">http://stud.epsilon.slu.se/5117/1/Yazdkhasti_E_121204.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref060">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Characteristics of the microplate method of enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay for the detection of plant viruses</article-title>. <source>J Gen Virol</source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>483</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1099/0022-1317-34-3-475">10.1099/0022-1317-34-3-475</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 323416?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">323416</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref061">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fargette</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pinel-Galzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>S&#xE9;r&#xE9;m&#xE9;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lacombe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>H&#xE9;brard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Traor&#xE9;</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Diversification of <italic>Rice yellow mottle virus</italic> and related viruses spans the history of agriculture from the neolithic to the present</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e1000125</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000125">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000125</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18704169?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18704169</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref062">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stukenbrock</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>. <article-title>The origins of plant pathogens in agro-ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>46</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>100</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.phyto.010708.154114">10.1146/annurev.phyto.010708.154114</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18680424?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18680424</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref063">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pallas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garc&#xED;a</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>. <article-title>How do plant viruses induce disease? Interactions and interference with host components</article-title>. <source>J Gen Virol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>2691</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2705</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1099/vir.0.034603&#x2013;0">10.1099/vir.0.034603&#x2013;0</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21900418?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21900418</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref064">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hanley-Bowdoin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bejarano</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mansoor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Geminiviruses: masters at redirecting and reprogramming plant processes</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>788</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro3117">10.1038/nrmicro3117</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 24100361?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24100361</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref065">
        <label>65</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hohn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vazquez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>RNA silencing pathways of plants: silencing and its suppression by plant DNA viruses</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>1809</volume>: <fpage>588</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>600</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bbagrm.2011.06.002">10.1016/j.bbagrm.2011.06.002</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21683815?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21683815</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref066">
        <label>66</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <article-title>Replication-associated proteins encoded by <italic>Wheat dwarf virus</italic> act as RNA silencing suppressors</article-title>. <source>Virus research</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>190</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>39</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.virusres.2014.06.014">10.1016/j.virusres.2014.06.014</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 25016035?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25016035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref067">
        <label>67</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification of an RNA silencing suppressor encoded by a mastrevirus</article-title>. <source>J Gen Virol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>95</volume>: <fpage>2082</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2088</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1099/vir.0.064246&#x2013;0">10.1099/vir.0.064246&#x2013;0</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 24866851?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24866851</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref068">
        <label>68</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prokhnevsky</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gopinath</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dolja</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Viral RNA silencing suppressors inhibit the microRNA pathway at an intermediate step</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1179</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1186</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/gad.1201204">10.1101/gad.1201204</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 15131083?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15131083</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref069">
        <label>69</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eamens</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M-B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Viral small interfering RNAs target host genes to mediate disease symptoms in plants</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002022</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002022">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002022</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21573142?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21573142</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref070">
        <label>70</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ohki</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>. <article-title>Coat protein mutations in an attenuated <italic>Cucumber mosaic virus</italic> encoding mutant 2b protein that lacks RNA silencing suppressor activity induces chlorosis with photosynthesis gene repression and chloroplast abnormalities in infected tobacco plants</article-title>. <source>Virology</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>456&#x2013;457</volume>: <fpage>292</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>299</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.virol.2014.04.010">10.1016/j.virol.2014.04.010</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref071">
        <label>71</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roitsch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Plant physiology meets phytopathology: plant primary metabolism and plant&#x2013;pathogen interactions</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>58</volume>: <fpage>4019</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4026</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jxb/erm298">10.1093/jxb/erm298</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18182420?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18182420</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref072">
        <label>72</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Callose deposition at plasmodesmata is a critical factor in restricting the cell-to-cell movement of <italic>Soybean mosaic virus</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Reports</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>905</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>916</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00299-011-1211-y">10.1007/s00299-011-1211-y</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22200865?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22200865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref073">
        <label>73</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>E-J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Y-P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Callose deposition in the phloem plasmodesmata and inhibition of phloem transport in citrus leaves infected with &#x201C;<italic>Candidatus Liberibacter asiaticus</italic>&#x201D;</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>249</volume>: <fpage>687</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>697</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00709-011-0312-3">10.1007/s00709-011-0312-3</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21874517?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21874517</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref074">
        <label>74</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bisnieks</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eckersten</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sigvald</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effects on yield and components of yield in oats infected with BYDV-PAV at different growth stages</article-title>. <source>J Plant Dis Prot</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>116</volume>: <fpage>521</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>528</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/09064710500412497">10.1080/09064710500412497</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref075">
        <label>75</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boulton</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Catherall</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effect of increasing dosage of barley yellow dwarf virus on some resistant and susceptible barleys</article-title>. <source>Ann App Biol</source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>94</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>75</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1744-7348.1980.tb03897.x">10.1111/j.1744-7348.1980.tb03897.x</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref076">
        <label>76</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eckersten</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kvarnheden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Modelling influence of virus infection on leaf area and radiation use in oats under controlled climatic conditions</article-title>. <source>Acta Agric Scand</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>57</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/09064710500487895">10.1080/09064710500487895</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref077">
        <label>77</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Culver</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Padmanabhan</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Virus-induced disease: altering host physiology one interaction at a time</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>243</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.phyto.45.062806.094422">10.1146/annurev.phyto.45.062806.094422</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 17417941?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17417941</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref078">
        <label>78</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lemoine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>La Camera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Atanassova</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dedaldechamp</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allario</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pourtau</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Source-to-sink transport of sugar and regulation by environmental factors</article-title>. <source>Front Plant Sci</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>272</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2013.00272">10.3389/fpls.2013.00272</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23898339?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23898339</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref079">
        <label>79</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chellappan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vanitharani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pita</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fauquet</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Short interfering RNA accumulation correlates with host recovery in DNA virus-infected hosts, and gene silencing targets specific viral sequences</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>78</volume>: <fpage>7465</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7477</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JVI.78.14.7465&#x2013;7477.2004">10.1128/JVI.78.14.7465&#x2013;7477.2004</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 15220420?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15220420</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref080">
        <label>80</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Idris</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ostrow</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>French</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stenger</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genetic and phenotypic variation of the <italic>Pepper golden mosaic virus</italic> Complex</article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>95</volume>: <fpage>1217</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1224</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1094/PHYTO-95-1217">10.1094/PHYTO-95-1217</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18943475?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18943475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref081">
        <label>81</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Carrillo-Tripp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lozoya-Gloria</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rivera-Bustamante</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Symptom remission and specific resistance of pepper plants after infection by <italic>Pepper golden mosaic virus</italic></article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>97</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1094/PHYTO-97-0051">10.1094/PHYTO-97-0051</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18942936?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18942936</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref082">
        <label>82</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gilbertson</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Recovery from <italic>Cucurbit leaf crumple virus</italic> (family Geminiviridae, genus <italic>Begomovirus</italic>) infection is an adaptive antiviral response associated with changes in viral small RNAs</article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>98</volume>: <fpage>1029</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1037</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1094/PHYTO-98-9-1029">10.1094/PHYTO-98-9-1029</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18943741?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18943741</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref083">
        <label>83</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanville</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buchmann</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bisaro</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Viral genome methylation as an epigenetic defense against geminiviruses</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>82</volume>: <fpage>8997</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9007</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JVI.00719-08">10.1128/JVI.00719-08</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18596098?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18596098</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref084">
        <label>84</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodriguez-Negrete</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carrillo-Tripp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rivera-Bustamante</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>. <article-title>RNA silencing against geminivirus: complementary action of posttranscriptional gene silencing and transcriptional gene silencing in host recovery</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>83</volume>: <fpage>1332</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1340</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JVI.01474-08">10.1128/JVI.01474-08</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 19019951?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19019951</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref085">
        <label>85</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tsuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ohki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meshi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Pathogenicity of <italic>Pepper mild mottle virus</italic> is controlled by the RNA silencing suppression activity of its replication protein but not the viral accumulation</article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>97</volume>: <fpage>412</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>420</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1094/PHYTO-97-4-0412">10.1094/PHYTO-97-4-0412</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18943281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18943281</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref086">
        <label>86</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jay</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taconnat</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colot</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Misregulation of AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR 8 underlies the developmental abnormalities caused by three distinct viral silencing suppressors in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002035</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002035">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002035</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21589905?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21589905</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0121580.ref087">
        <label>87</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The geographic mosaic of coevolution</chapter-title><edition>1st ed.</edition><publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
