<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4397062</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25875107</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120691</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-42929</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Comparative Transcriptome Profiling of the Early Infection of Wheat Roots by <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic></article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Comparative Transcriptome of <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic></alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Lirong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xie</surname>
            <given-names>Lihua</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xue</surname>
            <given-names>Baoguo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Goodwin</surname>
            <given-names>Paul H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Quan</surname>
            <given-names>Xin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <given-names>Chuanlin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Taiguo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lei</surname>
            <given-names>Zhensheng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaojie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chao</surname>
            <given-names>Yueen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Chao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff001">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Institute of Plant Protection Research, Henan Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Henan Key Laboratory for Control of Crop Diseases and Insect Pests, IPM Key Laboratory in Southern Part of North China for Ministry of Agriculture, Zhengzhou, P. R. China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff002">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>School of Environmental Sciences, University of Guelph, Guelph, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff003">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Institute of Plant Protection, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing, P. R. China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff004">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line>Research Centre for Wheat, Henan Academy of Agricultural Science, Zhengzhou, P. R. China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff005">
        <label>5</label>
        <addr-line>Economic Crop Research Institute, Henan Academy of Agricultural Science, Zhengzhou, P. R. China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>Dongsheng</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Academic Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Beijing Institute of Microbiology and Epidemiology, CHINA</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LY BX. Performed the experiments: LY LX XQ CW ZL YC. Analyzed the data: LY LX XY. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: XQ CW CZ TL. Wrote the paper: PHG LY LX XY.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>xue@hnaa.org</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <elocation-id>e0120691</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Yang et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0120691.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Take-all, which is caused by the fungal pathogen, <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici (Ggt)</italic>, is an important soil-borne root rot disease of wheat occurring worldwide. However, the genetic basis of <italic>Ggt</italic> pathogenicity remains unclear. In this study, transcriptome sequencing for <italic>Ggt</italic> in axenic culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots was performed using Illumina paired-end sequencing. Approximately 2.62 and 7.76 Gb of clean reads were obtained, and 87% and 63% of the total reads were mapped to the <italic>Ggt</italic> genome for RNA extracted from <italic>Ggt</italic> in culture and infected roots, respectively. A total of 3,258 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were identified with 2,107 (65%) being 2-fold up-regulated and 1,151 (35%) being 2-fold down-regulated between <italic>Ggt</italic> in culture and <italic>Ggt</italic> in infected wheat roots. Annotation of these DEGs revealed that many were associated with possible <italic>Ggt</italic> pathogenicity factors, such as genes for guanine nucleotide-binding protein alpha-2 subunit, cellulase, pectinase, xylanase, glucosidase, aspartic protease and gentisate 1, 2-dioxygenase. Twelve DEGs were analyzed for expression by qRT-PCR, and could be generally divided into those with high expression only early in infection, only late in infection and those that gradually increasing expression over time as root rot developed. This indicates that these possible pathogenicity factors may play roles during different stages of the interaction, such as signaling, plant cell wall degradation and responses to plant defense compounds. This is the first study to compare the transcriptomes of <italic>Ggt</italic> growing saprophytically in axenic cultures to it growing parasitically in infected wheat roots. As a result, new candidate pathogenicity factors have been identified, which can be further examined by gene knock-outs and other methods to assess their true role in the ability of <italic>Ggt</italic> to infect roots.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nsfc.gov.cn/">http://www.nsfc.gov.cn/</ext-link>, (No.31401815) to YLR and Ministry of Science and Technology, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.most.gov.cn/">http://www.most.gov.cn/</ext-link>, &#x201C;The 12th Five-Year Plan&#x201D; National Technology Project in Rural Areas (Grant No. 2012BAD19B04) to XBG. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="5"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <page-count count="19"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta id="data-availability">
          <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
          <meta-value>All relevant data are included within the paper and its Supporting Information. Sequence data were deposited in the NCBI SRA database under the accession number SRP050157.</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability</title>
      <p>All relevant data are included within the paper and its Supporting Information. Sequence data were deposited in the NCBI SRA database under the accession number SRP050157.</p>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Global wheat production is severely affected by take-all, a major fungal disease that is caused by <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic> (<italic>Ggt</italic>), which can lead to yield losses of up to 40%-60% [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. <italic>Ggt</italic> is a necrotrophic pathogen infecting wheat roots via hyphae that can survive in the soil in root debris of wheat plants. <italic>Ggt</italic> hyphae penetrate root cortical cells causing a root rot and then progress into the base of the stem, disrupting water flow. The result is stunting and premature death of the plant with symptoms of white heads, empty spikes, reduced grain panicles and reduced grain weight. <italic>Ggt</italic> is highly invasive on wheat roots, but has a wide host range, including wheat, triticale, barley and rye [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120691.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Hence, considerable effort has been exerted to understand the mechanisms underlying <italic>Ggt</italic> pathogenicity to help reduce <italic>Ggt</italic>-caused wheat losses [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p>
      <p>The ability of a soil-borne fungus, like <italic>Ggt</italic>, to cause disease on roots is affected by many factors, such as how well it is able to colonize the root surface and infect roots with the use of extracellular enzymes, toxins, and effectors. In <italic>Ggt</italic>, some genes coding for extracellular enzymes have been linked to pathogenicity, such as laccases [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120691.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], endo-&#x3B2;-1,4-xylanase [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], &#x3B2;-1,3-glucanase [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], &#x3B2;-1,3-exoglucanase [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and gentisate 1,2-dioxygenase-like enzyme [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. For another soil-borne fungus, <italic>Fusarium</italic>, some genes encoding for proteins of the signaling pathway, such as mitogen-activated protein kinase [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], vacuolar Ca<sup>2+</sup> exchanger protein [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and plasma membrane calcium ATPase, have also been implicated in pathogenesis through recognition and signal transduction of extracellular signals [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</p>
      <p>The mechanisms of pathogenicity of <italic>Ggt</italic> to wheat roots are still not well understood as most research on wheat&#x2013;<italic>Ggt</italic> interactions has focused on biological characteristics of the disease [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], pathogen distribution [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], pathogen genetic diversity [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], and the use of antagonists [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. One approach to elucidating the mechanisms of fungal plant pathogenicity is to conduct large scale transcipt sequencing (RNA-seq analysis) of infected plant tissues. An advantage of RNA-seq is that the level of detection of transcript abundance enables broad measurements of expression levels of transcripts without prior sequence knowledge. Recent RNA-seq studies on plant-pathogen interactions include <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> infection of rice [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> infection of barley [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, there have not yet been any RNA-seq studies of <italic>Ggt</italic>-plant interactions. The present study is an RNA-seq examination of the transcriptomes of <italic>Ggt</italic> in axenic culture and <italic>Ggt</italic> in infected wheat roots using the Illumina GA IIx sequencing platform. This data was then used for de novo assembly of the reads into contigs, and then mapping the reads against the contigs to identify differentially expressed genes (DEGs) between the two conditions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="sec003">
        <title>Plant and fungal material and infection of roots</title>
        <p>An isolate of <italic>Ggt</italic> (GGT-007, Henan Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Zhengzhou, China) was isolated from wheat root samples, This strain was identified by morphological characteristics, pathogenicity and molecular identification according to the methods of Quan.et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] Liquid cultures were grown in potato dextrose broth at 25&#xB0;C with shaking at 180 rpm for 5 d to prepare inoculum for wheat root infection and <italic>Ggt</italic> RNA extraction.</p>
        <p>Seeds of winter wheat (<italic>Aestivum triticum</italic> cv 'Zhengmai 366') were placed in 75% ethanol for 5 s, rinsed with sterile water three times, surface sterilized with 1% AgNO<sub>3</sub> for 9 min, and then rinsed again with sterile water five times. The seeds were germinated in sterile Petri dishes (12 cm diameter) with sterile filter paper and 5 mL of sterile water. After one day, the germinated wheat seedlings were transferred to another sterile Petri dish with sterile filter paper (50 seedlings and 10 mL sterile water added per dish). After two days, the root lengths were 2 cm to 3 cm, and the seedlings were transferred to tissue culture vessels containing <italic>Ggt</italic> inoculum (5 mg mycelium in 5 mL potato dextrose broth). All plants were grown in 16 h day/8 h night at 22&#xB0;C.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec004">
        <title>Sampling and experimental design</title>
        <p>Root samples of the control group from two biological replicates were collected at 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 7, and 9 d after inoculation. The samples were immediately frozen and then stored in liquid nitrogen until analysis. Total RNA was extracted from these materials using RNAiso Plus (Total RNA extraction reagent) (TaKaRa, Otsu, Japan). RNA purity was verified using a NanoPhotometer spectrophotometer (Implen, Westlake Village, CA, USA). RNA concentration was measured using a Qubit RNA Assay Kit in a Qubit 2.0 Fluorometer (Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY, USA). RNA integrity was assessed using the RNA Nano 6000 Assay Kit of the Bioanalyzer 2100 system (Agilent Technologies, Wilmington, DE, USA).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec005">
        <title>Library construction and sequencing for RNA-seq</title>
        <p>Sequencing libraries were generated using 3 &#x3BC;g of RNA per sample with a NEBNext Ultra RNA Library Prep Kit for Illumina (NEB, Ipswich, MA, USA) following the manufacturer&#x2019;s recommendations, and tags were added to each sample for identification. Briefly, mRNA was purified from total RNA using poly-T oligo-attached magnetic beads. Fragmentation was performed using divalent cations under elevated temperature in NEBNext First Strand Synthesis Reaction Buffer (5&#xD7;). First-strand cDNA was synthesized using random hexamer primer and M-MuLV Reverse Transcriptase (RNase H-). Second-strand cDNA was synthesized using DNA polymerase I and RNase H. Remaining overhangs were converted into blunt ends via exonuclease/polymerase activities. After the adenylation of 3&#x2032; ends of DNA fragments, NEBNext Adaptor with hairpin loop structure was ligated to prepare for hybridization. To select cDNA fragments of preferentially 150 bp to 200 bp in length, the library fragments were purified with the AMPure XP system (Beckman Coulter, Beverly, MA, USA). Then, 3 &#x3BC;L of USER Enzyme (NEB, Ipswich, MA, USA) was used with size-selected, adaptor-ligated cDNA at 37&#xB0;C for 15 min and then at 95&#xB0;C for 5 min before PCR. PCR was performed with Phusion High-Fidelity DNA polymerase, Universal PCR primers, and Index (X) Primer. The PCR products were purified (AMPure XP System, Brea, CA, USA), and library quality was assessed on the Agilent Bioanalyzer 2100 system.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec006">
        <title>Clustering and sequencing and quality control</title>
        <p>The tag-coded samples were clustered on a cBot Cluster Generation System using the TruSeq PE Cluster Kit v3-cBot-HS (Illumia, San Diego, CA, USA) according to manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. After cluster generation, the library preparations were sequenced on an Illumina Hiseq 2000 platform to generate 100 bp paired-end reads were generated. Raw data (raw reads) of fastq format were initially processed through in-house PERL scripts provided by Novogene (China). In this step, the clean reads were obtained by removing adapter sequences, reads with more than 10% N, and low-quality sequences (more than 50% of the reads having aphred base sQ &#x2264; 5. The Q20, Q30, and GC contents of the clean data were calculated. All downstream analyses were based on the quality-trimmed clean data.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec007">
        <title>Read mapping to the reference genome</title>
        <p><italic>Ggt</italic> genome and gene model annotation files were directly downloaded from the genome website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ftp://ftp.ensemblgenomes.org/pub/release-20/fungi/fasta/gaeumannomyces_graminis/dna/">ftp://ftp.ensemblgenomes.org/pub/release-20/fungi/fasta/gaeumannomyces_graminis/dna/</ext-link>). Index of the reference genome was constructed using Bowtie v2.0.6 [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], and paired-end clean reads were aligned to the reference genome using TopHat v2.0.9 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tophat.cbcb.umd.edu/">http://tophat.cbcb.umd.edu/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] with all parameters set to their default values.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec008">
        <title>Differential expression analysis</title>
        <p>HTSeq v0.5.4p3 [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] was used to count the read numbers that were mapped to each gene. The Reads Per Kilobase of exon model per Million mapped reads (RPKM) of each gene was calculated based on the length of the gene and read counts that were mapped to this gene. RPKM simultaneously considers the effect of sequencing depth and gene length for the read counts, and it is currently the most commonly used method for estimating gene expression levels [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p>
        <p>Differential expression analysis between <italic>Ggt</italic> in culture and <italic>Ggt</italic> in infected wheat roots was performed using the DESeq R package (1.10.1) using a model based on the negative binomial distribution [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The resulting P-values were adjusted using the Benjamini and Hochberg&#x2019;s approach for controlling the false discovery rate. Genes with an adjusted P-value &lt;0.05 found by DESeq were assigned as differentially expressed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec009">
        <title>Gene Ontology (GO) and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) enrichment analysis, novel transcript prediction, and alternative splicing analysis</title>
        <p>GO enrichment analysis of DEGs was implemented by the GO seq R package [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], in which gene length bias was corrected. GO terms with corrected P value less than 0.05 were considered significantly enriched by DEGs. KEGG is a database resource for understanding high-level functions and utilities of the biological system [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], such as the cell, the organism, and the ecosystem, from molecular-level information, particularly large-scale molecular datasets generated by genome sequencing and other high-throughput experimental technologies (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/">http://www.genome.jp/kegg/</ext-link>). KOBAS software was used to test the statistical enrichment of DEGs in KEGG pathways. The Cufflinks v2.1.1 Reference Annotation Based Transcript assembly method was used to construct and identify both known and novel transcripts from TopHat alignment results. Alternative splicing events were classified into 12 basic types by Asprofile v1.0. The number of AS events in each sample was estimated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec010">
        <title>Quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) validation</title>
        <p>The expression levels of 12 DEGs were determined by qRT-PCR to confirm the results of mRNA-Seq analysis. Total RNA (1 &#x3BC;g) from <italic>Ggt</italic> culture (5 d after inoculation) and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots (1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 7, and 9 d after inoculation) was reverse transcribed using a PrimeScript RT reagent Kit with gDNA Eraser (Perfect Real Time) (Takara, Otsu, Japan) for RT-PCR according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s protocols. qRT-PCR was performed on the Step One Plus Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) with SYBR Premix Ex Taq (Tli RNaseH Plus, Takara, Otsu, Japan). The qRT-PCR conditions were as follows: 95&#xB0;C for 30 s and 40 cycles of 95&#xB0;C for 5 s and 60&#xB0;C for 5 s. Then, melting curves were generated. The primers used in qRT-PCR for DEG validation are shown in <xref rid="pone.0120691.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>. Each plate was repeated thrice in independent runs for all reference and selected genes. Gene expression was evaluated by the 2<sup>-&#x394;&#x394; Ct</sup> method [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec011">
      <title>Results and Discussion</title>
      <sec id="sec012">
        <title>mRNA-Seq general data analyses</title>
        <p>RNA-seq expression profiling of <italic>Ggt</italic> was performed under two conditions: <italic>Ggt</italic> cultured in potato dextrose broth (PDB) and symptomatic <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots. For pure cultures of <italic>Ggt</italic> in PDB, the fungus was grown for 5 days as that is the time period used to prepare inoculum. Growing <italic>Ggt</italic> for longer periods in PDB does not increase the level of disease when hyphae is used to inoculated plants. The samples for <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots were chosen at 7 days post-inoculation when symptoms of root rot were prevalent but tissue damage was not so severe and so extraction of high quality RNA was still possible. One biological replicate with paired-end was sequenced for each condition. A total of 30,305,754 and 83,222,108 raw reads resulting in 26,172,744 and 77,645,702 clean reads were generated from the RNA of <italic>Ggt</italic> in culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots, respectively (<xref rid="pone.0120691.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The quality of each library was similar with 95.86% and 94.88% of the raw reads from the <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots having quality values of Q&#x2265;20 and error probabilities of 0.05 and 0.06, respectively. The GC contents were almost identical for the <italic>Ggt</italic> and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots (59.71% and 58.30%, respectively).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0120691.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120691.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Transcriptome statistics of cDNA libraries from 5 day old culture of <italic>Ggt</italic> and 7 day old <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0120691.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0120691.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample name</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Raw reads<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>1</sup></xref></th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clean reads<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>2</sup></xref></th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cleanbases<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>3</sup></xref></th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Error rate<xref rid="t001fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>4</sup></xref>(%)</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q20<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>5</sup></xref> (%)</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q30<xref rid="t001fn006" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>6</sup></xref> (%)</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC content<xref rid="t001fn007" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>7</sup></xref> (%)</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ggt</italic> culture</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30,305,754</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,172,744</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62G</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.62</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.83</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.71</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83,222,108</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77,645,702</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.76G</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.59</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.39</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t001fn001">
              <p><sup>1</sup> The numbers of original data sequence</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn002">
              <p><sup>2</sup> The filtered data sequence</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn003">
              <p><sup>3</sup><italic>Qphred</italic> = - 10<italic>log</italic><sub>10</sub>(<italic>e</italic>)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn004">
              <p><sup>4</sup> the sequence length multiplied by the number of sequencing</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn005">
              <p><sup>5</sup> The percentage of bases with a Phred value&gt;20</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn006">
              <p><sup>6</sup> The percentage of bases with a Phred value&gt;30</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn007">
              <p><sup>7</sup> The percentage of bases number of G and C</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>The sequenced reads were mapped to the <italic>Ggt</italic> genome. Among the transcripts from the <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots, up to 87% and 63%, respectively, of the total reads (52,345,488 and 155,291,404) were uniquely mapped to the <italic>Ggt</italic> genome, whereas only small proportions (0.19% and 0.13%) were mapped to multiple locations in the <italic>Ggt</italic> genome (<xref rid="pone.0120691.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Among the uniquely mapped reads, 94.5% were mapped to the genome over one exon, 5.1% over an intergenic region, and 0.4% over an intron. Reads mapped to intergenic regions occurred because some gene annotations were inadequate. All uniquely mapped reads were used to calculate reads per kilobase of exon model per million mapped reads (RPKM) values, which were used to normalize expression levels. Alternative splicing (AS) events had occurred for 24,498 uniquely mapped reads from the <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and 23,410 uniquely mapped reads from the <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat, and these were classified into 12 types using Asprofile v1.0 (<xref rid="pone.0120691.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). The largest AS event groups under both conditions were TSS (alternative 5&#x2019; first exon) and TTS (alternative 3&#x2019; last exon) events.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0120691.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120691.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Summary of mapping the sequenced reads to the <italic>Ggt</italic> genome from the 5 day old culture of <italic>Ggt</italic> and 7 day old <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0120691.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0120691.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Event of mapping</th>
                  <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Sample</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ggt</italic> culture</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total reads</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52,345,488</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155,291,404</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total mapped<xref rid="t002fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>1</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45,808,804 (87.51%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98,785,653 (63.61%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple mapped<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>2</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96,928 (0.19%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205,702 (0.13%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uniquely mapped<xref rid="t002fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>3</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45,711,876 (87.33%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98,579,951 (63.48%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Read-1<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>4</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,935,163 (43.81%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49,503,896 (31.88%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Read-2<xref rid="t002fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>5</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,776,713 (43.51%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49,076,055 (31.6%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reads map to '+'<xref rid="t002fn006" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>6</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,844,490 (43.64%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49,230,953 (31.7%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reads map to '-'<xref rid="t002fn007" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>7</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,867,386 (43.69%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49,348,998 (31.78%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-splice reads</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39,686,714 (75.82%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86,211,659 (55.52%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Splice reads</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,025,162 (11.51%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,368,292 (7.96%)</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t002fn001">
              <p><sup>1</sup>Total number of reads mapped on the <italic>Ggt</italic> genome</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t002fn002">
              <p><sup>2</sup>Total number of reads mapped to multiple locations in <italic>Ggt</italic> genome</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t002fn003">
              <p><sup>3</sup>Total number of reads mapped to uniquely locations in the <italic>Ggt</italic> genome</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t002fn004">
              <p><sup>4</sup> The two directions of the paired-end sequencing</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t002fn005">
              <p><sup>5</sup> The two directions of the paired-end sequencing</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t002fn006">
              <p><sup>6</sup>Total number of reads mapped to positive strand of <italic>Ggt</italic> genome</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t002fn007">
              <p><sup>7</sup> Total number of reads mapped to negative strand of <italic>Ggt</italic> genome</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec013">
        <title>Identification of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) between <italic>Ggt</italic> growing in culture and wheat roots</title>
        <p>Log 2-fold DEGs between <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots were identified using DEG-Seq, and P-values were corrected by the Hochberg and Benjamini method [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Corrected P-value of 0.005 and log2 (fold change) &#xB1;1 were set as thresholds for significant differential expression. A total of 3,258 DEGs were detected between the <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and infected wheat root libraries, with 2,107 up-regulated genes and 1,151 down-regulated genes in the <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected roots compared to the <italic>Ggt</italic> culture (<xref rid="pone.0120691.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0120691.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120691.g001</object-id>
          <label>Fig 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Volcano of DEGs between <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots.</title>
            <p>Ggt: <italic>Ggt</italic>-culture, wheat: <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots; the y-axis corresponds to the mean expression value of log10 (p-value), and the x-axis displays the log2 fold change value. The red dots represent up-regulated DEGs, the blue dots represent down-regulated DEGs.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0120691.g001"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The DEGs were divided into three groups according the RPKM values as per Mortazavi et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Genes with RPKM values between 0 to 3 were considered to be expressed at a low level, 3 to 15 were at a medium level and above 15 were at a high level (<xref rid="pone.0120691.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The percentage of highly expressed genes was smaller in the control than in the <italic>Ggt</italic> samples, whereas the percentage of low-level expressed genes was larger in the <italic>Ggt</italic> culture than in the <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected root samples. The Pearson correlation coefficient for the replicates calculated by log<sup>10</sup> RPKM was 1 and between the <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and infected samples was 0.71, indicating reliable sequencing data (<xref rid="pone.0120691.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). A comparison of the RPKM distribution of the DEGs showed that the box plots of the log10 (RPKM+1) values and distribution of the density of the log10 (RPKM+1) values overlapped between the samples from the <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected roots indicating that the range of of the expression values in the two samples were generally similar, although there was a considerable spread in the expression levels of the DEGs (<xref rid="pone.0120691.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0120691.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120691.t003</object-id>
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Number of transcripts of <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots at different expression level intervals.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0120691.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0120691.t003"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Sample</th>
                  <th colspan="5" align="center" rowspan="1">RPKM level</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0~1</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1~3</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3~15</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15~60</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;60</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ggt</italic> culture</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4068(26.90%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2046(13.53%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4337(28.67%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2944(19.46%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1730(11.44%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3462(22.89%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1448(9.57%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3755(24.83%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4402(29.10%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2058(13.61%)</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t003fn001">
              <p>RPKM levels were chosen based on divisions described in [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Hierarchical clustering of the DEGs according to the log10 (RPKM+1) values showed the overall gene expression pattern to be divided into several clusters based on the expression levels of the DEGs in <italic>Ggt</italic> culture versus <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected roots conditions (<xref rid="pone.0120691.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Only one relatively small cluster contained DEGs with very high expression levels in both <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected roots, whereas all the other DEGs formed a second cluster with multiple subclusters mostly showing medium to low expression levels under both conditions or slightly higher expression under either the <italic>Ggt</italic> culture or <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected root conditions.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0120691.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120691.g002</object-id>
          <label>Fig 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Hierarchical clustering analyses of DEGs.</title>
            <p>According to the two sample&#x2019;s log10 (RPKM+1), red indicates high expression of the gene, blue indicates low expression of genes. Ggt: <italic>Ggt</italic>-cultures, Wheat: <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0120691.g002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec014">
        <title>Functional annotation and classification of DEGs</title>
        <p>The GOseq R package was used to annotate and assign different functional GO categories to the DEGs of <italic>Ggt</italic> in infected wheat roots. The 3,258 significant DEGs between the <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots (q-value &lt; 0.05) belonged to 9 GO groups based on biological process, 3 groups based on cellular component and 18 groups based on molecular function (<xref rid="pone.0120691.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). For biological process, the dominant categories were metabolism process (GO: 0008152) with 1,101 DEGs, single-organism metabolism (GO: 0044710) with 461 DEGs, oxidation-reduction processes (GO: 0055114) with 285 DEGs and carbohydrate metabolic processes (GO: 0005975) with 176 DEGs. For cellular component, the three categories were extracellular region (GO: 0005576) with 25 DEGs, external encapsulating structure (GO: 0030312) with 14 DEGs and cell wall (GO: 0005618) with 12 DEGs. For molecular function, the largest categories were general molecular function (GO: 0008152) with 1,733 DEGs, catalytic activity (GO: 0003824) with 1,099 DEGs, hydrolase activity (GO: 0016787) with.447 DEGs and transition metal ion binding (GO: 0046914) with 291 DEGs (<xref rid="pone.0120691.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0120691.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120691.g003</object-id>
          <label>Fig 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Functional annotation of DEGs based on gene ontology (GO) categorization.</title>
            <p>Each annotated sequence was assigned at least one GO term.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0120691.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The biological pathways of the DEGs of <italic>Ggt</italic> were mapped to the reference pathways in KEGG (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.ad.jp/kegg/">http://www.genome.ad.jp/kegg/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The DEGs between the <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots were assigned to 100 KEGG pathways (<xref rid="pone.0120691.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). The pathways with the most significant representation were general metabolic pathways (mgr01100) with 242 members and biosynthesis of secondary metabolites (mgr01110) with 100 members. These results indicate that fungal genes involved in the metabolism or biosynthesis of secondary metabolic pathways were being expressed more when the fungus was growing parasitically in wheat roots than growing saprophytically on culture medium, which may indicate an importance in the pathogenicity of <italic>Ggt</italic>.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0120691.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120691.g004</object-id>
          <label>Fig 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Statistics of KEGG pathway enrichment.</title>
            <p>The y-axis corresponds to KEGG Pathway, and the x-axis shows the enrichment factor. The color of the dot represent q value, and the size of the dot represents the number of DEGs mapped to the reference pathways.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0120691.g004"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec015">
        <title>Expression of selected DEGs</title>
        <p>qRT-PCR of 12 selected DEGs was performed to validate the RNA-seq data. Eleven were up-regulated DEGs and one was a down-regulated DEG between <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots (<xref rid="pone.0120691.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>). A comparison of the ratio of the qRT-PCR expression and RPKM values for the <italic>Ggt</italic> culture to the 7 day <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots revealed that these were basically consistent indicating that the RNA-seq data were credible (<xref rid="pone.0120691.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0120691.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120691.g005</object-id>
          <label>Fig 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Relative expressions of selected DEGs in <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots.</title>
            <p>The x-axis shows the sample: <italic>Ggt</italic> culture, and infected wheat roots at 1 day, 2 days, 3 days, 4 days, 5 days, 7 days and 9 days post infection.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0120691.g005"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0120691.t004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120691.t004</object-id>
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The ratio of the expression levels of 12 DGEs of 7 day old <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots to <italic>Ggt</italic> 5 days in culture as determined by qRT-PCR versus RPKM values from RNA-seq.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0120691.t004g" xlink:href="pone.0120691.t004"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DEG number</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">qRT-PCR<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>1</sup></xref></th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RPKM<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>2</sup></xref></th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTG_06356</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTG_10325</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.06</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.64</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTG_03068</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTG_03357</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTG_11051</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTG_01138</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.92</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTG_03287</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.31</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.52</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTG_02124</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.65</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.20</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTG_02417</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTG_05722</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.11</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.62</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTG_02686</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.45</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTG_09200</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.87</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.31</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t004fn001">
              <p><sup>1</sup> qRT-PCR ratio was determined from the log2 of the<sup>&#x2212; &#x394;&#x394;</sup> CT values from the <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat root sample divided by that from the <italic>Ggt</italic> in culture</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t004fn002">
              <p><sup>2</sup> RPKM ratio determined by the log2 of the RPKM value from the <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots divided by that of the <italic>Ggt</italic> culture sample.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>qRT-PCR of the 11 selected up-regulated DEGs showed several patterns over the course of infection. Expression of GGTG_03357 (Adhesion and hyphal regulator 1), GGTG_06356 (Adenylate cyclase), GGTG_11051 (Calcium-binding protein) and GGTG_03068 (Protein scd2/ral3) were all relatively high at 1 day of the infection followed by much lower levels for the rest of the infection comparable to that of <italic>Ggt</italic> in culture. This indicates that these DEGs may be particularly important for penetration or establishing infection. Expression of GGTG_02124 (Glucan 1,3-beta-glucosidase), GGTG_02686 (Linoleate 9S-lipoxygenase), GGTG_05722 (Xyloglucan-specific endo-beta-1,4-glucanase), GGTG_09200 (Exopolygalacturonase B), GGTG_01138 (Scytalone dehydratase) and GGTG_03287 (Endo-1,4-beta-xylanase A) were more highly expressed late in the infection indicating roles in the later stages of root colonization. However, those DEGs did not all have the same pattern of change over time with some, like GGTG_02124 (Glucan 1,3-beta-glucosidase) and GGTG_01138 (Scytalone dehydratase), generally gradually increasing over time, while others, like GGTG_03287 (Endo-1,4-beta-xylanase A), being only be expressed for a limited time late in infection. Expression of GGTG_10325 (G2-specific protein kinase) was unique among the 11 selected up-regulated DEGs in that it remained relatively high throughout the infection compared to expression in culture, only slightly decreasing over time as the infection progressed. qRT-PCR of the one selected down-regulated DEG, GGTG_02417(Laccase-2), showed that its expression was relatively unchanged during infection with a slight decline in the mid-period of infection.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec016">
        <title>DEGs for signal transduction pathways</title>
        <p>The signal transduction pathway in plant pathogenic fungi is essential for surface recognition, adaptation to the host milieu, appresorium formation, infection establishment, and invasive growth [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Several DEGs were identified from the GO annotation or KEGG analyses related to Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling, cyclic AMP- protein kinase A (cAMP-PKA), and mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathways.</p>
        <p>Among the up-regulated DEGs related to the Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling pathway in <italic>Ggt</italic>- infected roots versus <italic>Ggt</italic> culture, there were two DEGs (GGTG_00202 and GGTG_02953) for vacuolar calcium ion transporter, three DEGs (GGTG_03594, GGTG_08053 and GGTG_08581) for calcium-transporting ATPase, two DEGs (GGTG_04060 and GGTG_08412) for calcium channel protein, and one DEG (GGTG_11051) for calcium-binding protein (<xref rid="pone.0120691.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>). In contrast, there was only one down-regulated DEG in the infected roots related to Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling (GGTG_02953) for vacuolar calcium ion transporter. Calcium ions are extremely important for signal transduction. Two important calcium mediators in eukaryotic cells are calmodulin and phosphatase, calcineurin. Calcineurin is required for fundamental biological events of pathogenic fungus, such as mating, morphogenesis and virulence [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Calcium transporters, such as vacuolar Ca<sup>2+</sup> exchanger (<italic>Vcx1</italic>), calcium-channel protein <italic>(Cch1</italic>), and plasma membrane calcium ATPase (<italic>Pmc1</italic>), are required for fungal virulence, supporting a role for calcium-mediated signaling in fungal pathogenesis [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. For example, a knockout of the <italic>Ggt Vcx1</italic> significantly decreased the pathogenicity of <italic>Ggt</italic> to wheat roots [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], a knockout of <italic>PmcA</italic> significantly reduced <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> virulence in invasive pulmonary aspergillosis of mice and a knockout of <italic>PmcA</italic> affected cation homeostasis and in cell wall integrity of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>fumigatus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. qRT-PCR of the DEG (GGTG_11051) for calcium-binding protein showed high expression early in infection (<xref rid="pone.0120691.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>). Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling may be more important for <italic>Ggt</italic> in infected roots than in <italic>Ggt</italic> culture because the fungus may need to identify and the change in the environment, particularly early in the infection when switching from saprophytic growth in the soil to parasitic growth inside wheat roots.</p>
        <p>Among the up-regulated DEGs related to the cAMP-PKA pathway in <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected roots versus <italic>Ggt</italic> in culture, there was one DEG (GGTG_02473) for guanine nucleotide-binding protein alpha-2 subunit, one DEG (GGTG_06356) for adenylate cyclase, and one DEG (GGTG_05905) for cAMP-independent regulatory protein. qRT-PCR analysis showed that GGTG_06356 expression peaked at 1 d post-infection, and then decreased to the level observed in <italic>Ggt</italic> culture (<xref rid="pone.0120691.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>). The key components of the cAMP&#x2014;PKA pathway include adenylate cyclase and regulatory and catalytic subunits of protein kinase A. Both small GTPase Ras and guanine nucleotide-binding protein alpha-2 subunit function upstream from the cAMP&#x2014;PKA pathway. Adenylate cyclase is activated by G&#x3B1; subunits in <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> and in the model filamentous fungus <italic>Neurospora crassa</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Once again, it appears that parasitic growth of <italic>Ggt</italic> may involve different signaling than saprophytic growth.</p>
        <p>For the MAPK pathway, there were 8 DEGs up-regulated for eight key enzymes in the pathway (KEGG PATH: mgr04011, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/">http://www.genome.jp/kegg/</ext-link>) in <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected roots versus <italic>Ggt</italic> culture. These were a DEG (GGTG_03068) for protein scd2/ral3, a DEG (GGTG_07051) for osmosensing histidine protein kinase, a DEG (GGTG_12416) for Rho guanine nucleotide exchange factor scd1, a DEG (GGTG_07905) for cytokinesis protein sepA, a DEG (GGTG_04689) for GTP-binding protein rho5, a DEG (GGTG_05786) for MAP kinase kinase kinase mkh1, a DEG (GGTG_10157) for MAP kinase kinase kinase wis4 and a DEG (GGTG_03934) for tyrosine-protein phosphatase pmp1. The MAPK pathway is highly conserved in eukaryotes from yeasts to humans [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120691.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In this pathway, MAP kinase kinases kinases (MAPKKK) first activate MAP kinase kinases (MAPKK), which then activate MAP kinases (MAPK). The MAPK pathway in several fungal pathogens are well known for transducing various extracellular signals in regulating cell growth, differentiation, and condition, which are important for fungal pathogenesis [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. qRT-PCR for GGTG_03068 showed that its expression was high at 1 d post-infection and then decreased to levels similar to that in <italic>Ggt</italic> cultures for the remainder of the infection (<xref rid="pone.0120691.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>). The scd2/ral3 protein has been shown to involved MAPK pathway in yeast during cell growth [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. This indicates that the <italic>Ggt</italic> scd2/ral3-honolog may be needed for extracellular signal transduction in early root infection, such as during penetration. However, like the other DEGs in the signal transduction pathway of <italic>Ggt</italic>, parasitic growth in roots is a complex process that involves numerous factors, and RNA-seq only indicates its involvement. Additional studies on molecular and proteomic analysis are required to validate these predictions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec017">
        <title>DEGs for development</title>
        <p>Several up-regulated DEGs were also found that have previously been related to development in fungal plant pathogens, some of which are directly linked to signaling pathways. There was one DEG for adhesion and hyphal regulator 1 (GGTG_03357), one DEG for scytalone dehydratase (GGTG_01138), one DEG for linoleate 9S-lipoxygenase (GGTG_02686), one DEG for DN24 (GGTG_03133), two DEGs for cyclophilin (GGTG_01246 and GGTG_06971), two DEGs for chitin synthase (GGTG 03012 and GGTG_14037), six DEGs for hydrophobin (GGTG_03085, GGTG_02383, GGTG_06272, GGTG_07637, GGTG_04864 and GGTG_08655), and six DEGs for phosphodiesterase (GGTG_01358, GGTG_01857, GGTG_03142, GGTG_06261, GGTG_10058 and GGTG_11065). Adhesion and hyphal regulator 1 is involved in cellular processes that are mediated through an iron-independent mechanism during development [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Scytalone dehydratase is an enzyme involved in the synthesis of dihydroxynapthalene-derived melanin, and it has been identified as a pathogenicity determinant of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>grisea</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Linoleate 9S- lipoxygenase of fungi may form specific oxylipins and participate in sporulation [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. DN24, which is associated with nitrogen starvation, was expressed during infection of <italic>Colletotrichum gloeosporioides</italic> and was needed for normal hyphal development [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Cylcophilins are related to the signaling molecule, calcineurin, and a cyclophilin of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>grisea</italic> was linked to pathogenicity, appressorial development and hyphal growth [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Different chitin synthase genes of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>oryzae</italic> had different effects on virulence, appressorium penetration, hyphal growth and conidiation during infection [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. A hydrophobin of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>girsea</italic> affected conidial production, conidial germination, appressorium formation and the ability to infect rice [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Phophodiesterases play roles in cAMP signaling affecting conidial morphology, cell wall integrity and pathogenicity of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>oryzae</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. qRT-PCR was performed for three DEGs related to fungal development. The DEG for adhesion and hyphal regulator showed high expression early in the infection indicating a role in penetration and infection establishment. In contrast, qRT-PCR of a scytalone dehydratase DEG and a linoleate 9S- lipoxygenase DEG showed that both were highly expressed late in the infection indicating that melanin and oxylipin synthesis is needed later in the infection process.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec018">
        <title>DEGs for plant cell wall degradation</title>
        <p>A total of 62 DEGs were related to plant cell-wall-degrading-enzymes (CWDEs) in this study (<xref rid="pone.0120691.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). There were 27 DEGs for cellulase, 12 for xylanase, 1 for xyloglucanase, 21 for glucosidase, 2 for pectinase and 1 for aspartic protease. CWDEs are needed for initial penetration, invasion within the host tissue and conversion of the host tissues into nutrients [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Plant cell walls are composed of pectin, cellulose, hemicelluloses and associated proteins [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Polygalacturonase can degrade pectin, which is the major sugar of the middle lamellae, resulting in rotting of the tissues, and an endopolygalacturonase was needed by <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> to grow in host tissue from the inoculation site [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Pectinesterase catalyzes the de-esterification of pectin into pectate and methanol and is also important in the virulence of <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Cellulase hydrolyzes the &#x3B2;-1, 4 glycoside bonds in the cellulose polymer and have been implicated in the virulence of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>cinerea</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The hemicellulase, endo-&#x3B2;-1, 4-xylanase, hydrolyzes the &#x3B2;-1, 4-linked polysaccharide backbone of xylan, which forms the major component of hemicellulose, and among the three xylanases of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>cinerea</italic>, xyn11A is required for full virulence to tomato [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. There are also a variety of proteins in plant cell walls with most having structural functions cross-linking in the cell wall, although some act in plant morphogenesis and development [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Aspartic proteases, possibly degrading some of structural proteins thus destabilizing cell wall integrity, have been implicated in the virulence of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>cinerea</italic>, although single and double gene knock-outs of five aspartic proteases did not affect pathogenicity [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. qRT-PCR of two CWDEs, endo-1,4-beta-xylanase A (GGTG_03287) and exopolygalacturonase B (GGTG_09200), showed that both had was relatively low expression in culture and during infection, except at 7 d post-infection (<xref rid="pone.0120691.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>). This indicates that thes CWDEs may only be needed late in infection by <italic>Ggt</italic>, perhaps because of a need to degrade pectin and hemicellulose to obtain nutrients or to weaken the wall to allow hyphal growth in the root. If correct, then particular CWDEs may have highly specialized functions in the infection process of <italic>Ggt</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec019">
        <title>DEGs for response to plant defense compounds</title>
        <p>Roots have a variety of defense mechanisms against fungal pathogens, such as pathogenesis-related proteins and cell wall strengthening [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Callose is a cell wall material composed of &#x3B2;-1,3-glucan produced in response to wounding, infection by pathogens and abiotic stresses, and it provides penetration resistance against pathogens [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Callose degradation occurs by 1, 3-&#x3B2;-glucanase, which has been shown to be secreted by <italic>Ggt</italic> to break down post-infectionally [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Lignin is composed of hydroxycinnamyl alcohols (or monolignols), coniferyl alcohol and sinapyl alcohol and also helps to strengthen plant cell walls against microbial degradation [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Gentisate 1, 2-dioxygenase-like enzymes may be involved in lignin degradation by causing oxidative ring-opening of protocatechuate allowing lignin derived aromatic compounds to be degraded to phenols [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Laccases can also participate in lignin depolymerization by oxidizing phenolic and non-phenolic components of lignin [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. There are three laccase genes (<italic>Lac</italic>1, <italic>Lac</italic>2, and <italic>Lac</italic>3) in the <italic>Ggt</italic> genome, and they play an important function in <italic>Ggt</italic> pathogenesis [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120691.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. In this study, two DEGs for laccase were up-regulated, while one was down-regulated. The DEGs associated with degradation of cell wall callose and lignin in this study imply a defense against plant defenses related to cell wall strengthening during <italic>Ggt</italic> growth inside wheat roots.</p>
        <p><italic>Ggt</italic> infection can induce the biosynthesis of phytoalexins in wheat [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The major phytoalexins in wheat are cyclic hydroxamic acids and 2.4-dihydroxy-7-methoxy-2H-1.4-benzoxazin-3(4H)-one [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120691.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporters are involved in limiting the sensitivity of the fungus to phytoalexins [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. ABC transporter can act as efflux pumps, providing resistance to a variety of metabolic poisons, such as when a phytoalexin enters the hyphae [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. There were 3 DEGs for ATP-binding cassette up-regulated in infected roots.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec020">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>This study is the first to analyze the transcriptome of <italic>Ggt</italic> and infected wheat root using Illumina platform. A comparison of <italic>Ggt</italic> in culture to that in roots showed that there were 3,258 2-fold DEGs, of which twice as many were up-regulated than down-regulated. Some of these DEGs have previously been shown to be closely related to <italic>Ggt</italic> pathogenicity, but many have not been previously associated with <italic>Ggt</italic> and are promising candidates for further investigation. To the best our knowledge, this study is the first to use Illumina deep sequencing technology to compare the entire transcriptome of <italic>Ggt</italic> growing saprophytically in culture to <italic>Ggt</italic> grwoing parasitically in wheat roots. qRT-PCR of a small number of the DEGs showed that expression can be very specific to certain times during the infection, and some DEGs may play specific roles either early or late in the disease.</p>
      <p>The use of fungal genomics and transcriptomics has started to make major contributions to identifying genes required for pathogenesis, such as those related to signaling, penetration, fungal nutrition and host colonization [<xref rid="pone.0120691.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The results of this study has contributed to advancing our knowledge of this pathosystem by revealing that <italic>Ggt</italic> preferentially expresses a considerable number of genes during parasitic growth in roots to signal changes in its environment as it colonizes the root, to combat host resistance mechanisms related to cell wall appositions and antimicrobial compounds, as well as to degrade the plant cell walls, possibly both for obtaining nutrients and allowing for growth of its hyphae through the root tissues. Ultimately, targeting these candidate virulence genes by further analysis, such as gene disruption, will result in a better understanding of these virulence mechanisms of <italic>Ggt</italic>, which may lead to improving its control resulting in higher yields of wheat and other crop hosts of <italic>Ggt</italic> worldwide</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec021">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0120691.s001">
        <label>S1 Fig</label>
        <caption>
          <title>The Pearson correlation coefficient between <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots calculated using log10-based RPKM.</title>
          <p>Ggt: <italic>Ggt</italic> culture, Wheat: <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0120691.s001.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0120691.s002">
        <label>S2 Fig</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Comparison of the RPKM distribution for DEGs between <italic>Ggt</italic> culture (<italic>Ggt</italic>) and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots (wheat).</title>
          <p>Fig.a: RPKM distribution with the y-axis displaying log10 (RPKM+1). Fig.b: RPKM density distribution with the x-axis displaying log10 (RPKM+1).</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0120691.s002.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0120691.s003">
        <label>S1 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>The primers used in this study.</title>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0120691.s003.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0120691.s004">
        <label>S2 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Alternative splicing (AS) events of <italic>Ggt</italic> culture and <italic>Ggt</italic>-infected wheat roots.</title>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0120691.s004.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0120691.s005">
        <label>S3 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>DEGs for signal transduction pathways, plant cell wall degradation and response to plant defense compounds.</title>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0120691.s005.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This work was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31401815) and Ministry of Science and Technology &#x201C;The 12th Five-Year Plan&#x201D; National Technology Project in Rural Areas (Grant No. 2012BAD19B04). We thank the anonymous referees and the editor for their comments and suggestions that helped improve the manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref001">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gutteridge</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Variation in the effects of take-all disease on grain yield and quality of winter cereals in field experiments</article-title>. <source>Pest Manag Sci</source>
<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>244</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12587875?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12587875</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref002">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Take-all of wheat</article-title>. <source>Physiol Mol Plant Path</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref003">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guilleroux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osbourn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Gene expression during infection of wheat roots by the &#x2018;take-all&#x2019; fungus <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Pathol</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>216</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1364-3703.2004.00219.x">10.1111/j.1364-3703.2004.00219.x</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20565610?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20565610</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref004">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Solel</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barash</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Cell wall-degrading enzymes produced by <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic> in vitro and in vivo</article-title>. <source>Physiol Mol Plant Path</source>
<volume>46</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>198</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref005">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>QM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buchenauer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Immunolocalization of 1, 3-&#x3B2;-glucanases secreted by <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic> in infected wheat roots</article-title>. <source>J Phytopath</source>
<volume>158</volume>: <fpage>344</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>350</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref006">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <chapter-title>Screening wheat take-all diease mutant by <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated genetic transformation</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name> (ed), <source>Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of Chinese Society for Plant Pathology</source>, <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>China Agricuture Press</publisher-name>: <fpage>555</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref007">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Litvintseva</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Cloning, characterization, and transcription of three laccase genes from <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic>, the take-all fungus</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>1305</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1311</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11872481?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11872481</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref008">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Daval</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lebreton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gazengel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boutin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guillerm-Erckelboudt</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sarniguet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The biocontrol bacterium <italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic> Pf29Arp strain affects the pathogenesis-related gene expression of the take-all fungus <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic> on wheat roots</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Path</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>839</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>854</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1364-3703.2011.00715.x">10.1111/j.1364-3703.2011.00715.x</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21726382?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21726382</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref009">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Edens</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goins</surname><given-names>TQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dooley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Purification and characterization of a secreted laccase of <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic></article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>3071</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3074</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10388705?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10388705</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref010">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Virulence and cellulolytic enzyme activity of isolates of <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic></article-title>. <source>Trans Br Mycol Soc</source>
<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>202</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref011">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>MAP kinases in fungal pathogens</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source>
<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>152</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11273677?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11273677</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref012">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arbabi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Mitogen-activated protein kinases</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Med</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>S74</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>S79</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11891407?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11891407</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref013">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kmetzsch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Staats</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sobrino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The vacuolar Ca<sup>2+</sup> exchanger Vcx1 is involved in calcineurin-dependent Ca<sup>2+</sup> tolerance and virulence in <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic></article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1798</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1805</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/EC.00114-10">10.1128/EC.00114-10</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20889719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20889719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref014">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dinamarco</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>FZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dos Reis</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramalho</surname><given-names>LNZ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Functional characterization of an <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> calcium transporter (PmcA) that is essential for fungal infection</article-title>. <source>PloS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e37591</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0037591">10.1371/journal.pone.0037591</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22649543?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22649543</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref015">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gosme</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lebreton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sarniguet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gilligan</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A new model for the pathozone of the take-all pathogen, <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic></article-title>. <source>Ann Appl Biol</source>
<volume>163</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>366</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref016">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Summarization of wheat take all and pathogenic fungi</article-title>. <source>J Henan Agricult Sci</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>134</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>137</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref017">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Analysis of simple sequence repeats in the <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic> genome and the development of microsatellite markers</article-title>. <source>Curr Genet</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1432</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>0983</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref018">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Elahe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soheila</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Younes</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mehrdad</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of some antagonistic bacteria in biological control of <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var <italic>tritici</italic> causal agent of wheat take-all disease in Iran</article-title>. <source>Afr J Micro Res</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>5165</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5173</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref019">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanamori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Minami</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Simultaneous RNA-Seq analysis of a mixed transcriptome of rice and blast fungus interaction</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e49423</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0049423">10.1371/journal.pone.0049423</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23139845?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23139845</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref020">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boddu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kruger</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muehlbauer</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Transcriptome Analysis of the Barley&#x2013;<italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> Interaction</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>417</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16610744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16610744</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref021">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>More powerful procedures for multiple significance testing</article-title>. <source>Stati Med</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>811</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>818</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 2218183?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2218183</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref022">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq</article-title>. <source>Nature Methods</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>621</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>628</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.1226">10.1038/nmeth.1226</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 18516045?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18516045</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref023">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okuno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The KEGG resource for deciphering the genome</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>D277</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>D280</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 14681412?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681412</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref024">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kmetzsch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Staats</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cupertino</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schrank</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The calcium transporter Pmc1 provides Ca<sup>2+</sup> tolerance and influences the progression of murine cryptococcal infection</article-title>. <source>FEBS J</source>
<volume>280</volume>: <fpage>4853</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4864</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/febs.12458">10.1111/febs.12458</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23895559?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23895559</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref025">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marchi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sorin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Induction of vacuolar Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase and H<sup>+</sup>/Ca<sup>2+</sup> exchange activity in yeast mutants lacking Pmr1, the Golgi Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>
<volume>454</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>186</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10431803?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10431803</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref026">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pinchai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Juvvadi</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fortwendel</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perfect</surname><given-names>BZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rogg</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Asfaw</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> P-type Golgi apparatus Ca<sup>2+</sup>/Mn<sup>2+</sup> ATPase PmrA is involved in cation homeostasis and cell wall integrity but is not essential for pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>472</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>476</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/EC.00378-09">10.1128/EC.00378-09</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20097742?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20097742</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref027">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kurnellas</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nicot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shull</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elkabes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Plasma membrane calcium ATPase deficiency causes neuronal pathology in the spinal cord: a potential mechanism for neurodegeneration in multiplesclerosis and spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>, <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>300</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15576480</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref028">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kays</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rowley</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baasiri</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borkovich</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Regulation of conidiation and adenylyl cyclase levels by the G&#x3B1; protein GNA-3 in <italic>Neurospora crassa</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>7693</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7705</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11003665?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11003665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref029">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Herskowitz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>MAP kinase pathways in yeast: for mating and more</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>80</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>197</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 7834739?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7834739</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref030">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Mitogen-activated protein kinases: specific messages from ubiquitous messengers</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2435</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2444</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10082509?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10082509</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref031">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mehrabi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Mitogen-activated protein kinase pathways and fungal pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1701</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1714</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17715363?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17715363</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref032">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thines</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>MAP kinase signalling pathway components and targets conserved between the distantly related plant pathogenic fungi <italic>Mycosphaerella graminicola</italic> and <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source>
<volume>46</volume>: <fpage>667</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>681</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.fgb.2009.06.001">10.1016/j.fgb.2009.06.001</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19520179?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19520179</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref033">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dickman</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yarden</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Serine/threonine protein kinases and phosphatases in filamentious fungi</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>117</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10328981?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10328981</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref034">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Askew</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sellam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Epp</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mallick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hogues</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mullick</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The zinc cluster transcription factor Ahr1p directs Mcm1p regulation of <italic>Candida albicans</italic> adhesion</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>940</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2010.07504.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2010.07504.x</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21299649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21299649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref035">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lundqvist</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hodge</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Basarab</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lindqvist</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Crystal structure of scytalone dehydratasea disease determinant of the rice pathogen, <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic></article-title>. <source>Structure</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>937</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 7866745?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7866745</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref036">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wennman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oliw</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Secretion of two novel enzymes, manganese 9S-lipoxygenase and epoxy alcohol synthase, by the rice pathogen <italic>Magnaporthe salvinii</italic></article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source>
<volume>54</volume>: <fpage>762</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>75</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1194/jlr.M033787">10.1194/jlr.M033787</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23233731?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23233731</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref037">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>CgDN24: a gene involved in hyphal development in the fungal phytopathogen <italic>Colletotrichum gloeosporioides</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiol Res</source>
<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>389</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>397</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16255144?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16255144</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref038">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Viaud</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balhad&#xE8;re</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic> cyclophilin acts as a virulence determinant during plant infection</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>917</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11971145?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11971145</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref039">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Different chitin synthase genes are required for various developmental and plant infection processes in the rice blast fungus <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Path</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002526</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref040">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rho</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>MHP1 a <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic> hydrophobin gene, is required for fungal development and plant colonization</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>1224</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16101997?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16101997</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref041">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Two phosphodiesterase genes, <italic>pdel</italic> and <italic>pdeh</italic>, regulate development and pathogenicity by modulating intracellular cyclic AMP levels in <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic></article-title>. <source>Plos One</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e17241</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0017241">10.1371/journal.pone.0017241</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21386978?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21386978</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref042">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weste</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1970</year>) <article-title>Extra-cellular enzyme production by various isolates of <italic>Ophiobolus graminis</italic> and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>graminis</italic> var. <italic>avenae</italic></article-title>. <source>J Phytopath</source>
<volume>67</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>204</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref043">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buchenauer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Cytochemistry of cell wall component alteration on wheat roots infected by <italic>Gaumonomyces graminis</italic> var <italic>tritici</italic></article-title>. <source>J Plant Dis Prot</source>
<volume>107</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>351</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref044">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Valette-Collet</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cimerman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reignault</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boccara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Disruption of <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> pectin methylesterase gene <italic>Bcpme1</italic> reduces virulence on several host plants</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>360</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>367</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12744465?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12744465</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref045">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>ten Have</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Kan</surname><given-names>JAL</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The endopolygalacturonase gene <italic>bcpg1</italic> is required for full virulence of <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1009</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1016</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 9768518?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9768518</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref046">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Urbanek</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zalewska-Sobczak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Multiplicity of cell wall degrading glycosidic hydrolases produced by apple infecting <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic></article-title>. <source>J Phytopath</source>
<volume>110</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref047">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Espino</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonz&#xE1;lez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The endo-&#x3B2;-1, 4-xylanase Xyn11A is required for virulence in <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16404950?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16404950</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref048">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cassab</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Plant cell wall proteins</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol</source>. <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>309</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15012236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012236</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref049">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>ten Have</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Espino</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dekkers</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Sluyter</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> aspartic proteinase family</article-title>. <source>Fung Genet Biol</source>
<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>65</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.fgb.2009.10.008">10.1016/j.fgb.2009.10.008</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19853057?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19853057</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref050">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Okubara</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paulitz</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Root defense responses to fungal pathogens: a molecular perspective</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>
<volume>274</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>226</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref051">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>H&#xFC;ckelhoven</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Cell wall&#x2014;associated mechanisms of disease resistance and susceptibility</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Phytopath</source>
<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>127</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 17352660?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17352660</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref052">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vanholme</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Demedts</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morreel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boerjan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Lignin biosynthesis and structure</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>153</volume>: <fpage>895</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>905</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.110.155119">10.1104/pp.110.155119</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20472751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20472751</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref053">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Characterizing the promiscuity of LigAB, a lignin catabolite degrading extradiol dioxygenase from <italic>Sphingomonas paucimobilis</italic> SYK-6</article-title>. <source>Biochem</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>6724</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6736</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/bi400665t">10.1021/bi400665t</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23977959?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23977959</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref054">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bourbonnais</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paice</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Oxidation of non-phenolic substrates: An expanded role for laccase in lignin biodegradation</article-title>. <source>FFEBS Lett</source>
<volume>267</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>102</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 2365094?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2365094</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref055">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Litvintseva</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Cloning, characterization, and transcription of three laccase genes from <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic>, the take-all fungus</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>1305</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1311</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11872481?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11872481</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref056">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guilleroux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osbourn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Gene expression during infection of wheat roots by the &#x2018;take-all&#x2019; fungus <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Pathol</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>216</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1364-3703.2004.00219.x">10.1111/j.1364-3703.2004.00219.x</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20565610?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20565610</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref057">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Niemeyer</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Copaja</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barr&#xED;a</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>The triticeae as sources of hydroxamic acids, secondary metabolites in wheat conferring resistance against aphids</article-title>, <source>Hereditas</source>
<volume>116</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>299</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref058">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schalchli</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hormazabal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guerrero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bensch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Antifungal activity of wheat root exudate extracts on <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic> growth</article-title>. <source>Soil Sci Plant Nut</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>337</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref059">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schoonbeek</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raaijmakers</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Waard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Fungal ABC transporters and microbial interactions in natural environments</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1165</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1172</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12423022?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12423022</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref060">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Waard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Significance of ABC transporters in fungicide sensitivity and resistance</article-title>. <source>Pestic Sci</source>. <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>275</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref061">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van De Wouw</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howlett</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Fungal pathogenicity genes in the age of 'omics'</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Pathol</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>507</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1364-3703.2010.00680.x">10.1111/j.1364-3703.2010.00680.x</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21535355?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21535355</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref062">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Isolation and variety identification of <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> causing wheat take-all in Henan Province</article-title>. <source>Acta Phytopath Sinica</source>
<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>146</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref063">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title>. <source>Nature Methods</source><volume>9</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>359</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.1923">10.1038/nmeth.1923</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22388286?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref064">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Differential gene and transcript expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments with TopHat and Cufflinks</article-title>, <source>Nature Prot</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>562</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>578</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref065">
        <label>65</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <source>HTSeq: Analysing high-throughput sequencing data with Python</source>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/002824">10.1101/002824</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref066">
        <label>66</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>DEGseq: an R package for identifying differentially expressed genes from RNA-seq data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>136</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>138</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp612">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp612</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19855105?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19855105</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref067">
        <label>67</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oshlack</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Gene ontology analysis for RNA-seq: accounting for selection bias</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>R14</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2010-11-2-r14">10.1186/gb-2010-11-2-r14</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20132535?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20132535</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref068">
        <label>68</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gotol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Itoh1</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>KEGG for linking genomes to life and the environment</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>480</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>484</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0120691.ref069">
        <label>69</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of Relative Gene Expression Data Using Real-Time Quantitative PCR and the 2<sup>&#x2212; &#x394;&#x394; CT</sup> Method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>408</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11846609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
