<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3769392</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-17024</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072915</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>AbaA Regulates Conidiogenesis in the Ascomycete Fungus <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Roles of AbaA in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Son</surname>
            <given-names>Hokyoung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Myung-Gu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Min</surname>
            <given-names>Kyunghun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Seo</surname>
            <given-names>Young-Su</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lim</surname>
            <given-names>Jae Yun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>Gyung Ja</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Jin-Cheol</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chae</surname>
            <given-names>Suhn-Kee</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Yin-Won</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Agricultural Biotechnology and Center for Fungal Pathogenesis, Seoul National University, Seoul, Republic of Korea</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Microbiology, Pusan National University, Busan, Republic of Korea</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Eco-friendly New Materials Research Group, Research Center for Biobased Chemistry, Division of Convergence Chemistry, Korea Research Institute of Chemical Technology, Daejeon, Republic of Korea</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff4">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Biochemistry, Paichai University, Daejeon, Republic of Korea</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Yun</surname>
            <given-names>Sung-Hwan</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Soonchunhyang University, Republic of Korea</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>lee2443@snu.ac.kr</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: HS MGK KM YSS SKC YWL. Performed the experiments: HS MGK KM JYL GJC JCK YWL. Analyzed the data: HS YSS JYL YWL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YSS JYL GJC JCK SKC YWL. Wrote the paper: HS YSS YWL.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>9</issue>
      <elocation-id>e72915</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Son et al</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p><italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> (teleomorph <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic>) is a prominent pathogen that infects major cereal crops such as wheat, barley, and maize. Both sexual (ascospores) and asexual (conidia) spores are produced in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. Since conidia are responsible for secondary infection in disease development, our objective of the present study was to reveal the molecular mechanisms underlying conidiogenesis in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> based on the framework previously described in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic>. In this study, we firstly identified and functionally characterized the ortholog of AbaA, which is involved in differentiation from vegetative hyphae to conidia and known to be absent in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. Deletion of <italic>abaA</italic> did not affect vegetative growth, sexual development, or virulence, but conidium production was completely abolished and thin hyphae grew from abnormally shaped phialides in <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutants. Overexpression of <italic>abaA</italic> resulted in pleiotropic defects such as impaired sexual and asexual development, retarded conidium germination, and reduced trichothecene production. AbaA localized to the nuclei of phialides and terminal cells of mature conidia. Successful interspecies complementation using <italic>A. nidulans</italic> AbaA and the conserved AbaA-WetA pathway demonstrated that the molecular mechanisms responsible for AbaA activity are conserved in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> as they are in <italic>A. nidulans</italic>. Results from RNA-sequencing analysis suggest that AbaA plays a pivotal role in conidiation by regulating cell cycle pathways and other conidiation-related genes. Thus, the conserved roles of the AbaA ortholog in both <italic>A. nidulans</italic> and <italic>F. graminearum</italic> give new insight into the genetics of conidiation in filamentous fungi.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) grant funded by the Korean government (MSIP) (No.2008-0061897). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="11"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> (teleomorph <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic>), a homothallic ascomycete fungus, is the major causal agent of head blight disease in wheat, barley, and rice as well as ear and stalk rot in maize worldwide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Leslie1">[1]</xref>. Severe epidemics of these diseases result in not only yield losses but also mycotoxicoses in both humans and livestock through the production of mycotoxins in infected crops <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Desjardins1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Marasas1">[3]</xref>. Both sexual (ascospores) and asexual (conidia) spores are produced in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, and ascospores are the primary inocula during the period of flowering <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Leslie1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Trail1">[4]</xref>. Ascospores of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> are produced and discharged from the perithecia, i.e., fruiting bodies, and the initial structures or associated hyphae of the perithecia are the survival structures for overwintering <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Sutton1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Guenther1">[6]</xref>. Conidia are produced from the sporodochia on infected crops and are responsible for secondary infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Guenther1">[6]</xref>. Moreover, modified conidia (chlamydospores or chlamydospore-like structures) are proposed to be other survival structures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Leslie1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Goh1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Nyvall1">[8]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Considering the importance of conidia and ascospores in the life cycle of <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, these biological processes should be precisely regulated temporally and spatially. To date, many genes related to various biological and biochemical functions have been known to be important for sexual development and virulence in <italic>F. graminearum</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Baldwin1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Bluhm1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Ding1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Han1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Hou1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Jenczmionka1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Li1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Lyse1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Rittenour1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Urban1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Yu1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Zhou1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Lin1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Lin2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Wang1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son2">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son3">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son4">[27]</xref>. However, there is scant information on conidiogenesis and little is known regarding the molecular mechanism of conidium production in this fungus. Most of the previously reported mutant phenotypes that are related to conidium production or morphogenesis seem to be derived from indirect effects of broken cellular homeostasis because most of the genes responsible for these mutant phenotypes have pivotal roles in major cellular processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Baldwin1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Li1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Rittenour1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son2">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Lee1">[28]</xref>. Recently, FgStuAp and Htf1 transcriptional regulators have been shown to be required for the formation of coniophores and phialides in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Lyse1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Zheng1">[29]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Many researchers have long tried to understand conidiogenesis in the model filamentous fungi <italic>Neurospora crassa</italic> and <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Clutterbuck1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Garnjobst1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Martinelli1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Miller1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Springer1">[34]</xref>. In <italic>A. nidulans</italic>, decades of research have provided an in-depth understanding of the genetic, molecular, and biochemical processes in asexual development; moreover, upstream development activators (UDAs) and the central development pathway (CDP) have been known to regulate conidiogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Etxebeste1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Adams1">[36]</xref>. Through <italic>fluffy</italic> mutant analysis, UDA genes have been characterized and their regulatory networks have been well formulated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Adams1">[36]</xref>. Downstream CDP proteins have stage-specific functions during conidiogenesis. BrlA and AbaA comprise the pathway required for differentiation from vegetative hyphae to conidia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Adams2">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Sewall1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Mirabito1">[39]</xref>. WetA also plays an important role in cell wall synthesis, which is related to conidium maturation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Marshall1">[40]</xref>. In addition, the sensory and regulatory roles of the velvet complex that affect differentiation have been well studied <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Etxebeste1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Bayram1">[41]</xref>. In phytopathogenic fungi, large-scale forward genetic approaches to find genes related to conidiation have been attempted, especially in <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Jeon1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Shi1">[43]</xref>. Furthermore, a recent genome-wide functional analysis of transcription factors and kinases of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> has broadly expanded our understanding of fungal biology including conidium production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Wang2">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son5">[45]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The aims of this study were to determine whether the conidiogenesis-related pathway of <italic>A. nidulans</italic> is conserved in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> and to identify the potential target genes for crop disease control. In this study, we successfully identified and functionally characterized the AbaA ortholog, which was previously considered as absent in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. We also studied the regulatory mechanisms of AbaA through transcriptomic analysis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Fungal strains and media</title>
        <p>The <italic>F. graminearum</italic> Z-3639 strain was used as the wild-type strain in this study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-ODonnell1">[46]</xref>, and the other transgenic mutants derived from this strain are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0072915-t001">Table 1</xref>. For genomic DNA (gDNA) isolation, each strain was inoculated in 5 ml of complete medium (CM) at 25&#xB0;C for 3 days on a rotary shaker (150 rpm). For fungal sporulation, conidia of all strains were induced on yeast malt agar (YMA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Harris1">[47]</xref> and in carboxymethyl cellulose (CMC) medium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Cappellini1">[48]</xref>. A minimal medium containing 5 mM agmatine (MMA) was used to evaluate trichothecene production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Gardiner1">[49]</xref>. The other media used in this study were made and used according to the <italic>Fusarium</italic> Laboratory Manual <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Leslie1">[1]</xref>. These wild-type and transgenic strains were stored in a 20% glycerol stock at &#x2212;80&#xB0;C.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0072915-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072915.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains used in this study.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0072915-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0072915.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source or reference</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z-3639</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> wild-type</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Bowden1">[75]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic> wild-type</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGSC<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hH1-GFP</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>hH1::hH1-gfp-hyg</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Hong1">[53]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mat1g</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>mat1-1-1::gen</italic>; <italic>hH1::hH1-gfp-hyg</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Hong1">[53]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mat1r</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>mat1-1-1::gen</italic>; <italic>hH1::hH1-rfp-hyg</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son1">[18]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>abaA</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>abaA::gen</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>abaA</italic>-g</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>abaA::gen; hH1::hH1-gfp-hyg</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AbaAc</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>&#x394;abaA::abaA-gfp-hyg</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AnAbaAc</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>&#x394;abaA::AnabaA-hyg</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AbaA-OE</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>abaA::gen- P<sub>ef1&#x3B1;</sub> -abaA</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AbaA-OE-g</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>abaA::gen- P<sub>ef1&#x3B1;</sub> -abaA; hH1::hH1-gfp-hyg</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AbaAcr</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>&#x394;abaA::abaA-gfp-hyg; hH1::hH1-rfp-gen</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>FGSC, Fungal Genetics Stock Center.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Nucleic acid manipulations, PCR primers, and DNA sequencing</title>
        <p>The gDNA was extracted as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Leslie1">[1]</xref>. Restriction endonuclease digestion, agarose gel electrophoresis, gel blotting, and DNA blot hybridization were performed in accordance with standard techniques <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Sambrook1">[50]</xref>. The polymerase chain reaction (PCR) primers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0072915.s003">Table S1</xref>) used for this study were synthesized by an oligonucleotide synthesis facility (Bionics, Seoul, Korea). DNA sequencing was performed with an ABI 3730xl DNA analyzer by Macrogen Inc. (Seoul, Korea), and the sequences were set against the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> Genome Database <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Wong1">[51]</xref> and the <italic>Fusarium</italic> Comparative Database at the Broad Institute (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/fusarium_graminearum">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/fusarium_graminearum</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RACE)-PCR</title>
        <p>We determined the <italic>abaA</italic> open reading frame (ORF) using RACE-PCR. A previously constructed cDNA library was used for the RACE-PCR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son1">[18]</xref>. Four fragments located around the <italic>abaA</italic> ORF were amplified with pPRN3-N-For/AbaA-RACE-7, AbaA-RACE-1/AbaA-RACE-4, AbaA-RACE-2/AbaA-RACE-3, and AbaA-RACE-5/pPRN3-N-Rev primers and then directly sequenced.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Genetic manipulations and fungal transformations</title>
        <p>A DNA construct for targeted gene deletion and complementation was amplified by the double-joint (DJ) PCR method, as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Yu2">[52]</xref>. Briefly, the 5&#x2032;- and 3&#x2032;-flanking regions of the <italic>abaA</italic> gene and a geneticin resistance cassette (<italic>gen</italic>) were amplified from Z-3639 and pII99, and fused by DJ PCR under the PCR conditions previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Hong1">[53]</xref>. To complement the <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutant, the DNA fragment carrying the native promoter and the <italic>abaA</italic> ORF was fused with green fluorescent protein gene (<italic>gfp</italic>), and the hygromycin resistance cassette (<italic>hyg</italic>) was amplified with pIGPAPA-sGFP F/HYG-F1 primers from the pIGPAPA vector <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Horwitz1">[54]</xref>. Fungal transformation was performed as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Han1">[12]</xref>.</p>
        <p>For interspecies complementation using <italic>A. nidulans abaA</italic> (<italic>AnabaA</italic>), the <italic>abaA</italic> ORF, which was amplified with AnAbaA-For/AnabaA-Rev hyg primers from the gDNA of <italic>A. nidulans</italic>, was fused with DNA fragments amplified from gDNA of the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> wild-type strain with AbaA-5F/AbaA-5R AnabaA and AbaA-3F/AbaA-3R primers, respectively. The <italic>hyg</italic> gene was amplified with pBCATPH-comp-3 R/Gen-for primers from the pBCATPH vector <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Kim1">[55]</xref>. The subsequent procedures for the third round of PCR and transformation were the same as for complementation using the <italic>abaA</italic> gene of <italic>F. graminearum</italic>.</p>
        <p>To generate mutants overexpressing <italic>abaA</italic>, the 5&#x2032;-end of <italic>abaA</italic> was amplified by primer pairs AbaA-5F/AbaA-5R OE and AbaA-3F OE/AbaA-3R OE, respectively. The <italic>gen-P<sub>ef1&#x3B1;</sub></italic> construct, containing the elongation factor 1&#x3B1; promoter (<italic>P<sub>ef1&#x3B1;</sub></italic>) from <italic>F. verticillioides</italic>, was amplified from pSKGEN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Lee2">[56]</xref> with Neo-for new/EF Pro-Rev new primers. Three amplicons were fused by DJ PCR as described above, and a final PCR product was amplified by the nested primers AbaA-5N and AbaA-3N OE.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Conidium production and morphology</title>
        <p>After each strain was incubated in 50 ml of CM for 72 h at 25&#xB0;C on a rotary shaker (150 rpm), mycelia of each strain were harvested and washed twice with distilled water. To induce conidiation, harvested mycelia were spread on YMA and incubated for 48 h at 25&#xB0;C under near UV light (wavelength: 365 nm, HKiv Import &amp; Export Co., Ltd., Xiamen, China), and then conidia were collected with distilled water, filtered through cheese cloth, washed, and resuspended in distilled water to 1&#xD7;10<sup>5</sup> conidia/ml. After inoculating a 10-&#xB5;l conidium suspension (1&#xD7;10<sup>5</sup> conidia/ml) of each strain in 5 ml of CMC and incubation for 72 h at 25&#xB0;C on a rotary shaker (150 rpm), the number of conidia produced was counted to measure conidium production with a hemocytometer (Superior, Marienfeld, Germany). For observation of conidium morphology, the conidia produced by each strain on YMA or CMC were harvested and differential interference contrast (DIC) images were obtained with a DE/Axio Imager A1 microscope (Carl Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Quantitative real time (qRT)-PCR</title>
        <p>Total RNA of the wild-type and &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic> strains were extracted from the vegetative stage at 72 h after inoculation in CM liquid, and then the cultures at 6 h and 12 h after asexual induction were extracted using an Easy Spin Total RNA Extraction Kit (iNtRON Biotech, Seongnam, Korea). First-strand cDNA was synthesized with SuperScriptIII reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). qRT-PCR was performed with a SYBR Green Supermix (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA) and a 7500 real-time PCR system (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). For normalization, the endogenous housekeeping gene cyclophilin (<italic>cyp1</italic>; Broad Institute ID: FGSG_07439.3) was used <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Lin1">[22]</xref>. The PCR assays were repeated three times with two biological replications. The threshold cycle (&#x394;<italic>C<sub>T</sub></italic>) value of gene expression was subtracted from the &#x394;<italic>C<sub>T</sub></italic> value of each sample to obtain a &#x394;&#x394;<italic>C<sub>T</sub></italic> value. The transcript level relative to the calibrator was expressed as 2<sup>&#x2212;&#x394;&#x394;<italic>CT</italic></sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Livak1">[57]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Fertility test, virulence test, and trichothecene analysis</title>
        <p>Mycelia grown on carrot agar for 5 days were mock-fertilized with 2.5% Tween 60 solution to induce sexual reproduction as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Leslie1">[1]</xref>. For outcrosses, mycelia of the female strain grown on carrot agar plates were fertilized with 1 ml of a male strain conidium suspension (1&#xD7;10<sup>6</sup> conidia/ml). After sexual induction, the fertilized cultures were incubated for 7 days under near UV light (HKiv Import and Export Co., Ltd.) at 25&#xB0;C.</p>
        <p>The virulence test was performed as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son1">[18]</xref>. In brief, 10 &#xB5;l of conidium suspension (1&#xD7;10<sup>5</sup> conidia/ml) was injected into a center spikelet of wheat cultivar &#x201C;Eunpamil&#x201D; head at midanthesis. Since <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutants did not produce conidia, the mycelia suspension was used for inoculation. After inoculation, inoculated plants were placed in a humidity chamber for 3 days and transferred to a greenhouse; then, head blight symptoms were checked after 18 days.</p>
        <p>Deoxynivalenol (DON) and 15-acetyldeoxynivalenol (15-AcDON) production from MMA was measured with a Shimadzu QP-5050 gas chromatograph-mass spectrometer (GC-MS, Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan) with a selected ion monitoring and quantified on the basis of the biomass produced by each strain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son1">[18]</xref>. Five agar blocks (diameter, 5 mm) from a 5-day-old CM agar of each strain were used for inoculation because <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutants were unable to produce conidia. The experiment was repeated three times.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Microscopic observation</title>
        <p>To observe localization of AbaA and histone H1 (hH1) in the nuclei, the mat1r strain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son1">[18]</xref> was fertilized with the AbaAc strain. Ascospores carrying both <italic>abaA-gfp-hyg</italic> and <italic>hH1-red fluorescent protein (rfp)-gen</italic> were selected using antibiotic resistance and confirmed by PCR. Localization was observed in cultures from CM, minimal medium (MM), and CMC. Chitin staining was conducted by adding Calcofluor white stock solution (10 mg/ml; Sigma, 18909) to mycelia samples on slide glasses as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son6">[58]</xref>. Microscopic observation was performed with a DE/Axio Imager A1 microscope (Carl Zeiss) using filter set 38HE (excitation 470/40; emission 525/50) for GFP, filter set 15 (excitation 546/12; emission 590) for RFP, and filter set 49 (excitation 356; emission 445/50) for Calcofluor white.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2i">
        <title>RNA sequencing and bioinformatic analysis</title>
        <p>RNA-sequencing libraries were created using the Illumina TruSeq&#x2122; RNA sample prep kit with no modifications to the standard low-throughput protocol. Sequencing was performed on an Illumina HiSeq2000 instrument using the reagents provided in the Illumina TruSeq PE Cluster kit V3-cBot-HS and the TruSeq SBS Kit-HS (200 cycles) kit. The data discussed in this publication have been deposited in NCBI's Gene Expression Omnibus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Wong1">[51]</xref> and are accessible through GEO Series accession number GSE 46133 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE46133">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE46133</ext-link>). The relative transcript abundance was measured in reads per kilobase of exon per million mapped sequence reads (RPKM) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Mortazavi1">[59]</xref>. The log<sub>2</sub> ratios of the RPKM values were used to identify differentially expressed genes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2j">
        <title>Promoter and pathway analysis</title>
        <p>All information on the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> sequences and annotation were obtained from the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> Genome Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mips.helmholtz-muenchen.de/genre/proj/FGDB/">http://mips.helmholtz-muenchen.de/genre/proj/FGDB/</ext-link>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Wong1">[51]</xref>. Resource version 32 (<ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftpmips.gsf.de/fungi/FGDB/v32/">ftp://ftpmips.gsf.de/fungi/FGDB/v32/</ext-link>) was used for gene annotation. From this genome sequence and gene annotation, 500-bp upstream sequences were collected from all predicted genes and surveyed for finding CATTCY motifs in these regions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Andrianopoulos1">[60]</xref>. For the pathway analysis, the KEGG PATHWAY database was downloaded from the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/">http://www.genome.jp/kegg/</ext-link>) and then it was combined with RNA-sequencing data.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Identification of <italic>abaA</italic> in <italic>F. graminearum</italic></title>
        <p>Previous analysis of fungal genomes for orthologs of developmental regulators known in <italic>A. nidulans</italic> to participate in conidiogenesis showed that AbaA and BrlA lack of orthologs in the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> genome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Fischer1">[61]</xref>. The BLASTp search of AbaA of <italic>A. nidulans</italic> (<italic>An</italic>AbaA) against the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> genome using the <italic>Fusarium</italic> Comparative Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/fusarium_graminearum">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/fusarium_graminearum</ext-link>) provided the FGSG_11851.3 locus encoding 111 amino acids (6% identity). Recently, the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> Genome Database <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Wong1">[51]</xref> re-annotated FGSG_11851.3 as FGSG_15794, which encodes 173 amino acids and contains a TEA/ATTS (IPR000818) DNA-binding domain. <italic>An</italic>AbaA also contains the TEA/ATTS (IPR000818) domain. Further sequencing analysis of the flanking regions of the FGSG_15794 locus and the RACE-PCR results indicated that some parts of FGSG_157941 and FGSG_11850 constitute a single gene (<italic>abaA</italic>) with an intron and that <italic>abaA</italic> encodes 783 amino acids with 20% identity to <italic>An</italic>AbaA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). The AbaA of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> contains a nuclear localization signal (NLS), whereas <italic>An</italic>AbaA does not have a detectable NLS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-NguyenBa1">[62]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). The AbaA sequence was deposited in the GenBank database <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Benson1">[63]</xref> as accession number KC825340. BLASTMatrix analysis result showed that AbaA is only conserved in the Eurodiales order and the Sordariomycetes class (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g001">Figure 1C</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0072915-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072915.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Identification and deletion of <italic>abaA</italic> in <italic>F.</italic>
<italic>graminearum</italic>.</title>
            <p>(A) Re-annotation of the <italic>abaA</italic> ortholog gene in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. cDNA sequencing analysis revealed an exact <italic>abaA</italic> open reading frame with an intron. (B) Comparison of AbaA orthologs between <italic>A. nidulans</italic> and <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. A schematic representation of the protein orthologs shows the location and alignment of conserved domains. The TAE and TEA/ATTS domains (IPR000818) predicted with InterProScan; NLS, nuclear localization signal predicted by using NLStradamus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-NguyenBa1">[62]</xref>. (C) Distribution of AbaA homologs in representative fungal species. The distribution image was constructed using the BLASTMatrix tool that is available on the Comparative Fungal Genomics Platform (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cfgp.riceblast.snu.ac.kr/">http://cfgp.riceblast.snu.ac.kr/</ext-link>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Park2">[74]</xref>. Pi, <italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic>; Pr, <italic>P. ramorum</italic>; Ps, <italic>P. sojae</italic>; Af, <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>; An, <italic>A. nidulans</italic>; Ao, <italic>A. oryzae</italic>; Pm, <italic>Penicillium marneffei</italic>, Hc, <italic>Histoplasma capsulatum</italic>; Bd, <italic>Blastomyces dermatitidis</italic>; Pb, <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic>; Fo, <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic>; Fv, <italic>F. verticillioides</italic>; Mo, <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic>; Pa, <italic>Podospora anserine</italic>; Nc, <italic>Neurospora crassa</italic>; Ca, <italic>Candida albicans</italic>; Kl, <italic>Kluyveromyces lactis</italic>; Sc, <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>; Cc, <italic>Coprinus cinereus</italic>; Cn, <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic>; Pc, <italic>Phanerochaete chrysosporium</italic>; nd, not detected. (D) Targeted deletion of the <italic>abaA</italic> gene. The <italic>abaA</italic> gene was deleted from the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> wild-type genome. Left panel, schematic representation of the homologous gene recombination strategy used to generate the <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutants. Right panel, Southern blot analysis. Sizes of the DNA standards used are indicated in kilobases to the left of the blot.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0072915.g001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Phenotypes of <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutants</title>
        <p>To investigate the function of <italic>abaA</italic>, we performed targeted gene deletion in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. The ORF of <italic>abaA</italic> was successfully replaced with <italic>gen</italic> by homologous recombination and confirmed by Southern blot analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g001">Figure 1D</xref>).</p>
        <p>Radial growth, sexual development, and virulence of <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutants were not significantly different compared to the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0072915-t002">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Inoculation of the &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic> hyphae suspension caused similar disease symptoms as that of the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g002">Figure 2D</xref>). To visualize nuclei during conidiophore formation <italic>in vivo</italic>, &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic>-g strains (&#x394;<italic>abaA::gen</italic>; <italic>hH1::hH1-gfp-hyg</italic>) were generated by an outcross between mat1g <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Hong1">[53]</xref> and &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic> strains. In <italic>F. graminearum</italic> conidiogenesis, the wild-type strain (hH1-GFP) initially produced phialides from the hyphae, and mature phialides continuously produced conidia with 2&#x2013;6 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Deletion of the <italic>abaA</italic> gene completely abolished conidium production in conidium induction media (CMC and YMA). In addition, <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutants produced extremely immature phialides with abnormal morphology. Although some phialides seemed to generate conidia at the beginning, they germinated and resulted in thin hyphae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0072915-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072915.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Phenotypic analyses of <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutants.</title>
            <p>(A) Mycelial growth of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains on complete media (CM). Pictures were taken 5 days after inoculation on CM. (B) Perithecium formation of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains on carrot agar. Pictures were taken 7 days after sexual induction from carrot agar. Scale bar&#x200A;=&#x200A;500 &#xB5;m. (C) Asci rosettes of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains. Imaging was performed 7 days after sexual induction. (D) Virulence on wheat heads. A center spikelet of each wheat head was injected with 10 &#xB5;l of a conidium suspension. Pictures were taken 21 days after inoculation. Values with different letters are significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) based on Tukey's test. Scale bar&#x200A;=&#x200A;20 &#xB5;m. WT, <italic>F. graminearum</italic> wild-type strain Z-3639; &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic>, <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutant; AbaA-OE, transgenic strain with the abaA promoter replaced with the <italic>ef1&#x3B1;</italic> promoter.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0072915.g002"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0072915-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072915.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Morphology of conidiophores of <italic>F.</italic>
<italic>graminearum</italic> strains.</title>
            <p>Morphology of conidiophores of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains in carboxymethyl cellulose (CMC) medium. Pictures were taken 1 to 3 days after conidium induction. Scale bar&#x200A;=&#x200A;10 &#xB5;m. WT, <italic>F. graminearum</italic> wild-type strain Z-3639; &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic>, <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutant; AbaA-OE, transgenic strain with the abaA promoter replaced with the <italic>ef1&#x3B1;</italic> promoter.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0072915.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0072915-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072915.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Mycelial growth and trichothecene production of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0072915-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0072915.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radial growth (mm)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biomass (mg/ml)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total trichothecenes (&#xB5;g/g)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">c</xref></td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160.0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,723</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>abaA</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,704</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AbaAc</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,112</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AnAbaAc</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,328</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AbaA-OE</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">**</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">694<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">**</xref></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>Radial growth was measured after a 4-day incubation on complete media (CM).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label>b</label>
              <p>Biomass was measured after a 3-day incubation in complete media (CM).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label>c</label>
              <p>DON and 15-AcDON concentrations were measured after a 7-day incubation in a minimal medium containing 5 mM agmatine.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt105">
              <label>**</label>
              <p>Asterisk indicates data differed significantly (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01) based on Tukey's test.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Complementation analysis</title>
        <p>For inter- and intra-species genetic complementations, the <italic>abaA</italic> ORF fused with <italic>gfp</italic> and the <italic>AnabaA</italic> ORF of <italic>A. nidulans</italic> driven by the <italic>abaA</italic> native promoter of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> were introduced into an <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutant resulting in AbaAc and AnAbaAc strains, respectively. All of the complemented mutants were confirmed with Southern hybridizations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0072915.s001">Figure S1</xref>). Conidium production of AbaAc complemented strains demonstrated that the AbaA-GFP fully functional for conidiogenesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g004">Figure 4</xref>). The interspecies-complemented AnAbaAc strains also completely restored defective conidiogenesis of the <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutants.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0072915-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072915.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Conidiation of <italic>F.</italic>
<italic>graminearum</italic> strains.</title>
            <p>Conidiation was measured by counting the number of conidia produced in 5-day-old carboxymethyl cellulose (CMC) cultures. ND, not detected; WT, <italic>F. graminearum</italic> wild-type strain Z-3639; &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic>, <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutant; AbaAc, &#x394;<italic>abaA-</italic>derived strain complemented with <italic>abaA</italic> of <italic>F. graminearum</italic>; AnAbaAc, &#x394;<italic>abaA-</italic>derived strain complemented with <italic>abaA</italic> of <italic>A. nidulans</italic> (<italic>AnAbaA</italic>).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0072915.g004"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>AbaA-GFP localization</title>
        <p>To examine AbaA localization, the <italic>abaA-gfp</italic> fusion construct under the control of its native promoter was transformed into the <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutant for genetic complementation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0072915.s001">Figure S1A</xref>). To confirm nuclear localization of AbaA-GFP, the AbaAcr (&#x394;<italic>abaA::abaA-gfp-hyg</italic>; <italic>hH1-rfp-gen</italic>) strain was generated by an outcross between the mat1r <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son1">[18]</xref> and the AbaAc strains. AbaA-GFP in the AbaAcr strain colocalized with hH1-RFP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g005">Figure 5</xref>). The GFP signals were highly fluorescent in the nuclei of phialides and mature conidia. In mature conidia, AbaA-GFP highly accumulated in the nuclei of terminal cells. However, the GFP signals became blurred after the conidia began to germinate and were undetectable 6 h after germination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). The GFP signal was undetectable in mature ascospores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g005">Figure 5B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0072915-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072915.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Cellular localization of AbaA.</title>
            <p>AbaA was fused with green fluorescent protein (GFP), and histone H1 was fused with red fluorescent protein (RFP). (A) The GFP signals were highly fluorescent in the phialides (indicated with arrows) and maturing conidia (indicated with arrow heads). The GFP signals became blurred after germination. (B) The GFP signals were undetectable in mature ascospores. Scale bar&#x200A;=&#x200A;10 &#xB5;m.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0072915.g005"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title>Overexpression of <italic>abaA</italic></title>
        <p>We also generated <italic>abaA</italic> overexpression strains (AbaA-OE) in which <italic>abaA</italic> expression was under the control of a strong promoter, the <italic>ef1&#x3B1;</italic> promoter of <italic>F. verticillioides</italic>. Southern hybridization was performed to confirm the expected genetic manipulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). The <italic>abaA</italic> transcript level in wild-type and AbaA-OE strains was determined by qRT-PCR. In the wild-type strain, the <italic>abaA</italic> expression level was significantly upregulated at 6 h after conidium induction, which increased until 12 h. In the AbaA-OE strain, the transcript level was constitutively upregulated during conidiogenesis compared to the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g006">Figure 6B</xref>). <italic>abaA</italic> deletion completely abolished <italic>abaA</italic> transcript accumulation.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0072915-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072915.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Overexpression of <italic>abaA</italic>.</title>
            <p>(A) The <italic>abaA</italic> promoter was replaced with the <italic>ef1&#x3B1;</italic> promoter. The left and right panels show the strategy of AbaA-OE strain construction and Southern hybridization, respectively. The sizes of DNA standards (kb) are indicated on the left of the blot. (B) Relative transcript accumulation of <italic>abaA</italic> in wild-type, <italic>abaA</italic>-deleted, and <italic>abaA</italic>-overexpressed strains. The transcript level of <italic>abaA</italic> was analyzed by quantitative real time-PCR (qRT-PCR) during the conidium induction stage. WT, <italic>F. graminearum</italic> wild-type strain Z-3639; &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic>, <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutant; AbaA-OE, a transgenic strain with the <italic>abaA</italic> promoter replaced with the <italic>ef1&#x3B1;</italic> promoter.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0072915.g006"/>
        </fig>
        <p><italic>abaA</italic> overexpression mutants produced increased amounts of aerial mycelia and total biomass compared to the other strains (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0072915-t002">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Number of perithecia and total trichothecene (DON + 15-AcDON) production were reduced in AbaA-OE strains compared to the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0072915-t002">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g002">Figure 2B</xref>); furthermore, ascospore maturation was also delayed by one day (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). The virulence of AbaA-OE mutants was not significantly different from the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g002">Figure 2D</xref>). Moreover, AbaA-OE strains produced fewer numbers of conidia compared to the wild-type strain (0.1-fold), with extremely abnormal morphology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g007">Figure 7</xref>). Multiple phialides were induced from a single hyphal cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g007">Figure 7A</xref>). Many phialides of the AbaA-OE strains resembled abacus-like structures, and some cells near the end did not contain detectable nuclei (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g007">Figure 7C and D</xref>). Conidia produced from the AbaA-OE strains were multi-nucleated and were likely produced by abscission of abacus-like structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g007">Figure 7D and E</xref>). However, hyphal morphology and septation and nuclei distribution patterns were not markedly different between the wild type and AbaA-OE strains (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0072915.s002">Figure S2</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0072915-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072915.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Morphology of conidiophores of AbaA-OE strains.</title>
            <p>Pictures were taken 1 to 3 days after conidium induction from carboxymethyl cellulose (CMC) medium. Multiple phialides were produced from a single hyphal compartment (A). Some phialides resembled abacus-like structures, and some cells near the end did not contain detectable nuclei (B&#x2013;D). (E) Conidia produced from AbaA-OE strains (E). Cells that did not contain detectable nuclei and mature conidia resembling abacus-like structures are indicated by white arrows and arrow heads, respectively. Scale bar&#x200A;=&#x200A;20 &#xB5;m.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0072915.g007"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Overexpression of <italic>abaA</italic> led to a decrease in the germination rate. In the wild-type strain, 47% and 86% of conidia germinated 4 h and 6 h after incubation, respectively. In AbaA-OE mutants, approximately 10% of conidia germinated 4 h after incubation, and 46% of conidia germinated within 6 h of incubation in CM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g008">Figure 8</xref>). After incubation for 12 h, there was no significant difference in the germination rates between wild-type and <italic>abaA</italic> overexpression mutant strains.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0072915-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072915.g008</object-id>
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Germination rate of conidia.</title>
            <p>One ml of conidium suspension of each strain was incubated in 10 ml of complete medium (CM) at 25&#xB0;C on a rotary shaker (150 rpm). One hundred spores were observed in each examination with light microscopy, and the number of conidia that germinated was counted. All data were obtained from three biological replicates. Asterisks indicate data that significantly differed (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) based on Tukey's test. WT, <italic>F. graminearum</italic> wild-type strain Z-3639; AbaA-OE, a transgenic strain with the <italic>abaA</italic> promoter replaced with the <italic>ef1&#x3B1;</italic> promoter.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0072915.g008"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3f">
        <title>Genetic relationship between <italic>abaA</italic> and <italic>wetA</italic></title>
        <p>Since <italic>wetA</italic> is known to be a direct target gene of AbaA in <italic>Aspergilli</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Andrianopoulos1">[60]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Tao1">[64]</xref>, the transcript level of <italic>wetA</italic> homolog genes (FGSG_10166, 24% identity) was analyzed in the wild-type and <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutants. In the wild-type strain, the <italic>wetA</italic> expression level was significantly upregulated at 12 h after conidium induction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g009">Figure 9</xref>). However, the transcript level of <italic>wetA</italic> was similarly or constitutively downregulated during conidiogenesis in <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutants compared to the wild-type strain. In <italic>abaA</italic> overexpression mutant, transcript level of <italic>wetA</italic> was slightly increased compared to the <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutants.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0072915-g009" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072915.g009</object-id>
          <label>Figure 9</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Relative transcript accumulation of <italic>wetA</italic>.</title>
            <p>The transcript levels of <italic>wetA</italic> (FGSG_17727) were analyzed by quantitative real time-PCR (qRT-PCR) during the conidium induction stage in the wild-type, <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutant, and <italic>abaA</italic> overexpression mutant strains. WT, <italic>F. graminearum</italic> wild-type strain Z-3639; &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic>, <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutant; AbaA-OE, a transgenic strain with the <italic>abaA</italic> promoter replaced with the <italic>ef1&#x3B1;</italic> promoter.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0072915.g009"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3g">
        <title>Determination of AbaA-dependent pathways through transcriptomic analysis</title>
        <p>To understand the pathways regulated by AbaA, we obtained and analyzed the transcriptional profiles from RNA-sequencing data using two strains. We compared the &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic> mutants with the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> wild-type strain at three different time points (0 h, 6 h, and 12 h after induction of conidiogenesis). To identify the AbaA-regulated genes, differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were selected from 2.0-fold changes of RPKM values <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Mortazavi1">[59]</xref>. Based on this criterion, 3303 and 3579 genes were identified 6 h after and 12 h after induction of conidiogenesis, respectively. In addition, 946 genes were expressed in an AbaA-dependent manner both 6 h and 12 h after induction of conidiogenesis.</p>
        <p>For pathway analysis data downloaded from the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> KEGG database, 22 out of 101 pathways had at least two DEGs either 6 h or 12 h after induction of conidiogenesis. Most genes involved in these 22 pathways were upregulated (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0072915.s004">Table S2</xref>). In the beginning of conidiogenesis (6 h after induction), many genes involved in alanine, aspartate, and glutamate metabolism; glycolysis/gluconeogenesis and fatty acid pathways; and vitamin B6 metabolism were upregulated (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0072915.s004">Table S2</xref>). All annotated genes (7 out of 7) involved in fatty acid pathways were upregulated. At the end of conidiogenesis (12 h after induction), 9 and 7 genes involved in the cell cycle and DNA replication were upregulated, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0072915.s004">Table S2</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3h">
        <title>RNA sequencing-based expression patterns of core genes involved in conidiogenesis</title>
        <p>Due to successful complementation of <italic>A. nidulans</italic> AbaA in the &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic> mutant, <italic>F. graminearum</italic> AbaA supposed to have shared features such as a conserved binding motif (CATTCY). Thus, we surveyed this binding motif in the upstream regions (&#x2212;500 to &#x2212;1 bp) of genes involved in conidiogenesis and AbaA-regulated genes. Five out of eight genes possibly involved as key regulators of condiogenesis have at least one motif in the surveyed upstream (promoter) regions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0072915.s005">Table S3</xref>). In the promoter regions of <italic>abaA</italic> and <italic>wetA</italic>, multiple binding sites were observed, which is similar to results found with <italic>A. nidulans</italic> and <italic>A. fumigatus</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Andrianopoulos1">[60]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Tao1">[64]</xref>. From the genome-wide survey of this binding motif, 30% (4156/13820) of genes were found to have this motif. Interestingly, genes that were more tightly regulated by AbaA as well as more abundantly expressed were more likely to have this motif. In the case of AbaA-regulated genes both 6 h and 12 h after induction of conidiogenesis, we found that 55.8% (29/52) of the genes had at least a 4-fold change and were greater than 7900 RPKM (an average expression per gene in this RNA-sequencing analysis) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g010">Figure 10</xref>). With the same criteria except for having at least a 2-fold change, 42.7% (91/213) of genes had this motif (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0072915.s006">Table S4</xref>). From this analysis, we found three putative AbaA target genes that were already known to be required for conidiation in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>: FgAxl2 (FGSG_10237), one kinase (FGSG_16988), and one transcription factor (GzHOME005; FGSG_16777) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Wang2">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son5">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Si1">[65]</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0072915-g010" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0072915.g010</object-id>
          <label>Figure 10</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Percentage of DEGs among AbaA binding motif-containing genes.</title>
            <p>All information on <italic>F. graminearum</italic> sequences and annotation was obtained from the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mips.helmholtz-muenchen.de/genre/proj/FGDB/">http://mips.helmholtz-muenchen.de/genre/proj/FGDB/</ext-link>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Wong1">[51]</xref>. From this genome sequence and gene annotation, 500-bp upstream sequences were collected from all predicted genes and surveyed for finding CATTCY motifs in these regions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Andrianopoulos1">[60]</xref>. DEGs between <italic>F. graminearum</italic> wild-type strain Z-3639 and <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutant were compared with genes having CATTCY motifs within 500-bp upstream sequences to calculate percentages of DEGs among CATTCY motifs -containing genes. DEG, differentially expressed genes; RPKM, reads per kilobase of exon per million.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0072915.g010"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Due to reports on cell cycle control via <italic>A. nidulans</italic> AbaA, we monitored the expression patterns of 53 genes involved in cell cycle pathways obtained from the KEGG database. We observed that 14 out of 53 genes were upregulated with a 1.7-fold change 12 h after induction of conidiogenesis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0072915.s007">Table S5</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In <italic>A. nidulans</italic>, conidiation begins with cessation of vegetative growth and with subsequent formation of the footcell and the stalk of the hyphal cell. After stalk elongation to some extent, a globular structure called the vesicle is formed at the stalk tip and then metulae are produced by multipolar budding from the vesicle. Two apical buds emerge from each mature metulae to become phialides. Finally, single-celled conidia are basipetally produced from the mature phialide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Etxebeste1">[35]</xref>. Like this, morphological transformations leading to a conidiophore include several steps of cessation of cell elongation/division and specialized cell differentiations in <italic>A. nidulans</italic>. Therefore, these processes require precise control of cell division and differentiation at the molecular level both in terms of time and location. Decades of genetic and biochemical studies have constructed genetic networks and have revealed the mechanistic roles of the factors required for conidiogenesis in the model filamentous fungus <italic>A. nidulans</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Etxebeste1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Adams1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Fischer1">[61]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Park1">[66]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Yu3">[67]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Compared to conidiation processes in <italic>A. nidulans</italic>, <italic>F. graminearum</italic> has a much simpler conidiogenesis system. <italic>F. graminearum</italic> directly produces a conidiogenous cell, i.e., a phialide, from the hyphae and continuously generates multiseptate conidia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Leslie1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Harris1">[47]</xref>. Since conidia are responsible for disease propagation and conidiation is a unique characteristic of fungal species, it has been hypothesized that conidiogenesis-related genes might be novel targets for disease control <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Guenther1">[6]</xref>. Therefore, the aim of this study was to elucidate the molecular mechanisms underlying conidiogenesis in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> based on the framework provided in the conidiation study in <italic>A. nidulans</italic>.</p>
      <p>In this study, we first found and characterized the functions of the <italic>abaA</italic> ortholog gene, which is known to be absent in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. AbaA is specifically required for morphogenesis and differentiation of phialides in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, similar to that in <italic>A. nidulans</italic>. The interspecies complementation assay additionally demonstrated that the molecular mechanisms of AbaA activity are also conserved in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> as they are in <italic>A. nidulans</italic>. AbaA predominantly localized to the nuclei of phialides and terminal cells of mature conidia. Overexpression and constitutive expression of <italic>abaA</italic> resulted in pleiotropic defects such as impaired sexual and asexual development and decreased conidium germination rate and trichothecene production. Furthermore, three putative AbaA target genes that were already known to be required for conidiation in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> were found <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Wang2">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son5">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Si1">[65]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The AbaA of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> has some conserved functions as those of other fungi in conidiogenesis. Abacus mutants (knockout mutants of <italic>abaA</italic>) of <italic>A. nidulans</italic> produce nearly normal conidiophores bearing stalk, vesicle, and metulae. However, abacus-like structures with properties of metulae are continuously formed from the metulae instead of normal phialides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Clutterbuck1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Sewall1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Mirabito1">[39]</xref>. Similarly, <italic>abaA</italic>-null mutants of <italic>A. fumigatus</italic> and <italic>Penicillium marneffei</italic> also show defects similar to those of <italic>A. nidulans</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Tao1">[64]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Borneman1">[68]</xref>. <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutants of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> produced impaired phialides, which failed to make conidia but instead made thin hyphae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Even though conidiophore structures of <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, <italic>Aspergilli</italic>, and <italic>P. marneffei</italic> are different from each other, AbaA has conserved roles in phialide formation and functions in these fungal species.</p>
      <p>Another distinct function of AbaA in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> conidiogenesis is as a regulator for cell division in conidia. Conidium maturation in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> requires specific cell differentiation processes, which inhibit filamentous growth but maintain cell elongation with appropriate septum formation and nuclear division inside of the conidium. <italic>abaA</italic> deletion resulted in failure of conidium formation from the phialide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g003">Figure 3</xref>), and <italic>abaA</italic> overexpression mutants delayed conidial germination in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g008">Figure 8</xref>). Moreover, AbaA proteins were highly accumulated in mature conidia and the terminal cells of conidia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0072915-g005">Figure 5</xref>). The terminal cells of conidia tend to preferentially germinate compared to intercalary cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Seong1">[69]</xref>. In addition, AbaA is well known as a cell cycle regulator in <italic>A. nidulans</italic> and <italic>P. marneffei</italic>, and an <italic>abaA</italic> mutation in <italic>A. nidulans</italic> caused disruption of G1 arrest of conidium initial cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Borneman1">[68]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Ye1">[70]</xref>. Furthermore, AbaA can regulate the cell cycle in the late stage rather than in the early stage of conidiogenesis. Taken together, we suggest that AbaA is required for maturation and dormancy of conidia in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> through cell cycle regulation.</p>
      <p>The presence of the AbaA ortholog gives new insights into the genetics of asexual spore formation in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. A previous comparative genomic analysis of conidiation-related regulators showed that the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> genome does not have AbaA and BrlA but does have FlbC, FlbD, FluG, and WetA orthologs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Fischer1">[61]</xref>. However, we found that the AbaA ortholog exists and that the AbaA-WetA pathway is also conserved in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. In the case of BrlA, we utilized the previously generated <italic>F. graminearum</italic> Transcription Factor Phenotype Database <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son5">[45]</xref> and found that a homolog of BrlA (GzBrlA, 17% identity) is not related to conidiation in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. This result is consistent with morphological differences of conidiophores between <italic>A. nidulans</italic> and <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. The <italic>A. nidulans</italic> conidiophore bears vesicles whereas that of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> does not; and BrlA is a key transcription factor required for vesicle formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Adams2">[37]</xref>. Moreover, deletion of the homologous genes of FlbC (GzC2H2047, 32% identity) and FlbD (GzFlbD, 35% identity) resulted in reduced and abolished conidiation in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Son5">[45]</xref>, suggesting that some UDAs might have conserved roles for conidiation in both <italic>A. nidulans</italic> and <italic>F. graminearum</italic>.</p>
      <p>Some unexpected results of this study also suggest that there are considerable differences between <italic>A. nidulans</italic> and <italic>F. graminearum</italic> in mechanism of action of AbaA. In <italic>A. nidulans</italic> phialide cells, <italic>An</italic>AbaA both activates <italic>velB</italic> and <italic>vosA</italic> and resulting gene products represses <italic>brlA</italic> expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Park1">[66]</xref>. Since BrlA is a direct upstream regulator for <italic>abaA</italic> in BrlA-AbaA-WetA pathway, the amount of <italic>abaA</italic> mRNA started to be reduced 24 h after conidia induction and mostly disappear in conidia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Ni1">[71]</xref>. However, AbaA was highly accumulated in conidium terminal cells in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> indicating that additional functions of AbaA exist in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> conidia as mentioned above. Similarly <italic>abaA</italic> overexpression results in opposite phenotypic changes in <italic>A. nidulans</italic> and <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. Overexpression of <italic>AnabaA</italic> causes growth cessation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Mirabito1">[39]</xref> whereas AbaA-OE mutants showed excessive production of aerial mycelia and biomass. These differences seem to be firstly derived from lack of conserved genes between two fungi e.g. <italic>brlA</italic> and <italic>vosA</italic>. In addition, transcriptional rewiring might be the reason for these phenomena since orthologs of transcriptional factors can participate in different transcriptional regulations because of variable <italic>Cis</italic>-regulatory elements <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Tuch1">[72]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0072915-Gasch1">[73]</xref>. Our results from promoter analysis also support this hypothesis.</p>
      <p>Although there are distinct morphological differences between conidiophores of <italic>A. nidulans</italic> and <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, AbaA has conserved roles for phialide formation and function in both fungi. As a key cell cycle regulator during conidiation, AbaA is additionally required for conidium maturation and dormancy in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. Utilizing our previous phenome database and our current results, we suggest that homologs of FlbC and FlbD and the AbaA-WetA pathway have conserved roles for conidiation in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. Future work will focus on identifying other putative regulators related to conidiation in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> based on <italic>A. nidulans</italic> studies, allowing us to construct genetic networks underlying conidiogenesis in this fungus.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0072915.s001">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Complementation of </bold><bold><italic>abaA</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> Intra- (A) and interspecies (B) complementation of <italic>abaA</italic> in the <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutant. &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic>, <italic>abaA</italic> deletion mutant; AbaAc, &#x394;<italic>abaA-</italic>derived strain complemented with <italic>abaA</italic> of <italic>F. graminearum</italic>; AnAbaAc, &#x394;<italic>abaA-</italic>derived strain complemented with <italic>abaA</italic> of <italic>A. nidulans</italic> (<italic>AnabaA</italic>); <italic>gen</italic>, geneticin resistance gene cassette; <italic>hyg</italic>, hygromycin B resistance gene cassette. The sizes of DNA standards (kb) are indicated on the left of the blot.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0072915.s001.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0072915.s002">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Mycelial morphology of </bold><bold><italic>F. graminearum</italic></bold><bold> strains.</bold> Differential interference contrast (DIC) and fluorescent microscopic observations were conducted 1 day after inoculation in complete medium (CM). Chitin accumulation in hyphae was visualized with Calcofluor white (CFW) staining. WT, hH1-GFP strain; &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic>, &#x394;<italic>abaA</italic>-g strain; AbaA-OE, AbaA-OE-g strain. Scale bar&#x200A;=&#x200A;50 &#xB5;m.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0072915.s002.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0072915.s003">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Primers used in this study.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0072915.s003.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0072915.s004">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Distribution of AbaA-dependent genes in the pathway.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0072915.s004.xls">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0072915.s005">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>RNA sequencing-based expression patterns of core genes involved in conidiogenesis in the &#x394;</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>abaA</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> mutant strain.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0072915.s005.xls">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0072915.s006">
        <label>Table S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Differentially expressed AbaA-dependent genes (&gt;4-fold).</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0072915.s006.xls">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0072915.s007">
        <label>Table S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Expression patterns of genes involved in cell cycle pathways.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0072915.s007.xls">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Leslie1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leslie JF, Summerell BA (2006) The <italic>Fusarium</italic> laboratory manual. Ames, IA: Blackwell Pub.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Desjardins1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Desjardins</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular biology of <italic>Fusarium</italic> mycotoxins</article-title>. <source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><volume>119</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17707105</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Marasas1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marasas WFO, Nelson PE, Toussoun TA (1984) Toxigenic <italic>Fusarium</italic> species, identity and mycotoxicology. University Park, PA: The Pennsylvania State University Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Trail1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trail</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loranger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gadoury</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Physiological and environmental aspects of ascospore discharge in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic> (anamorph <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source><volume>94</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21156487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Sutton1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Epidemiology of wheat head blight and maize ear rot caused by <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Can J Plant Pathol</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>209</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Guenther1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guenther</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trail</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The development and differentiation of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic> (anamorph: <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>) during colonization of wheat</article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source><volume>97</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16389974</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Goh1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daida</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vujanovic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Effects of abiotic factors and biocontrol agents on chlamydospore formation in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> and <italic>Fusarium sporotrichioides</italic></article-title>. <source>Biocontrol Sci Technol</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>167</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Nyvall1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nyvall</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name> (<year>1970</year>) <article-title>Chlamydospores of <italic>Fusarium roseum</italic> &#x2018;Graminearum&#x2019; as survival structures</article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source><volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1175</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1177</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Baldwin1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A role for topoisomerase I in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> and <italic>F</italic>. <italic>culmorum</italic> pathogenesis and sporulation</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>23</volume>: <fpage>566</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20367465</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Bluhm1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bluhm</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flaherty</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J-R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dunkle</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title><italic>RAS2</italic> regulates growth and pathogenesis in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>627</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17555271</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Ding1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mehrabi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koten</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Transducin beta-like gene <italic>FTL1</italic> Is essential for pathogenesis in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>867</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>876</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19377037</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Han1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y-K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M-D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y-W</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A novel F-box protein involved in sexual development and pathogenesis in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>63</volume>: <fpage>768</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>779</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17302802</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Hou1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A mitogen-activated protein kinase gene (<italic>MGV1</italic>) in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> is required for female fertility, heterokaryon formation, and plant infection</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1119</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12423017</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Jenczmionka1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jenczmionka</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>L&#xF6;sch</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#xE4;fer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Mating, conidiation and pathogenicity of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>, the main causal agent of the head-blight disease of wheat, are regulated by the MAP kinase gpmk1</article-title>. <source>Curr Genet</source><volume>43</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12695848</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Li1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The <italic>HDF1</italic> histone deacetylase gene is important for conidiation, sexual reproduction, and pathogenesis in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>24</volume>: <fpage>487</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21138346</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Lyse1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lys&#xF8;e</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pasquali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Breakspear</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The transcription factor FgStuAp influences spore development, pathogenicity, and secondary metabolism in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>24</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20879840</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Rittenour1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rittenour</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Characterization of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> Mes1 reveals roles in cell-surface organization and virulence</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>45</volume>: <fpage>933</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18339563</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Son1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y-W</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>ATP citrate lyase is required for normal sexual and asexual development in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>48</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21237280</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Urban1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mott</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Farley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Fusarium graminearum MAP1</italic> gene is essential for pathogenicity and development of perithecia</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Pathol</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>347</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20569395</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Yu1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>J-A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>W-B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Functional analyses of heterotrimeric G protein G&#x3B1; and G&#x3B2; subunits in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology-(UK)</source><volume>154</volume>: <fpage>392</fpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Zhou1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y-E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mehrabi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J-R</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The <italic>CID1</italic> cyclin C-like gene is important for plant infection in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>47</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19909822</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Lin1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A putative transcription factor MYT1 is required for female fertility in the ascomycete <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e25586</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21984921</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Lin2">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A putative transcription factor MYT2 regulates perithecium size in the ascomycete <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e37859</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22649560</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Wang1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A novel transcriptional factor important for pathogenesis and ascosporogenesis in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>24</volume>: <fpage>118</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20795857</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Son2">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial carnitine-dependent acetyl coenzyme A transport is required for normal sexual and asexual development of the ascomycete <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1143</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22798392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Son3">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Differential roles of pyruvate decarboxylase in aerial and embedded mycelia of the ascomycete <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><volume>329</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22276936</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Son4">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y-W</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A novel gene, <italic>GEA1</italic>, is required for ascus cell wall development in the ascomycete fungus, <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology-(UK)</source><volume>159</volume>: <fpage>1077</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1085</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Lee1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K-W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title><italic>GzSNF1</italic> is required for normal sexual and asexual development in the ascomycete <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>116</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19028993</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Zheng1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A conserved homeobox transcription factor Htf1 is required for phialide development and conidiogenesis in <italic>Fusarium</italic> Species</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e45432</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23029006</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Clutterbuck1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Clutterbuck</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>1969</year>) <article-title>A mutational analysis of conidial development in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic></article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>63</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5366214</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Garnjobst1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Garnjobst</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tatum</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>A survey of new morphological mutants in <italic>Neurospora crassa</italic></article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>57</volume>: <fpage>579</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5583730</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Martinelli1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martinelli</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clutterbuck</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>A quantitative survey of conidiation mutants in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology-(UK)</source><volume>69</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Miller1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>The developmental genetics of asexual reproduction in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic></article-title>. <source>Semin Dev Biol</source><volume>1</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>219</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Springer1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Genetic control of fungal differentiation: The three sporulation pathways of <italic>Neurospora crassa</italic></article-title>. <source>BioEssays</source><volume>15</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8357339</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Etxebeste1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Etxebeste</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garzia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Espeso</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ugalde</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title><italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic> asexual development: making the most of cellular modules</article-title>. <source>Trends Microbiol</source><volume>18</volume>: <fpage>569</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21035346</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Adams1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wieser</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Asexual sporulation in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><volume>62</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9529886</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Adams2">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boylan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Timberlake</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title><italic>brlA</italic> is necessary and sufficient to direct conidiophore development in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>54</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3293800</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Sewall1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sewall</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mims</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Timberlake</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title><italic>abaA</italic> controls phialide differentiation in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>2</volume>: <fpage>731</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2152124</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Mirabito1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mirabito</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Timberlake</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Interactions of three sequentially expressed genes control temporal and spatial specificity in <italic>Aspergillus</italic> development</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>57</volume>: <fpage>859</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2655931</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Marshall1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Timberlake</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title><italic>Aspergillus nidulans wetA</italic> activates spore-specific gene expression</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1986246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Bayram1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bayram</surname><given-names>&#xD6;</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krappmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bok</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Helmstaedt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>VelB/VeA/LaeA complex coordinates light signal with fungal development and secondary metabolism</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>320</volume>: <fpage>1504</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18556559</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Jeon1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>M-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide functional analysis of pathogenicity genes in the rice blast fungus</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source><volume>39</volume>: <fpage>561</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17353894</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Shi1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Genetic analysis of sporulation in <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic> by chemical and insertional mutagenesis</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>949</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>959</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Wang2">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Functional analysis of the kinome of the wheat scab fungus <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002460</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22216007</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Son5">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A phenome-based functional analysis of transcription factors in the cereal head blight fungus, <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002310</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22028654</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-ODonnell1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tacke</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Casper</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Gene genealogies reveal global phylogeographic structure and reproductive isolation among lineages of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>, the fungus causing wheat scab</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>97</volume>: <fpage>7905</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7910</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10869425</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Harris1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Morphogenesis in germinating <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> macroconidia</article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source><volume>97</volume>: <fpage>880</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16457357</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Cappellini1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cappellini</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>1965</year>) <article-title>Macroconidium formation in submerged cultures by a non-sporulating strain of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source><volume>57</volume>: <fpage>962</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>966</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Gardiner1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Novel genes of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> that negatively regulate deoxynivalenol production and virulence</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1588</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19888824</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Sambrook1">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sambrook J, Russell DW (2001) Molecular cloning: a laboratory manual, 2nd ed. Cold Spring Harbor, NY: Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Wong1">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mannhaupt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>M&#xFC;nsterk&#xF6;tter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>FGDB: revisiting the genome annotation of the plant pathogen <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>39</volume>: <fpage>D637</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>D639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21051345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Yu2">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamari</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reyes-Dominguez</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Double-joint PCR: a PCR-based molecular tool for gene manipulations in filamentous fungi</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>973</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15465386</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Hong1">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>So</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Functional analyses of two syntaxin-like SNARE genes, <italic>GzSYN1</italic> and <italic>GzSYN2</italic>, in the ascomycete <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>47</volume>: <fpage>364</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20102747</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Horwitz1">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Horwitz</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ritter</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sandrock</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>A G protein alpha subunit from <italic>Cochliobolus heterostrophus</italic> involved in mating and appressorium formation</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>26</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10072317</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Kim1">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Putative polyketide synthase and laccase genes for biosynthesis of aurofusarin in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1701</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15811992</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Lee2">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Functional analyses of two acetyl coenzyme A synthetases in the ascomycete <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1043</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21666077</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Livak1">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2<sup>&#x2212;&#x394;&#x394;<italic>C</italic>T</sup> method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Son6">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y-W</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Mannitol induces the conversion of conidia to chlamydospore-like structures that confer enhanced tolerance to heat, drought, and UV in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiol Res</source><volume>167</volume>: <fpage>608</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22580127</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Mortazavi1">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>621</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18516045</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Andrianopoulos1">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andrianopoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Timberlake</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Aspergillus nidulans abaA</italic> gene encodes a transcriptional activator that acts as a genetic switch to control development</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>2503</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8139553</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Fischer1">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fischer R, K&#xFC;es U (2006) Asexual sporulation in mycelial fungi. In: K&#xFC;es U, Fischer R, editors. The Mycota I growth, differentiation and sexuality. Germany: Springer Berlin Heidelberg. pp. 263&#x2013;292.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-NguyenBa1">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nguyen Ba</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pogoutse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Provart</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>NLStradamus: a simple Hidden Markov Model for nuclear localization signal prediction</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>202</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19563654</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Benson1">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karsch-Mizrachi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ostell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>GenBank</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>40</volume>: <fpage>D48</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>D53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22144687</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Tao1">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>AbaA and WetA govern distinct stages of <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> development</article-title>. <source>Microbiology-(UK)</source><volume>157</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>326</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Si1">
        <label>65</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Si</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rittenour</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nicksarlian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Morphogenetic and developmental functions of the <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic> homologues of the yeast bud site selection proteins Bud4 and Axl2</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>85</volume>: <fpage>252</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22651396</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Park1">
        <label>66</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H-S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Genetic control of asexual sporulation in filamentous fungi</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source><volume>15</volume>: <fpage>669</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23092920</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Yu3">
        <label>67</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Regulation of development in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic> and <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></article-title>. <source>Mycobiology</source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23956662</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Borneman1">
        <label>68</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Borneman</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hynes</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andrianopoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The <italic>abaA</italic> homologue of <italic>Penicillium marneffei</italic> participates in two developmental programmes: conidiation and dimorphic growth</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1034</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1047</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11123677</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Seong1">
        <label>69</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seong</surname><given-names>K-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J-R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>G&#xFC;ldener</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Conidial germination in the filamentous fungus <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>45</volume>: <fpage>389</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17950638</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Ye1">
        <label>70</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wolkow</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>S-L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Interaction between developmental and cell cycle regulators is required for morphogenesis in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic></article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source><volume>18</volume>: <fpage>6994</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10601021</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Ni1">
        <label>71</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A novel regulator couples sporogenesis and trehalose biogenesis in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e970</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17912349</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Tuch1">
        <label>72</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tuch</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Evolution of eukaryotic transcription circuits</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>319</volume>: <fpage>1797</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18369141</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Gasch1">
        <label>73</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gasch</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berardini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Conservation and evolution of <italic>Cis</italic>-regulatory systems in ascomycete fungi</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source><volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e398</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15534694</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Park2">
        <label>74</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>CFGP: a web-based, comparative fungal genomics platform</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>36</volume>: <fpage>D562</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>D571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17947331</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0072915-Bowden1">
        <label>75</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Sexual recombination in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source><volume>89</volume>: <fpage>182</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944794</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
