<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3786984</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-22420</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074859</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Haplotype Variation of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> Locus and the Origin of <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> Allele Conferring Superior End-Use Qualities in Common Wheat</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">New Insights into <italic>Glu-D1</italic> Locus and <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> Allele</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>Zhenying</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Yushuang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Yiwen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Kunpu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lou</surname>
            <given-names>Haijuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>An</surname>
            <given-names>Xueli</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>Lingli</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
            <given-names>Yong Qiang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>Olin D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Xin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Qin</surname>
            <given-names>Huanju</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Daowen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>The State Key Laboratory of Plant Cell and Chromosomal Engineering, Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Graduate University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>United States Department of Agriculture-Agricultural Research Service, Western Regional Research Center, Albany, California, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Palsson</surname>
            <given-names>Arnar</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>University of Iceland, Iceland</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>dwwang@genetics.ac.cn</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: ZD YY DW. Performed the experiments: ZD YY HL XA LD. Analyzed the data: ZD YY LD KZ DW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YL KZ XL HQ. Wrote the paper: ZD YY YQG ODA DW.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>9</issue>
      <elocation-id>e74859</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Dong et al</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>In higher plants, seed storage proteins (SSPs) are frequently expressed from complex gene families, and allelic variation of SSP genes often affects the quality traits of crops. In common wheat, the <italic>Glu-D1</italic> locus, encoding 1Dx and 1Dy SSPs, has multiple alleles. The <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> allele frequently confers superior end-use qualities to commercial wheat varieties. Here, we studied the haplotype structure of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> genomic region and the origin of <italic>Glu-D1d</italic>. Using seven diagnostic DNA markers, 12 <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes were detected among common wheat, European spelt wheat (<italic>T. spelta</italic>, a primitive hexaploid relative of common wheat), and <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> (the D genome donor of hexaploid wheat). By comparatively analyzing <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes and their associated <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>1Dy</italic> genes, we deduce that the haplotype carrying <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> was likely differentiated in the ancestral hexaploid wheat around 10,000 years ago, and was subsequently transmitted to domesticated common wheat and <italic>T. spelta</italic>. A group of relatively ancient <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes was discovered in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, which may serve for the evolution of other haplotypes. Moreover, a number of new <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> variants were found in <italic>T. spelta</italic>. The main steps in <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> differentiation are proposed. The implications of our work for enhancing the utility of <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> in wheat quality improvement and studying the SSP alleles in other crop species are discussed.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This project was supported by grants from Ministry of Science and Technology of China (2009CB118300, 2011BAD07B02-2) and Ministry of Agriculture of China (2011ZX08002-004, 2011ZX08009-003-004). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Seed storage proteins (SSPs) occur in diverse plant species. They provide energy for seed germination and seedling growth, and form a major source of dietary protein for mankind <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Shewry1">[1]</xref>. In crop plants, SSPs are frequently crucial determinants of quality traits <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Shewry1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Holding1">[2]</xref>. Many superior SSP alleles have been identified and used in breeding (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Gibbon1">[3]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Jegadeesan1">[5]</xref>), and substantial efforts have been devoted in sequencing the genomic regions containing SSP coding genes (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Wicker1">[6]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Miclaus1">[8]</xref>). In general, SSPs tend to be expressed from complex gene families, and often possess multiple alleles with different phenotypic effects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Shewry2">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Sofi1">[10]</xref>. In order to more effectively use SSPs in improving crop quality traits, it is necessary to understand the variations of the genomic loci harbouring SSP genes in germplasm resources and the origins of superior SSP alleles.</p>
      <p>High-molecular-weight glutenin subunits (HMW-GSs) are a family of SSPs essential for the end-use quality control of common wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>, AABBDD) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Wrigley1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Shewry3">[11]</xref>. HMW-GSs, together with the low-molecular-weight glutenin subunits (LMW-GSs) and gliadins, are the major factors conferring viscoelastic properties to wheat doughs. The relative balance of elasticity (controlled mainly by HMW-GSs and LMW-GSs) and viscosity (largely by gliadins) in the doughs determines their suitability for being processed into different types of wheat foods. In hexaploid wheat, the genes encoding HMW-GSs are contained in homoeologous <italic>Glu-1</italic> loci (<italic>Glu-A1</italic>, <italic>B1</italic>, and <italic>D1</italic>), which are located on the 1A, 1B and 1D chromosomes, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Shewry3">[11]</xref>. The loci orthologous to <italic>Glu-A1</italic>, <italic>B1</italic>, and <italic>D1</italic> have been found in the <italic>Triticeae</italic> species closely related to common wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Garg1">[12]</xref>. The genomic regions of <italic>Glu-1</italic> loci are structurally complex, with the core of a <italic>Glu-1</italic> locus being composed of four genes arranged in the order of <italic>Globulin 1</italic>&#x2212;<italic>Glu-1-2</italic>&#x2212;<italic>Globulin 2</italic>&#x2212;<italic>Glu-1-1</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Gu2">[13]</xref>. <italic>Glu-1-1</italic> and <italic>Glu01-2</italic> encode x- and y-type subunits, respectively. Owing to allelic variation and gene inactivation, both <italic>Glu-1-1</italic> and <italic>Glu-1-2</italic> have multiple alleles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Payne1">[14]</xref>. For example, <italic>Glu-D1</italic> has several commonly found alleles, <italic>Glu-D1a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>, <italic>c</italic>, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>e</italic> and <italic>f</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Wrigley1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Payne2">[15]</xref>. The two HMW-GS genes of <italic>Glu-D1a</italic> are <italic>1Dx2</italic> and <italic>1Dy12</italic> (encoding 1Dx2 and 1Dy12 subunits, respectively), whereas those of <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> are <italic>1Dx5</italic> and <italic>1Dy10</italic> (specifying 1Dx5 and 1Dy10 subunits, respectively) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Payne2">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Payne3">[16]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The primary structure of HMW-GSs is composed of a signal peptide (removed from mature subunit), a N terminal domain, a central repetitive domain, and a C-terminal domain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Shewry2">[9]</xref>. The cysteine residues in HMW-GSs are usually conserved in both number and position. However, compared to 1Dx2, 1Dx5 harbors the amino acid substitution at position 118, causing the replacement of a serine residue by cysteine at the beginning of the repetitive domain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Anderson1">[17]</xref>. Relative to 1Dx2, the presence of this extra cysteine in 1Dx5 is frequently associated with the doughs exhibiting stronger elasticity and superior end-use qualities for breadmaking and noodle processing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Anderson1">[17]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Zhang1">[21]</xref>. Interestingly, several studies have also shown that the wheat varieties carrying <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> are generally more tolerant to heat stress-induced decline of dough quality than those having <italic>Glu-D1a</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Don1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Irmak1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Blumenthal1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Uthayakumaran1">[23]</xref>. This suggests that <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> is likely to be even more useful for future improvement of wheat end-use qualities, as heat stress may become increasingly frequent in the next 30&#x2013;50 years owing to global warming <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Meehl1">[24]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Despite its agronomical importance, the evolutionary origin of <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> remains a mystery. Since extant common wheat was descended from domestication of the ancestral hexaploid wheat formed about 10,000 years ago through natural hybridization between tetraploid wheat (<italic>T. turgidum</italic>, AABB) and the D genome donor <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> (DD) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Feldman1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Gustafson1">[26]</xref>, it is possible that <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> may come directly from <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, or be differentiated during hexaploidization. The <italic>Glu-D1</italic> genomic region has been sequenced in one <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accession and one common wheat variety <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Gu1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Anderson2">[27]</xref>. The <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>1Dy</italic> genes in the sequenced <italic>Glu-D1</italic> region are usually separated by more than 50 kb with each surrounded by multiple repetitive elements <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Gu1">[7]</xref>. Furthermore, complex differences were found in not only <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>1Dy</italic> genes but also the repetitive elements between the <italic>Glu-D1</italic> region in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> and that of common wheat, indicating close relationships between the molecular variations of <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>1Dy</italic> genes and those of surrounding repetitive elements. Therefore, the main objectives of this work were to obtain a more comprehensive understanding of the haplotype variation of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> genomic region, and to shed new light on the origin of <italic>Glu-D1d.</italic> European spelt wheat (<italic>T. spelta</italic> thereafter), cultivated as land races, was included in this work because it possessed a hexaploid genome highly similar to that of common wheat, and represents a more primitive hexaploid relative of common wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Yan1">[28]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Matsuoka1">[31]</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Plant Materials</title>
        <p>A total of 208 common wheat varieties (listed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s010">Tables S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s011">S2</xref>), along with 355 <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s012">Table S3</xref>) and 215 <italic>T. spelta</italic> lines (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s013">Table S4</xref>), were employed in this study to investigate <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes. Additional materials and the main suppliers of the germplasm stocks used in this work are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s019">Methods S1</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0074859-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074859.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Development of seven new molecular markers in <italic>Glu-D1</italic> region.</title>
            <p>(A) Organization of homologous <italic>Glu-D1</italic> regions in the common wheat variety Renan and the <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accession AUS18913. The diagrams illustrating the organization of the various transposon elements and genes in the two <italic>Glu-D1</italic> regions were adapted from previously published works <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Gu1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Anderson2">[27]</xref>. Only the structures relevant to this work are shown. The letters &#x201C;a&#x201D; and &#x201C;b&#x201D; denote distinct copies of the duplicated genes. Positions of the seven newly developed DNA markers (<italic>Xms1</italic>, <italic>Xid1</italic>, <italic>Xrj1</italic>, <italic>Xrj2</italic>, <italic>Xms2</italic>, <italic>Xrj3</italic>, and <italic>Xrj4</italic>) are indicated by filled arrowheads. The &#x201C;*&#x201D; and &#x201C;#&#x201D; symbols indicate the markers based on microsatellite or indel. The <italic>HMW-GS</italic> genes <italic>Glu-D1d-1</italic> (<italic>1Dx5</italic>), <italic>Glu-D1d-2</italic> (<italic>1Dy10</italic>), <italic>Glu-D1a-1</italic> (<italic>1Dx2</italic>) and <italic>Glu-D1a-2</italic> (<italic>1Dy12</italic>) are marked by empty arrowheads. The <italic>Wis-1</italic> and <italic>Wis-2p</italic> insertions were unique to Renan <italic>Glu-D1</italic>. The <italic>Angela-4</italic> element, although intact in AUS18913 <italic>Glu-D1</italic>, had its internal region deleted in Renan <italic>Glu-D1</italic> (and thus named as <italic>Angela-4p</italic>). Compared to the solo-LTR <italic>Sabrina-3s</italic> in Renan <italic>Glu-D1</italic>, its counterpart in AUS18913 <italic>Glu-D1</italic> underwent further sequence deletion (and thus designated as <italic>Sabrina-3sd</italic>). (B) SDS-PAGE analysis of HMW-GS subunits from 14 common varieties containing <italic>Glu-D1a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>, <italic>c</italic>, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>e</italic> or <italic>f</italic> alleles. The 1Dx and 1Dy subunit pairs (1Dx5+1Dy10, 1Dx2+1Dy12, 1Dx3+1Dy12, 1Dx4+1Dy12, 1Dx2+1Dy10, 1Dx2.2+1Dy12) encoded by different <italic>Glu-D1</italic> alleles are indicated by Arabic numbers. (C) Amplification patterns of seven <italic>Glu-D1</italic> markers in the 14 common wheat lines with <italic>Glu-D1a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>, <italic>c</italic>, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>e</italic> or <italic>f</italic> alleles. The size (bp) of the amplicons and the names of the markers are provided on the left and right sides of the graph, respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0074859.g001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Marker Development and Haplotype Analysis</title>
        <p>The BAC sequences of DQ537337 (from Renan) and AF497474 (from <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accession AUS18913) harboring <italic>Glu-D1</italic> locus were retrieved from NCBI database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>). Three types of polymorphisms, including transposable element (TE) insertions or deletions, simple sequence repeats, and short nucleotide indels, between the two sequences were considered for marker development. The software Primer Premier 5.0 (PREMIER Biosoft International, CA, USA) was used for designing the primer pairs specific for each of the seven <italic>Glu-D1</italic> markers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s014">Table S5</xref>). Genomic DNA samples were extracted from desired plant lines grown in the greenhouse using a CTAB method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-SaghaiMaroof1">[32]</xref>, and used for PCR amplifications (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s019">Methods S1</xref>). <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes were distinguished by differences in the alleles of the seven diagnostic markers.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Detection of <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>1Dy</italic> Genes using the PCR Markers UMN25 and UMN26</title>
        <p>The PCR markers UMN25 and UMN26 developed by Liu <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Liu1">[33]</xref> were used to detect the <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>1Dy</italic> genes in one set of common wheat lines (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s011">Tables S2</xref>), and to investigate the <italic>1Dy</italic> genes hosted by 12 <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes. PCR amplification and gel analysis were conducted as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Liu1">[33]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Isolation of <italic>1Dx</italic> or <italic>1Dy</italic> Coding Sequences and the Long Terminal Repeat (LTR) Regions of <italic>Sabrina-2</italic></title>
        <p>The primers for amplifying <italic>1Dx</italic> or <italic>1Dy</italic> coding sequences and the left or right LTR regions of <italic>Sabrina-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s014">Table S5</xref>) were developed using Primer Premier 5.0 (PREMIER Biosoft International, CA, USA). Genomic PCR was employed for isolating the desired sequences, which was always conducted using the high fidelity DNA polymerase ExTaq (TaKaRa, Tokyo, Japan), with the cycling parameters identical to those reported previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Liu2">[34]</xref>. The PCR fragments of the expected size were cloned and sequenced (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s019">Methods S1</xref>). To facilitate recognition, the <italic>1Dx</italic> (or <italic>1Dy</italic>) genes from <italic>T. spelta</italic> and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> were labeled by <italic>1D<sup>s</sup>x</italic> (<italic>1D<sup>s</sup>y</italic>) and <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>x</italic> (<italic>1D<sup>s</sup>y</italic>), respectively. Additionally, each of the newly characterized <italic>1Dx</italic> (<italic>1D<sub>y</sub></italic>) gene was tagged by the name and <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotype of the accession from which it was isolated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Dating LTR Retrotransposon Insertion Times</title>
        <p>The insertion time of retroelement was estimated based on nucleotide substitution rate in the left and right LTR sequences according to a previous study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-SanMiguel1">[35]</xref>. Kimura-2 parameter distances (K) between the two LTRs of individual elements were calculated by software MEGA 5.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Tamura1">[36]</xref>. The average substitution rate (r) of 1.3&#xD7;10<sup>&#x2212;8</sup> substitutions per synonymous site per year <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Ma1">[37]</xref>, was used to date the insertions of retroelements. The time (<italic>T</italic>) since element insertion was calculated using the formula <italic>T</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;<italic>K/</italic>2r <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Li1">[38]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Multiple Alignment and Phylogenetic Analysis</title>
        <p>Sequence alignment was performed using the ClustalW program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk">www.ebi.ac.uk</ext-link>). The resultant multiple alignment was then used for constructing phylogenetic trees using the software MEGA 5.0 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s019">Methods S1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Estimation of Approximate Divergence Times of <italic>1Dx</italic> or <italic>1Dy</italic> Genes</title>
        <p>Synonymous substitution (Ks) was estimated with MEGA 5.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Tamura1">[36]</xref>, Divergence time (<italic>T</italic>) was calculated using <italic>T</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;<italic>K</italic>s/2<italic>r</italic>, where <italic>r</italic> is the grass <italic>Adh1</italic> and <italic>Adh2</italic> substitution rate of 6.5&#xD7;10<sup>&#x2212;9</sup> substitutions per synonymous site per year <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Gaut1">[39]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Phylogenetic Network Analysis</title>
        <p>The alleles of the seven <italic>Glu-D1</italic> markers and the types of the <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>1Dy</italic> genes were employed for phylogenetic network analysis of 12 <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes with the Median-Joining network algorithm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Bandelt1">[40]</xref>, which is installed in the software network 4.6.1.0 (Fluxus Technology Ltd., Suffolk, UK).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2i">
        <title>Accession Numbers</title>
        <p>All novel sequences were submitted to GenBank with reference numbers JX173931&#x2013;JX173953.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Development of New DNA Markers for <italic>Glu-D1</italic> Locus</title>
        <p>The genomic sequences available for <italic>Glu-D1</italic> regions in the <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accession AUS18913 and common wheat variety Renan allowed for understanding structural variations in this locus between the diploid D and hexaploid D genomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Gu1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Anderson2">[27]</xref>. The <italic>Glu-D1</italic> allele of Renan encodes 1Dx5 and 1Dy10 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Groos1">[41]</xref>, and thus belongs to <italic>Glu-D1d</italic>, whereas the <italic>Glu-D1</italic> allele of AUS18913 is likely <italic>Glu-D1a</italic>, because the two HMW-GSs in this accession resemble highly 1Dx2 and 1Dy12 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Anderson2">[27]</xref>. The patterns of transposon insertion and deletion vary considerably between the two <italic>Glu-D1</italic> regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g001">Figure 1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Gu1">[7]</xref>). We therefore developed seven new DNA markers based on their sequence variations to investigate the haplotype structure of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). Among these markers, two (<italic>Xms1</italic> and <italic>Xid1</italic>) were located upstream of <italic>1Dy</italic> (<italic>Glu-D1&#x2013;2</italic>), two (<italic>Xrj1</italic> and <italic>Xrj2</italic>) resided between <italic>1Dy</italic> and <italic>1Dx</italic> (<italic>Glu-D1-1</italic>), and the remaining three (<italic>Xms2</italic>, <italic>Xrj3</italic> and <italic>Xrj4</italic>) were downstream of <italic>1Dx</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). <italic>Xms1</italic> and <italic>2</italic> were two microsatellite markers, and <italic>Xid1</italic> was an indel marker. <italic>Xrj1</italic>, <italic>2</italic>, <italic>3</italic> and <italic>4</italic> were repeat DNA insertion site based polymorphism (ISBP) markers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Wanjugi1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Paux1">[43]</xref>. <italic>Xrj1</italic> and <italic>2</italic> were designed based on the unique insertion of the retrotransposon <italic>Wis-1</italic> and specific deletion of the internal region in the retroelement <italic>Angela-4</italic> in Renan <italic>Glu-D1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). <italic>Xrj3</italic> was developed based on structural difference between <italic>Sabrina-3s</italic> and <italic>Sabrina-3sd</italic> in Renan and AUS18913 <italic>Glu-D1</italic> regions, while <italic>Xrj4</italic> was derived from the specific presence of another partially deleted retrotransposon (<italic>Wis-2p</italic>) in Renan <italic>Glu-D1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). The location of the seven markers in the 1D chromosome was confirmed by PCR mapping (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s001">Figure S1</xref>).</p>
        <p>The capacity of the newly developed markers for revealing potential haplotype variation of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> was tested by examining 14 common wheat varieties carrying <italic>Glu-D1a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>, <italic>c</italic>, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>e</italic> or <italic>f</italic> alleles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). Clearly, two distinct haplotypes (H1 and H2) were detected, with H1 unique to the two varieties (Attila and Bobwhite) carrying <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> and H2 shared by the remaining 12 varieties harboring <italic>Glu-D1a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>, <italic>c</italic>, <italic>e</italic> or <italic>f</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). H1 was characterized by positive amplifications of all seven markers. In contrast, H2 was characterized by positive amplifications of <italic>Xid1</italic>, <italic>Xrj2</italic> and <italic>Xms2</italic>, but not <italic>Xms1</italic> or <italic>Xrj1</italic>, <italic>3</italic> and <italic>4</italic>. Moreover, the alleles of <italic>Xid1</italic>, <italic>Xrj2</italic> or <italic>Xms2</italic> amplified for the varieties carrying <italic>Glu-D1a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>, <italic>c</italic>, <italic>e</italic> or <italic>f</italic> were identical, indicating that the three markers were monomorphic, and could not differentiate, among the five <italic>Glu-D1</italic> alleles. Among the three markers co-dominant for H1 and H2, the amplicon size of <italic>Xrj2</italic> was smaller in H1 than in H2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g001">Figure 1C</xref>), which was due to sequence deletion in <italic>Angela-4p</italic> in the <italic>Glu-D1</italic> region represented by Renan (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). The amplicon lengths of <italic>Xms2</italic> in H1 and H2 were 368 and 346 bp, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s002">Figure S2</xref>), which corresponded to a 22 bp indel between the two amplicons of this microsatellite marker in Renan and AUS18913. Finally, the amplicon size of <italic>Xid1</italic> did not differ between the two <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes detected in the 14 common wheat genotypes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Detection and Analysis of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> Haplotypes</title>
        <p>The haplotype variation of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> locus in common wheat was further investigated using two larger sets of materials. The first set was composed of 60 common wheat varieties from diverse geographic locations and with known information on their <italic>Glu-D1</italic> alleles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s010">Table S1</xref>). After genotyping with the seven diagnostic <italic>Glu-D1</italic> markers, H1 was specifically detected in the varieties carrying <italic>Glu-D1d</italic>, whereas H2 was shared by the remaining having other <italic>Glu-D1</italic> alleles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s010">Table S1</xref>). In the second set of 134 common wheat varieties, the status of their <italic>Glu-D1</italic> alleles was unknown before this work. After screening by PCR amplification of the co-dominant markers UMN25 (co-dominant for <italic>1Dx2</italic> and <italic>1Dx5</italic>) and UMN26 (co-dominant for <italic>1Dy12</italic> and <italic>1Dy10</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Liu1">[33]</xref>, these lines were divided into two groups, one carrying <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> and the other with <italic>Glu-D1a</italic>. Upon genotyping with the seven <italic>Glu-D1</italic> markers, the varieties having <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> were all found to belong to H1, while those harboring <italic>Glu-D1a</italic> alleles could all be assigned to H2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s011">Table S2</xref>). Clearly, H1 and H2 were the two main haplotypes of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> locus in common wheat. H1 was specific for <italic>Glu-D1d</italic>, whereas H2 was shared by <italic>Glu-D1a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>, <italic>c</italic>, <italic>e</italic> or <italic>f</italic>.</p>
        <p>Using the seven markers, a total of nine <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes was identified among 355 diverse <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions collected from over 20 countries (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s012">Table S3</xref>). Compared with common wheat, <italic>Xid1</italic> detected additional polymorphisms in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, but <italic>Xrj2</italic> and <italic>Xrj4</italic> were both monomorphic (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>). Among the nine haplotypes found in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, H3 was most common (found in 49.3% accessions), followed by H2 (in 23.7% accessions). The only difference between H2 and H3 was the positive amplification of <italic>Xrj3</italic> in the latter (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>). H4 was the third most frequent haplotype (in 9.6% accessions), and differed from H3 in the size of the product of <italic>Xms2</italic>, which was 368 bp in H4, but 346 bp in H3 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>). Collectively, H2, H3 and H4 were found in 82.6% of the <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions examined. The remaining six haplotypes were detected in only small numbers of accessions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>). The marker alleles of <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> H2 were identical to those of common wheat H2 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>). Surprisingly, we did not find H1 in the large number of <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions analyzed in this work.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0074859-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074859.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>Glu-D1</italic> locus haplotypes detected in <italic>T. aestivum</italic>, <italic>T. spelta</italic> and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> populations.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0074859-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0074859.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haplotype</td>
                  <td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1">Marker</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xms1</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xid1</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xrj1</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xrj2</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xms2</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xrj3</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Xrj4</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">351</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">428</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">460</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">631</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. spelta</italic> (9, 4.2%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">c</xref><italic>T. aestivum</italic> (99, 47.7%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1085</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (84, 23.7%)<italic>T. spelta</italic> (175, 81.4%)<italic>T. aestivum</italic> (109, 52.3%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1085</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">460</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (175, 49.3%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1085</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">460</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (34, 9.6%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1085</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">460</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (3, 0.8%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1085</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (10, 2.8%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">663</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1085</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (20, 5.6%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">663</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">351</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1085</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (4, 1.1%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">351</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1085</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (6, 1.7%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">351</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1085</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (19, 5.4%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1085</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">631</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. spelta</italic> (30, 14.1%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">351</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1085</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">460</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">631</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. spelta</italic> (1, 0.5%)</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>Length (bp) of amplified fragment by the corresponding marker.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label>b</label>
              <p>Null allele.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label>c</label>
              <p>Items in the brackets indicate the number and percentage of lines in which the given <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotype was detected.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>A total of 215 <italic>T. spelta</italic> accessions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s013">Table S4</xref>) was genotyped with the seven <italic>Glu-D1</italic> markers, resulting in the identification of four haplotypes (H1, H2, H11, and H12, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>). H1, although not found in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, was detected in <italic>T. spelta</italic>. On the other hand, H11 and H12 were found in <italic>T. spelta</italic>, but not <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> or common wheat. H2 was the predominant <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotype, followed by H11. H11 differed from H2 in the positive amplification of <italic>Xrj4</italic>, and H12 differed from H1 in the size of the product of <italic>Xrj2</italic>, which was 428 bp in H1, but 1085 bp in H12 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <p>All together, 12 unique haplotypes were identified for <italic>Glu-D1</italic> locus in the <italic>T. aestivum</italic>, <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, and <italic>T. spelta</italic> materials in this study (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>). An important feature shared by H1, H11, and H12 was the positive amplification of <italic>Xrj4</italic>, which was not the case for the nine <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>. Among the 12 haplotypes, only H1 had the 428 bp allele at <italic>Xrj2</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Approximate Timing for the Differentiation of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> Haplotypes</title>
        <p>To estimate the time periods in which the different <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes were differentiated, transposon insertion and deletion events found in subsets of the 12 haplotypes were investigated, followed by molecular clock analysis using nucleotide substitutions in the LTRs of retroelements. Based on structural differences between the <italic>Glu-D1</italic> locus sequences of Renan and AUS18913 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g001">Figure 1A</xref>), and the polymorphic amplification patterns of <italic>Xrj1</italic>, <italic>2</italic> and <italic>3</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>), the 12 haplotypes could be divided into five categories (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t002">Table 2</xref>). The H2 to H7 haplotypes in category I all contained the insertion of an intact <italic>Angela-4</italic> element, but lacked those by <italic>Wis-1</italic>, <italic>Wis-2p</italic> and <italic>Angela-4p</italic>. Molecular dating with <italic>Angela-4</italic> indicated that the insertion of this element into <italic>Glu-D1</italic> region took place approximately 1.42 MYA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t002">Table 2</xref>), suggesting that the six haplotypes in category I were differentiated around 1.42 MYA. H8 to H10 in category II were characterized by possessing both <italic>Angela-4</italic> and <italic>Wis-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t002">Table 2</xref>). The insertion of <italic>Wis-1</italic> into <italic>Glu-D1</italic> region was estimated to be approximately 0.46 MYA based on nucleotide substitutions in the two LTRs of this element (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t002">Table 2</xref>). Therefore, H8 to H10 arose possibly around 0.46 MYA. The haplotypes in category III (H11), IV (H12) or V (H1) all contained the <italic>Wis-2p</italic> element with only one LTR. Therefore, the insertion time of <italic>Wis-2p</italic> could not be dated. However, considering that the <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes harboring <italic>Wis-2p</italic> were found in only common wheat (H1) and <italic>T. spelta</italic> (H1, H11 and H12), but not in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>), <italic>Wis-2p</italic> insertion might occur after the hexaploidization event that gave rise to the ancestral hexaploid wheat (around 0.01 MYA). Thus, the <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes in categories III, IV or V might all be differentiated relatively recently compared to those in categories I and II, possibly around 0.01 MYA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0074859-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074859.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Approximate differentiation times of five categories of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0074859-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0074859.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TE event</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haplotype</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TE used forestimation</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rough timing ofdifferentiation (MYA)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<italic>Angela-4</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref>- <italic>Wis-1</italic>- <italic>Wis-2p</italic>-<italic>Angela-4p</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H2 to H7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Angela-4</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42&#xB1;0.18</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (H2 to H7)<italic>T. spelta</italic> (H2)<italic>T. aestivum</italic> (H2)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<italic>Angela-4</italic>+<italic>Wis-1</italic>- <italic>Wis-2p</italic>-<italic>Angela-4p</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H8 to H10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Wis-1</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46&#xB1;0.09</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<italic>Angela-4</italic>- <italic>Wis-1</italic>+<italic>Wis-2p</italic>-<italic>Angela-4p</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Wis-2p</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>T. spelta</italic>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<italic>Angela-4</italic>+<italic>Wis-1</italic>+<italic>Wis-2p</italic>-<italic>Angela-4p</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Wis-2p</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>T. spelta</italic>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212; <italic>Angela-4</italic>+<italic>Wis-1</italic>+<italic>Wis-</italic><italic>2p</italic>+<italic>Angela-4p</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Wis-2p</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>T. speltaT. aestivum</italic>
                  </td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>The plus and minus symbols indicate the presence or absence of TE insertion.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>The differentiation of H1 and H12 occurred around similar times was further investigated by analyzing the terminal sequences of the LTR element <italic>Sabrina-2</italic>, which existed in the <italic>Glu-D1</italic> region of both Renan and AUS18913 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). This element was inserted into <italic>Glu-D1</italic> locus around 2.01&#x2013;2.30 MYA based on molecular dating using its LTR sequences (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s015">Table S6</xref>). No nucleotide substitution was found between the LTR sequences of the <italic>Sabrina-2</italic> elements resided in H1 and H12, although such substitutions existed between the <italic>Sabrina-2</italic> elements hosted by H1 and H5 or by H1 and H10 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s016">Table S7</xref>). Further examination revealed that the number of nucleotide substitutions in <italic>Sabrina-2</italic> LTR sequences between H1 and H5 was substantially higher than that between H1 and H10 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s016">Table S7</xref>). This observation was consistent with the findings that H5 was differentiated earlier than H10, and H10 was formed earlier than H1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Characterization of <italic>1Dx</italic> Genes and their Deduced Proteins</title>
        <p>Because a major difference between <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> and <italic>Glu-D1a</italic> lies in their 1Dx subunits, we conducted sequence analysis of the <italic>1Dx</italic> genes in a range of <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> and <italic>T. spelta</italic> accessions with their <italic>Glu-D1</italic> locus haplotyped in this study. A total of 20 unique <italic>1Dx</italic> ORFs was analyzed at both coding sequence and deduced protein levels by comparing with the two well characterized common wheat <italic>1Dx</italic> genes, <italic>1Dx5</italic> and <italic>1Dx2</italic> that belonged to <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> or <italic>Glu-D1a</italic> and were carried by <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes H1 and H2, respectively. The 20 <italic>1Dx</italic> ORFs were all intact and active because their products could be found in the grains by SDS-PAGE analysis of seed protein extracts (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s003">Figure S3</xref>).</p>
        <p>Like the coding sequences of <italic>1Dx5</italic> and <italic>1Dx2</italic>, the newly cloned <italic>1Dx</italic> ORFs contained no intron. The 20 deduced 1Dx proteins from these accessions shared a highly similar primary structure consisting of a signal peptide (21 residues), a N-terminal domain (89 residues), a central repetitive domain (681 to 702 residues), and a C-terminal domain (42 or 43 residues) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t003">Table 3</xref>). Their central repetitive domains were composed of mainly tandem and interspersed repeats with base units of tripeptide, hexapeptide, and nonapeptide motifs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s004">Figure S4</xref>). For eight 1Dx subunits, the number of conserved cysteine residues and their relative positions in the protein sequence were identical to those in 1Dx5 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t003">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s004">Figure S4</xref>). For the remaining 12 1Dx subunits, the number of conserved cysteine residues and their relative positions in the protein sequence were the same as those in 1Dx2 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t003">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s004">Figure S4</xref>). Interestingly, the eight accessions with 1Dx5-like subunits all belonged to <italic>T. spelta</italic>, and their <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotype was H1; for the 12 accessions with 1Dx2-like subunits, nine belonged to <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> and three to <italic>T. spelta</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t003">Table 3</xref>). Subsequently, we compared the substitution and indel patterns among 1Dx5, 1Dx2, and the 20 1Dx subunits. A total of 15 polymorphic sites, including 10 substitutions (S1 to S10) and five indels (ID1 to ID5), were analyzed. As shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s017">Table S8</xref>, each of the ten substitutions occurred between two residues. The S1 substitution, S118C, was linked to functional difference between 1Dx2 and 1Dx5 (see Introduction). The indels occurred at the five sites caused removal or addition of short peptides (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s017">Table S8</xref>). In general, the 1Dx subunits specified by <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes H3 to H5 showed the highest dissimilarities from both 1Dx5 and 1Dx2 in the 15 sites (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s017">Table S8</xref>). Remarkably, the 1Dx2-like subunit 1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI19057<sup>H12</sup>, although lacking S118C substitution, strongly resembled 1Dx5 and 1Dx5-like subunits in the majority of the remaining sites; three 1Dx2-like subunits (1D<sup>t</sup>x-PI511368<sup>H2</sup>, 1D<sup>s</sup>x-PI348360<sup>H2</sup> and 1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI5008<sup>H11</sup>) were either highly similar, or identical to, 1Dx2 in these 15 sites (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s017">Table S8</xref>). Apart from the substitutions and indels described above, there also existed additional changes that were either specific to individuals, or shared by subsets, of the 20 compared 1Dx protein sequences (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s004">Figure S4</xref>). For example, extra and unique cysteine residues were found in the repetitive domain of the 1Dx5-like subunits 1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI9883<sup>H1</sup> and 1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI16607<sup>H1</sup> and the 1Dx2-like subunit 1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI5008<sup>H11</sup>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0074859-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074859.t003</object-id>
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Main features of the 20 newly isolated 1Dx subunits.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0074859-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0074859.t003"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1Dx</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ORF size (bp)</td>
                  <td colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1">Deduced protein (aa)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SP</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RD</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1Dx5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2550</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">a</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">696 (1)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">a</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">a</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">848 (5)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">b</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1Dx2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2523</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">687 (0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">839 (4)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>1D<sup>s</sup>x-PI15865<sup>H1</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2550</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">696 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">848 (5)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>1D<sup>s</sup>x-PI361813<sup>H1</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2550</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">696 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">848 (5)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI9883<sup>H1</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2550</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">696 (2)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">848 (6)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI16607<sup>H1</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2550</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">696 (2)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">848 (6)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI16981<sup>H1</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2550</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">696 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">848 (5)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>1D<sup>s</sup>x-PI347904<sup>H1</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2550</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">696 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">848 (5)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>1D<sup>s</sup>x-PI348150<sup>H1</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2550</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">696 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">848 (5)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>1D<sup>s</sup>x-PI348171<sup>H1</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2550</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">696 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">848 (5)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>1D<sup>s</sup>x-PI348360<sup>H2</sup></underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2523</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">687 (0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">839 (4)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>1D<sup>t</sup>x-PI511368<sup>H2</sup></underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2532</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">690 (0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">842 (4)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>1D<sup>t</sup>x-IG46663<sup>H3</sup></underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2541</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">693 (0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">845 (4)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>1D<sup>t</sup>x-PI603224<sup>H4</sup></underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2541</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">693 (0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">845 (4)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>1D<sup>t</sup>x-IG48561<sup>H5</sup></underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2541</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">693 (0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">845 (4)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>1D<sup>t</sup>x-PI603236<sup>H6</sup></underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2505</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">681 (0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">833 (4)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>1D<sup>t</sup>x-CIAE24<sup>H7</sup></underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2541</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">693 (0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">845 (4)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>1D<sup>t</sup>x-TA2527<sup>H8</sup></underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2541</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">693 (0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">845 (4)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>1D<sup>t</sup>x-PI349047<sup>H9</sup></underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2568</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">702 (0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">855 (4)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>1D<sup>t</sup>x-PI603223<sup>H10</sup></underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2568</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">702 (0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">855 (4)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI5008<sup>H11</sup></underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2523</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">687 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">839 (5)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <underline>1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI19057<sup>H12</sup></underline>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2523</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (3)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">687 (0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">839 (4)</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt105">
              <label/>
              <p>ORF: open reading frame; SP: signal peptide; ND: N-terminal domain; RD: repetitive domain; CD: C-terminal domain. The 1Dx5-like and 1Dx2-like subunits are shown in bold and underlined, respectively.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt106">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>Items in the brackets indicate the number of cysteine residues in the ND, RD or CD regions of each 1Dx protein.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt107">
              <label>b</label>
              <p>The number of total cysteine residues in each 1Dx subunit is provided in the brackets.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title>Phylogenetic Analysis of <italic>1Dx</italic> Genes and Estimation of <italic>1Dx</italic> Divergence Times</title>
        <p>Phylogenetic analysis was conducted to investigate the relatedness among the 20 <italic>1Dx</italic> genes. In a typical neighbor joining tree constructed with full length nucleotide sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g002">Figure 2</xref>), there were three well supported clades (C1 to C3), with C1 and C2 in the upper and parallel positions and C3 located at the basal side. Six major branches, including three (B1 to B3) in C1, two (B4 to B5) in C2, and one (B6) in C3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g002">Figure 2</xref>), could be recognized. Within C1, the top branch B1 was formed by <italic>1Dx5</italic> from common wheat and the seven <italic>1Dx5</italic>-like genes from <italic>T. spelta</italic>, the middle branch B2 was composed of the <italic>1Dx2</italic>-like gene <italic>1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI19057<sup>H12</sup></italic> and the <italic>1Dx5</italic>-like gene <italic>1D<sup>s</sup>x-PI15865<sup>H1</sup></italic>, and the basal branch B3 contained two <italic>1Dx2</italic>-like genes from <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Within C2, B4 was composed of exclusively <italic>1Dx2</italic>-like genes from <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, and B5 of <italic>1Dx2</italic> from common wheat and three <italic>1Dx2</italic>-like genes from <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> and <italic>T. spelta</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g002">Figure 2</xref>). C3 contained the <italic>1Dx2</italic>-like genes from only <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g002">Figure 2</xref>). The <italic>1Dx</italic> genes aggregated in the three clades were derived from separate sets of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes, namely, H1, H9, H10 and H12 for the genes in C1, H2, H6, H7, H8 and H11 for those in C2, and H3, H4 and H5 for those in C3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Phylogenetic trees were also constructed using full length amino acid sequences and an alternative program (i.e., minimum evolution). The result was identical to that displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g002">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0074859-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074859.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>1Dx</italic> genes.</title>
            <p>The tree shown was constructed using the multiple alignment of nucleotide sequences, and the neighbor joining program. Three distinctive clades (C1 to C3) and six major branches (B1 to B6) were observed. Highly similar trees were obtained with multiple alignment of deduced protein sequences, and an alternative tree building programs (i.e., minimum evolution). The <italic>1Dx5</italic>-like and <italic>1Dx2</italic>-like genes are shown in bold and underlined, respectively. <italic>1Ax1</italic> from common wheat <italic>Glu-A1</italic> locus was used as an outgroup control. Bootstrap values were obtained with 1000 permutations. The GenBank accession numbers for <italic>1Dx5</italic>, <italic>1Dx2</italic> and <italic>1Ax1</italic> are X12928, X03346 and X61009, respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0074859.g002"/>
        </fig>
        <p>On the basis of the phylogenetic analysis, the divergence times between the <italic>1Dx</italic> genes of hexaploid wheat and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> were estimated. In the C1 cluster, the averaged divergence time between <italic>1Dx5</italic> (representing hexaploid wheat <italic>1Dx5</italic> and <italic>1Dx5-</italic>like genes) and the two <italic>Ae. tauschii 1Dx2</italic>-like genes (<italic>1D<sup>t</sup>x-PI349047<sup>H9</sup></italic> and <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>x-PI603223<sup>H10</sup></italic>) was found to be around 0.29 MY (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s018">Table S9</xref>). In C2, the averaged divergence time between <italic>1Dx2</italic> (representing hexaploid wheat <italic>1Dx2</italic> and <italic>1Dx2-</italic>like genes) and the four <italic>Ae. tauschii 1Dx2</italic>-like genes (<italic>1D<sup>t</sup>x-PI511368<sup>H2</sup></italic>, <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>x-PI603236<sup>H6</sup></italic>, <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>x-CIAE24<sup>H7</sup></italic> and <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>x-TA2527<sup>H8</sup></italic>) was approximately 0.13 MY, with the specific time between <italic>1Dx2</italic> and <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>x-PI511368<sup>H2</sup></italic> being only about 0.04 MYA (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s018">Table S9</xref>). Interestingly, the three <italic>Ae. tauschii 1Dx2</italic>-like genes in C3 exhibited relatively the longest averaged divergence times from both <italic>1Dx5</italic> (0.37 MY) and <italic>1Dx2</italic> (0.36 MY) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s018">Table S9</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3f">
        <title>Analysis of <italic>1Dy</italic> Genes and their Deduced Proteins</title>
        <p>Initially, the <italic>1Dy</italic> genes hosted by different <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes were analyzed using the UMN26 marker that permits the distinction of <italic>1Dy10</italic> from <italic>1Dy12</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Liu1">[33]</xref>. By comparing with the fragments amplified from the common wheat varieties Bobwhite (carrying <italic>1Dy10</italic>) and CS (harboring <italic>1Dy12</italic>), <italic>1Dy10</italic> (or <italic>1Dy10</italic>-like) was found in <italic>T. spelta</italic> haplotypes H1 and H12 and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> haplotypes H9 and H10, with <italic>1Dy12</italic> (or <italic>1Dy12</italic>-like) present in the remaining haplotypes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s005">Figure S5</xref>). To verify the presence of intact <italic>1Dy10</italic> ORF, the <italic>1Dy</italic> coding sequence in the <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accession PI603223 (with haplotype H10) and the <italic>T. spelta</italic> accession TRI19057 (with haplotype H12) were cloned. To facilitate further comparisons, the <italic>1Dy</italic> coding sequence in the two <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions PI511368 and IG48561 (with haplotypes H2 and H5, respectively) and the <italic>T. spelta</italic> accession PI348360 (representing the H2 haplotype in spelt wheat) were also isolated. The expression of these <italic>1Dy</italic> genes was verified by SDS-PAGE analysis of seed protein extracts (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s003">Figure S3</xref>).</p>
        <p>Like <italic>1Dy10</italic> and <italic>1Dy12</italic>, the five <italic>1Dy</italic> sequences (designated as <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>y-PI603223<sup>H10</sup></italic>, <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>y-PI511368<sup>H2</sup></italic>, <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>y-IG48561<sup>H5</sup>, 1D<sup>s</sup>y-PI348360<sup>H2</sup></italic>, and <italic>1D<sup>s</sup>y-TRI19057<sup>H12</sup></italic>, respectively) did not contain intron, and were all terminated by tandem stop codons. The primary structure of their deduced proteins was identical to that of 1Dy10 and 1Dy12 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s006">Figure S6</xref>). Nucleotide sequence comparisons revealed that <italic>1D<sup>s</sup>y-TRI19057<sup>H12</sup></italic> was identical to <italic>1Dy10</italic>, and <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>y-PI603223<sup>H10</sup></italic> showed higher identity to <italic>1Dy10</italic> (99.6%) than to <italic>1Dy12</italic> (96.7%). In contrast, <italic>1D<sup>s</sup>y-PI348360<sup>H2</sup></italic> was identical to <italic>1Dy12</italic>, and <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>y-PI511368<sup>H2</sup></italic> exhibited higher identity to <italic>1Dy12</italic> (99.7%) than to <italic>1Dy10</italic> (96.7%). <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>y-IG48561<sup>H5</sup></italic> displayed comparable identities to both <italic>1Dy10</italic> (96.2%) and <italic>1Dy12</italic> (97.9%).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3g">
        <title>Phylogenetic Network Analysis of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> Haplotypes and a Possible Homologous Recombination Event between H5 and H10</title>
        <p>Based on the variations of <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>1Dy</italic> genes and the similarities and differences in the alleles of the seven DNA markers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s007">Figure S7</xref>), a phylogenetic network analysis was conducted to investigate relationships among the 12 haplotypes. In <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, direct network connection was found among H2, H3, H4, H5, H6, H7 and H8, as well as between H9 and H10 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g003">Figure 3</xref>). In common wheat and <italic>T. spelta</italic>, direct connection was found between H12 and H1, and between H2 and H11 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Two hypothetical intermediate haplotypes were predicted by the analysis program, one (X) connecting H6, H7 and H8 to H9 and H10, and the other (Y) linking H5 and H10 to H12 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0074859-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074859.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Phylogenetic network analysis of 12 <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes.</title>
            <p>The haplotypes detected in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> were circled, whereas those in <italic>T. spelta</italic> and common wheat were boxed. H2 was a shared haplotype. Two hypothetical intermediate haplotypes (X and Y) were predicted by the network analysis program.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0074859.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The linkage of both H5 and H10 to H12 was of particular interest considering the direct relationship between H12 and H1 that carries <italic>Glu-D1d</italic>. A simple explanation could be that both H5 and H10 might contribute to the differentiation of H12 through a recombination event. Judging from the alleles of <italic>1Dx</italic>, <italic>1Dy</italic> and the seven diagnostic markers, H12 resembled H10 in the upstream portion and including <italic>Xrj2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g004">Figure 4</xref>). In the downstream portion of <italic>Xrj2</italic>, H12 shared two identical marker alleles (specified by <italic>Xms2</italic> and <italic>Xrj3</italic>, respectively) with H5, although the two haplotypes differed in the alleles of <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>Xrj4</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g004">Figure 4</xref>). We thus speculated that a homologous recombination event might have happened between H5 and H10 at a position downstream of <italic>1Dx</italic>, resulting in the prototype of H12 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g004">Figure 4</xref>). In the prototype H12, the segment with the <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>1Dy</italic> genes was dissented from H10, whereas the remaining segment was derived from H5. Since neither H5 nor H10 were detected in extant common wheat and <italic>T. spelta</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>), the recombination event yielding the prototype H12 occurred in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0074859-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074859.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>A possible homologous recombination event between <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes H5 and H10.</title>
            <p>This event might take place in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> between H5 and H10 downstream of the <italic>1Dx</italic> gene (as indicated by the cross). The descendent was introduced to the ancestral hexaploid wheat via hexaploidization, giving rise to H12 after further differentiation (as evidenced by the positive amplification of <italic>Xrj4</italic> due to <italic>Wis-2p</italic> insertion, boxed area). The types of <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>1Dy</italic> genes and the alleles of the seven <italic>Glu-D1</italic> markers hosted by the different haplotypes were indicated.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0074859.g004"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Consistent with the homologous recombination hypothesized above, it was found that <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>x-PI603223<sup>H10</sup></italic> and <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>y-PI603223<sup> H10</sup></italic> showed higher identities to <italic>1Dx5</italic> and <italic>1Dy10</italic> (98.8% and 99.6%, respectively) than to <italic>1Dx2</italic> and <italic>1Dy12</italic> (96.2% and 96.7%, respectively). On the other hand, <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>x-IG48561<sup>H5</sup></italic> and <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>y-IG48561<sup>H5</sup></italic>, derived from the <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accession with haplotype H5, exhibited lower levels of identities to <italic>1Dx5</italic> and <italic>1Dy10</italic> (97.5% and 96.2%, respectively).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this study, three complementary approaches were taken in order to investigate haplotype variation of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> and the origin of <italic>Glu-D1d</italic>. The development and application of seven diagnostic markers distributed in <italic>Glu-D1</italic> region permitted a rapid survey of the haplotype variation of this locus in several hundred germplasm lines. Molecular cloning of <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>1Dy</italic> coding sequences provided accurate gene sequence information in important <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes. Phylogenetic analysis and molecular dating were deployed to understand the relationships and divergence times of different <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes and the associated <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>1Dy</italic> genes. The new insights gained and their implications for further research are discussed below.</p>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Major Characteristics of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> Haplotypes</title>
        <p>First, the number of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes is highest in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> (totally nine), intermediate in <italic>T. spelta</italic> (four), and relatively low in common wheat (only two). Considering that more than two hundred diverse common wheat varieties had been haplotyped, the low number of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes in common wheat is unlikely due to a biased selection of accessions. Since more than 200 <italic>T. spelta</italic> lines were genotyped, the four haplotypes revealed is likely a reasonable representation of the variation of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> region in this species.</p>
        <p>Second, most <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes are not shared among <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, <italic>T. spelta</italic>, and <italic>T. aestivum</italic>, and haplotypes H1, H11 and H12 are not present in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>. Among the 12 haplotypes detected, only H2 was shared among common wheat, <italic>T. spelta</italic> and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, and H1 by common wheat and <italic>T. spelta</italic>. H2 was the dominant haplotype in both common wheat and <italic>T. spelta</italic>, and is the second most abundant haplotype in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>. In contrast, H1 was not detected in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, and a relatively rare haplotype (compared to H2 and H11) in <italic>T. spelta</italic>. The failure in detecting H1 in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> is consistent with the fact that typical 1Dx5 subunit with the S118C substitution has not been found in this species by this and previous studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Yan2">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Zhang2">[45]</xref>. Therefore, it is highly probable that H1 (and the <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> allele contained therein) is absent in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>. A potential concern on this suggestion is that H1 may exist in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> in a very low frequency and was not detected by the present study. However, the failure of detecting H1 in 355 diverse <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions collected from over 20 countries (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s012">Table S3</xref>), the presence of <italic>Xrj2</italic> and <italic>Xrj4</italic> in H1 but none of the <italic>Ae. tauschii Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s007">Figure S7</xref>), and the coincidence between the times of H1 differentiation and hexaploidization (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t002">Table 2</xref>) are strongly in favor of the emergence of H1 in hexaploid wheat but not <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>. Although detected in <italic>T. spelta</italic>, H11 and H12 were also not found in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>. Because H11 and H12 shared the <italic>Wis-2p</italic> insertion with H1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>), and may be differentiated around the same time as H1, it is possible that, like H1, H11 and H12 are also absent in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>.</p>
        <p>Third, some <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes are relatively ancient, whereas others may have emerged only recently. H2 to H10 were already present in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> before the hexaploidization event around 10,000 years ago. In contrast, H1, H11, and H12 may be emerged in more recent times (around 0.01 MYA, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t002">Table 2</xref>), coinciding with the time frame in the formation of the ancestral hexaploid wheat. Among H2 to H7 (differentiated around 1.42 MYA), H3 to H5 might be differentiated earlier, and H2, H6 and H7 might be derived from H3 to H5 (after further sequence deletion in <italic>Sabrina-3s</italic>). The direct derivation of H2 from H3 is also supported by a straight connection between the two haplotypes in the phylogenetic network analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g003">Figure 3</xref>). On the other hand, H8 to H10 were differentiated later than H2 to H7 (around 0.46 MYA, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
        <p>Fourth, comparative analyses among <italic>1Dx</italic> or <italic>1Dy</italic> genes provide further clues on the differentiation of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes. The <italic>1Dx</italic> alleles carried by H3 to H5 clustered together (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g002">Figure 2</xref>), and exhibited relatively the longest divergence times to both <italic>1Dx5</italic> and <italic>1Dx2</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s018">Table S9</xref>), supporting the idea that H3 to H5 may be the most ancient ones among the 12 haplotypes. The <italic>1Dx</italic> alleles from H1, H9, H10 and H12 aggregated together, with those from H9 and H10 at the basal position (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g002">Figure 2</xref>), pointing to the involvement of H9 and H10 in the evolution of H12 and H1. The <italic>1Dx</italic> alleles from H2, H6 to H8, and H11 formed another well supported cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g002">Figure 2</xref>), with the <italic>1Dx</italic> allele from the <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> H2 haplotype at the most basal position, indicating that the <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> H2 is important for the evolution of H6 to H8, the presence of H2 in <italic>T. spelta</italic> and common wheat, and the emergence of H11 in <italic>T. spelta</italic>. The discovery of <italic>1Dy10-</italic>like gene in H10 and <italic>1Dy10</italic> in H12 further supports the role of the two haplotypes in the evolution of H1 that carries <italic>1Dx5</italic> and <italic>1Dy10</italic>. On the other hand, the finding of <italic>1Dy12-</italic>like gene in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> H2 and <italic>1Dy12</italic> in <italic>T. spelta</italic> H2 reinforces the likelihood that the H2 in <italic>T. spelta</italic> and common wheat was directly derived from the H2 of <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> due to hexaploidization. Lastly, the direct relationship between <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> H2 and the H2 in hexaploid wheat was also consistent with the very short divergence time between the <italic>1Dx2</italic>-like gene (e.g., <italic>1D<sup>t</sup>x-PI511368<sup>H2</sup></italic>) in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> and <italic>1Dx2</italic> of common wheat (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s018">Table S9</xref>).</p>
        <p>Finally, homologous recombination may contribute to the diversification of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>. In higher plants, haplotype variation and diversification of genes and chromosomal loci are usually caused by multiple means <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Chia1">[46]</xref>. From the data presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>, it is clear that haplotype variation of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> is caused by several reasons. These include nucleotide sequence alterations in two microsatellites (<italic>Xms1</italic> and <italic>Xms2</italic>), the indel in <italic>Xid1</italic>, and the mutations associated with four TEs (<italic>Wis-1</italic>, <italic>Angela-4</italic>, <italic>Sabrina-3s</italic>, and <italic>Wis-2p</italic>). Furthermore, we hypothesized that a homologous recombination event could have happened between H5 and H10 in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, leading to further diversification of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g004">Figure 4</xref>). The involvement of homologous recombination in the differentiation of new haplotypes has also been reported in other plant species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Stdler1">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Wicker2">[48]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Important Steps in the Differentiation of H1 Haplotype Containing <italic>Glu-D1d</italic></title>
        <p>Given the discussion above, the network relationships among 12 <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g003">Figure 3</xref>), and the hypothetical recombination between H5 and H10 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g004">Figure 4</xref>), a simplified model could be drawn on possible derivative relationships among 12 <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes. In this model (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s008">Figure S8</xref>), H3, H4 and H5 are probably the founder haplotypes, H2 (derived from H3), H5 and H10 play an important role in the diversification of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes. H2 is likely to give rise to a number of haplotypes (H6 to H10) in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, and to H11 after being introduced into hexaploid wheat through hexaploidization.</p>
        <p>Compared to H2 and H11, the route of H1 differentiation is more complex. Three steps may be important for the evolution of H1 containing <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s008">Figure S8</xref>). The first one is the differentiation of H10, hosting a <italic>1Dx2-</italic>like allele and a <italic>1Dy10-</italic>like allele in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>. This step likely occurred around 0.46 MYA. The second step is the differentiation of H12 in the ancestral hexaploid wheat. This step might take place around 0.01 MYA. The source material for H12 differentiation might be the descendant from the homologous recombination event between H5 and H10, which was introduced to the ancestral hexaploid wheat via hexaploidization. The <italic>1Dx2-</italic>like allele in H12, although encoding a 1Dx subunit lacking the S118C substitution, was highly similar to <italic>1Dx5</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0074859-g002">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s017">Table S8</xref>). The <italic>1Dy</italic> gene in H12 was identical to <italic>1Dy10</italic>. The third step is the differentiation of H1, containing <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> allele and specifying the expression of 1Dx5 (or 1Dx5-like) and 1Dy10 subunits, from H12. This step might happen during or shortly after hexaploidization, with the resultant H1 retained in both common wheat and <italic>T. spelta</italic> populations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Impact of Hexaploidization and Domestication on <italic>Glu-D1</italic> Haplotypes</title>
        <p>As a hexaploid crop species, the genetic structure of common wheat has been greatly influenced by hexaploidization, domestication, and breeding selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Matsuoka1">[31]</xref>. The strong effects of these processes on the birth and dissemination of new haplotypes are well demonstrated by recent studies on the powdery mildew resistance gene <italic>Pm3</italic> and the <italic>Lr34</italic> gene conferring multi-pathogen resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Yahiaoui1">[49]</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Krattinger2">[51]</xref>. A preponderance of the haplotype data obtained in this study leads us to suggest that the differentiation and dissemination of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes might have also been affected by hexaploidization, domestication, and breeding in at least two aspects.</p>
        <p>First, as noted above, the number of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes detected varied substantially among <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, <italic>T. spelta</italic>, and common wheat. The most probable explanation for the low degree of haplotype diversity in common wheat may be genetic bottlenecks associated with hexaploidization (i.e., formation of the ancestral hexaploid wheat by hybridization between tetraploid wheat and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>) and domestication and breeding (from ancestral hexaploid wheat to extant common wheat varieties). It is well known that nucleotide diversity is substantially higher in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> genome than in the D genome of contemporary common wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Caldwell1">[52]</xref>, and that relative few types (or individuals) of <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> were involved in the formation of ancestral hexaploid wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Dvorak1">[53]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Akhunov1">[55]</xref>. Moreover, it is widely accepted that human selection tends to further reduce the genetic diversity of plant and animal populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Matsuoka1">[31]</xref>. As land races, <italic>T. spelta</italic> accessions are less affected by artificial breeding efforts, and may have thus preserved more genetic diversities inherited from the ancestral hexaploid wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Yan1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Blatter1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Matsuoka1">[31]</xref>. This may, at least partly, be responsible for the existence of relatively more <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes in <italic>T. spelta</italic> than in common wheat. Several studies have speculated that <italic>T. spelta</italic> may be evolved from secondary hybridization between ancient free-threshing hexaploid wheat with hulled emmer wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Yan1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Blatter1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Salamini1">[56]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Dvorak2">[57]</xref>. This process might have also affected the differentiation and retention of <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes in <italic>T. spelta</italic>. Thus, the spectrum of <italic>T. spelta Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes revealed by this work might have been shaped by multiple forces (e.g., secondary hybridization, less artificial selection).</p>
        <p>Second, the differentiation and dissemination of H1 (carrying <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> allele) might have been more intimately connected with hexaploidization and human selection. Terasawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Terasawa1">[58]</xref> found that the frequency of <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> was exceptionally high in the hexaploid wheat lines collected from Caucasian regions. Considering that common wheat originated near Caucasia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Dvorak1">[53]</xref>, it is possible that H1 might be differentiated during or shortly after the hexaploidization event in Caucasia, and was subsequently selectively enriched in the free threshing common wheat populations around Caucasian regions due to the beneficial effects of <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> on end-use qualities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Terasawa1">[58]</xref>. As found in this work, H1 was a relatively rare haplotype compared to H2 and H11 in <italic>T. spelta</italic>, but its presence in extant common wheat almost equaled to that of H2 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0074859-t001">Table 1</xref>). Because common wheat has been subjected to breeder&#x2019;s selection more strongly than <italic>T. spelta</italic>, the increased presence of H1 in contemporary common wheat is largely caused by artificial breeding.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Implications for Further Research</title>
        <p>Apart from common wheat, there have also been substantial interests in recent years in identifying the elite alleles of SSPs in other crops, such as rice (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Wang1">[59]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Kawakatsu1">[60]</xref>), maize (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Wu1">[61]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Wang2">[63]</xref>), and soybean (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Jegadeesan1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Kim1">[64]</xref>). As exemplified by this work, haplotype analysis with appropriate germplasm populations may be employed as an efficient strategy for increasing the understanding of SSP alleles, especially for those harbored by complex genomic loci and potentially impacted by genome polyploidization events. The resulting new knowledge may facilitate more effective use of SSP alleles in improving the quality traits of crops.</p>
        <p>In this work, we found that the deduced protein sequences of the eight <italic>T. spelta</italic> 1Dx5-like subunits, although all carrying the S118C substitution (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s017">Table S8</xref>), differed considerably from that of the 1Dx5 subunit in common wheat (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0074859.s009">Figure S9</xref>). These <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> variants are likely valuable materials for further improvement of common wheat end-use qualities. We are now developing chromosomal introgression lines containing <italic>T. spelta Glu-D1d</italic> variants in common wheat background, which may be useful for testing the functionality of these new <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> variants. The seven DNA markers developed for <italic>Glu-D1</italic> region are being used for monitoring the transfer of <italic>Glu-D1d</italic> variants from <italic>T. spelta</italic> to common wheat. These markers may also be used in other end-use quality improvement programs involving the transfer of <italic>Glu-D1d</italic>, which are ongoing in many wheat production regions of the world <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Wrigley1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0074859-Liu3">[65]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s001">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Validation of the chromosomal specificity of the seven newly developed </bold><bold><italic>Glu-D1</italic></bold><bold> markers in this study.</bold> Genomic DNA samples were extracted from Chinese Spring (CS), the nulli-tetrasomic line N1DT1A (lacking 1D chromosome and associated <italic>Glu-D1</italic> locus), the ditelosomic line of chromosomal arm 1DS (Dt1DS, lacking 1DL and associated <italic>Glu-D1</italic> locus), three additional common wheat genotypes (Attila, Bobwhite and Kenong 199), two tetraploid wheat genotypes (Langdon and Cofa), and two <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions (AUS18913 and AL8/78). They were then used in genomic PCR with the primer pairs for each of the seven markers (<italic>Xms1</italic>, <italic>Xid1</italic>, <italic>Xrj1</italic>, <italic>Xrj2</italic>, <italic>Xms2</italic>, <italic>Xrj3</italic>, and <italic>Xrj4</italic>). These markers did not amplify products in tetraploid wheat genotypes, N1DT1A, and Dt1DS, confirming that they are D genome specific, and that their target sequences are located on chromosomal 1DL on which <italic>Glu-D1</italic> resides. As anticipated, the seven markers showed polymorphisms in common wheat and between common wheat and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>. Lane M contains DNA size standard. The size (bp) of the amplified PCR fragments is shown on the left side of the graph. Items in the brackets indicate genome constitution of the examined wheat or <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> genotypes.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s001.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s002">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Multiple alignment of the DNA sequences of </bold><bold><italic>Xms2</italic></bold><bold> amplicons from Attila, Bobwhite, Chinese Spring (CS) and Kenong 199, as well as the reference sequences from Renan and AUS18913.</bold> Chinese Spring (CS) and Kenong 199, as well as the reference sequences from Renan and AUS18913. The 22 bp deletion in the amplicons from CS, Kenong 199 and AUS18913 was indicated by dashed line.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s002.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s003">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Detection of 1Dx and 1Dy subunits expressed by </bold><bold><italic>T. spelta</italic></bold><bold> and </bold><bold><italic>Ae. tauschii Glu-D1</italic></bold><bold> Haplotypes.</bold> The 1Dx and 1Dy HMW-GSs in the two common wheat varieties, Bobwhite (expressing 1Dx5 and 1Dy10) and Chinese Spring (CS, expressing 1Dx2 and 1Dy12), and the <italic>T. spelta</italic> and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions with different <italic>Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes were revealed by SDS-PAGE analysis of seed protein extracts. 1Dx and 1Dy subunits specified by different <italic>T. spelta</italic> and <italic>Ae. tauschii Glu-D1</italic> haplotypes were indicated by arrowheads and arrows, respectively. The protein band labeled by asterisk in H7 is a &#x3C9;-gliadin protein.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s003.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s004">
        <label>Figure S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Multiple alignment of the deduced amino acid sequences of 1Dx5 and 1Dx2 subunits from common wheat, and the 20 1Dx subunits from </bold><bold><italic>Ae. tauschii</italic></bold><bold> and </bold><bold><italic>T. spelta</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> The signal peptide is underlined, while the N- and C-terminal domains are labeled bold and bold italic, respectively. The repetitive domain is situated between the N- and C-terminal domains. The amino acid substitutions (S1 to S10) and indels (ID1 to ID5) between 1Dx5 and 1Dx2, and their variations in the 20 1Dx subunits from <italic>T. spelta</italic> and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, are indicated. The four cysteine residues conserved among the 22 compared 1Dx subunits are marked by arrowheads. In addition, the cysteine reside unique to 1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI9883<sup>H1</sup>, 1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI16607<sup>H1</sup> or 1D<sup>s</sup>x-TRI5008<sup>H11</sup> is boxed.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s004.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s005">
        <label>Figure S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Detection of </bold><bold><italic>1Dy</italic></bold><bold> genes in the two common wheat varieties, Bobwhite (harboring </bold><bold><italic>1Dy10</italic></bold><bold>) and Chinese Spring (CS, containing </bold><bold><italic>1Dy12</italic></bold><bold>), and the </bold><bold><italic>T. spelta</italic></bold><bold> and </bold><bold><italic>Ae. tauschii</italic></bold><bold> accessions with different </bold><bold><italic>Glu-D1</italic></bold><bold> haplotypes using the PCR marker UMN26.</bold> This marker is co-dominant for <italic>1Dy10</italic> and <italic>1Dy12</italic>, and allows the distinction between the two genes. Lane M contains DNA size standard (bp).</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s005.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s006">
        <label>Figure S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Multiple alignment of the amino acid sequences of 1Dy10 and 1Dy12 subunits from common wheat and the five 1Dy subunits from </bold><bold><italic>Ae. tauschii</italic></bold><bold> and </bold><bold><italic>T. spelta</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> The signal peptide is underlined, while the N- and C-terminal domains are labeled bold and bold italic, respectively. The repetitive domain resides between the N- and C-terminal domains. The amino acid substitutions (S1 to S12) and indels (ID1 to ID3) patterns between 1Dy10 and 1Dy12, and their variations in the five 1Dy subunits from <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>, are indicated. The seven cysteine residues conserved among the seven compared 1Dy subunits are labeled by arrowheads.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s006.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s007">
        <label>Figure S7</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>A diagram illustrating the variations of </bold><bold><italic>1Dx</italic></bold><bold> and </bold><bold><italic>1Dy</italic></bold><bold> genes and the alleles of the seven DNA markers in 12 </bold><bold><italic>Glu-D1</italic></bold><bold> haplotypes.</bold> The types of <italic>1Dx</italic> and <italic>1Dy</italic> genes and the alleles of the seven <italic>Glu-D1</italic> markers were indicated.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s007.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s008">
        <label>Figure S8</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>A simplified model illustrating possible derivative relationships among 12 </bold><bold><italic>Glu-D1</italic></bold><bold> haplotypes.</bold> The arrows indicate the likely directions of haplotype differentiation. The approximate differentiation times (MYA) of the haplotypes in <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> and hexaploid wheat were indicated. The three haplotypes (H5, H10 and H12) involved in the differentiation of H1 are labeled in bold. H2, detected in both <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> and hexaploid wheat, was shown in italic.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s008.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s009">
        <label>Figure S9</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>A diagram illustrating the positions of polymorphic sites among the 1Dx5 subunits from two common wheat varieties (Cheyenne and Renan) and the eight 1Dx5-like subunits from </bold><bold><italic>T. spelta</italic></bold><bold> genotypes.</bold> 1Dx5 protein sequence (GenBank accession CAA31395) from Cheyenne was used as reference for locating the positions of polymorphic sites, where amino acid substitutions were detected. The diagram is not drawn in scale.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s009.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s010">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Haplotype variation of </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Glu-D1</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> locus in the common wheat varieties with known information on their </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Glu-D1</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> allele.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s010.xls">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s011">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Haplotype variation of </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Glu-D1</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> locus in the common wheat lines from different countries.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s011.xls">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s012">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>
              <italic>Glu-D1</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> haplotypes detected in 355 </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> accessions.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s012.xls">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s013">
        <label>Table S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>
              <italic>Glu-D1</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> haplotypes detected in 215 </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>T. spelta</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> accessions.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s013.xls">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s014">
        <label>Table S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>The oligonucleotide primers used in this study.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s014.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s015">
        <label>Table S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Estimation of approximate insertion time of </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Sabrina-2</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> into </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Glu-D1</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> locus.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s015.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s016">
        <label>Table S7</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Number of nucleotide substitutions between the LTR sequences in the </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Sabrina-2</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> elements resided in several </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Glu-D1</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> haplotypes.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s016.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s017">
        <label>Table S8</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Amino acid substitutions (S1 to S10) and indels (ID1 to ID5) between 1Dx5 and 1Dx2 of common wheat and their variations in the 20 1Dx subunits from </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>T. spelta</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> or </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Ae. Tauschii.</italic>
            </bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s017.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s018">
        <label>Table S9</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Divergence time estimates between two representative hexaploid wheat </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>1Dx</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> genes (</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>1Dx5</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> and </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>1Dx2</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>) and </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Ae. tauschii 1Dx</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> genes.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s018.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0074859.s019">
        <label>Methods S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Additional methods.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0074859.s019.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank many institutions (detailed in Methods S1) for supplying the germplasm materials used in this study.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Shewry1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shewry</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Napier</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tatham</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Seed storage proteins: structures and biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>945</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7640527</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Holding1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holding</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larkins</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Genetic engineering of seed storage proteins</article-title>. <source>Advan Plant Biochem Mol Bio</source><volume>1</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>133</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Gibbon1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gibbon</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larkins</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Molecular genetic approaches to developing quality protein maize</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source><volume>21</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15797618</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Wrigley1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wrigley C, Asenstorfer R, Batey I, Corbish G, Day L, <etal>et al</etal>. (2009) The biochemical and molecular basis of wheat quality. In: Carver BF, editor. Wheat Science and Trade. Iowa: Wiley-Blackwell. 495&#x2013;520.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Jegadeesan1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jegadeesan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woodrow</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Molecular analysis of glycinin genes in soybean mutants for development of gene-specifc markers</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>124</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21959908</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Wicker1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wicker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yahiaoui</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guyot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schlagenhauf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Rapid genome divergence at orthologous low molecular weight glutenin loci of the A and A<sup>m</sup> genomes of wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1186</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724543</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Gu1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coleman-Derr</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dupin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crossman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Types and rates of sequence evolution at the high-molecular-weight glutenin locus in hexaploid wheat and its ancestral genomes</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>174</volume>: <fpage>1493</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17028342</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Miclaus1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miclaus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Differential gene expression and epiregulation of alpha zein gene copies in maize haplotypes</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source><volume>7(6)</volume>: <fpage>e1002131</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21731501</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Shewry2">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shewry</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Halford</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Cereal seed storage proteins: structures, properties and role in grain utilization</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source><volume>53</volume>: <fpage>947</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>958</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11912237</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Sofi1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sofi</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rather</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Quality protein maize (QPM): genetic manipulation for the nutritional manipulation of maize</article-title>. <source>J Plant Breed Crop Sci</source><volume>1</volume>: <fpage>244</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>253</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Shewry3">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shewry</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Wheat</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source><volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1537</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19386614</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Garg1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsujimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Exploration of <italic>Triticeae</italic> seed storage proteins for improvement of wheat end-product quality</article-title>. <source>Breed Sci</source><volume>59</volume>: <fpage>519</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>528</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Gu2">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wanjugi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coleman-Derr</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Conserved globulin gene across eight grass genomes identify fundamental units of the loci encoding seed storage proteins</article-title>. <source>Funct Integr Genomics</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19707805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Payne1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Genetics of wheat storage proteins and the effect of allelic variation on bread-making quality</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Physiol</source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>153</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Payne2">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Catalogue of alleles for the complex gene loci, <italic>Glu-A1</italic>, <italic>Glu-B1</italic>, and <italic>Glu-D1</italic> which code for high molecular weight subunits of glutenin in hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Cereal Res Commun</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>35</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Payne3">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nightingale</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krattiger</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>The relationship between HMW glutenin subunit composition and the bread-making quality of British-grown varieties</article-title>. <source>J Sci Food Agric</source><volume>40</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>65</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Anderson1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Halford</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shewry</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Nucleotide sequences of the two high-molecular -weight glutenin genes from the D-genome of a hexaploid bread wheat, <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L. cv Cheyenne</article-title>. <source>Nucl Acids Res</source><volume>17</volume>: <fpage>461</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2563152</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Lafiandra1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lafiandra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>D&#x2019;Ovidio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Porceddu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Margiotta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colaprico</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>New data supporting high Mr glutenin subunit 5 as the determinant of quality differences among the pairs 5+10 vs 2+12</article-title>. <source>J Cereal Sci</source><volume>18</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>205</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Don1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Don</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lookhart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naeem</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>MacRitchie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Heat stress and genotype affect the glutenin particles of the glutenin macropolymer-gel fraction</article-title>. <source>J Cereal Sci</source><volume>42</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>80</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Irmak1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Irmak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naeem</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lookhart</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>MacRitchle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Effect of heat stress on wheat proteins during kernel development in wheat near-isogenic lines differing at <italic>Glu-D1</italic></article-title>. <source>J Cereal Sci</source><volume>48</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>516</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Zhang1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Effect of allelic variation and expression quantity at <italic>Glu-1</italic> loci on size distribution of glutenin polymer in common wheat</article-title>. <source>Acta Agronomica Sinica</source><volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1606</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1612</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Blumenthal1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bekes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gras</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>EWR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wrigley</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Identification of wheat genotypes tolerant to the effects of heat stress on grain quality</article-title>. <source>Cereal Chem</source><volume>72</volume>: <fpage>539</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>544</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Uthayakumaran1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Uthayakumaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newberry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Genotype-based stability of dough quality in wheat from different growth environments</article-title>. <source>J Agric Sci</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>50</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Meehl1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Meehl GA, Stocker TF, Collins WD, Friedlingstein P, Gaye AT, <etal>et al</etal>. (2007) Global climate projections. In: Solomon S, Qin D, Manning M, Chen Z, Marquis M, Averyt KB, Tignor M, Miller HL, editors. Climate Change 2007: The Physical Science Basis. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. 747&#x2013;845.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Feldman1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Feldman M (2001) Origin of cultivated wheat. In: Bonjean AP, Angus WJ, editors. The World Wheat Book. Paris: Lavoisier Publishing. 3&#x2013;56.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Gustafson1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gustafson PG, Raskina O, Ma XF, Nevo E (2009) Wheat evolution, domestication and improvement. In: Carver BF, editor. Wheat Science and Trade. Iowa: Wiley-Blackwell. 5&#x2013;30.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Anderson2">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rausch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moullet</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lagudah</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The wheat D genome HMW-glutenin locus: BAC sequencing, gene distribution, and retrotransposon clusters</article-title>. <source>Funct Integr Genomics</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>56</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12590343</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Yan1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsam</surname><given-names>SLK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ohtsuka</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>HMW and LMW glutenin alleles among putative tetraploid and hexaploid European spelt wheat (<italic>Triticum spelta</italic> L.) progenitors</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>107</volume>: <fpage>1321</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13679994</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Blatter1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Blatter</surname><given-names>RHE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacomet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schlumbaum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>About the origin of European spelt (<italic>Triticum spelta</italic> L.): allelic differentiation of the HMW glutenin B1&#x2013;1 and A1&#x2013;2 subunit genes</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>108</volume>: <fpage>360</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14564390</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Akeret1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Akeret</surname><given-names>&#xD6;</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Plant remains from a Bell Beaker site in Switzerland, and the beginnings of <italic>Triticum spelta</italic> (spelt) cultivation in Europe</article-title>. <source>Veget Hist Archaeobot</source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>286</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Matsuoka1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Evolution of polyploid <italic>Triticum</italic> wheats under cultivation: the role of domestication, natural hybridization and allopolyploid speciation in their diversification</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><volume>52</volume>: <fpage>750</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21317146</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-SaghaiMaroof1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saghai-Maroof</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soliman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Ribosomal DNA spacer-length polymorphisms in barley: Mendelian inheritance, chromosomal location, and population dynamics</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>81</volume>: <fpage>8014</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6096873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Liu1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>New DNA markers for high molecular weight glutenin subunits in wheat</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>118</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18797838</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Liu2">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>er</surname><given-names>al</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Analysis of HMW glutenin subunits and their coding sequences in two diploid <italic>Aegilops</italic> species</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>106</volume>: <fpage>1368</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12750780</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-SanMiguel1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>SanMiguel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaut</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tikhonov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennetzen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The paleontology of intergene retrotransposons of maize</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9731528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Tamura1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MEGA5: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>28</volume>: <fpage>2731</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546353</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Ma1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennetzen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Rapid recent growth and divergence of rice nuclear genomes</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>101</volume>: <fpage>12404</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>12410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15240870</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Li1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li W (1997) Molecular Evolution. Sunderland: Sinauer Associates.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Gaut1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gaut</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCaig</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clegg</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Substitution rate comparisons between grasses and palms: synonymous differences at the nuclear gene <italic>Adh</italic> parallel rate differences at the plastid gene <italic>rbc</italic>L</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>93</volume>: <fpage>10274</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8816790</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Bandelt1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bandelt</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>R&#xF6;hl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Median-joining networks for inferring intraspecific phylogenies</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>16</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10331250</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Groos1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Groos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bervas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chanliaud</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Charmet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genetic analysis of bread-making quality scores in bread wheat using a recombinant inbred line population</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>115</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17581736</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Wanjugi1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wanjugi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coleman-Derr</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kianian</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Rapid development of PCR-based genome-specific repetitive DNA junction markers in wheat</article-title>. <source>Genome</source><volume>52</volume>: <fpage>576</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19483776</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Paux1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paux</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choulet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Insertion site-based polymorphism markers open new perspectives for genome saturation and marker-assisted selection in wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>196</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20078842</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Yan2">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Characterization of HMW-GS genes <italic>Dx5<sup>t</sup></italic> and <italic>Dy12<sup>t</sup></italic> from <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> accession with subunit combination Dx5<sup>t</sup>+Dy12<sup>t</sup></article-title>. <source>Cereal Res Commun</source><volume>36</volume>: <fpage>477</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>487</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Zhang2">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>An</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Novel x-type high-molecular-weight glutenin genes from <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> and their implications on the wheat origin and evolution mechanism of Glu-D1&#x2013;1 proteins</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>178</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18202355</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Chia1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Costich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Leon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Maize HapMap2 identifies extant variation from a genome in flux</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source><volume>44</volume>: <fpage>803</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>807</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22660545</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Stdler1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>St&#xE4;dler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delph</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Ancient mitochondrial haplotypes and evidence for intragenic recombination in a gynodioecious plant</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>99</volume>: <fpage>11730</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11735</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12192087</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Wicker2">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wicker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krattinger</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lagudah</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Komatsuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pourkheirandish</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Analysis of intraspecies diversity in wheat and barley genomes identifies breakpoints of ancient haplotypes and provides insight into the structure of diploid and hexaploid <italic>Triticeae</italic> gene pools</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>149</volume>: <fpage>258</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19011002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Yahiaoui1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yahiaoui</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Rapid generation of new powdery mildew resistance genes after wheat domestication</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>47</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16740148</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Krattinger1">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krattinger</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lagudah</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wicker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Risk</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ashton</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title><italic>Lr34</italic> multi-pathogen resistance ABC transporter: molecular analysis of homoeologous and orthologous genes in hexaploid wheat and other grass species</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>65</volume>: <fpage>392</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21265893</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Krattinger2">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krattinger</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raghavan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Recent emergence of the wheat <italic>Lr34</italic> multi-pathogen resistance: insights from haplotype analysis in wheat, rice, sorghum and <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic></article-title>. <source>Ther Appl Genet</source><volume>126</volume>: <fpage>663</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>672</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Caldwell1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dvorak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lagudah</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akhunov</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Sequence polymorphism in polyploid wheat and their D-genome diploid ancestor</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>167</volume>: <fpage>941</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15238542</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Dvorak1">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dvorak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The structure of <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> genepool and the evolution of hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>97</volume>: <fpage>657</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>670</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Giles1">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>GluDy allele variations in <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> and <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>: implications for the origins of hexaploid wheats</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>112</volume>: <fpage>1563</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16568284</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Akhunov1">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Akhunov</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deal</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akhunova</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Nucleotide diversity maps reveal variation in diversity among wheat genomes and chromosomes</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>702</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21156062</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Salamini1">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Salamini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>&#xD6;zkan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandolini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#xE4;fer-Pregl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Genetics and geography of wild cereal domestication in the Near East</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>429</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12042770</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Dvorak2">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dvorak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deal</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>You</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Von Borstel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The origin of spelt and free-threshing hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>J Hered</source><volume>103</volume>: <fpage>426</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22378960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Terasawa1">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Terasawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Genetic variation of high-molecular weight glutenin subunit composition in Asian wheat</article-title>. <source>Genet Resour Crop Evol</source><volume>58</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>289</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Wang1">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Fine mapping and marker assisted selection (MAS) of a low glutelin content gene in rice</article-title>. <source>Cell Res</source><volume>15</volume>: <fpage>622</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16117852</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Kawakatsu1">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kawakatsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takaiwa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Characterization of a new rice glutelin gene <italic>GluD-1</italic> expressed in the starchy endosperm</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source><volume>59</volume>: <fpage>4233</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18980953</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Wu1">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holding</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>&#x3B3;-Zeins are essential for endosperm modification in quality protein maize</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>107</volume>: <fpage>12810</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>12815</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20615951</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Miclaus2">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miclaus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dooner</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The maize high-lysine mutant <italic>opaque 7</italic> is defective in an acyl-CoA synthetase-like protein</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>189</volume>: <fpage>1271</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21926304</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Wang2">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title><italic>Opaque7</italic> encodes an acyl-activating enzyme-like protein that affects storage protein synthesis in maize endosperm</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>189</volume>: <fpage>1281</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21954158</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Kim1">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Identification of sevreal <italic>gy4</italic> nulls from the USDA soybean germplasm collection provides new genetic resources for the development of hig-quality tofu cultivars</article-title>. <source>J Agr Food Chem</source><volume>56</volume>: <fpage>11320</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18991447</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0074859-Liu3">
        <label>65</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Appels</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Functional markers in wheat: current status and future prospects</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>125</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22366867</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
