<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4524710</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26241856</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134598</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-22328</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Novel Bread Wheat Lines Enriched in Carotenoids Carrying <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> Chromosome Arms in the <italic>ph1b</italic> Background</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Novel Bread Wheat Lines Enriched in Carotenoids</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rey</surname>
            <given-names>Mar&#xED;a-Dolores</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Calder&#xF3;n</surname>
            <given-names>Mar&#xED;a-Carmen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rodrigo</surname>
            <given-names>Mar&#xED;a Jes&#xFA;s</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zacar&#xED;as</surname>
            <given-names>Lorenzo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Al&#xF3;s</surname>
            <given-names>Enriqueta</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Prieto</surname>
            <given-names>Pilar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff001">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Departamento de Mejora Gen&#xE9;tica Vegetal, Instituto de Agricultura Sostenible, Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#xED;ficas, Apartado, C&#xF3;rdoba, Spain</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff002">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Instituto de Agroqu&#xED;mica y Tecnolog&#xED;a de Alimentos, Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#xED;ficas, Paterna, Valencia, Spain</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>Wujun</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Murdoch University, AUSTRALIA</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MDR PP. Performed the experiments: MDR MCC MJR LZ EA PP. Analyzed the data: MDR MCC MJR LZ EA PP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MDR MCC MJR LZ EA PP. Wrote the paper: MDR PP.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>pilar.prieto@ias.csic.es</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>8</issue>
      <elocation-id>e0134598</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Rey et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0134598.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>The use of crop wild relative species to improve major crops performance is well established. <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> has a high potential as a genetic donor to increase the carotenoid content of wheat. Crosses between the 7<bold>H<sup>ch</sup></bold><italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> substitution lines in wheat and the wheat <italic>pairing homoeologous1b (ph1b</italic>) mutant allowed the development of wheat-<italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> translocation lines for both 7<bold>H<sup>ch</sup></bold>&#x3B1; and 7<bold>H<sup>ch</sup></bold>&#x3B2; chromosome arms in the wheat background. These translocation lines were characterized by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization and using molecular markers. In addition, reverse phase chromatography (HPLC) analysis was carried out to evaluate the carotenoid content and both 7<bold>H<sup>ch</sup></bold>&#x3B1;&#x2219;7<bold>A</bold>L and 7<bold>A</bold>S&#x2219;7<bold>H<sup>ch</sup></bold>&#x3B2; disomic translocation lines. The carotenoid content in 7<bold>H<sup>ch</sup></bold>&#x3B1;&#x2219;7<bold>A</bold>L and 7<bold>A</bold>S&#x2219;7<bold>H<sup>ch</sup></bold>&#x3B2; disomic translocation lines was higher than the wheat-7<bold>H<sup>ch</sup></bold> addition line and double amount of carotenoids than the wheat itself. A proteomic analysis confirmed that the presence of chromosome 7<bold>H<sup>ch</sup></bold> introgressions in wheat scarcely altered the proteomic profile of the wheat flour. The <italic>Psy1</italic> (<italic>Phytoene Synthase1</italic>) gene, which is the first committed step in the carotenoid biosynthetic pathway, was also cytogenetically mapped on the 7<bold>H<sup>ch</sup></bold>&#x3B1; chromosome arm. These new wheat-<italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> translocation lines can be used as a powerful tool in wheat breeding programs to enrich the diet in bioactive compounds.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by the ERC Starting Grant 243118 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ias.csic.es/ercstg-superwheatcrops/">http://www.ias.csic.es/ercstg-superwheatcrops/</ext-link>).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="4"/>
        <table-count count="2"/>
        <page-count count="16"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta id="data-availability">
          <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
          <meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability</title>
      <p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Wild species of bread wheat <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> (2n = 6x = 42, genome <bold>AABBDD</bold>) are important resources for broadening the genetic variability of crop plants and useful traits have been transferred from these species to wheat [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> (2n = 2x = 14, genome <bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup><bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>) is an extremely polymorphic diploid wild barley from South of America. It has high crossability with other members of the <italic>Triticeae</italic> tribe and presents several agronomical characteristics which could be transferred into wheat, such as high carotenoid content among others [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> addition and substitution lines in wheat [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] are generally used as a bridge to generate wheat-<italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> translocation or recombinant lines [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. However, pairing between wheat and related chromosomes from these species is rare [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Chromosome pairing between homoeologous (related) chromosomes can be achieved using the <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The <italic>Ph1</italic> locus, which is located on the 5<bold>B</bold>L chromosome arm, ensures chromosome pairing and recombination between homologous (identical) chromosomes [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In the absence of the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus (<italic>pairing homoeologous</italic>1 locus; <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant) unspecific chromosome associations can occur between related chromosomes and therefore can be used to induce homoeologous recombination [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. An extensive molecular analysis of the region including the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus has been carried out, and the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus has been restricted to a 2.5 Mb region containing a cluster of <italic>Cdk-2 (cyclin dependent kinase-2)</italic> related genes [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], and regulates premeiotic replication, chromatin condensation, transcription of the earliest meiotic gene (<italic>Asy1</italic>), homologue pairing/synapsis, resolution of incorrect pairing at pachytene and recombination [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p>
      <p>The <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant can be used to facilitate interspecific recombination between chromosomes from wheat and those chromosomes from related species to transfer desirable agronomics traits from those relatives into wheat [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. For example, bread wheat has lower carotenoid contents than other plant species [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Carotenoids are a diverse family of natural isoprenoid pigments responsible of the characteristic color, from pale yellow to red, of different plant tissues and organs [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Carotenoids play crucial roles in many plant physiological processes and are essential for animals since some of them are the precursors of vitamin A and have a broad range of function, as antioxidants and other health-related properties [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Since carotenoids are almost exclusively synthetized by plants, and certain fungi and bacteria, animals and humans rely upon the diet as the source of these compounds. Carotenoids can be grouped in two main classes: carotenes, which are tetraterpenoid hydrocarbons, and xanthophylls, which are carotenoids with one or more oxygenated groups in the molecule. Lutein, a xanthophyll which accumulates in eye macula and plays an essential role in human vision, is the main carotenoid found in wheat, and is, in most cases, accompanied by lower amounts of zeaxanthin, &#x3B2;-cryptoxanthin and &#x3B2;-carotene [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The chromosomal location of genes involved in carotenoid synthesis in <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> was deciphered using <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> addition lines in wheat [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The presence of chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> increased the carotenoid content in wheat, and moreover, the ditelosomic addition line for 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1; chromosome arm showed greater influence on the pigment content [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. A chromosomal region on the distal part of chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> related to the carotenoid content has been recently reported [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. New genes controlling the carotenoid content were also found in the genome of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic>, such as <italic>Carot1</italic> and <italic>Zds</italic> (codifying for a zeta-carotene desaturase) genes, located on the centromeric region of chromosome 2<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> and the <italic>Psy1</italic> (<italic>Phytoene synthase 1</italic>) gene, which was located on the 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup><italic>&#x3B1;</italic> chromosome arm [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In fact, the enzyme PSY catalyses the first step of the carotenoids biosynthetic pathway and it is considered a limiting factor for carotenoid production [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p>
      <p>Genomic <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (GISH) is the most efficient and accurate technique to estimate the amount of alien chromatin introgressed in wheat [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Moreover, fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (FISH) combined with GISH enables the determination of the exact chromosomal compositions and resolutions of the chromosome arms involved in wheat-<italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> translocations [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. <italic>In situ</italic> hybridization can be also used to physically map single-copy genes on mitotic chromosomes [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</p>
      <p>Classical genetic breeding can result in undesirable side-effects as a consequence of the alteration of the genomic composition. Thus it is important to evaluate the quality of the introgression lines produced by conventional breeding. Ten to fifteen percent of the wheat grain dry weight are proteins, mainly storage proteins, which are the major responsible of dough properties, and also other minority proteins which might modify flour quality and/or be involved in hypersensitivity reactions such as food allergy and celiac disease [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Hence, deciphering the composition of the endosperm proteins through proteomics approaches is useful to evaluate the potential interest of wheat introgression lines.</p>
      <p>In this paper, we describe the development and characterization of new wheat-<italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> translocation lines for both 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1; and 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; chromosome arms with the aim of increasing the wheat carotenoid content. In addition, the <italic>Psy1</italic> gene, the first committed step in the carotenoid biosynthetic pathway, was cytogenetically mapped on <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>. The study is supplemented by an analysis of the proteomic profile of the flour of these new wheat-<italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> translocation lines with a higher carotene content.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002">
      <title>Material and Methods</title>
      <sec id="sec003">
        <title>Plant material</title>
        <p><italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> substitution lines for chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> in bread wheat [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] were used as parental lines in initial crosses with the wheat line deficient for the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> cv. <italic>`</italic>Chinese Spring&#xB4; (CS), <italic>ph1bph1b</italic> genotype; [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134598.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]). The descendence was backcrossed by the wheat <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant to obtain chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> in the <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant background as described in <xref rid="pone.0134598.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>. Seeds from the descendence of the backcrosses were germinated in Petri dishes on wet filter papers in darkness for 5 days at 4&#xB0;C followed by 24 hours incubation at 25&#xB0;C. Roots about 1 cm long were cut, incubated for 4 hours in a 0.05% colchicine solution at 25&#xB0;C and then fixed in 100% ethanol- acetic acid, 3:1 (v/v). Fixed roots were stored at 4&#xB0;C for at least 1 month to perform cytogenetic experiments. All plants were grown in a greenhouse at 26&#xB0;C (day) and 22&#xB0;C at night with a photoperiod of long days (16 h of daylight&#x2014;8 h of darkness).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0134598.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134598.g001</object-id>
          <label>Fig 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Development of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> introgression lines in hexaploid wheat in the <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant background.</title>
            <p>Crosses between the 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> substitution line in bread wheat and the <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant were developed and backcrossed to the <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant to obtain <italic>Hordeum</italic> translocation in the absence of the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0134598.g001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec004">
        <title>Characterization of the translocation lines using molecular markers</title>
        <p>Genomic DNA was extracted from frozen young leaf tissue using the cetyltrimethylammonium bromide (CTAB) method [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] with some modifications according to [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Bread wheat <italic>ph1b</italic> mutants were checked for the <italic>ph1b</italic> deletion using the ABC<sub>920</sub> SCAR marker as previously described [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The PCR reactions were performed in 30 &#x3BC;l of reaction mixture containing 1x PCR buffer with MgCl<sub>2</sub> (Bioline USA, Taunton, MA), 0.25 mM dNTPs, 5 pmol primers, 0.02 U/ &#x3BC;l of Taq DNA polymerase (Bioline USA, Taunton, MA). The PCR cocktail was initially denatured at 94&#xB0;C for 5 min, and then the amplification reaction consisted in 35 cycles of 1 min at 94&#xB0;C, 1 min at 51&#xB0;C and 1 min at 72&#xB0;C, followed by a final extension reaction of 7 min at 72&#xB0;C. The PCR products were solved on 1% agarose gels in 1xTBE and visualized by ethidium bromide staining under UV light. The presence of both 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1; and 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; chromosome arms was analyzed using the microsatellites BAWU550 and BAWU763, respectively, as described in [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The confirmation of the wheat chromosome involved in chromosome translocations (chromosome 7<bold>A</bold>) was also carried out using the microsatellites Xgwm471-7<bold>A</bold>S, Xgwm332-7<bold>A</bold>L as described in [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec005">
        <title>Cytogenetic analysis</title>
        <p>GISH experiments were performed according to [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] using genomic <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> DNA as probe to confirm the presence of chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>. Sonicated salmon sperm DNA was used as blocking DNA (salmon sperm DNA: DNA probe, 2:1). The identification of the 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1; or 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; chromosomes arms was also confirmed by FISH using the pAs1 sequences [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The wheat chromosome arms involved in inter-specific translocations with the <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> were also identified using both the GAA-satellite sequence [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and the pAs1 probe [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] as described in [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec006">
        <title>Physical mapping of <italic>Psy1</italic></title>
        <p>Physical localization of <italic>Psy1</italic> gene from the carotenoid biosynthetic pathway was performed by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization. A 2538bp genomic region of the <italic>Psy1</italic> gene was amplified by PCR in a (7<bold>A</bold>)7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> substitution line in bread wheat to be used as a probe in further <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization experiments. A pair of primers was designed using the Primer3plus software [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] based on the <italic>Psy1</italic> sequence previously described in <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> (GenBank accession number HM598415) [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0134598.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. The sequences for the forward and reverse primers used for <italic>Psy1</italic> amplification were, 5&#x2019;AGTGGTGAATCCATCCCTTG3&#x2019; and 5&#x2019;CCTTCCTCTTCTTGCACTGG3&#x2019;, respectively. PCR amplification for <italic>Psy1</italic> gene was performed using MyFi DNA polymerase (Bioline USA, Taunton, MA) according to the manufacturer&#xB4;s instructions as follows: 3 min 94&#xB0;C, 35 cycles of 15 s at 94&#xB0;C, 15 s at 60&#xB0;C and 3.5 min at 72&#xB0;C. PCR products were resolved on 1% agarose gels in 1xTBE and stained with ethidium bromide and visualized under UV light. The PCR fragments corresponding to the <italic>Pys1</italic> locus amplified from both <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> (used as a positive control) and the (7<bold>A</bold>)7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> substitution line, were sequenced to confirm the identity of the gene probe.</p>
        <p>Chromosome spreads from root tips of germinated wheat seeds, probe labelling and <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization were carried as described by [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Detection of hybridization signals was carried out using the Tyramide Signal Amplification Kit (TSA, PerkinElmer Life and Analytical Sciences, Inc., Waltham, MA, USA). To identify wheat chromosomes with positive signals, samples were re-hybridized using the pAs1 repetitive sequence and GAA-satellite sequence as probes [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Individual slides were observed under a Nikon Eclipse 80i, microscope (Nikon Instruments Europe BV, UK). Images were captured with a Nikon CCD camera using the appropriate Nikon 3.0 software and processed with Photoshop 4.0 software (Adobe Systems Inc., San Jose, California, USA).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec007">
        <title>Analysis of the carotenoid content in wheat-<italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> translocation lines</title>
        <p>Carotenoids from mature grains were determined according to [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Grains of each line were milled to fine flour and 1 g of flour per replicate was extracted to analyze the carotenoid composition. Three biological replicates per line were analyzed. Briefly, samples were extracted in 4 mL acetone containing 0.1% BHT (butylated hydroxytoluene) by vortexing for 2 min and additionally sonicated for 5 min at room temperature. The mixture was centrifuged at 4500 rpm at 4&#xB0;C for 10 min and the supernatant was recovered. The sediment was re-extracted with 4 mL of acetone until supernatant was colorless. Acetone extracts were pooled and dried under nitrogen stream. Dried extracts were stored at -25&#xB0;C until HPLC analysis.</p>
        <p>Composition of each sample was analyzed by HPLC as described in [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] by using a Waters liquid chromatography system equipped with a 600E pump, a 2998 photodiode array detector, and the Empower software (Waters). A C30 carotenoid column (250 x 4.6 mm, 5 &#x3BC;m) coupled to a C30 guard column (20 x 4.0 mm, 5 &#x3BC;m; YMC Europe GmbH, Germany) was used. Samples were prepared for HPLC by dissolving the dried carotenoid extracts in methanol: acetone (1:1 v:v). A ternary (methanol, water and methyl tert-butyl ether) gradient elution was used for carotenoid separation as is described in [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. The flow rate was 1 mL min<sup>-1</sup>, column temperature was set to 25&#xB0;C and the injection volume was 20 &#x3BC;L. The photodiode array detector was set to scan from 250 to 540 nm, and for each elution a Maxplot chromatogram, which plots each carotenoid peak at its corresponding maximum absorbance wavelength, was obtained. Carotenoids were identified by their retention time, absorption and fine spectra [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. The carotenoid peaks were integrated at their individual maxima wavelength and their content were calculated using calibration curves of lutein (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) for free and esterified lutein, and zeaxanthin (Extrasynthese). All operations were carried out on ice under dim light to prevent photodegradation, isomerizations and structural changes of the carotenoids.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec008">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>Statistical analyses were performed using STATISTIX 9.0 software (Analytical Software, Tallahassee, FL, USA). The analysis of variance (ANOVA) was based on randomised blocks. Means were separated using the Least Significant Difference (LSD) test with a probability level of 0.05.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec009">
        <title>Protein extraction and quantification</title>
        <p>Proteins were extracted following a phenol-based protocol described in [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] with slight modifications. Briefly, from each genotype two independent samples composed of a pool of 2&#x2013;3 seeds was ground into a fine powder using a Star-Beater mill (VWR Company, Darmstadt, Germany). The ground tissue was resuspended in phenol extraction buffer (0.9 M sucrose, 0.5 M Tris-HCl, 50 mM EDTA, 0.1 M KCl, Milli-Q water and freshly added 1% Triton X-100, 2% &#x3B2;-mercaptoethanol and 1% protease inhibitor cocktail set VI (Merck KGaA, Darmstadt, Germany), pH 8) and homogenized on ice using Eppendorf micropestles. Samples were subsequently mixed with one volume of phenol solution equilibrated with 10 mM Tris HCl pH 8, 1 mM EDTA (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA), shaken for 1 min, incubated for 20 min in a tube rotator at 4&#xB0;C and centrifuged at 18000 &#xD7; <italic>g</italic> for 10 min at 4&#xB0;C. The upper phenolic phase was collected and proteins were precipitated by adding five volumes of ice cold 0.1 M ammonium acetate and 13 mM DTT in methanol at -80&#xB0;C for 2 h. A pellet of proteins was obtained by centrifugation at 20000 &#xD7; <italic>g</italic> for 20 min at 4&#xB0;C. Then, the pellet was washed once with ice cold 0.1 M ammonium acetate, 13 mM DTT in methanol and twice with 80% ice cold acetone. Finally, the pellet was air dried, dissolved in denaturing buffer (6 M urea, 50 mM ammonium bicarbonate pH 8) and stored at -80&#xB0;C. Protein concentration was determined with the BCA Protein Assay Kit (Pierce Chemical Co., Rockford, EL), using BSA as a standard according to manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions for the microplate procedure. Protein quality was checked by 1D-SDS-PAGE using Mini-Protean cell (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Richmond, CA) and 12% Mini-PROTEAN TGX precast polyacrylamide gels (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Richmond, CA) stained with Coomassie Blue G250.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec010">
        <title>Reverse phase-liquid chromatography RP-LC-MS/MS analysis</title>
        <p>Protein extracts in 6 M urea and 50 mM ammonium bicarbonate pH 8 were reduced and alkylated. Disulfide bonds from cysteinyl residues were reduced with 10 mM DTT for 1 h at 37&#xB0;C, and then thiol groups were alkylated with 50 mM iodoacetamide for 1 h at room temperature in the dark. Samples were diluted to reduce urea concentrations below 1.4 M and digested using sequencing grade trypsin (Promega, Madison, WI) overnight at 37&#xB0;C in a trypsin/protein ratio of 1:5 (w/w). Digestion was stopped by the addition of 1% TFA. Then, the supernatants were dried down and desalted onto ZipTip C18 Pipette tips (EMD Millipore Corporation, Billerica, MA) until mass spectrometric analysis.</p>
        <p>Desalted digested proteins were dried out, resuspended in 0.1% formic acid and analyzed by RP-LC-MS/MS in an Easy-nLC II system coupled to an ion trap LTQ-Orbitrap-Velos-Pro mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Waltham, MA). The peptides were concentrated (on-line) by reverse phase chromatography using a 0.1 mm &#xD7; 20 mm C18 RP precolumn (Acclaim PepMap100 nanoViper, Dionex), and then separated using a 0.075 mm &#xD7; 100 mm C18 RP column (Acclaim PepMap100 nanoViper, Dionex) operating at 0.3 &#x3BC;l/min. Peptides from a 5 &#x3BC;g aliquot of the protein extract were eluted in a 180-min gradient of 5 to 40% solvent B (solvent A: 0.1% formic acid in water, solvent B: 0.1% formic acid, 80% acetonitrile in water). ESI ionization was carried out using a Nano-bore emitters Stainless Steel ID 30 &#x3BC;m (Proxeon) interface. The Orbitrap resolution was set at 30.000. Peptides were detected in survey scans from 400 to 1600 amu (1 &#x3BC;scan), followed by twenty data dependent MS/MS scans (Top 20), using an isolation width of 2 u (in mass-to-charge ratio units), normalized collision energy of 35%, and dynamic exclusion mode applied during 30 s periods. Peptide identification from raw data was carried out using the SEQUEST algorithm (Proteome Discoverer 1.4, Thermo Scientific). Database search was performed against Uniprot_Viridiplantae. The following constraints were used for the searches: tryptic cleavage after Arg and Lys, up to two missed cleavage sites, and tolerances of 10 ppm for precursor ions and 0.8 Da for MS/MS fragment ions. Searches were performed allowing optional Met oxidation and Cys carbamidomethylation. Search against decoy database (integrated decoy approach) was performed using false discovery rate (FDR) &lt; 0.01. Protein identification by nLC-MS/MS was carried out at the CBMSO protein chemistry facility, a member of ProteoRed network.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec011">
        <title>Bioinformatics and functional analysis of identified proteins</title>
        <p>The output accessions obtained with the Proteome Discoverer software were exported to Microsoft Excel for data analysis. Firstly, a table containing information of all the proteins identified in the four genotypes analyzed was generated (<xref rid="pone.0134598.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). The data obtained from the Uniprot-Viridiplantae search revealed that there were 372 proteins whose best hit was a protein with unknown function, meaning 50% of the proteins identified. Hence, to improve the information about the peptides matching proteins with unknown function a manual blastp was carried out. This analysis consisted on the blastp of the protein with unknown function with the Uniprot database; this allowed the identification of highly homologous proteins with an assigned function (identity with the protein with the best hit and the protein with described function &gt; 80%).</p>
        <p>In addition, a table containing the proteins exclusively identified in the genotypes with increased carotenoid content was created (<xref rid="pone.0134598.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). To this end, only the proteins that were present in the two replicates of each line were considered for the comparison between lines. Exceptionally, interesting proteins that were not exclusively found in one of the lines or in the two replicates of the proteomics experiments were also included in the list because they could have a relationship with the accumulation of carotenoids. These exceptions are indicated in the table and marked with asterisks.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0134598.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134598.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>List of proteins exclusively identified in the protein extracts of the lines with enhanced carotenoid accumulation.</title>
            <p>Unless otherwise stated the proteins were identified in the two replicates of the lines and not in any other protein extracts. The Uniprot identification number (ID; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org/">http://www.uniprot.org/</ext-link>) and the protein name of the best matches of the identified peptides are included. When the best match corresponded to a protein with a yet unassigned function the protein with the highest homology (&gt;80% identity) was also indicated in brackets. The proteins with a possible implication in carotenoid enrichment are highlighted in bold.</p>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0134598.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0134598.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Line</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uniprot ID</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein name</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Addition</bold> 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>O49996</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>14-3-3-like protein</bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F2CX17</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted protein (88% identity with cold shock domain protein 2; Q75QN9)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W5FAI9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein (100% identity with defensin; A0A060AQ78)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R7W8W0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Defensin-like protein 1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>A5A8U9</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>26.4kDa heat-shock protein</bold>
                    <xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#xB7;7<bold>A</bold>L</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q2QLR2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycine-rich RNA-binding protein GRP1A</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I1QDX3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein (99% identity with 2,3-bisphosphoglycerate-independent phosphoglycerate mutase; Q10LY9)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F2E2F1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted protein (100% identity with 60S ribosomal protein L21-2; M8CY06)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F2CSZ7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7<bold>A</bold>S&#xB7;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>D2E9R6</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Hsp organizing protein/stress-inducible protein</bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M7YCT7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-ketoacyl-CoA thiolase 2, peroxisomal</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A2YP75</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W5A1H5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;<bold>&#xB7;7A</bold>L and 7<bold>A</bold>S&#xB7;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q39782</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol dehydrogenase 2a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Addition 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> and7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#xB7;7<bold>A</bold>L</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F2D712</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W5GCI3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Addition 7H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup><bold>and</bold>7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;<bold>&#xB7;7A</bold>L and 7<bold>A</bold>S&#xB7;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B9VUV5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low molecular weight glutenin subunit</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q1ZZT4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low-molecular-weight glutenin subunit</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q6J162</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S-type low molecular weight glutenin</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K4AAT0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein (83% identity with Serpin-ZXA; Q75H81)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M8BX24</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t001fn001">
              <p>* This protein was identified in the two replicates of addition 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> and also in one replicate of the line 7<bold>A</bold>S&#xB7;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2;.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="sec012">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="sec013">
        <title>Development of wheat- chromosome 7H<sup>ch</sup> translocation lines in hexaploid wheat</title>
        <p>Crosses between chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> substitution line in wheat and the <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant in hexaploid wheat were made with the aim to introgress chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> in the background of the wheat <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant, to promote interespecific chromosome associations between chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> and its 7A wheat homoeologous and to reduce the size of chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> in the wheat background (<xref rid="pone.0134598.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Screening and characterization of plants carrying introgressions from <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> were carried out by molecular markers and multicolor <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization. BAWU550 and BAWU763 microsatellites were used to identify several plants carrying chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> introgressions (<xref rid="pone.0134598.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). The presence of both molecular markers indicated the presence of the whole chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> but could not discern between a whole chromosome introgression or heterozygous Robertsonian translocations between the <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> and the wheat homoeologous chromosomes, carrying one copy of 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;-7<bold>A</bold>L translocation and one copy of 7<bold>A</bold>S-7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; translocation. Translocations between chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> and wheat chromosomes were detected by GISH (<xref rid="pone.0134598.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). The use of molecular markers combined with GISH and FISH experiments enabled the determination of the exact chromosomal compositions and resolution of the chromosome arms involved in wheat-chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> translocations (Figs <xref rid="pone.0134598.g002" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0134598.g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Heterozygous 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#xB7;7<bold>A</bold>L and 7<bold>A</bold>S&#xB7;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; robertsonian translocations were only detected by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization. Several homozygous 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#xB7;7<bold>A</bold>L and 7<bold>A</bold>S&#xB7;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; translocation lines were obtained in the final selfed population.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0134598.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134598.g002</object-id>
          <label>Fig 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Identification of 7H<sup>ch</sup>&#x3B1; or 7H<sup>ch</sup>&#x3B2; chromosome arms in the wheat background and characterization of the wheat chromosome involved in chromosome translocations.</title>
            <p>The presence of A) 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;, B) 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2;, C) 7<bold>A</bold>S and D) 7<bold>A</bold>L chromosome arms is detected using BAWU550, BAWU763, Xgwm471 and Xgwm332 markers, respectively. Positive controls 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1; and 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; in panels A) and B) represent the wheat lines carrying either the 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1; or the 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; telosomic chromosomes in the wheat background. Lanes 1&#x2013;6 in A) and 1&#x2013;8 in B) corresponds to several 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#x2219;7<bold>A</bold>L and 7<bold>A</bold>S&#x2219;7 <bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; translocation lines, respectively. The polymorphic band in D) has been arrowed. L, ladder; CS, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>aestivum</italic> cv. Chinese Spring; H1, <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic>; L(7<bold>A</bold>)7<bold>D</bold>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>turgidum</italic> cv. Langdon (LDN) in which a pair of chromosome 7<bold>A</bold> has been substituted by chromosome 7<bold>D</bold> from CS; L(7<bold>B</bold>)7<bold>D</bold>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>turgidum</italic> cv. Langdon (LDN) in which a pair of chromosome 7<bold>B</bold> has been substituted by chromosome 7<bold>D</bold> from CS; CS(7<bold>A</bold>)7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>aestivum</italic> cv. Chinese Spring (CS) in which a pair of chromosome 7<bold>A</bold> has been substituted by a pair of chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> from <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic>, 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#x2219;7<bold>A</bold>L and 7<bold>A</bold>S&#x2219;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2;, disomic translocation lines in wheat.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0134598.g002"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone.0134598.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134598.g003</object-id>
          <label>Fig 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Example of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> chromosome introgressions in the progeny derived from the crosses (7A)7H<sup>ch</sup> substitution lines x <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant*2 and physical location of the <italic>Psy1</italic> gene on <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> chromosome 7H<sup>ch</sup> of bread wheat CS-<italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> (7A)7H<sup>ch</sup> substitution line.</title>
            <p>Genomic <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (GISH) was carried out using total <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> genomic DNA as a probe (detected in green). In fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (FISH) experiments, the pAs1 and the GAA sequences were used as probes (detected in green and red, respectively) to identify chromosomes involves in <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic>-wheat translocations. A PCR amplification product (2538bp) of the <italic>Psy1</italic> gene was used as a probe for physical mapping of the <italic>Psy1</italic> locus. The DNA was counterstained with DAPI (blue). A<bold>)</bold> GISH and B) FISH pattern of a mitotic metaphase carrying two copies of the 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#x2219;7<bold>A</bold>L Robertsonian translocation (arrowed). C) GISH and D) FISH of a mitotic metaphase carrying two copies of 7AS&#x2219;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; Robertsonian translocation (arrowed). E) GISH and F) FISH of a (7<bold>A</bold>)7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> substitution line showing two positive signals corresponding to the <italic>Psy1</italic> locus only on the two <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> chromosomes (arrowed). Scale Bar in F represents 10&#x3BC;m in all panels.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0134598.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In addition, the physical localization of <italic>Psy1</italic> gene was performed by fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization using a 2538bp fragment of the <italic>Pys1</italic> genomic DNA sequence as a probe. Based on the <italic>Psy1</italic> DNA sequence, primers were designed as described in the materials and methods section, to amplify the 2538bp fragment of the <italic>Psy1</italic> gene in <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic>. As expected, the <italic>Psy1</italic> locus was visualized on <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>and no signals were detected on the homoeologous wheat chromosomes (<xref rid="pone.0134598.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec014">
        <title>Analysis of the carotenoid composition in wheat-<italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> translocation lines</title>
        <p>The carotenoid profile was determined in <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> translocation lines for chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> in wheat and compared to wheat. The main carotenoids identified in all samples were lutein (free and esterified with fatty acids) and zeaxanthin, accounting for more than 95% of the total carotenoids. Trace amounts of &#x3B2;-carotene were additionally detected in some of the samples but were below the quantification threshold. Quantification of individual carotenoids and the amount of total carotenoids are showed in <xref rid="pone.0134598.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Total carotenoids (1215 &#xB1; 13 ng g<sup>-1</sup> dry weight (DW)) content in the 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#x2219;7<bold>A</bold>L translocation line was double than the wheat control and similar to that of the 7<bold>A</bold>S&#x2219;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; translocation line (1133 &#xB1; 68 ng g<sup>-1</sup> DW). As expected, the carotenoid content of the bread flour was the lowest (603 &#xB1; 59 ng g<sup>-1</sup> DW), followed by the chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> addition line in bread wheat (803 &#xB1; 58 ng g<sup>-1</sup> DW). Thus, the maximum carotenoid content was detected in the translocation lines for both 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1; or 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; chromosome arms in the background of <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant. The maximum content for zeaxanthin was detected in the 7<bold>A</bold>S&#x2219;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; translocation line, although this line showed the minimum content in esterified lutein. Our results clearly indicate that the new translocation lines generated showed higher carotenoid content than both bread wheat and the wheat line carrying the addition of a pair of the whole chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>, mainly due to the higher accumulation of free lutein.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0134598.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134598.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Carotenoid content in bread wheat, wheat-7H<sup>ch</sup> addition lines, and <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic>-wheat translocation lines.</title>
            <p>Data are mean &#xB1; SE of three biological replicates. The letters in italics indicate statistical significance (P &lt; 0.05).</p>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0134598.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0134598.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Wheat lines</th>
                  <th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Total carotenoids ng g<sup>-1</sup> DW</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free lutein</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#xA0;</th>
                  <th colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Esterified lutein</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zeathantin</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#xA0;</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ng g<sup>-1</sup> DW</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ng g<sup>-1</sup> DW</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ng g<sup>-1</sup> DW</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bread wheat</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">603 &#xB1; 59<italic>c</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">321 &#xB1; 39<italic>b</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.23</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 &#xB1; 13<italic>c</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.60</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 &#xB1; 6<italic>ab</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.32</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat-7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> disomic addition</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">803 &#xB1; 58<italic>b</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">326 &#xB1; 17<italic>b</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.60</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">268 &#xB1; 25<italic>a</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.37</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209 &#xB1; 15<italic>b</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.02</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#x2219;7<bold>A</bold>L disomic translocation</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1215 &#xB1; 13<italic>a</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">844 &#xB1; 17<italic>a</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.47</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176 &#xB1; 12<italic>b</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.47</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 &#xB1; 14<italic>c</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.08</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7<bold>A</bold>S&#x2219;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; disomic translocation</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1133 &#xB1; 68<italic>a</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">874 &#xB1; 43<italic>a</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23&#xB1; 5<italic>d</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235 &#xB1; 30<italic>a</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.80</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t002fn001">
              <p>*ng per g of dry weight (DW): ng g<sup>-1</sup> of dry weight</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec015">
        <title>Comparison of the seed proteomic profile among wheat and the introgression lines with carotenoid-enriched seeds</title>
        <p>Seed proteins were extracted from bread wheat and the three introgression lines with carotenoid enriched-seeds: the wheat lines carrying the addition of chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>, the translocation of 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1; chromosome arm (7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#x2219;7<bold>A</bold>L translocation) and the translocation of 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; chromosome arm (7<bold>A</bold>S&#x2219;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; translocation). The protein extraction protocol consisted on the extraction from two replicates of each line with a phenol-based buffer followed by precipitation with ammonium acetate. The quality and the complexity of the extracted proteins were checked by sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (1D-SDS-PAGE) prior to Nano-scale liquid chromatographic tandem mass spectrometry (nLC-MS/MS). The band pattern of the seed extracts was highly similar among lines (<xref rid="pone.0134598.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). Then, a high sensitive system of reverse-phase nLC coupled to a high resolution and mass accuracy mass spectrometer (LTQ-Orbitrap-Velos-Pro) was used to analyse the samples. To minimise the number of false positives or misidentifications a high level of confidence was applied for protein identification. Thus, only peptides with 5 to 30 amino acids and a minimum of two peptides per protein allowed a positive identification. A false discovery rate (FDR) &lt; 0.01 was also set. As a result, 741 different proteins were identified from all the seed extracts analysed (<xref rid="pone.0134598.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>).</p>
        <p>Only proteins that were present in the two replicates of each line were considered for further analysis (368). Ninety percent of the proteins (328) were common to the bread wheat and the introgression lines, while only ten percent of the proteins (40) were specifically present in some of the lines (<xref rid="pone.0134598.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). Twelve proteins were only identified in either the addition or in each of the translocation lines but not in the wild type. Out of them 7 proteins had as best hit a protein with unknown function, therefore to increase the information about these proteins manual blastp were performed in an attempt to find highly similar proteins with an assigned function. Only those proteins showing at least 80% identity were considered (<xref rid="pone.0134598.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0134598.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134598.g004</object-id>
          <label>Fig 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Venn diagram summarizing the proteins identified in seed extracts of bread wheat and carotenoid-enriched lines.</title>
            <p>Only peptides with 5 to 30 amino acids and a minimum of two peptides per protein allowed positive identifications, and peptide FDR &lt; 0.01</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0134598.g004"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The search for proteins with functions that could be potentially related to the regulation of carotenoid accumulation was carried out by searching at the whole set of proteins that were not present in bread wheat but in some of the other lines with higher carotenoid contents. This analysis led to the selection of a 14-3-3 protein, a small heat shock protein (sHSP, 26.4 kDa), and a HSP70-HSP90 organizing protein (O49996, A5A8UA, and D2E9R6, respectively).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec016">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Most mapping studies in wheat agree that quantitative trait loci (QTL) located on group 7 chromosomes largely determine the yellow pigment content of the grains (YPC). The <italic>Psy1</italic> gene, which encodes for the first reaction of the carotenoid biosynthetic pathway, was considered a candidate gene to explain the YPC of wheat grain since it maps to chromosomes 7<bold>A</bold> and 7<bold>B</bold> of durum and bread wheat [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>].</p>
      <p><italic>Tritordeums</italic>, which are amphiploids obtained after chromosome doubling of the hybrid between diploid, tetraploid or hexaploid wheat and <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic>, have higher carotenoid pigment content than durum or bread wheat [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Analysis of the flour pigment content in wheat-<italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> addition lines led to the conclusion that chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> from <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> confers the capacity to accumulate higher carotene concentration in seeds [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Moreover, the <italic>Psy1</italic> gene is the only gene related with the carotenoid biosynthetic pathway physically mapped in <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Taking into account all this information, we developed crosses between the (7<bold>A</bold>)7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> substitution line in wheat and the wheat <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant to facilitate chromosome associations and recombination between chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> and those from the wheat homoeologous group 7. Homozygous 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#x387;7<bold>A</bold>L and 7<bold>A</bold>S&#x2219;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; translocation lines in hexaploid wheat were obtained and the evaluation of the pigment content in this translocation lines was carried out. The 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#x2219;7<bold>A</bold>L translocation lines showed higher carotenoid content than bread wheat as expected because <italic>Psy1</italic> gene is located in 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1; chromosome arm from <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. This <italic>Psy1</italic> locus has been cytogenetically mapped on chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> in a (7<bold>A</bold>)7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> substitution line in bread wheat using the biotinyl tyramide system (Tyr-FISH) (<xref rid="pone.0134598.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>), and seemed to be specific from <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> as no signals were detected in any of the related wheat chromosomes 7<bold>A</bold>, 7<bold>B</bold> or 7<bold>D</bold>. In addition, the 7<bold>A</bold>S&#x2219;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; translocation line also showed higher total carotenoid content than the wheat control and similar to the 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#x2219;7<bold>A</bold>L. The high carotenoid levels in the 7<bold>A</bold>S&#x2219;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; line can be related to the presence of a QTL in the distal part of the 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; chromosome arm associated with the increment of YPC, although so far, there are no candidate genes described in this region related to YPC [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p>
      <p>The proteomics analysis comparing the endosperm proteome of the addition of 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> and the translocation of the 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; chromosome arms revealed the presence of 14-3-3 and heat shock proteins (HSPs, <xref rid="pone.0134598.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Both 14-3-3 and HSPs were previously described to be required for the translocation of nucleus-encoded chloroplast precursor proteins into the chloroplast [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. For example, plant DXP reductoisomerase (DXR) which catalyses the second step in the MEP pathway has an N-terminal transit domain with a putative motif for a 14-3-3 binding site [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Therefore, the post-translational modifications of biosynthetic proteins due to the interaction with 14-3-3 proteins and/or HSPs could be involved in the accumulation of carotenoids observed in the introgressed lines (<xref rid="pone.0134598.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Furthermore, several studies in tomato and grapefruit have revealed that HSPs are related to carotenoid accumulation [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. The 26.4 KDa heat-shock protein (A5A8U9), which was present in the line with the addition of 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> could also be playing a key role in the accumulation of carotenoids as small heat shock proteins were found to be the most abundant proteins present in the carotenoid-protein complexes of cassava roots, suggesting their involvement in the accumulation of these pigments. [<xref rid="pone.0134598.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec017">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>The translocation lines developed in this work are an important tool to enrich the carotenoid content in bread wheat. Moreover, there are not available neither substitution/addition lines nor translocation lines for chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> in durum wheat. Thus, these translocation lines are also a useful tool to transfer these chromosome arms into durum wheat, and therefore, to enrich carotenoid content in durum wheat.</p>
      <p>The comparison of the proteomic profile of the wheat introgression lines with bread wheat CS revealed that the overall protein content was scarcely altered by the introgression of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic> chromosome 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> or 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1; and 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; chromosome arms and suggested that HSPs and a 14-3-3-like protein could play a key role in the enhancement of carotenoid accumulation in seeds.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec018">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0134598.s001">
        <label>S1 Fig</label>
        <caption>
          <title>SDS-PAGE of seed protein extracts from bread wheat and carotenoid-enriched lines.</title>
          <p>SDS-PAGE stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue G250 of the seed protein extracts obtained from bread wheat (CS, lane 1), wheat-7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> disomic addition line (lane 2), and the 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#xB7;7<bold>A</bold>L (lane 3) and 7<bold>A</bold>S&#xB7;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; (lane 4) disomic translocation line<bold>s.</bold></p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0134598.s001.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0134598.s002">
        <label>S1 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Proteins identified by nLC-MS/MS.</title>
          <p>Proteins identified in seeds of bread wheat, wheat-7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup> disomic addition line, and the 7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B1;&#xB7;7<bold>A</bold>L and 7<bold>A</bold>S&#xB7;7<bold>H</bold><sup><bold>ch</bold></sup>&#x3B2; disomic translocation lines analyzed by nLC-MS/MS. Uniprot accession number, description, sequence of identified peptides, number of amino acids (AAs) of the identified protein, molecular weight of the identified protein, and number of peptides identified in each line are described.</p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0134598.s002.xlsx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors are grateful to Steve Reader (John Innes Centre, Norwich, UK) for the gift of the necessary cytogenetic stocks. Protein identification by LC/MS/MS was carried out in the CBMSO PROTEIN CHEMISTRY FACILITY that belongs to ProteoRed, PRB2-ISCIII.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref001">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Friebe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>,<name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Recent advances in alien gene transfer in wheat</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source>. <year>1994</year>; <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>212</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref002">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mart&#xED;n</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mart&#xED;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chromosomal localization of genes for carotenoid pigments using addition lines of <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> in wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant Breeding</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>289</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref003">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fosrter</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chromosome location of genes controlling tolerance to salt (NaCl) and vigour in <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> and <italic>H</italic>. <italic>chilense</italic></article-title>. <source>Heredity</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref004">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mart&#xED;n A, Mart&#xED;n LM, Cabrera A, Ramirez MC, Jimenez MJ, Rubiales D,et al. The potential of <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> in breeding Triticeae species. In Triticeae III. 1998; 377&#x2013;386.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref005">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rubiales</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reader</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mart&#xED;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chromosomal location of resistance of <italic>Septoria tritici</italic> in <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> determined by the study of chromosomal addition and substitution lines in &#x201C;Chinese Spring&#x201D; wheat</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>115</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>224</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref006">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mart&#xED;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cytogenetics of <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic>: current status and considerations with reference to breeding</article-title>. <source>Cytogenetic and Genome Research</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>109</volume>: <fpage>378</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>384</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15753600?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15753600</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref007">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Miller TE, Reader SM, Chapman V. addition of <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> chromosomes to wheat. In Induced variability in plant breeding: Internat. Symp. of the Sect. Mutation and Polyploidy of the European Assoc. for Research on Plant Breeding, Wageningen. 1982; 79&#x2013;81.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref008">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Islam AKMR. Production and characterization of wheat-barley addition lines. In Proceedings of the 5<sup>th</sup> International Wheat genetics Symposium. (<italic>Edited by</italic>: <italic>Ramanujam S</italic>). 1978; 356&#x2013;371.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref009">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>AKMR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>DHB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Isolation and characterization of euplasmic wheat-barley chromosome addition lines</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>46</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>174</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref010">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>. <article-title>Agropyron-wheat transfer through induced homoeologous pairing</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Genetics and Cytology</source>. <year>1972</year>;<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>746</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref011">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>. <article-title>Transfer of alien genetic material to wheat</article-title>. <source>Wheat Science-today and tomorrow</source>. <year>1981</year>; <fpage>75</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref012">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Islam AKMR, Shepherd KW. Induced pairing between wheat and barley chromosomes. In Proceedings of the 7<sup>th</sup> International Wheat Genet Symposium. (Edited by: Miller TE, Koebner RMD). 1988; 309&#x2013;314.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref013">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>A synaptic effect of chromosome V</article-title>. <source>Wheat Information Service</source>. <year>1957</year>;<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>6</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref014">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genetic control of cytologically diploid behaviour of hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1958</year>;<volume>182</volume>: <fpage>713</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>715</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref015">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>The diploidization of polyploidy wheat</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source><year>1960</year>;<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>429</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref016">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Intergenomic chromosomes relationships in hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>In Proceeding Tenth International Congress of Genetics</source><year>1958</year>;<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>258</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>259</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref017">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>. <article-title>Induced mutant with homoeologous pairing in common wheat</article-title>. <source><italic>Canadian</italic> Journal of Genetics and Cytology</source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>593</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref018">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Foote</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bertin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wanous</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reader</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Molecular characterization of <italic>Ph1</italic> as a major chromosome pairing locus in polyploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>439</volume>: <fpage>749</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>752</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16467840?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16467840</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref019">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dynamics of DNA replication during premeiosis and early meiosis in wheat</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>: (10)<fpage>e107714</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25275307</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref020">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mart&#xED;n</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pendle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal><article-title>The <italic>Ph1</italic> locus suppresses cdk2-type activity during premeiosis and meiosis in wheat</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>152</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>162</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.111.094771">10.1105/tpc.111.094771</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22274628?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22274628</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref021">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yousafzai</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Al-Kaff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>The molecular features of chromosome pairing at meiosis: the polyploidy challenge using wheat as a reference</article-title>. <source>Functional and Integrative Genomics</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>147</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>156</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10142-010-0171-6">10.1007/s10142-010-0171-6</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 20422242?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20422242</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref022">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calderon</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>The use of the ph1b mutant to induce recombination between the chromosomes of wheat and barley</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>160</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2015.00160">10.3389/fpls.2015.00160</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 25852713?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25852713</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref023">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Halvorsen</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holte</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Myhrstad</surname><given-names>MCW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barikmo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hvattum</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Remberg</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A systematic screening of total antioxidants in dietary plants</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Nutrition</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>132</volume>: <fpage>461</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>471</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11880572?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11880572</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref024">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Farr&#xE9;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanahuja</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naqvi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Capell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Travel advice on the road to carotenoids in plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Science</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>179</volume>: <fpage>28</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref025">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bramley</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>. <article-title>The biosynthesis and nutritional uses of carotenoids</article-title>. <source>Progress in Lipids Research</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>228</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>265</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref026">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodr&#xED;guez-Su&#xE1;rez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mellado-Ortega</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hornero-M&#xE9;ndez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Atienza</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Increase in transcript accumulation of <italic>Psy1</italic> and e<italic>-Lcy</italic> genes in grain development is associated with differences in seed carotenoid content between durum Wheat and tritordeum</article-title>. <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>. <year>2014</year>:<volume>84</volume>: <fpage>659</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>673</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11103-013-0160-y">10.1007/s11103-013-0160-y</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 24306494?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24306494</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref027">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lepage</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>RPA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Carotenoids of wheat flour: Their identification and composition</article-title>. <source>Cereal Chemistry</source>. <year>1968</year>;<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>600</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>604</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref028">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagamine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Esterification of endosperm lutein with fatty acids during the storage of wheat seeds</article-title>. <source>Bioscience, Biotechnology, and Biochemistry</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref029">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hentschel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katja</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hollmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lindhauer</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>B&#xF6;hm</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bitsch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Spectrophotometric determination of yellow pigment content and evaluation of carotenoids by high-performance liquid chromatography in durum wheat grain</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>50</volume>: <fpage>6663</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6668</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12405758?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12405758</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref030">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodr&#xED;guez-Su&#xE1;rez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Atienza</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>. <article-title><italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> genome, a useful tool to investigate the endosperm yellow pigment content in the <italic>Triticeae</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biology</source>. <year>2012b</year>;<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>200</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23122232</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref031">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Atienza</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>&#xC1;vila</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mart&#xED;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The development of a PCR-based marker for <italic>PSY1</italic> from <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic>, a candidate gene for carotenoid content accumulation in tritordeum seeds</article-title>. <source>Crop and Pasture Science</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>58</volume>: <fpage>767</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>773</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref032">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Atienza</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ram&#xED;rez</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hern&#xE1;ndez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mart&#xED;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chromosomal location of genes for carotenoid pigments in <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Breeding</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>123</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>304</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref033">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vallabhaneni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wurtzel</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>. <article-title>PSY3, a new member of the phytoene synthase gene family conserved in the Poaceae and regulator of abiotic stress-induced root carotenogenesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>146</volume>: <fpage>1333</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1345</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 18162592?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18162592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref034">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schwarzacher</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leitch</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heslop-Harrison</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>. <article-title><italic>In situ</italic> localization of parental genomes in a wild hybrid</article-title>. <source>Annals of Botany</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>64</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>324</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref035">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ram&#xED;rez</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, J. <name><surname>Ballesteros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>,<name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification of intergenomic translocations involving wheat, <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> and <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> chromosomes by FISH</article-title>. <source>Hereditas</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>135</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>174</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12152330</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref036">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Gijlswijk</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zijlmans</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weigant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bobrow</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Fuorochrome-labeled tyramides: use in immunocytochemistry and fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization</article-title>. <source>Journal of Histochemistry and Cytochemistry</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>382</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 9071319?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9071319</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref037">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dinesh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagendra</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Wheat triticin: a potential target for nutritional quality improvement</article-title>. <source>Asian Journal of Biotechnology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref038">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tasleem-Tahir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nadaud</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Girousse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Branlard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Proteomic analysis of peripheral layers during wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) grain development</article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>379</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/pmic.201000333">10.1002/pmic.201000333</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21268267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21268267</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref039">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Larr&#xE9;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lupi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gombaud</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brossard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Branlard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moneret-Vautrin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Assessment of allergenicity of diploid and hexaploid wheat genotypes: identification of allergens in the albumin/globulin fraction</article-title>. <source><italic>Journal of</italic> Proteomics</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>74</volume>: <fpage>1279</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1289</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21473946</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref040">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Altenbach</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vensel</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>: <article-title>The spectrum of low molecular weight alpha-amylase/protease inhibitor genes expressed in the US bread wheat cultivar Butte 86</article-title>. <source>BMC Research Notes</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>242</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1756-0500-4-242">10.1186/1756-0500-4-242</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21774824?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21774824</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref041">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nadolska-Orczyk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gasparis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orczyk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>The determinants of grain texture in cereals</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Genetics</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>50</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF03195672">10.1007/BF03195672</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 19638673?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19638673</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref042">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De Angelis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Minervini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cassone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calasso</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>,<etal>et al</etal><article-title>Proteomic analysis by two-dimensional gel electrophoresis and starch characterization of <italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> L. var. durum cultivars for pasta making</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>8619</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8628</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/jf8008876">10.1021/jf8008876</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18754666?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18754666</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref043">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genetic control of chromosome pairing in wheat</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Genetic</source>. <year>1976</year>:<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>51</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref044">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Rapid isolation of high molecular weight plant DNA</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>4321</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4326</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 7433111?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7433111</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref045">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hern&#xE1;ndez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dorado</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jim&#xE9;nez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ram&#xED;rez</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A core genetic map of <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> and comparisons with maps of barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>) and wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>1259</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1264</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref046">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Development of a Scar marker for the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus in common wheat and its application</article-title>. <source>Crop Science</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1365</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1368</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref047">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hagras</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kishii</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsujimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genomic differentiation of <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> from <italic>H</italic>. <italic>vulgar</italic>e a revealed by repetitive and EST sequences</article-title>. <source>Genes and Genetic Systems</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>80</volume>: <fpage>147</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>159</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16172528?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16172528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref048">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>R&#xF6;der</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Korzun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wendehake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plaschke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tixier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leroy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A microsatellite map of wheat</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>149</volume>: <fpage>2007</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2023</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 9691054?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9691054</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref049">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mart&#xED;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chromosomal distribution of telomeric and telomeric-associated sequences in <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization</article-title>. <source>Hereditas</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>141</volume>: <fpage>122</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>127</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15660972?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15660972</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref050">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Friebe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Characterization of <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> chromosomes by C-banding and <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization using highly repeated DNA probes</article-title>. <source>Genome</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>435</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>442</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 18470181?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18470181</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref051">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rayburn</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Isolation of a D-genome specific repeated DNA sequence from <italic>Aegilops squarrosa</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Molecular Biology Reporter</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>102</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>109</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref052">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Langridge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification of the entire chromosome complement of bread wheat by two-color FISH</article-title>. <source>Genome</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>589</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>593</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 18464850?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18464850</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref053">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Linde-Laursen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genome and chromosome identification in cultivated barley and related species of the Triticeae (Poaceae) by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization with the GAA-satellite sequence</article-title>. <source>Genome</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>104</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8851798?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8851798</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref054">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calder&#xF3;n</surname><given-names>MDC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>MDC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mart&#xED;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>,<name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Development of <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> 4H<sup>ch</sup> introgression lines in durum wheat: a tool for breeders and complex trait analysis</article-title>. <source>Plant Breeding</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>131</volume>: <fpage>733</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>738</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref055">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Untergasser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nijveen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bisseling</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geurts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <article-title>Leunissen JA: Pimer3plus, an enhanced web interface to Primer3</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>W71</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>W74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17485472</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref056">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodr&#xED;guez-Su&#xE1;rez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gim&#xE9;nez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guti&#xE9;rrez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>&#xC1;vila</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huttner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Development of wild barley (<italic>Hordeum chilense</italic>)-derived DArT markers and their use into genetic and physical mapping</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>. <year>2012a</year>;<volume>124</volume>: <fpage>713</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>722</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00122-011-1741-2">10.1007/s00122-011-1741-2</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22048641?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22048641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref057">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>. <article-title>Allelic variants at the <italic>TaZds-D1</italic> locus on wheat chromosome 2DL and their association with yellow pigment content</article-title>. <source>Crop Science</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1580</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1590</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref058">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Carmona</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zacar&#xED;as</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stimulation of coloration and carotenoid biosynthesis during postharvest storage of &#x2018;Navelina&#x2019; orange fruit at 12&#xB0;C</article-title>. <source>Postharvest Biology and Technology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>74</volume>: <fpage>108</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>117</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref059">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marcos</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zacar&#xED;as</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biochemical and molecular analysis of carotenoid biosynthesis in flavedo of orange (<italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> L.) during fruit development and maturation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>6724</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6731</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15506808?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15506808</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref060">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marcos</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alferez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mallent</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zacar&#xED;as</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Characterization of Pinalate, a novel Citrus sinensis mutant with a fruit-specific alteration that results in yellow pigmentation and decreased ABA content</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>54</volume>: <fpage>727</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>738</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12554716?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12554716</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref061">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Overwiew of carotenoid biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>In Carotenoids: Biosynthesis and Metabolism</source>. (Edited by: <name><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>LiaaenJensen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Pfander</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>). <year>1998</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>384</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>389</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref062">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rouseff</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hofsommer</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Application of diode array detection with a C-30 reversed phase column for the separation and identification of saponified orange juice carotenoids</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>2176</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2181</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref063">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Collado-Romero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Al&#xF3;s</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Unravelling the proteomic profile of rice meiocytes during early meiosis</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>356</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2014.00356">10.3389/fpls.2014.00356</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 25104955?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25104955</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref064">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodr&#xED;guez-Su&#xE1;rez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gim&#xE9;nez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Atienza</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Progress and perspectives for carotenoid accumulation in selected <italic>Triticeae</italic> species</article-title>. <source>Crop and Pasture Science</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>743</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>751</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref065">
        <label>65</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>,<name><surname>Soll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>.<article-title>14-3-3 proteins form a guidance complex with chloroplast precursor proteins in plants</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10634907</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref066">
        <label>66</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krushkal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weathers</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Computational analysis of the evolution of 1-deoxy-D-xylulose-5-phosphate Reductoisomerase, an important enzyme in plant terpene biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Chemistry and Biodiversity</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1098</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1110</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/cbdv.200900313">10.1002/cbdv.200900313</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 20491066?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20491066</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref067">
        <label>67</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Neta-Sharir</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Isaacson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lurie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dual role for tomato heat shock protein 21: protecting photosystem II from oxidative stress and promoting colour changes during fruit maturation</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1829</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1838</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15879560?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15879560</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref068">
        <label>68</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lado</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cronje</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alqu&#xE9;zar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>G&#xF3;mez-Cadenas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Fruit shading enhances peel colour, carotenes accumulation and chromoplast differentiation in red grapefruit</article-title>. <source>Physiologia Plantarum</source>. <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref069">
        <label>69</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karlova</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosin</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Busscher-Lange</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parapunova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fernier</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Transcriptome and metabolite profiling show that APETALA2a is a major regulator of tomato fruit ripening</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>923</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>941</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.110.081273">10.1105/tpc.110.081273</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21398570?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21398570</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0134598.ref070">
        <label>70</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>LJCB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lippolis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>CRB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>.<article-title>Characterization of carotenoid-protein complexes and gene expression analysis associated with carotenoid sequestration in pigmented cassava (<italic>Manihot Esculenta</italic> Crantz) storage root</article-title>. <source>The Open Biochemistry Journal</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>116</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>130</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2174/1874091X01206010116">10.2174/1874091X01206010116</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23230451?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23230451</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
