<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4561380</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep13845</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep13845</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Unveiling the metabolic potential of two soil-derived microbial consortia selected on wheat straw</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jim&#xE9;nez</surname>
            <given-names>Diego Javier</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chaves-Moreno</surname>
            <given-names>Diego</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>van Elsas</surname>
            <given-names>Jan Dirk</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Microbial Ecology, Groningen Institute for Evolutionary Life Sciences, University of Groningen</institution>. Nijenborgh 7, 9747AG. Groningen, <country>The Netherlands</country></aff>
        <aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Helmholtz&#x2013;Centre for Infection Research</institution>, Inhoffenstr 7, 38124. Braunschweig, <country>Germany</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1">
          <label>a</label>
          <email>d.j.jimenez.avella@rug.nl</email>
        </corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>07</day>
        <month>09</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>5</volume>
      <elocation-id>13845</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>08</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2015, Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-holder>
        <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <!--author-paid-->
          <license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x2019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Based on the premise that plant biomass can be efficiently degraded by mixed microbial cultures and/or enzymes, we here applied a targeted metagenomics-based approach to explore the metabolic potential of two forest soil-derived lignocellulolytic microbial consortia, denoted RWS and TWS (bred on wheat straw). Using the metagenomes of three selected batches of two experimental systems, about 1.2&#x2009;Gb of sequence was generated. Comparative analyses revealed an overrepresentation of predicted carbohydrate transporters (ABC, TonB and phosphotransferases), two-component sensing systems and &#x3B2;-glucosidases/galactosidases in the two consortia as compared to the forest soil inoculum. Additionally, &#x201C;profiling&#x201D; of carbohydrate-active enzymes showed significant enrichments of several genes encoding glycosyl hydrolases of families GH2, GH43, GH92 and GH95. Sequence analyses revealed these to be most strongly affiliated to genes present on the genomes of <italic>Sphingobacterium</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Flavobacterium</italic> and <italic>Pedobacter spp</italic>. Assembly of the RWS and TWS metagenomes generated 16,536 and 15,902 contigs of &#x2265;10&#x2009;Kb, respectively. Thirteen contigs, containing 39 glycosyl hydrolase genes, constitute novel (hemi)cellulose utilization loci with affiliation to sequences primarily found in the Bacteroidetes. Overall, this study provides deep insight in the plant polysaccharide degrading capabilities of microbial consortia bred from forest soil, highlighting their biotechnological potential.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>The recent thrust to use plant waste such as straw for the production of compounds such as biofuel, plastics and intermediates for pharmaceuticals has raised major questions about the efficiency of lignocellulose deconstruction driven by microorganisms<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>. Moreover, the physical-chemical structures of different plant remains may vary considerably, hampering efforts to design strategies to completely degrade lignocellulose across plant waste sources<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. One major source of straw is wheat, which contains, on average, 21% lignin, 28% hemicellulose and 36% cellulose<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. Heat treatment of wheat tissue results in a softening of the lignin part, turning the (hemi)cellulose moiety more amenable to enzymatic digestion<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>. However, heating produces trace amounts of process-inhibiting furanic compounds, next to sugars, small polysaccharides, acids and ash<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>. Thus, in the light of the complexity of the (wheat) waste source, efficient bioconversion may depend on the synergistic action of diverse enzymes, such as hemicellulases, endo/exoglucanases and &#x3B2;-glucosidases. Hemicellulases include a variety of enzymes with different activities, such as mannosidases, arabinofuranosidases, fucosidases, galactosidases and xylanases. These glycosyl hydrolases (GH) act directly on the three major hemicellulose structures xylan, xyloglucan and galacto(gluco)mannan<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>. Hemicellulases, by nature, are known to enhance the conversion of lignocellulosic biomass to monosaccharides, thus improving the action of commercial cellulase-based enzyme cocktails<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>.</p>
    <p>Unfortunately, we hitherto understand very little about the intricacies of lignocellulose biodegradation processes in microbial consortia. A key assumption about the mechanisms in such consortia is that the Darwinian principle of survival of the fittest reigns. Thus, sets of &#x201C;locally fit&#x201D; microorganisms in relative abundances that are appropriate for efficient biodegradation are predicted to be obtained at each time point in the process. A &#x201C;matured&#x201D; consortium then presumably contains all of the microbial members that have been, or are, important for the biodegradative process. Based on such assumptions, analyses of such matured consortia via metagenomics<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref> offer exciting possibilities to foster our understanding of the biodegradative process. In such analyses, the interplay of biodegradative next to other (supporting) processes may be unveiled, shedding light on the intricate ways in which the microbes that constitute the consortium interact with their environment and among themselves. In addition, genes that encode novel enzymes may become accessible, improving our knowledge on the biodegradative capacity of the individual members of the selected microbial communities<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>.</p>
    <p>Current analyses of metagenomics-based datasets rely strongly on alignment of sequences against those present in databases. In the &#x201C;Carbohydrate-Active Enzyme database&#x201D; (CAZy), enzymes that hydrolyze diverse carbohydrates are classified into different GH families on the basis of their amino acid sequences<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>. Examination of the CAZy database reveals enormous sequence diversity, even within each gene family. On top of that, every new study on natural systems is expected to add more diversity to the database, as evidenced by recent work on the microbiomes of switchgrass-adapted compost<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>, herbivorous insects<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>, poplar wood chips<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>, buffalo rumen<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref> and snail guts<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>. To foster our understanding of the interplay of the different enzymatic processes in biodegradative microbial communities, it is important to reduce the diversity. Lignocellulose-based enrichments constitute an excellent vehicle to achieve this aim. Recently, Wongwilaiwalin <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref> analyzed a rice straw-degrading microbial consortium enriched from sugarcane bagasse. Nine hundred and fifty seven GH-encoding genes were found, the most abundant ones belonging to the GH2, GH3 and GH43 families. Also, Deangelis <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref> compared the metagenomes of two switchgrass-bred consortia (one of them amended with Fe). Enrichments of the GH65 family, sugar transporters (ABC systems), oxidoreductases and [Fe-S] binding proteins were found in the Fe-amended consortia. However, both studies did not address the levels of enrichment of such genes as compared to the microbial source nor did they analyze the genetic backgrounds of the identified GH-encoding genes. The latter analysis might allow the detection of metabolic pathways, regulatory mechanisms and substrate sensing/transport functions.</p>
    <p>In previous work, we obtained two microbial consortia from forest soil by sequential transfers on <italic>i</italic>) untreated and <italic>ii</italic>) heat-treated wheat straw. Both consortia grew efficiently in each step and showed (hemi)cellulolytic enzymatic activities in the extracellular fractions<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>. In order to analyze the lignocellulolytic machineries present in the two consortia, we performed whole-metagenome analyses of selected consortia in a time course. We hypothesize that the microbial consortia analyzed were or became fine-tuned with respect to the utilization of resources from the wheat straw. The data from this study foster our understanding of the ecology of straw degradation and straw-based selection. They also give insight into the metabolic potential present in the resulting microbial consortia, opening up possibilities for further ecological and biotechnological studies.</p>
    <sec disp-level="1" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Selection of microbial consortia and production of metagenomic DNA</title>
        <p>To foster our understanding of the genetic make-up of the &#x201C;phylogenetically-stable&#x201D; lignocellulose-degrading consortia, two biodegradative consortia, denoted RWS (bred on untreated wheat straw) and TWS (bred on heat-treated wheat straw), were selected, each at three time points. In addition, the source community (forest soil-derived) was selected as a comparator. Based on preliminary results from Fourier transformed infrared spectroscopical (FTIR) analyses, we obtained evidence for slightly higher percentages of lignin, hemicellulose and cellulose in the RWS (untreated wheat straw) compared with TWS (heat treated) substrate (data not shown).</p>
        <p>Metagenomic DNA from all microbial consortia was successfully obtained at a rate of, on average, about 0.75&#x2009;&#x3BC;g/ml culture (containing roughly 10<sup>8</sup> bacterial cells/ml). A calculation of the extraction efficiency revealed that &gt;90% of the bacterial cells in these had been captured into the extracts<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. Illumina Mi-Seq sequencing of the metagenomes of the seven samples (forest soil-derived inoculum: FS1; transfer 1, 3 and 10 in RWS: 1W, 3W and 10W; and transfer 1, 3 and 10 in TWS: 1T, 3T and 10T) yielded a total of 5,067,095 sequence reads (average length 272&#x2009;bp) that passed the quality criteria used, with a range of 385,175 to 1,026,339 reads per sample. The total genomic information (Mb) thus obtained for each metagenome was 136.82 (FS1), 170.58 (1W), 293.17 (3W), 112.23 (10W), 238.95 (1T), 221.46 (3T) and 198.10 (10T). On this basis, calculated coverage values for these respective metagenomes were 0.10, 0.39, 0.65, 0.28, 0.59, 1.23 and 1.05. The average G&#x2009;+&#x2009;C contents per metagenome showed strongly reduced values, of &lt;50%, in the selected consortium samples as compared to that of the source community (60&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9%). Thus, G&#x2009;+&#x2009;C values measured in the latest enrichments were 41&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;12% and 49&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;13%, for 10W and 10T, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Taxonomic assignment based on total protein-encoding and bacterial 16S rRNA gene sequences</title>
        <p>MG-RAST-based<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref> annotation analyses of the reads in all metagenomes showed that around 70% of those in the RWS and TWS datasets had homologs on bacterial genomes (RefSeq database). The remaining reads (roughly 30%) were similar to unannotated genomic regions (e.g. unknown DNA or intragenic sequences). The total reads that could be affiliated to Eukarya with the existing tools was consistently low (&lt;0.001% across all metagenomes). In contrast to the above, only 38% of the reads from the FS1 source community was predicted to encode proteins. On the basis of an analysis of the affiliation of the collective protein-encoding sequences, the bacterial community structures (at genus level) turned out to be quite different (r<sup>2</sup>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.480) between the RWS and the TWS consortia (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>). They were also different from that of the FS1 source community. Remarkably, in the FS1 metagenome, one 16S rRNA sequence was retrieved per 11,276 reads, whereas in the RWS as well as TWS consortium ones, the ratios were 1/800, 1/820, 1/618, 1/673, 1/576 and 1/628 for 1W, 3W, 10W, 1T, 3T and 10T, respectively. Considering the phylogenetic affiliations, some differences were observed between the taxonomic profile based on protein-encoding and the bacterial 16S rRNA gene sequences. For example after transfer-3, a predominance of <italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sequences (35% versus 3% of <italic>Klebsiella</italic>) was found in the 16S rRNA-based classification, while <italic>Klebsiella</italic>-like sequences were most abundant in the protein-encoding gene approach (~15% versus 10% of <italic>Sphingobacterium</italic>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Functional profiles &#x2014; evidence for a dominance of ABC transporters and TonB-dependent receptors</title>
        <p>In order to obtain a robust metabolic profile, two databases were used for the analyses (KEGG and SEED). Based on principal components analyses (PCA) of the KEGG-based functional profiles, the TWS metagenome samples 1T, 3T and 10T all clustered together, suggesting stabilization and preservation of function as from transfer-1. Quite remarkably, these metagenomes still revealed considerable levels of similarity with those from RWS (r<sup>2</sup>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.890). Thus, both consortia showed largely similar functional profiles at three time points, which were clearly different from those of the FS1 community (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1a,b</xref>). Pairwise analyses revealed that FS1 and RWS correlated at r<sup>2</sup>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.608 and FS1 and TWS at r<sup>2</sup>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.513.</p>
        <p>Close examination of the differences between the RWS and TWS consortium metagenomes on the one hand and the FS1 community one on the other hand showed several significantly enriched functions (p&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005), at KEGG orthology level 2. These were membrane transport systems (mainly ABC transporters) next to systems for the metabolism of cofactors and vitamins, cell motility and glycan biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. S2</xref>). ABC transporters (ABCT) (9.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.9% and 13&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.7% relative abundance -RA- in RWS and TWS samples, respectively, versus ~8.5% in FS1) and two-component system proteins (TCSP) (6.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.25% RA in both consortia, versus ~5% in FS1) were the most abundant functions in both consortia. The most overrepresented (p&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005) specific functions, after transfer-3, in the RWS and TWS metagenomes were iron transport system permease proteins (up to 10-fold RA increases), formate C-acetyltransferases (~2&#x2013;5-fold RA increase). In addition, methyl-accepting chemotaxis proteins and phosphotransferase system (PTS)-cellobiose-specific IIC components were also enriched. Interestingly and with respect to the biodegradative process, sequences predicted to encode enzymes involved in lignocellulose degradation were indeed also overrepresented in the RWS and TWS consortia as compared to the FS1 community. This included (partial) genes encoding &#x3B2;-glucosidases (1.62, 1.83, 1.62 and 1.29 -fold RA increases in 3W,10W, 3T and 10T, respectively), &#x3B2;-galactosidases (3.09, 2.57, 2.36 and 2.09 -fold RA increases in 3W, 10W, 3T and 10T, respectively) and catalases (2.61, 2.18, 1.96 and 2.72 -fold RA increases in 3W, 10W, 3T and 10T, respectively) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1c</xref>).</p>
        <p>Comparative SEED-based analyses of the RWS and TWS consortium metagenomes versus that of the FS1 community showed that the most enriched specific genes (p&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005) in the 3W, 10W and 3T metagenomes were those for utilization of monosaccharides (2.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.16 -fold RA increase) as well as iron acquisition (4.53&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.26 -fold RA increase). In the 10T one, genes for proteins involved in iron acquisition were also strongly enriched (5-fold RA increase) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>). In the 3W and 10W metagenomes, genes for TonB-dependent receptors (TBR) (4.63 and 4.15 -fold RA increases, respectively), and, to a lesser extent, for ferrichrome-iron receptors and &#x3B2;-galactosidases were enriched in comparison to the FS1 one (p&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005). In contrast, genes for decarboxylases were highly abundant in FS1, 3W and 10W (~0.65% RA) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2a</xref>). For TWS, TBR (3.4 and 5.6 -fold increases in 3T and 10T, respectively), ferrichrome-iron receptors and &#x3B2;-galactosidases were enriched in the 3T metagenome, whereas decarboxylases were depleted at 10T (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2b</xref>). On the other hand, three specific functions, i.e. adenylate cyclase, carbon monoxide dehydrogenase and cobalt/cadmium/zinc resistance proteins, were strongly deselected (p&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005) in the two systems.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Genes predicted to be involved in lignocellulose degradation</title>
        <p>In order to detect genes, or parts thereof, involved in lignocellulose deconstruction, we performed BLASTX of all metagenome reads against the CAZy database. The results show that, after transfer-3, the carbohydrate-active genetic profiles were stable and consistent in the RWS and TWS metagenomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>). The most enriched functions at the last transfers (compared with FS1) were polysaccharide lyases (PL) (0.43 and 0.33 log X-fold in 10W and 10T, respectively) and GH (0.11 and 0.12 log X-fold in 10W and 10T, respectively) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref>). The correlation (r<sup>2</sup>) between the RWS and TWS consortium metagenomes was 0.970. Specific enzyme families that abounded in the TWS and RWS metagenomes were glycosyl transferase (GT) families 2 (~8.5% RA) and 4 (~6.5% RA), followed by GH2, GH13 and GH3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3c</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <p>An overall examination of the data revealed the presence of a high diversity of predicted enzymes, with respect to the number and diversity of CAZy families. To reduce the complexity of the data, we selected a &#x201C;top-60&#x201D; of the most enriched CAZy families in both consortia for further analyses. Data on count matches, RA and log<sub>10</sub> fold increases for each consortium and transfer are presented in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>. As compared to the FS1 source community, some genes of particular families were highly enriched (&#x2265;1 log<sub>10</sub> unit) in both derived consortia, albeit at rather low (&#x2264;0.3) RA levels. Specifically, these were genes for the GH117, GH50, GT8 and PL17 family proteins. The most abundant (approximately&#x2009;&gt;1.5% RA) enriched (p&#x2009;&lt;0.005) families in the two consortia were GH1, GH2, GH3, GH20, GH29, GH31, GH43, GH92, GH95 and CBM50. Remarkably, enrichment of these was already apparent as from transfer-1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. S4</xref>), suggesting the occurrence of a strong selective effect early on in the consortium enrichments. Specifically, reads falling in families GH1, GH2, GH31 and CBM50 were enriched along the transfers in the RWS and those of families GH2, GH20, GH29, GH43, GH92 and GH95 in the TWS metagenomes. In contrast, reads for families PL17, GH50, GH3 and GH13 were deselected or showed a neutral behavior along the transfers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>CAZy families enriched at transfer-10 - tracking richness and microbial source</title>
        <p>The reads of overrepresented CAZy families at transfer-10 (stable community) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4a,b</xref>) were clustered at 97% nucleotide identity cut-off and taxonomically classified. Using the normalized numbers of clusters in each family, we observed that reads assigned to all enriched CAZy families (except CBM50) in 10T showed lower &#x201C;richness&#x201D; values than those in 10W and FS1. Richness was defined as the number of clusters at 97% nucleotide identity over total retrieved reads in each family. Families GH1, GH31, CBM50 and GH92 showed &#x201C;richness&#x201D; values between 0.71 to 0.69 in 10W, but GH20, GH95, GH92 and GH29 had &#x201C;richness&#x201D; values between 0.35 to 0.29 in 10T (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3d</xref>). Based on the taxonomic classification by the lowest common ancestor (LCA) algorithm<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4c</xref>), the GH2, GH20, GH29, GH43, GH92, GH95 reads were mainly assigned to genomes of members of the Bacteroidetes (e.g. <italic>Sphingobacterium</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Flavobacterium</italic> and <italic>Pedobacter</italic>). Moreover, sequences that belonged to the GH1, GH3, GH31 and CBM50 families were mostly affiliated with organisms from within the Enterobacteriaceae, especially within <italic>Klebsiella</italic>. The taxonomic affiliation of the GH retrieved from transfer-1 and -3, in both consortia, showed similar results, indicating that the enrichments selected for GH assigned to members of the Bacteroidetes and Enterobacteriaceae.</p>
        <p>Additionally, in order to explore whether the reads make part of any specific genetic region, we performed an assembly (contigs&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;750 bp as a cut-off) of all reads in each overrepresented family. This approach yielded no contigs for the FS1 metagenome, indicating great heterogeneity. From the 10W metagenome, 17, 12, 9, 8 and 5 contigs were produced for the GH2, GH92, GH43, GH31 and GH29 families, respectively. Between 28.03 to 59.38% of the total retrieved reads, in each of these last families, were used. In contrast, in the 10T metagenome, 88, 86, 82, 81 and 79% of the total retrieved reads in GH29, GH92, GH31, GH2 and GH43 were used to construct 12, 15, 7, 13 and 15 contigs, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). Contigs (or complete genes) with the highest read coverage were analyzed by BLASTX against the nr-NCBI database. All GH-encoding genes in 10T were thus identified to derive from members of the Bacteroidetes, especially <italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> spp. However, the most abundant GH1, GH3 and GH31-encoding genes in 10W were affiliated with predicted proteins of <italic>Kluyvera ascorbata</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Contigs containing gene clusters predicted to be involved in (hemi)cellulose degradation</title>
        <p>Totals of 16,536 (contig mean length 3.6&#x2009;Kb) and 15,902 (contig mean length 3.4&#x2009;Kb) contigs were generated for the metagenomes obtained for the RWS and TWS consortia, respectively. Of these, 10,571 and 9,987 contigs, respectively for RWS and TWS, were &gt;1,000&#x2009;bp. Moreover, in RWS, 94&#x2009;GH genes (specifically belonging to families GH2, GH3, GH29, GH31, GH43, GH92 and GH95) were detected in 70 contigs (&#x2265;5&#x2009;Kb). In TWS, 75&#x2009;GH were identified in 58 contigs (&#x2265;5&#x2009;Kb) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S3</xref>). Thirteen large contigs (&#x2265;10&#x2009;Kb; G&#x2009;+&#x2009;C content between 35 to 42%; read coverage 14X to 30X) contained at least two GH genes. Based on CAZy annotations, in these contigs we identified a total of 39&#x2009;GH genes. Interestingly, 11 of these showed an identity less than 60% to already described proteins (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>). Regarding the RAST annotations, 25, 19 and 20 genes encoding TBR, ABCT and TCSP, respectively, were detected in the selected 13 contigs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref>). The tetranucleotide frequencies (TTNF) and average nucleotide identities (ANIb) results showed that these contigs were mainly affiliated with regions on genomes of <italic>Sphingobacterium</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Parabacteroides</italic>, <italic>Flavobacterium</italic> and <italic>Pedobacter</italic>. However, the 13 contigs showed an ANIb&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;72% and a correlation of TTNF less than 0.79, suggesting that these genomic fragments make part of as yet unknown (yet related) genomes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S4</xref>). Seven contigs were presumed to belong to organisms affiliated with <italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> (contigs 278, 373, 26, 4309 and 1110), <italic>Pedobacter</italic> (contig 248) and <italic>Parabacteroides</italic> (contig 316), on the basis of BLAST analyses of the GH genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>). All contigs were found to contain at least one complete predicted operon. Contigs 242, 248, 1110, 4309 and 3786 contained operons/genes with predicted roles in xylan, xyloglucan and galacto(gluco)mannan degradation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref>). In addition, contigs 278 and 26 contained operons/genes involved in the bioconversion of cellobiose (GH3). Contig 939 contained genes encoding L-ribulose-5-phosphate 4-epimerase, L-arabinose isomerase, aldose-1-epimerase and a putative lipoprotein. Interestingly, in contigs 278, 582, 248 and 1110 we found genes involved in sugar metabolism steps, such as transketolases (TKT) (3), xylose isomerase (XI) (3) and xylulose kinase (XKN) (4). In contig 1110, one putative gene involved in lignin metabolism (cytochrome peroxidase - EC1.11.1.5) was found. Finally, six genes encoding transcriptional regulators of the AraC family were found in contigs 316, 3786 and 1110 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="1" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this study, we analyzed 576 (RWS) and 658 (TWS) Mb of sequence information from two lignocellulose-bred microbial consortia, in comparison to a source community from forest soil (FS1). This allowed a robust comparative metagenomic analysis to be performed. To avoid biases, we used two different methodologies. First, unassembled sequences were used for taxonomic and functional assignments (using RefSeq, KEGG, SEED and CAZy), on the premise that such analyses would not &#x201C;distort&#x201D; the abundance and representation of the sequences of abundant species in the dataset<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>. In addition, we performed an assembly of reads in our metagenomes, allowing to recover complete genes and gene clusters or operons, and to study the arrangement of genes for the most overrepresented GH (compared with FS1). An estimation of the predicted abundance of the organisms carrying these gene clusters resulted in the contention that such organisms occurred among the top-5 members of these consortia.</p>
      <p>Comparative analyses of the consortium metagenome datasets versus those from the source community first revealed that organisms with genomes with relatively low G&#x2009;+&#x2009;C content had been strongly selected in the consortia. This indicated a selection of fast-growing decomposer organisms with, on average, lower G&#x2009;+&#x2009;C% genomes, e.g. Proteobacteria and Bacteroidetes, and concurrent deselection of the high G&#x2009;+&#x2009;C positive members of the soil microbiota, e.g. Actinobacteria. The fact that a majority (around 70%) of the predicted protein-encoding genes, or parts thereof, in both consortia had homologs (&gt;50% homology) on published bacterial genomes supported the contention of selection of bacterially-dominated degrading consortia. The differences between the percentages of mappable reads between the bred microbial consortia (~70%) and the soil inoculum (~38%) could be explained by the fact that soil contains high microbial diversity and DNA novelty compared with most enrichment cultures. The percentage of annotated reads in FS1 was similar to that found in previous soil metagenomics-based studies<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. Remarkably, we found differences and fluctuations between the taxonomic profile based on protein-encoding and the bacterial 16S rRNA gene sequences in the metagenomes under study. However, it is known that major biases exist in both gene enumerations, as both 16S rRNA and functional gene copy numbers may vary, differently, across genomes. In addition, their accuracy also depends on the representation of the different taxonomic groups in a database<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>. Based on an average copy number of four 16S rRNA gene sequences per bacterial genome of 4 Mb, and a mean length of 1.5&#x2009;Kb per gene copy, indeed roughly 1/1000 sequences are expected to represent 16S rRNA genes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>. Hence, the ratio&#x2019;s (1/618 to 1/820) obtained in the RWS and TWS consortia are indicative of largely bacterially-driven communities, whereas that in the FS1 source community (1/11,276) may have come about as a result of (1) undetectable &#x201C;novel&#x201D; 16S rRNA gene sequences, (2) the co-occurrence of a larger proportion of fungi, (3) a generally larger bacterial genome per cell (6&#x2013;12&#x2009;Mb) and (4) a generally lower number of rRNA gene copies per genome.</p>
      <p>With respect to the functional profiles, ABCT and phosphotransferase systems function in the cellular uptake of sugars (e.g. cellobiose, cellodextrin, glucose, galactose and mannose). In addition, some ABCT can import key ions such as Sn, Fe and Co<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>. Interestingly, ABCT may be differentially expressed in <italic>Clostridium</italic>, <italic>Thermobifida</italic> and <italic>Streptomyces</italic> species in response to different lignocellulosic substrates<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>, indicating their involvement in transport of intermediate products of biodegradation or sugars. Deangelis <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref> suggested that ABCT mediate - in <italic>Enterobacter lignolyticus</italic> - the transport of xylose and lignin-derived aromatic compounds into the cells. Moreover, ABCT were also abundantly present in a metagenome of the gut of a wood-feeding beetle (<italic>Anoplophora glabripennis</italic>)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref>. Overrepresentation of genes for these type of proteins was also evident in a tropical soil-microbial consortia selected by switchgrass<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>.</p>
      <p>Regarding TonB-dependent receptors (TBR) (outer membrane proteins that are known for the active transport of Fe-siderophore complexes, vitamin B12 and plant carbohydrates in Gram-negative bacteria), in <italic>Caulobacter crescentus</italic>, expression is induced by xylose<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">42</xref>. Blanvillain <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">43</xref> reported that, in phytopathogenic and aquatic bacteria, TBR are involved in scavenging of plant sugars. Fern&#xE1;ndez-G&#xF3;mez <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">44</xref> showed that genes encoding several polysaccharide-degrading proteins (e.g. &#x3B2;-galactosidases or &#x3B2;-xylosidases) are located in close proximity to genes for TBR and transducers (especially in Bacteroidetes), suggesting an integrated regulation of adhesion to, and degradation of, polysaccharides that are attacked by the products of the neighboring genes. An interesting study, in <italic>Gramella forsetii</italic>, revealed that TBR also could work as anticipatory polysaccharide sensors<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">45</xref>. With respect to the two-component system proteins (TCSP), these may sense carbohydrates using the sensing domain in the periplasm<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref>. In <italic>Clostridium cellulolyticum</italic>, TCSP perceive the presence of extracellular soluble sugars and regulate most GH and associated ABCT<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref>. In <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, these TCSP act similarly and regulate (hemi)cellulose utilization loci (HULs)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">47</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">48</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49">49</xref>.</p>
      <p>The overrepresentation of genes for ABCT, TBR and proteins involved in lignocellulose degradation (e.g. &#x3B2;-xylosidases) in RWS and TWS is consistent with the hypothesis that enhanced capacities are required in these consortia in order to facilitate the utilization of complex plant materials (e.g. hemicellulose) and transport the products (e.g. xylose) of various structures into the cells. Bacterial consortia were thus selected that metabolize the partially degraded plant material. In addition, the genomic machineries in these consortia (especially TCSP or TBR) apparently sense the activation of GH and ABCT in response to a wide range of environments, stressors and growth conditions, such the use of wheat straw as carbon source.</p>
      <p>The functional assignments, in conjunction with the taxonomic profiles based on genes encoding proteins, as well as previous 16S rRNA gene and ITS pyrosequencing analysis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>, indicate that the RWS and TWS consortia had distinct microbial community structures, but highly similar functional profiles. Clearly, function was a much stronger driver of community structuring than phylogeny. Similar results have been reported in the past for other microbial communities<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">50</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51">51</xref>. We observed that different functional profiles had emerged in comparison to the FS1 community, although functional overlaps still existed. However, the high percentage of sequences with no homology (in FS1) could mask the conservation of function between the consortia and the soil inoculum. It is likely that selective force, in relation to the complexity of the wheat straw, offered many microbial niches, giving origin to a still rather complex consortium in both enrichments.</p>
      <p>The CAZy profile data were consistent with those previously reported based on the function predictor PICRUSt<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>. This suggests that, for relatively simple communities, such predictions are consistent with &#x201C;reality&#x201D;, as also suggested recently<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52">52</xref>. In terms of enriched CAZy families, GH50 and GH117 constitute enzymes involved in the degradation of complex polysaccharides, such as agarose and neoagarobiose<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53">53</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54">54</xref>. The role of these two GH families in lignocellulose deconstruction is still unknown, however their enrichment points to a role in plant biomass degradation. A subset of the enriched enzymes in our consortia is capable of degrading different structures in the lignocellulose materials. For example, GH1, GH2 and GH3 (mostly &#x3B2;-glucosidases and &#x3B2;-galactosidases) are mainly involved in cellobiose and oligosaccharide deconstruction. The &#x3B1;-mannosidases (GH92), &#x3B1;-fucosidases (GH95 and GH29), &#x3B1;-arabinofuranosidases and &#x3B2;-xylosidase (GH43) are the most important hemicellulose active exo-enzymes that catalyze the hydrolysis of plant polysaccharides in agricultural waste<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Fig. 6</xref>). High levels of these families were reported in a microbial community decomposing poplar wood chips, especially sourced from Bacteroidetes members<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>. GH92 family genes have been shown to be abundantly present in a buffalo rumen metagenome<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b55">55</xref>. Interestingly, previous enzymatic analysis showed that the &#x3B2;-glucosidases, &#x3B2;-galactosidases and &#x3B2;-xylosidase were highly active in the secretome of both our consortia at transfer-10<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>, confirming the presence of these types of genes and their expression.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, based on &#x201C;richness&#x201D; values and the contigs constructed from the reads that came from enriched GH families in transfer-10, we hypothesize that strong selection, yielding &#x201C;less niches or less complex and specific carbon sources&#x201D;, occurred for the 10T and 10W systems, compared with FS1. In addition, a reduction of the functional &#x201C;richness&#x201D; values was more evident in 10T than in 10W, confirming that pretreatment reduces the complexity of the substrate and can introduce a stronger, or narrower, selection, which is possibly also based on the presence of furanic compounds<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>. The low &#x201C;richness&#x201D; values and the classification, at &#x201C;high&#x201D; taxonomy ranking (e.g. family GH29 in 10T), might constitute evidence for selection of specific novel proteins. Finally, the large enrichment of GH families associated with Bacteroidetes (i.e. <italic>Sphingobacterium</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Flavobacterium</italic> and <italic>Pedobacter</italic>) types at transfer-10 indicated these taxa as prime agents in the deconstruction of the hemicellulose part on the wheat straw. This stood in contrast to the presumed role of Enterobacteriaceae (i.e. <italic>Klebsiella</italic> and/or <italic>Kluyvera</italic> types) which may act mainly on the cellulose structures, and possibly also the lignin<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Fig. 6</xref>). We hypothesize that soils with a majority of Bacteroidetes have elevated levels of metabolic capabilities to degrade plant polysaccharides, especially hemicellulose.</p>
      <p>In lignocellulolytic microbial consortia of reduced complexity, genome pieces and/or gene clusters might be assembled at the coverage levels used by us, allowing the description/detection of partial metabolic pathways related with plant waste deconstruction. Our metagenome assembly yielded thirteen putative novel Bacteroidetes HULs. This apparent &#x201C;bias&#x201D; towards Bacteroidetes is consistent with the reported relative dominance of this taxon in both our selected microbial consortia<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>. The collective contigs contained genes for 39 GH involved in (hemi)cellulose degradation, of which 11 might encode novel proteins based on the low identity percentage with database entries. Minor differences in the numbers of detected GH were observed between the CAZy and RAST based annotations (e.g. contigs ID 939, 248 and 316), which might be explained by differences in the two gene-calling systems used.</p>
      <p>Interestingly, the GH detected in the 13 retrieved HULs were mostly flanked by TBR, TCSP, ABCT and genes involved in sugar metabolism (e.g. TKT, XKN and XI). Recently, four types of regulatory systems were proposed to be involved in transcriptional regulation of genes for polysaccharide degradation in <italic>Bacteroides</italic> sp.: <italic>i</italic>) Sus-like regulators (or TBR), <italic>ii</italic>) TCSP, <italic>iii</italic>) extra cytoplasmic function (ECF) sigma/anti-sigma factors and <italic>iv</italic>) AraC family regulators<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56">56</xref>. In <italic>B. thetaiotaomicron</italic>, SusC is a member of the TBR family specialized in the transport of oligosaccharides from the outer membrane into the periplasmic space<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">44</xref>. Moreover, the presence of genes involved in sugar metabolism, in our retrieved contigs, was indicative of partial pathways encoded by these genomic fragments. Adav <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref> revealed an up-regulation of XI in <italic>Thermobifida fusca</italic> when grown on different lignocellulosic biomass. Interestingly, the heterologous expression of L-ribulose-5-phosphate 4-epimerase, L-arabinose isomerase, aldose-1-epimerase (found in contig 939) could improve sugar utilization and production of ethanol in <italic>Zymomonas</italic> and <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> species<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b57">57</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b58">58</xref>. Based on the cluster of genes in contig 1110, the theoretical and hypothetical pathway could be: D-xylose produced from the hydrolysis of xyloglucan by GH43, recognized by TBR or TCSP and transported into cells by ABCT. Once inside the cell, XI converts it to D-xylulose and subsequently to D-xylulose 5-phosphate by XKN. D-xylulose 5-phosphate then enters the pentose phosphate pathway with the help of the TKT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Fig. 6</xref>).</p>
      <p>Thus, our data demonstrate the presence of partial pathways related with plant biomass deconstruction and sugar (e.g. xylose, glucose, arabinose and fucose) transport and metabolism. As a prospect, abundant and enriched enzymes, such as mannosidases (GH92), arabinofuranosidases, xylanases (GH43), fucosidases (GH95 and GH29) and galactosidases (GH2) can be extracted from the HULs, custom-synthesized, codon-optimized and expressed in a suitable host. This will generate novel efficient enzyme cocktails that can enhance the activity of currently-used cellulolytic enzymes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>. Overall, the data from this study allow us to clarify the consortial metabolic capacities, including the unraveling of lignocellulose-active enzymatic machineries. This demonstrates the biotechnological potential of the two soil microbiome derived consortia selected by wheat straw.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="1" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Lignocellulolytic microbial consortia and metagenome sequencing</title>
        <p>Breeding of the microbial consortia has been reported before<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>. Briefly, cell suspensions were prepared by adding 10&#x2009;g of sampled soil to 250&#x2009;ml flasks containing 10&#x2009;g of sterile gravel in 90&#x2009;ml of mineral salts medium (MSM). The flasks were shaken for 20&#x2009;min at 250&#x2009;rpm. The cell extracts (250&#x2009;&#x3BC;l) were then introduced into triplicate flasks containing 25&#x2009;ml of MSM supplemented with 1% of <italic>i</italic>) &#x201C;raw&#x201D; wheat straw (RWS) and <italic>ii</italic>) heat-treated (240&#x2009;&#xB0;C, 1&#x2009;h) wheat straw (TWS). Subsequently, flasks were incubated at 25&#x2009;&#xB0;C with shaking (100&#x2009;rpm). Once the systems reached 7 to 8 log cells/ml (between 6 and 8 days), aliquots (25&#x2009;&#x3BC;l) were transferred to 25&#x2009;ml of fresh MSM containing the same substrates. Samples from the soil suspension (FS1) and from the triplicate RWS and TWS flasks were taken after 1, 3 and 10 transfers (n&#x2009;=&#x2009;21). The selection of the samples was based on previous bacterial PCR-DGGE results<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>. Metagenomic DNA was extracted from the FS1 (n&#x2009;=&#x2009;3) and from the selected RWS and TWS samples (n&#x2009;=&#x2009;18) using the UltraClean Microbial DNA Isolation Kit (MoBio&#xAE; Laboratories Inc., Carlsbad, CA, USA), according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. Based on previous bacterial 16S rRNA gene and fungal ITS1 diversity analyses (DGGE and pyrosequencing), the latter samples showed consistent microbial structure and composition per time point<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>. The triplicate DNAs from the FS1 and from each selected RWS and TWS consortia were pooled, yielding a total of 7 metagenomes. The DNA samples were then subjected to Illumina Mi-Seq v2 sequencing (250&#x2009;bp paired-end reads) at LGC Genomics (Berlin, Germany).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Sequence processing and annotation of unassembled sequences</title>
        <p>A total of 5,298,311 unassembled sequences (reads) were uploaded to the MG-RAST v3.1.2 server<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>. Overlapping sequence pairs were matched, and non-overlapping reads retained as individual reads, after which dereplication was performed. Duplicate read based inferred sequencing error estimation and quality trimming (phred score&#x2009;&lt;20) were done using default settings in MG-RAST. The coverage values of each metagenome was calculated based on the number of bacterial 16S rRNA OTUs at 97% cut-off value (338, 108, 112, 100, 102, 45 and 46 for FS1, 1W, 3W, 10W, 1T, 3T and 10T, respectively)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>, using as a reference 4 Mb per bacterial genome. Gene predictions were done using the FragGeneScan software and subsequently the predicted proteins were annotated based on BLASTX searches against the RefSeq, KEGG and SEED databases using an e-value cutoff of 1e-15, a minimum alignment length of 50 amino acids and a minimum identity of 50%. In order to retrieve 16S rRNA gene sequences from the metagenomes, we performed a BLASTN search against the RDP database using an e-value cutoff 1e-15, a minimum alignment of 200 base pairs (bp) and a minimum nucleotide identity of 90%. The 16S rRNA gene sequences were taxonomically classified using the Classifier software with a confidence threshold of 50%<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59">59</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b60">60</xref>. The total metagenome sequences are publically accessible under the MG-RAST project code 7220 (Metagenome IDs 4547279.3 to 4547285.3).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Detection and compositional profile of genes involved in plant waste deconstruction</title>
        <p>Genes, or parts thereof, involved in lignocellulose degradation were detected using as a starting point the reads (quality filtered and trimmed) obtained by MG-RAST. Annotation was performed via BLASTX against the CAZy database v3 (downloaded from dbCAN site)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b61">61</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62">62</xref> using an e-value cutoff 1e-15. Filtering was done based on a measure that relates the coverage and the identity percentage (ratio) (alignment length&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;% identity/query length) of &gt;30%. To evaluate the relative abundance (RA) of reads per family, the counts were normalized using the total numbers of quality reads (matched in the database) per metagenome. Moreover, the RA of reads of each class (AA, CBM, CE, GH, GT and PL) and family was compared between the metagenomes from the selected consortia (1W, 3W, 10W, 1T, 3T and 10T) as well as the FS1. Fold changes were calculated based on the normalized RA values (fold increase&#x2009;=&#x2009;RA consortia/RA of FS1) and then Log<sub>10</sub> transformed.</p>
        <p>Unassembled sequences belonging to CAZy families CBM50, GH1, GH2, GH3, GH20, GH29, GH31, GH43, GH92 and GH95 were extracted from FS1, 10W and 10T (stable consortia), re-annotated (in-house) using BLASTX searches against the nr-NCBI database and clustered at 97% of nucleotide identity using the CD-HIT software<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b63">63</xref>. The BLAST results were loaded into MEGAN v5 software and classified taxonomically according to suggested parameters for the Lowest Common Ancestor algorithm (LCA) (maximum number of matches per read: 10; min support: 5; min score: 35; max expected 0.01; min complexity 0.3; and top percent: 10)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>. To calculate the RA and the relative differences of read &#x201C;richness&#x201D; value, the counts and clusters were normalized using the total numbers of reads within each selected family. In addition, reads extracted in each family were assembled using the CLC Genomics Workbench v4.0.3 software (CLC Bio, Cambridge, MA, USA).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Comparisons and statistical analysis of unassembled metagenome data</title>
        <p>Data from MG-RAST and CAZy annotation were statistically analyzed using the STAMP package<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b64">64</xref>. Routinely, two-sided Fisher&#x2019;s and/or ANOVA tests were used for hypothesis testing. Differences in proportions and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were calculated according to the Newcombe-Wilson method. Multiple test corrections were done using the Storey FDR q-value or the Benjamini&#x2013;Hochberg false discovery rate. A heat-map was constructed based on the RA by the Ward method and a dendrogram produced at a threshold of 0.9.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Evaluation of gene clusters involved in (hemi)cellulose degradation</title>
        <p>The metagenome assembly was performed using the CLC Genomics Workbench v4.0.3 with the following parameters: mismatch cost 2, insertion cost 3, deletion cost 3, length fraction 0.5 and similarity 0.9<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b65">65</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b66">66</xref>. Each metagenome was assembled separately and contigs from 1W, 3W and 10W were used for subsequent assembly in order to obtain a dataset for RWS. The TWS consortia were analyzed similarly. In the RWS and TWS assembled datasets, genes were detected using the MetaGeneMark software<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b67">67</xref>. Subsequently, these were annotated by Hidden Markov Models (HMM) based on CAZy family domains (v3) in the dbCAN platform using default parameters. Contigs&#x2009;&#x2265;&#x2009;5&#x2009;Kb with GH genes (specifically belonging to families GH2, GH3, GH29, GH31, GH43, GH92 and GH95) were retrieved and annotated using the RAST server<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b68">68</xref>. The predicted GH were manually annotated using PSI-BLASTP against nr-NCBI database. Finally, to select contigs with GH &#x201C;hotspots&#x201D; and analyze their genomic contexts, we selected those contigs that had the followed parameters: 1) size&#x2009;&#x2265;&#x2009;10&#x2009;Kb, containing at least two GH genes, 2) size&#x2009;&#x2265;&#x2009;35&#x2009;Kb with at least one GH. G&#x2009;+&#x2009;C contents<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b69">69</xref>, tetranucleotide frequencies (TTNF) and average nucleotide identities (ANIb) against different genomes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b70">70</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b71">71</xref> were calculated in each selected contig.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="1">
      <title>Additional Information</title>
      <p><bold>How to cite this article</bold>: Jim&#xE9;nez, D. J. <italic>et al.</italic> Unveiling the metabolic potential of two soil-derived microbial consortia selected on wheat straw. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>5</bold>, 13845; doi: 10.1038/srep13845 (2015).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e25" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary figures</title>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep13845-s1.pdf"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e28" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Information</title>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep13845-s2.pdf"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e31" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Dataset 1</title>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep13845-s3.xls"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e34" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Dataset 2</title>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep13845-s4.xls"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e37" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Dataset 3</title>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep13845-s5.xls"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e40" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Dataset 4</title>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep13845-s6.xls"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank M.C. Pereira e Silva, M. Chaib de Mares and C.A. Mallon for their help in the tetranucleotide frequency analyses and for reviewing the manuscript. Further thanks are due to H. Ruijssenaars and R. van Kranenburg for support. This work was supported by the Netherlands Ministry of Economic Affairs and the BE-Basic partner organizations (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.be-basic.org">http://www.be-basic.org</ext-link>).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="b1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ragauskas</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>The path forward for biofuels and biomaterials</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>311</volume>, <fpage>484</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>489</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mabee</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saddler</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>An overview of second generation biofuel technologies</article-title>. <source>Bioresour. Technol.</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>1570</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1580</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chandel</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>O. V.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Weedy lignocellulosic feedstock and microbial metabolic engineering: advancing the generation of &#x2018;Biofuel&#x2019;</article-title>. <source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>89</volume>, <fpage>1289</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1303</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Changes of chemical and mechanical behavior of torrefied wheat straw</article-title>. <source>Biomass. BioEnerg.</source><volume>40</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>70</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Limayem</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Ricke</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Lignocellulosic biomass for bioethanol production: current perspectives, potential issues and future prospects</article-title>. <source>Prog. Energ. Combust.</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>449</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>467</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tumuluru</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sokhansanj</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Boardman</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A review on biomass torrefaction process and product properties for energy applications</article-title>. <source>Ind. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>384</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>401</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name><article-title>Microbial degradation of lignocellulosic biomass in Sustainable degradation of lignocellulosic biomass - techniques, applications and commercialization</article-title> (eds <name><surname>Chandel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>). <volume>Ch 9</volume>, <fpage>208</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>209</lpage> (de Vries, R. <italic>et al.</italic> 2001). Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.intechopen.com/books/sustainable-degradation-of-lignocellulosic-biomass-techniques-applications-and-commercialization/microbial-degradation-of-lignocellulosic-biomass">http://www.intechopen.com/books/sustainable-degradation-of-lignocellulosic-biomass-techniques-applications-and-commercialization/microbial-degradation-of-lignocellulosic-biomass</ext-link> (Accessed: 10th December <year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Hemicellulases and auxiliary enzymes for improved conversion of lignocellulosic biomass to monosaccharides</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol. Biofuels.</source><volume>4</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goldbeck</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Development of hemicellulolytic enzyme mixtures for plant biomass deconstruction on target biotechnological applications</article-title>. <source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>98</volume>, <fpage>8513</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8525</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X. Z.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Application of metagenomic techniques in mining enzymes from microbial communities for biofuel synthesis</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol. Adv.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>920</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>929</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A novel co-culture strategy for lignocellulosic bioenergy production: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Mod. Biol. Med.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>166</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>193</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Deangelis</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Strategies for enhancing the effectiveness of metagenomic-based enzyme discovery in lignocellulolytic microbial communities</article-title>. <source>Bioenerg. Res.</source><volume>3</volume>, <fpage>146</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>158</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Mining of novel thermo-stable cellulolytic genes from a thermophilic cellulose-degrading consortium by metagenomics</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e53779</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kamei</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Identification of novel glycosyl hydrolases with cellulolytic activity against crystalline cellulose from metagenomic libraries constructed from bacterial enrichment cultures</article-title>. <source>Springerplus.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>365</fpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cantarel</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>The carbohydrate-active enzymes database (CAZy): an expert resource for glycogenomics</article-title>. <source>Nucleic. Acids. Res.</source><volume>37</volume>, <fpage>233</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>238</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Allgaier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Targeted discovery of glycoside hydrolases from a switchgrass-adapted compost community</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source><volume>5</volume>, <fpage>e8812</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Suen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>An insect herbivore microbiome with high plant biomass-degrading capacity</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet.</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e1001129</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Comparative genomic analysis of the microbiome of herbivorous insects reveals eco-environmental adaptations: biotechnology applications</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet.</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e1003131</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van der Lelie</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>The metagenome of an anaerobic microbial community decomposing poplar wood chips</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e36740</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Microbial and carbohydrate active enzyme profile of buffalo rumen metagenome and their alteration in response to variation in the diet</article-title>. <source>Gene.</source><volume>545</volume>, <fpage>88</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>94</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Metagenomic analysis of the microbiota from the crop of an invasive snail reveals a rich reservoir of novel genes</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e48505</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wongwilaiwalin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Comparative metagenomic analysis of microcosm structures and lignocellulolytic enzyme systems of symbiotic biomass-degrading consortia</article-title>. <source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>97</volume>, <fpage>8941</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8954</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Deangelis</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Metagenomes of tropical soil-derived anaerobic switchgrass-adapted consortia with and without iron</article-title>. <source>Stand. Genomic. Sci.</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>382</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>398</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jim&#xE9;nez</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Korenblum</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>van Elsas</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Novel multispecies microbial consortia involved in lignocellulose and 5-hydroxymethylfurfural bioconversion</article-title>. <source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>98</volume>, <fpage>2789</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2803</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jim&#xE9;nez</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dini-Andreote</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>van Elsas</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Metataxonomic profiling and prediction of functional behaviour of wheat straw degrading microbial consortia</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol. Biofuels.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>92</fpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Bakken</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Flow cytometric measurements of cell volumes and DNA contents during culture of indigenous soil bacteria</article-title>. <source>Microb. Ecol.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>62</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>The metagenomics RAST server: a public resource for the automatic phylogenetic and functional analysis of metagenomes</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinform.</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huson</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruscheweyh</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Integrative analysis of environmental sequences using MEGAN4</article-title>. <source>Genome. Res.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1552</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1560</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Teeling</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Gl&#xF6;ckner</surname><given-names>F. O.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Current opportunities and challenges in microbial metagenome analysis -a bioinformatic perspective</article-title>. <source>Brief. Bioinform.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>728</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>742</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andreote</surname><given-names>F. D.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>The microbiome of Brazilian mangrove sediments as revealed by metagenomics</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e38600</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Delmont</surname><given-names>T. O.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Structure, fluctuation and magnitude of a natural grassland soil metagenome</article-title>. <source>ISME J.</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1677</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1687</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jim&#xE9;nez</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Structural and functional insights from the metagenome of an acidic hot spring microbial planktonic community in the Colombian Andes</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source><volume>12</volume>, <fpage>e52069</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>How much metagenomic sequencing is enough to achieve a given goal?</article-title>
<source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>1968</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>V&#x11B;trovsk&#xFD;</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Baldrian</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The variability of the 16S rRNA gene in bacterial genomes and its consequences for bacterial community analyses</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e57923</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aylward</surname><given-names>F. O.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Metagenomic and metaproteomic insights into bacterial communities in leaf-cutter ant fungus gardens</article-title>. <source>ISME J.</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1688</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1701</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Identification of an ABC transporter required for iron acquisition and virulence in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>188</volume>, <fpage>424</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>430</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Structure and regulation of the cellulose degradome in <italic>Clostridium cellulolyticum</italic></article-title>. <source>Biotechnol. Biofuels.</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>73</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adav</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheow</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ravindran</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Sze</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Label free quantitative proteomic analysis of secretome by <italic>Thermobifida fusca</italic> on different lignocellulosic biomass</article-title>. <source>J. Proteomics.</source>
<volume>75</volume>, <fpage>3694</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3706</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takasuka</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Book</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lewin</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Aerobic deconstruction of cellulosic biomass by an insect-associated <italic>Streptomyces</italic></article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>1030</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Deangelis</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Evidence supporting dissimilatory and assimilatory lignin degradation in <italic>Enterobacter lignolyticus</italic> SCF1</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source><volume>4</volume>, <fpage>280</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b41">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Scully</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Metagenomic profiling reveals lignocellulose degrading system in a microbial community associated with a wood-feeding beetle</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e73827</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b42">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hottes</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Transcriptional profiling of <italic>Caulobacter crescentus</italic> during growth on complex and minimal media</article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source><volume>186</volume>, <fpage>1448</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1461</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b43">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Blanvillain</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Plant carbohydrate scavenging through tonB-dependent receptors: a feature shared by phytopathogenic and aquatic bacteria</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source><volume>2</volume>, <fpage>e224</fpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b44">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fern&#xE1;ndez-G&#xF3;mez</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Ecology of marine Bacteroidetes: a comparative genomics approach</article-title>. <source>ISME J.</source><volume>5</volume>, <fpage>1026</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1037</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b45">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kabisch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Functional characterization of polysaccharide utilization loci in the marine Bacteroidetes <italic>&#x2018;Gramella forsetii</italic>&#x2019; KT0803</article-title>. <source>ISME J.</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1492</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1502</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b46">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ravcheev</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Godzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osterman</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Rodionov</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Polysaccharides utilization in human gut bacterium <italic>Bacteroides thetaiotaomicron</italic>: comparative genomics reconstruction of metabolic and regulatory networks</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>873</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b47">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sonnenburg</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Specificity of polysaccharide use in intestinal Bacteroides species determines diet-induced microbiota alterations</article-title>. <source>Cell.</source><volume>141</volume>, <fpage>1241</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1252</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b48">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Recognition and degradation of plant cell wall polysaccharides by two human gut symbionts</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol.</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e1001221</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b49">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Larsbrink</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>A discrete genetic locus confers xyloglucan metabolism in select human gut Bacteroidetes</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source><volume>506</volume>, <fpage>498</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>502</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b50">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>A human gut microbial gene catalogue established by metagenomic sequencing</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source><volume>464</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>65</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b51">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mhuantong</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Charoensawan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanokratana</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tangphatsornruang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Champreda</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Comparative analysis of sugarcane bagasse metagenome reveals unique and conserved biomass-degrading enzymes among lignocellulolytic microbial communities</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Biofuels.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>16</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b52">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Malmer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Langille</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Way</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Which is more important for classifying microbial communities: who&#x2019;s there or what they can do?</article-title>
<source>ISME J.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>2357</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2359</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b53">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H. T.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Overexpression and molecular characterization of Aga50D from <italic>Saccharophagus degradans</italic> 2-40: an exo-type beta-agarase producing neoagarobiose</article-title>. <source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>86</volume>, <fpage>227</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>234</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b54">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y. K.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Agar degradation by microorganisms and agar-degrading enzymes</article-title>. <source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>917</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>930</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b55">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>High potential source for biomass degradation enzyme discovery and environmental aspects revealed through metagenomics of indian buffalo rumen</article-title>. <source>Biomed. Res. Int.</source><volume>2014</volume>, <fpage>267189</fpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b56">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Metagenomic insights into the fibrolytic microbiome in yak rumen</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e40430</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b57">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mohagheghi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Cofermentation of glucose, xylose, and arabinose by genomic DNA-integrated xylose/arabinose fermenting strain of <italic>Zymomonas mobilis</italic> AX101</article-title>. <source>Appl. Biochem. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>98-100</volume>, <fpage>885</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>898</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b58">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kricka</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Metabolic engineering of yeasts by heterologous enzyme production for degradation of cellulose and hemicellulose from biomass: a perspective</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>174</fpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b59">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garrity</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tiedje</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Naive Bayesian classifier for rapid assignment of rRNA sequences into the new bacterial taxonomy</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>5261</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5267</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b60">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Claesson</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Comparative analysis of pyrosequencing and a phylogenetic microarray for exploring microbial community structures in the human distal intestine</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source><volume>4</volume>, <fpage>e6669</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b61">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>dbCAN: a web resource for automated carbohydrate-active enzyme annotation</article-title>. <source>Nucleic. Acids. Res.</source><volume>40</volume>, <fpage>445</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>451</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b62">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lombard</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Golaconda-Ramulu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drula</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The carbohydrate-active enzymes database (CAZy) in 2013</article-title>. <source>Nucleic. Acids. Res.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>490</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>495</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b63">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>CD-HIT Suite: a web server for clustering and comparing biological sequences</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>680</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>682</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b64">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Parks</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Beiko</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Identifying biologically relevant differences between metagenomic communities</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>715</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>721</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b65">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>O. U.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Metagenome, metatranscriptome and single-cell sequencing reveal microbial response to deepwater horizon oil spill</article-title>. <source>ISME J.</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1715</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1727</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b66">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ta&#x15F;</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Impact of fire on active layer and permafrost microbial communities and metagenomes in an upland Alaskan boreal forest</article-title>. <source>ISME J.</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1904</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1919</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b67">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lomsadze</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Borodovsky</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Ab initio gene identification in metagenomic sequences</article-title>. <source>Nucleic. Acids. Res.</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>e132</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b68">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>The RAST Server: rapid annotations using subsystems technology</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics.</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b69">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>GC-Profile: a web-based tool for visualizing and analyzing the variation of GC content in genomic sequences</article-title>. <source>Nucleic. Acids. Res.</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>686</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>691</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b70">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Teeling</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meyerdierks</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amann</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Gl&#xF6;ckner</surname><given-names>F. O.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Application of tetranucleotide frequencies for the assignment of genomic fragments</article-title>. <source>Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>938</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>947</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b71">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Rossell&#xF3;-M&#xF3;ra</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Shifting the genomic gold standard for the prokaryotic species definition</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>19126</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>19131</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p><bold>Author Contributions</bold> D.J.J. designed and constructed the experiments, participated in the bioinformatic analyses and drafted the manuscript. D.C.M. helped in the bioinformatic analyses. J.D.V.E. conceived of the study, and participated in its design, coordination and helped to draft the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f1">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Functional profile of the metagenomes based on KEGG identifiers.</title>
        <p>(<bold>a</bold>) PCA of the seven metagenomes using the lower hierarchical functional level; (<bold>b</bold>) Relative abundance (%) of microbial functions and pairwise comparison between RWS (1W, 3W and 10W) and TWS (1T, 3T and 10T) samples, red dots represent functions within the ABC transporters; (<bold>c</bold>) Highly enriched specific functions (compared with soil inoculum FS1) along three sequential transfers (fold-increase). Abbreviations: ABC transporters (ABCT), two-component system proteins (TCSP) and phosphotransferase systems (PTS).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep13845-f1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f2">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Comparison of functional profiles (percentage of relative abundance of SEED identifiers at lower hierarchical level) between the soil inoculum FS1 and metagenomes of the three sequential transfers of (<bold>a</bold>) RWS and (<bold>b)</bold> TWS. Numbers: are the selection of the eight most overrepresented functions in the consortial metagenomes. Asterisks (*) represent functions that were most enriched in RWS and TWS samples (p&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005). Letters a (adenylate cyclase), b (carbon monoxide dehydrogenase) and c (and cobalt/cadmium/zinc resistance proteins) correspond to the most deselected functions (p&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep13845-f2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f3">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Carbohydrate-active functional profiles.</title>
        <p>(<bold>a</bold>) Heat map of the relative abundance (%) of each CAZy class (AA, CBM, CE, GH, GT and PL) in each metagenome; (<bold>b</bold>) Log<sub>10</sub> X-fold increase of each CAZy class in RWS and TWS samples comparatively to the soil inoculum (FS1); (<bold>c</bold>) Pairwise comparison between RWS (1W, 3W and 10W) and TWS (1T, 3T and 10T) samples, red dots: are functions belonging to glycosyl hydrolases (GH) families; (<bold>d</bold>) &#x201C;Richness&#x201D; values (number of clusters at 97% nucleotide identity over the total retrieved reads in each family) of the most enriched CAZy families at transfer-10 (10W and 10T) and comparison with the soil inoculum (FS1).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep13845-f3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f4">
      <label>Figure 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Differentially enriched CAZy families (p&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005, 95% confidence intervals) between FS1 and (a) 10W and (b) 10T metagenomes; (c) Taxonomi<bold>c</bold> affiliation of reads belonging to families GH92, GH2, GH95, GH43, GH20, GH31, GH1, GH3, GH29 and CBM50, in 10W, 10T and FS1, using the Lowest Common Ancestor (LCA) algorithm.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep13845-f4"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f5">
      <label>Figure 5</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Graphical representation of thirteen novel Bacteroidetes HULs (hemicellulose utilization loci) recovered from the metagenome assemblages.</title>
        <p>Numbers represents annotated proteins that are flanked by glycosyl hydrolase (GH) genes. Abbreviations: Two-component system proteins (TCSP), ABC transporters (ABCT), TonB-dependent receptors (TBR), transketolases (TKT), xylose isomerase (XI) and xylulose kinase (XKN) genes.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep13845-f5"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f6">
      <label>Figure 6</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Graphical explanation of the presumed catalytic mode of action, on the major component of (hemi)cellulose, by the most enriched GH in our consortia (left).</title>
        <p>GH2 hydrolizes &#x3B2;-glycosidic bonds between galactose and its organic functional group; GH95 and GH29 are enzymes that hydrolyze Fuc-alpha1-2Gal linkages attached to the non-reducing ends of oligosaccharides; GH43 can act directly on xylan and release D-xylose and L-arabinose as main products. At the top: two different lignocellulose structures and microorganisms involved in their deconstruction (flask pictures were taken by the authors). Abbreviations: <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> (Ac), <italic>Klebsiella</italic>/<italic>Kluyvera</italic> (Kl), <italic>Flavobacterium</italic> (Fl), <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> (Ps) and <italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> (Sp). Right, partial metabolic reconstruction based on a theoretical (hemi)cellulose degradation pathway and uptake of sugars (intra - and extracellularly), in Bacteroidetes, using the contig_1110 genetic information. Abbreviations: Two-component system proteins (TCSP), ABC transporters (ABCT), TonB-dependent receptors (TBR), transketolases (TKT), xylose isomerase (XI) and xylulose kinase (XKN) and pentose phosphate pathway (PPP). Plus sign represent the regulation of the GH by the TCSP.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep13845-f6"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="t1">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <title>The most abundant and enriched CAZy families (top-15) in the RWS and TWS metagenomes (compared with FS1).</title>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
        <colgroup>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="left"/>
        </colgroup>
        <thead valign="bottom">
          <tr>
            <th rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CAZy family</th>
            <th colspan="14" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Metagenomes</th>
            <th rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Most common activities (EC Number)</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">FS1</th>
            <th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1W</th>
            <th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3W</th>
            <th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10W</th>
            <th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1T</th>
            <th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3T</th>
            <th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10T</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Log</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">RA</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Log</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">RA</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Log</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">RA</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Log</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">RA</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Log</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">RA</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Log</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">RA</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Log</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">RA</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">PL17</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,017</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,135</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,236</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,071</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,203</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,122<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn3">c</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,229</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,267</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,320</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,304</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,348</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,234<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn3">c</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,296</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alginate lyase (EC 4.2.2.3); Oligoalginate lyase (EC 4.2.2.-)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CBM50</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,742</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,342</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,633</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,293</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,458</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,427<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,983</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,548</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,622</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,426</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,980</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,228<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn2">b</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,254</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Carbohydrate-Binding Module (peptidoglycan and chitin binding module)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GT8</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,009</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,826</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,058</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,969</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,080</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,367<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,201</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,980</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,082</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,263</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,016</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,757<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn2">b</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,049</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Lipopolysaccharide galacto(gluco)syltransferase; Homogalacturonan galacturonosyltransferase; Xylan glucuronyltransferase (EC 2.4.1.-)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GH117</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,009</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,593</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,338</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,513</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,281</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,528<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn3">c</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,291</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,883</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,066</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,564</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,316</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,798<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,542</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Neoagarooligosaccharide hydrolase (EC 3.2.1.-)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GH92</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,311</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,060</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,564</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,978</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,955</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,861<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn2">b</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,254</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,465</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,906</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,980</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,967</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,197<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4,895</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-mannosidase (EC 3.2.1.24)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GH50</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,009</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,159</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,125</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,694</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,043</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,808<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn2">b</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,055</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,306</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,175</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,144</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,120</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,264<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn2">b</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,158</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-agarase (EC 3.2.1.81)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GH95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,423</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,663</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,944</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,606</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,707</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,649<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn3">c</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,886</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,181</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,642</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,636</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,831</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,797<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,648</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-1,2-L-fucosidase (EC 3.2.1.63); Alpha-L-fucosidase (EC 3.2.1.51)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GH20</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,570</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,523</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,900</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,462</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,652</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,384<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn2">b</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,380</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,078</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,682</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,405</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,449</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,617<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,359</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-hexosaminidase (EC 3.2.1.52); Lacto-N-biosidase (EC 3.2.1.140)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GH31</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,768</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,376</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,824</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,424</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,038</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,444<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,136</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,446</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,148</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,502</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,439</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,492<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn3">c</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,384</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-glucosidase (EC 3.2.1.20); Alpha-xylosidase (EC 3.2.1.177); Alpha-mannosidase (EC 3.2.1.24)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GH2</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,839</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,336</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,987</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,410</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4,722</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,417<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4,806</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,245</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,235</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,334</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,963</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,409<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4,715</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">*Beta-galactosidase (EC 3.2.1.23); *Beta-mannosidase (EC 3.2.1.25); Beta-glucuronidase (EC 3.2.1.31); Alpha-L-arabinofuranosidase (EC 3.2.1.55)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,364</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,378</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,257</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,411</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,517</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,362<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn3">c</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,141</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,210</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,214</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,366</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,166</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,348<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,039</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">*Beta-xylosidase (EC 3.2.1.37); Alpha-L-arabinofuranosidase (EC 3.2.1.55); Xylanase (EC 3.2.1.8); Galactan 1,3-beta-galactosidase (EC 3.2.1.145)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GH1</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,656</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,260</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,192</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,424</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,740</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,457<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,879</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,665</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,034</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,552</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,341</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,320<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn2">b</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,370</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">*Beta-glucosidase (EC 3.2.1.21); Beta-galactosidase (EC 3.2.1.23); Beta-mannosidase (EC 3.2.1.25); Beta-glucuronidase (EC 3.2.1.31); Beta-xylosidase (EC 3.2.1.37); Beta-D-fucosidase (EC 3.2.1.38)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GH29</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,716</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,326</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,517</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,349</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,602</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,342<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn3">c</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,574</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x2212;0,112</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,553</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,331</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1,534</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,536<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">a</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,461</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-L-fucosidase (EC 3.2.1.51); Alpha-1,3/1,4-L-fucosidase (EC 3.2.1.111)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GH3</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,762</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,177</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4,156</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,160</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,996</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,158<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn3">c</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,974</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,139</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,804</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,083</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,343</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0,035<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn2">b</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2,993</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-glucosidase (EC 3.2.1.21); Xylan 1,4-beta-xylosidase (EC 3.2.1.37); Beta-glucosylceramidase (EC 3.2.1.45); Beta-N-acetylhexosaminidase (EC 3.2.1.52); Alpha-L-arabinofuranosidase (EC 3.2.1.55)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GH13</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7,242</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x2212;0,245</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4,120</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x2212;0,258</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4,001</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x2212;0,257<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn3">c</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4,008</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x2212;0,090</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5,893</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x2212;0,099</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5,760</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x2212;0,264<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn2">b</xref></td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3,940</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-amylase (EC 3.2.1.1); Pullulanase (EC 3.2.1.41)</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn id="t1-fn1">
          <p><bold>Log</bold>: Log10 X-fold increase in relative abundance.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t1-fn2">
          <p><bold>RA</bold>: Relative abundance.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t1-fn3">
          <p>Negative values are subfamilies deselected comparatively with the FS1.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t1-fn4">
          <p>*Detected enzymatic activity in the secretome of both consortia at transfer-10 (Jimenez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014b).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t1-fn5">
          <p><sup>a</sup>Enriched along the transfers (selecting).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t1-fn6">
          <p><sup>b</sup>Depleted along the transfers (deselecting).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t1-fn7">
          <p><sup>c</sup>Neutral enrichment along the transfers.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="t2">
      <label>Table 2</label>
      <caption>
        <title>The most abundant/enriched CAZy family gene encoding metagenome fragments at transfer-10.</title>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
        <colgroup>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center" char="("/>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center" char="."/>
          <col align="center"/>
        </colgroup>
        <thead valign="bottom">
          <tr>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Consortia</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">CAZy family</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig/gene ID</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Length (bp)</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">NRC (%)<sup>a</sup></th>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BLASTx best hit [Taxa] (Accession number)</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">% QC</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">E</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">% I</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="10" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">10W</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">CBM50</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 1</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1357</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">21 (7.3)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">M23/M37 family cell wall endopeptidase [<italic>Kluyvera ascorbata</italic>] (KFD08719.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">85</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">97</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH2</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 5</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2755</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">33 (4.7)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-galactosidase [<italic>Parabacteroides merdae</italic>] (WP_005651198.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">98</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">60</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH20</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 3</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1373</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">15 (7.5)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-N-acetylhexosaminidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (WP_031288206.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">98</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 5</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1707</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">25 (9.1)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Fuc19 [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (ACX30659.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">92</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH31</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 2</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1572</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">25 (8.1)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-glucosidase [<italic>Kluyvera ascorbata</italic>] (KFD07596.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">91</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH3</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 1</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2127</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">36 (6.2)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Periplasmic beta-glucosidase [<italic>Kluyvera ascorbata</italic>] (KFC99801.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">96</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">95</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 6</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2144</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">32 (7.0)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Glycoside hydrolase family 43 [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (CDT33327.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">89</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">87</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH1</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 4</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1172</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">23 (8.4)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-glucosidase/6-phospho-beta-glucosidase [<italic>Kluyvera ascorbata</italic>] (KFC94642.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">93</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">94</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH92</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 3</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2533</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">29 (8.9)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-1,2-mannosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (CDT06451.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">88</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">92</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH29</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 1</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1438</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">25 (11.0)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-L-fucosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (WP_031288978.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">87</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1E-144</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="10" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">10T</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">CBM50</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 1</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1268</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">19 (5.3)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Peptidase [<italic>Enterobacter aerogenes</italic>] (WP_015705953.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">85</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">95</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH2</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 5</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4302</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">228 (17.0)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-galactosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (AIM35762.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">92</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">78</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH20</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 1</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1753</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">88 (13.1)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-N-acetylhexosaminidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (WP_031287911.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">93</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">98</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 4</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1792</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">84 (11.1)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Hypothetical protein [<italic>Pedobacter borealis</italic>] (WP_029274415.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">77</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH31</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 1</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4119</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">189 (27.9)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-xylosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (AIM36311.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">93</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">86</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH3</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 4</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2418</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">128 (15.0)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-glucosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (CDS91967.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">96</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">88</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 4</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4115</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">138 (15.9)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43D19 precursor [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (ACX30655.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">51</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH1</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 3</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1824</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">76 (19.5)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-glucosidase A [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (CDT05903.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">73</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">83</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH92</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 4</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2597</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">131 (9.4)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-1,2-mannosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (CDT06451.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">86</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">92</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH29</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig 7</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2779</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">109 (15.5)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-1,3/4-fucosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (AIM37951.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">94</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">90</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn id="t2-fn1">
          <p><bold>NRC</bold>: Number of reads within the contig/gene; <sup>a</sup>percentage of reads based on the total number of reads retrieved in each subfamily.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t2-fn2">
          <p><bold>QC</bold>: Query coverage</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t2-fn3">
          <p><bold>E</bold>: E-value</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t2-fn4">
          <p><bold>I</bold>: Amino acid identity</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="t3">
      <label>Table 3</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Glycosyl hydrolases detected by annotation using the CAZy database in thirteen putative novel predicted Bacteroidetes (hemi)cellulose utilization loci.</title>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
        <colgroup>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center" char="("/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
        </colgroup>
        <thead valign="bottom">
          <tr>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Contig ID (Consortia)</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">CL (bp)</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">NRC (%)<sup>a</sup></th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">CRC</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">CAZy family</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Length (aa)</th>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">PSI-BLASTp best hit [Taxa] (Accession number)</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">% QC</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">E</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">% I</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">278 (RWS)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">64,242</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">4,084 (0.19)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">19X</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH29</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">596</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-L-fucosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium spiritivorum</italic>] (WP_003008132.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">98</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">65</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH29</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">477</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-L-fucosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium spiritivorum</italic>] (WP_003008126.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">78</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH3</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">765</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-glucosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (YP_004318346.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">96</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">65</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH92</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">717</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-1,2-mannosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium spiritivorum</italic>] (WP_003008094.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">73</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">582 (RWS)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">59,220</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">3,501 (0.16)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">17.5X</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">360</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-xylosidase [<italic>Bacteroides fragilis</italic>] (WP_005778595.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">80</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH92</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1032</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Hypothetical protein [<italic>Parabacteroides</italic> sp.] (WP_010801039.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">70</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">373 (RWS)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">57,434</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">3,534 (0.17)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">17X</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH92</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">657</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-1 2-mannosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium spiritivorum</italic>] (WP_002997981.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">98</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">83</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH92</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">766</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-1,2-mannosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (YP_004319748.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">98</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">67</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH92</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">763</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-1,2-mannosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (YP_004317288.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">98</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">71</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">26 (RWS)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">41,283</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">2,396 (0.11)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">20X</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH29</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">326</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-L-fucosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium spiritivorum</italic>] (WP_003003741.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">88</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">8e-174</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">82</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH3</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">350</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-glucosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (YP_004316656.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">94</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">78</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">262 (RWS)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">38,022</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">2,177 (0.10)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">17X</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">320</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Arabinan endo-1,5-alpha-L-arabinosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (WP_002997231.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">93</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6e-176</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">78</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">165</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-xylosidase [<italic>Echinicola vietnamensis</italic>] (YP_007226458.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">93</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1e-54</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">58*</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">939 (RWS)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">23,370</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">1,210 (0.05)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">14X</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH2</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">833</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Glycoside hydrolase [<italic>Dysgonomonas gadei</italic>] (WP_006801003.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">62</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">641</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Glycoside hydrolase [<italic>Flavobacterium johnsoniae</italic>] (YP_001195445.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">98</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">66</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">328</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Glycosyl hydrolase family 32 [<italic>Paraprevotella clara</italic>] (WP_008623026.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">88</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1e-149</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">69</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">242 (RWS)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">21,746</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">1,305 (0.06)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">16.5X</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH2</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">670</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-galactosidase [<italic>Parabacteroides goldsteinii</italic>] WP_007653379.1</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">59*</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH29</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">543</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-1,3/4-fucosidase [<italic>Capnocytophaga canimorsus</italic>] (YP_004740108.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">98</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">63</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">747</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Hypothetical protein [<italic>Sphingobacterium spiritivorum</italic>] (WP_003005855.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">70</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH2</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1068</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-galactosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium spiritivorum</italic>] (WP_002995396.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">85</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">50*</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">248 (RWS)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">19,539</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">1,037 (0.05)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">15X</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">323</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-N-arabinofuranosidase [<italic>Dysgonomonas mossii</italic>] (WP_006843656.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7e-176</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">72</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">363</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Glycoside hydrolase family protein [<italic>Pedobacter saltans</italic>] (YP_004274934.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">96</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">77</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">602</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Glycosyl hydrolase [<italic>Pedobacter saltans</italic>] (YP_004274947.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">75</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">716</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-L-fucosidase [<italic>Pedobacter saltans</italic>] (YP_004274942.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">68</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">519 (TWS)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">107,716</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">10,720 (0.43)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">30X</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH2</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">439</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-galactosidase [<italic>Bacteroides fragilis</italic>] (WP_005786683.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3e-119</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">44*</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH31</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">705</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Glycosyl hydrolase [<italic>Sphingobacterium spiritivorum</italic>] (WP_003001890.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">79</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">4309 (TWS)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">39,914</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">4,462 (0.17)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">23X</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH2</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">442</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-galactosidase [<italic>Sphingobacterium spiritivorum</italic>] (WP_002997393.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">98</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">81</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">507</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Hypothetical protein [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (WP_021190421.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">98</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">316 (TWS)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">25,776</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">2,588 (0.10)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">22.5X</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH2</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">704</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Hypothetical protein [<italic>Parabacteroides</italic> sp.] (WP_010803531.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">59*</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH2</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">567</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-galactosidase [<italic>Parabacteroides merdae</italic>] (WP_005649701.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">97</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1e-97</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">33*</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH2</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">752</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-galactosidase [<italic>Parabacteroides merdae</italic>] (WP_005649701.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">59*</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">3786 (TWS)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">24,838</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">2,275 (0.09)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">20.5X</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH2</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">427</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beta-galactosidase/beta-glucuronidase [<italic>Flavobacterium</italic> sp.] (WP_007809792.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">90</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1e-155</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">56*</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH29</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">382</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Glycoside hydrolase family protein [<italic>Niastella koreensis</italic>] (YP_005006468.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6e-81</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">39*</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">807</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-L-fucosidase [<italic>Paludibacter propionicigenes</italic>] (YP_004041891.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">96</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">54*</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">682</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Hypothetical protein [<italic>Sphingobacterium spiritivorum</italic>] (WP_002994973.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">70</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="middle" charoff="50">1110 (TWS)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">24,779</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">2,150 (0.08)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">26X</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">140</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Glycoside hydrolase [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (YP_004317870.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">78</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9e-42</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">77</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH43</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">531</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Hypothetical protein [<italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> sp.] (WP_021189555.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">55</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">269</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-L-fucosidase [<italic>Pedobacter saltans</italic>] (YP_004274942.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1e-83</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">53*</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GH95</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">430</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alpha-L-fucosidase [<italic>Pedobacter salta</italic>ns] (YP_004274942.1)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">98</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">72</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn id="t3-fn1">
          <p><bold>CL</bold>: Contig length.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t3-fn2">
          <p><bold>NRC</bold>: Number of reads within the contig; <sup>a</sup> percentage of reads based on the total number of reads in RWS and TWS samples.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t3-fn3">
          <p><bold>CRC</bold>: Coverage of reads per contig.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t3-fn4">
          <p><bold>QC</bold>: Query coverage.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t3-fn5">
          <p><bold>E</bold>: E-value.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t3-fn6">
          <p><bold>I</bold>: Amino acid identity; *less than 60%.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
