<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.1 20050630//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.1?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformation</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformation</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Bioinformation</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Bioinformation</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0973-8894</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">0973-2063</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Biomedical Informatics</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4110429</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">97320630010371</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6026/97320630010371</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Hypothesis</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Study of rust resistance genes in wheat germplasm with DNA markers</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Haque</surname>
            <given-names>Asma</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shaheen</surname>
            <given-names>Tayyaba</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gulzar</surname>
            <given-names>Tahsin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rahman</surname>
            <given-names>Mahmood ur</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jalal</surname>
            <given-names>Fatima</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sattar</surname>
            <given-names>Summera</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ehsan</surname>
            <given-names>Beenish</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Iqbal</surname>
            <given-names>Zafar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Younas</surname>
            <given-names>Muhammad</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Bioinformatics and Biotechnology, Government College University, Faisalabad</aff>
        <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Applied Chemistry, Government College University, Faisalabad</aff>
        <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Agriculture Biotechnology Research Institute, AARI, Faisalabad</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>Tayyaba Shaheen: <email>tayaba_pgmb@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>371</fpage>
      <lpage>377</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2014 Biomedical Informatics</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium,for non-commercial purposes, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wheat is a vital dietary component for human health and widely consumed in the world. Wheat rusts are dangerous pathogens
and contribute serious threat to its production. In present study, PCR-Based DNA Markers were employed to check the rust
resistance genes among 20 wheat genotypes and 22 markers were amplified. NTSYS-pc 2.2 was used to calculate genetic diversity
and Nei and Li's coefficients ranged from 0.55 to 0.95. Cluster analysis was obtained using UPGMA (Unweighted Pair Group
Method of Arithmetic Average) algorithm. Maximum no. of genes (23) was amplified from TW-760010 genotype whereas
minimum no of genes (14) were amplified from TW-76005 genotype. The data gained from present study open up new ways to
produce new varieties by breeding rust resistant germplasm to avoid the economic and food loss and varieties with improved
characteristics.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Wheat</kwd>
        <kwd>germplasm</kwd>
        <kwd>leaf rust</kwd>
        <kwd>stem rust</kwd>
        <kwd>stripe rust</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Wheat is the most important staple diet all over the world. It is
internationally an important commodity for marketing.
According to Pakistan Agriculture Research Council, its
contribution to GDP is 3.0 % and it is cultivated at greater area
of the country. Pakistan and India contribute 20% in annual
world wheat production. Its contribution in value added in
agriculture is 14.4%. In Pakistan, wheat is contained in large
agro ecological area [<xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. During last decade, one reason for low
yield of wheat in Pakistan is due to the diseases of rust. Rusts
are known to be most harmful and epidemically spread
diseases of wheat. The genus of wheat rust pathogens is
puccinia. There are three types of rust (1) leaf rust (2) stem rust
and (3) stripe rust. The losses occurring because of each type
vary from each other. The characterization of wheat rust
resistance genes is necessary to control the disease so that we
could incorporate these genes into the germplasm of elite
varieties [<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Crops have been improved conventionally by
selecting noticeable phenotypes showing the cumulative effect
of all genes and environment. Nowadays, plant breeding has
been updated by molecular marker technologies. Molecular
markers brought forward efficient methods of plant breeding.
Methods application and automation of analysis demand the
need to reduce the cost of large quantity of materials that are
handled by molecular markers sufficiently [<xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Rusts are widely
spread among continents by wind and act with rust resistance
gene by gene-for-gene manner to induce production instability.
Many new races of leaf, stripe and stem resistance have been
known to evolve and showed threat for available rust resistance
genes. More efficient wheat cultivars for rust resistance should
be developed for production enhancement. Genetic markers
and virulence characters have been utilized for rust migration
patterns [<xref rid="R04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Various studies on wheat have been carried out
using molecular marker system to characterize gene of choice,
mapping of qualitative trait loci and genetic diversity analysis.
This allows the marker assisted selection to occur. The present
study was performed with the purpose of characterizing rust
resistance genes in the wheat genotypes using different marker
systems and phylogenetic analysis of the experimental data.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
      <title>Methodology</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title><italic>Sample Collection</italic>:</title>
        <p>A total of 20 genotypes of Wheat were obtained from different
research stations of Pakistan including genotypes from Thal.
Genotypes were V-4189, LASANI, V-4188, V-4022, AARI-10,
AS-02, Inqlab-91, Sehar, UQAB, Pasban-90, TW-76001, TW-
76002, TW-76003, TW-76004, TW-76005, Parwaz-94, TW-76007,
TW-76008, TW-76009 and TW-760010.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title><italic>DNA Isolation</italic>:</title>
        <p>For each genotype, genomic DNA was isolated by a modified
Cetyl Trimethyl Ammonium Bromide (CTAB) method 
[<xref rid="R05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].
Then, DNA quality was determined using 0.8 % (w/v) agarose
gel and DNA quantification was performed using NanoDrop-
1000 version 3.3.1 spectrophotometer.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title><italic>PCR-Marker Assay</italic>:</title>
        <p>PCR reaction mixture reagents were 10XPCR Buffer (MgCl<sub>2</sub>+
(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) in 1.5 to 2.0 &#xB5;l , 50mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> in 0.75 to 1.50&#xB5;l,
(1.5+1.5) &#xB5;l of each Primer (Forward+Reverse) in concentration
of 15ng /&#xB5;l, 2.0 to 5.0 &#xB5;l of genomic DNA (30ng /&#xB5;l), 3.0 &#xB5;l of
0.2Mm of total dNTP<sub>S</sub>, 0.2-0.6 &#xB5;l <italic>Taq</italic> DNA polymerase in the
concentration of 5unit /&#xB5;l and final volume of 16-21&#xB5;l was
made by adding deionized double distilled water in 5.6 to 9.5 &#xB5;l
quantity. Reagents were purchased from Invitrogen (USA).
Polymerase chain reaction was performed using the Eppendorf
Mastercycler, Germany. Mastercycler was programmed for:
initial denaturation at 940C for 5-7 min, followed by 35-45 cycles
of denaturing at 940C for 30 sec-1min., annealing at 360C-600C
for 30 sec-1 min. and extension at 720C for 1 min. And then a
final extension at 720C for 7-10 min. and then hold at 200C until
the tubes were replaced. 3.0% (w/v) high resolution agarose gel
was used for amplicons characterization and polyacrylamide
gel electrophoresis to separate them on molecular weight basis.
Gel was visualized under ultraviolet transilluminator and gel
pictures were obtained using GeneSnap version 7.6.03 of
Syngene gel documentation system and Gene Tool analysis
system.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title><italic>Data Analysis</italic>:</title>
        <p>The significant size of each fragment was determined using
Gene Ruler 100 bp DNA ladder plus (Fermentas, USA) as
reference. After running the gel and visualizing its picture, the
data was scored. The scoring was started from lower band
(small fragment size) and continued to upper band (large
fragment size). Present band was scored as 1 whereas absent
band was scored as 0. The number of shared amplification
products were used for investigation of genetic diversity 
[<xref rid="R06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].
The binary data was entered in computer for further analysis
by NTSYS-pc version 2.2. Dendrogram was constructed by
means of Unweighted Pair Group Method of Arithmetic means
(UPGMA) using similarity coefficient and similarity matrix was
obtained to measure similarity range.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>In the present study genotypes collected from different
breeding stations of Pakistan were analyzed for genomic
studies of rust resistance in these genotypes using molecular
marker system. A total of 30 molecular markers were
employed. Out of which 22 markers <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table 1</xref> (see
supplementary material) amplified the rust resistance gene.</p>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title><italic>Characterization of Rust Resistance Genes in Wheat</italic>:</title>
        <p>There are three types of rust resistance genes in wheat; leaf rust
resistance <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table 2</xref> (see supplementary material), stem rust
resistance <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table 3</xref> (see supplementary material) and stripe rust
resistance <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table 4</xref> (see supplementary material). 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table 2</xref>
shows Leaf rust resistance markers validation for wheat
genotypes. All 20 genotypes were observed with SSR marker
Xgwm-234 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) that is linked to Lr52 gene and located on
the chromosome arm 5BS. This marker exhibited recombination
value of 7.2 cM with Lr52 [<xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. All the amplification products
show the bands with the fragment size 229,250bp.</p>
        <p>Xgwm-44 marker is linked to two leaf rust resistance genes
Lr21 &amp; Lr22 genes. Lr21 &amp; Lr22 genes are located on
chromosome 7B with respect to Xgwm-44. V-4189, Lasani, V-
4188, V-4022, AARI-10, AS-02, Uqab-02, Pasban-90, TW-76001,
TW-76002, TW-76004, TW-76007, TW-76008, TW-76009, TW-
76010 genotypes known to carry Lr21 &amp; Lr22 genes at with
band size of 184 and 176bp. Lr21 &amp; Lr22 genes are also resistant
to leaf rust marker Xgwm-210. Lr21 &amp; Lr22 genes are located on
chromosome 2B, 2D with respect to Xgwm-210. Its bands show
the amplification in the range of 303,189bp. Xgwm-295 marker
shows association with the Lr34 gene. Lr34 is located on 7D. All
the amplification products show the bands with the fragment
size 254,258bp. Lr1 is resistant to wheat leaf rust and shows the
band with 108 bp. S30-13L is linked to leaf rust resistance gene
Lr51. It is located on chromosome 1S [<xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Lr51 bands exist in the
range of 790bp. Lr50 is a new leaf rust resistance gene and
firstly named for leaf rust. It is known to be evolved from wild
timopheevi wheat and is the only Lr gene located on the long
arm of wheat homoeologous group 2 chromosomes. It shows
the fragment size 110 bp. KSUD14 has the structure of a
resistance gene analog (RGA) including kinase2a and kinase3
domains similar to the Cre3 gene of wheat and the rust
resistance gene Rp1-D of maize [<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. KSUD-14 PCR-based assay
provides an excellent marker for Lr40 and Lr21 in broadening
wheat germplasm. KSUD-14 shows the band size of 885bp.
Two RAPD markers S265 and S253 which flanked the locus
Lr19 were converted to sequence characterized amplified
region markers SCS265 and SCS253, respectively. A leaf rust
resistance gene Lr19 on the chromosome 7DL of wheat derived
from <italic>Agropyron elongatum</italic> was tagged with random amplified
polymorphic DNA and random microsatellite markers [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. All
the amplification products were in the range of 730bp. Lr19
gene is also resistant to leaf rust marker Xgwm-37.The locus of
Lr19 with respect to Xgwm-37 marker is 7D. All the
amplification products show the bands with the fragment size
189 bp. All genotypes predicted Lr19 gene except the Sehar variety.</p>
        <p>PCR-based microsatellite marker Xgwm-11 located in
chromosome 1B were shown to be very effective for the
detection of Yr15 and Yr26 genes in segregating population and
can be applied in future wheat breeding strategies. Its band
exits in the range of 213 bp. 20 genotypes were observed with
SSR marker Xgwm-501 that is linked to the Yr5 gene resistant to
wheat stripe rust (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table 4</xref>). Yr5 located on the long arm of
chromosome 2B [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. All the amplification products show the
bands with the fragment size 176 bp. Leaf &amp; Stripe resistance
genes at the Lr46/Yr29 locus have 1BL [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Xgwm-259 is linked
to both of these Leaf &amp; Stripe resistance genes Lr46/Yr29.
Lr46/Yr29 have amplification fragment size 105bp. Lr46/Yr29
are not available in the following genotypes V-4189, V-4188,
Sehar, Pasban-90, TW-76005, Parwaz-94, TW-76007, TW-76008
and in TW-76009 advance line. XgWM-130 is linked to both of
Lr34/Yr18 leaf &amp; stripe rust resistance genes. It is located on
chromosome 7DS [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Its fragment size ranges is upto
121,126bp. AS-02 and TW-76007 advance line do not show the
amplification with Lr34/Yr18 leaf &amp; stripe rust resistance
genes.</p>
        <p>Xbrac-352 is also linked with these leaf &amp; stripe rust resistance
genes Lr34/Yr18.It is present on the locus of 7DS [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Its band
size is 150,211bp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Variety AS-02 and TW-76007
advance line does not show amplification. Xgwm-533 is linked
to stem rust resistance gene Sr2. Sr2 is present on the locus 2-3-
B. And its band size ranges upto 316bp. It does not show
amplification with V-4189, TW-76001, TW-76003, TW-76004,
TW-76005 and in TW-76009 advance line. XgWM-130 SSR
marker is linked to Lr19/Sr25 leaf and stem rust genes.
Lr19/Sr25 are present on 7D.Its fragment size ranges upto
109,111bp. Genotypes like V-4188, V-4022, Pasban-90, TW-
76003, TW-76005 and Parwaz-94 do not show the amplification
with Lr19/Sr25 leaf and stem rust genes. PCR-based diagnostic
marker STS-638 linked to Lr20 indicates recombination value of
7.1 cM with Lr20 [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. It is also linked with Sr15 gene. It is
resistant to both of leaf and stem rust. Its band size is 232bp and
located on 7A. Lr20 &amp; Sr15 are amplified in all genotypes
except in TW-76004 advance line. CFA 2019 Sr22 is SSR marker
that is used to check amplification of genotypes. Sr22 is a stem
rust resistance gene and located on 7AL. Its fragment size
ranges is upto 234,500bp. Lasani, V-4188, V-4022, AS-02 and
TW-76004 have not Sr22 stem rust resistance gene. STM-773-2 is
linked two of stem rust resistance genes Sr32 &amp; Sr36 
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>).
STM-773 is present on locus of 2B. All genotypes V-4189,
Lasani, V-4188, AARI-10, AS-02, Sehar, Pasban-90, V-4022,
Inqlab-91, Uqab-02, TW-76001, TW-76002, TW-76003, TW-
76004, and TW-76005, Parwaz-94, TW-76007, TW-76008, TW-
76009 and TW-76010 show the amplification with the fragment
size upto 192 &amp; 162bp.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title><italic>Phylogenetic Analysis of Wheat Genotypes</italic>:</title>
        <p>The dendrogram (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>) revealed four clusters among the
upland wheat genotypes. Cluster A comprised of genotypes V-
4189, TW-76009, V-4178, Uqab-02, TW-76002, TW-76010.
Cluster B comprised of V-4022, TW-76003, TW-76007, Pasban-
90 and Parwaz-94. Cluster C comprised of V-4188, TW-76008,
Sehar, TW-76004 and Cluster D comprised of Inqlab-91, V-3138
(Lasani), AS-02, and TW-76001. Cluster A is further divided
into two sub-cluster A<sub>1</sub> and A<sub>2</sub>. A<sub>1</sub> has two V-4189 and TW-
76009 advance lines. A<sub>2</sub> is consisted of four genotypes; AARI-
10, Uqab-02, TW-76002, TW-76005. Cluster B is further divided
into two sub-clusters. B1 has V-4022 &amp; TW-76003 advance lines
and B<sub>2</sub> include Pasban-90 &amp; Parwaz-94 varieties. Cluster C is
further divided into two sub-cluster C<sub>1</sub> and C<sub>2</sub>. C<sub>1</sub> has V-4188 &amp;
TW-76008, While C<sub>2</sub> has Sehar &amp; TW-76004. Cluster D consisted
of D<sub>1</sub> subgroup which has genotypes like Inqlab-91, V-3138
(Lasani), AS-02, and TW-76001. TW-76005 genotype did not
make cluster and could be helpful for crop improvement
programs.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The objectives of the present study was to check the rust
resistance genes among wheat genotypes by using PCR-Based
DNA Markers and for assessing the genetic relationships
among these genotypes by rust resistance markers. Statistical
validation was also performed using software NTSYSPC by
constructing dendrogram and similarity matrix. Molecular
markers could provide useful clues about agronomical
important and desirable qualitative genes by identifying or
manipulating. Markers help in breeding programs by
recognizing novel alleles in different species. Genetic maps of
these markers have been proved useful for the introgression of
novel genes into elite gemplasm [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Rusts pose threat to
wheat having narrow genetic background due to the lack of
resistance against evolving races of pathogen. It is necessary to
develop new techniques for incorporating efficient resistance in
wheat germplasm to avoid epidemics induced by plant
pathogens. Cultivars containing better characteristics have been
largely in use to stabilize wheat production. In wheat, it is
known that specific gene combinations provide durable and
improved resistance than using single gene because single
specific gene might become susceptible to genetic shift. Genetic
markers like STS (Sequence tagged site), RAPD (Randomly
amplified polymorphic DNA), SSR (Simple sequence repeats)
and others have been proved useful for identifying resistance
among different genotypes. Various researchers have utilized
these markers for the investigation of wheat cultivars for
different traits [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. 
45 stem rust resistance (<italic>Sr</italic>) markers (genes),
18 yellow rust resistance (Yr) genes (markers) [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and nearly
58 leaf rust resistance markers have been recognized for
different races of the pathogen. Leaf rust resistance genes were
named as Lr1 through Lr58 and mostly varieties consist of
some Lr genes [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Microsatellite <italic>gwm 60</italic> was the only marker
that co-segregated completely linked to Lr47.Lr47 is located
within an interstitial segment of <italic>Triticum speltoides</italic> Taush. 7S
chromosome translocated to the short arm of chromosome 7A
of bread wheat. Lr47 has been characterized using related
primers and gene amplification indicated the leaf rust
resistance comparing with already reported work [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The size
of the band corresponds to Lr47 was 380-450 bp. All the
genotypes possessed 380-450 bp size of band thought to be
resistant against leaf rust whereas Inqlab-91 which lack 380-450
bp of band which are susceptible to leaf rust carry no Lr47
gene. Flanking microsatellite markers were identified and one
tightly linked marker (gwm533) was shown to be associated
with presence of Sr2. All the amplification products show the
bands with the fragment size 316 bp. Genotypes like V-4189,
TW-76001, TW-76003, TW-76004, TW-76005 and TW-76009 do
not possess the Sr2 gene. The amplified fragments
corresponded to stripe rust resistance gene Yr26 and the results
were compared with the previous work which has been done
by [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. This yellow rust resistance gene was considered to be
Yr26 originally thought to be also located in chromosome arm
1BS linked to marker loci Xgwm273 and Xgwm11 with genetic
distances ranging from 1.075cM to 2.74cM in both combinations
studied. Xgwm11 is also linked with Yr15.The size of the bands
corresponds to Yr15 and Yr26 was 213 bp. It is not present in V-
4189, LASANI, V-4022, AARI-02, Inqlab-91, TW-76005 and in
TW-76008 genotypes. Among 20 genotypes that used for
molecular characterization of wheat genotypes for rust
resistance genes with the application of genetic analysis
software only TW-760010 genotype that has maximum no of
genes (23). Whereas TW-76005 genotype that has minimum no
of genes (14). Research was performed on improved varieties
and advance varieties, known as genotypes. Varieties are very
important in general cultivation in the fields. Varieties are
source of resistance and used as a parent in breeding. Eight
Varieties like LASANI, AARI-10, AS-02, Sehar, Pasban-90,
Parwaz-94, Inqlab-91 and UQAB are involved in this research
work. Pasban-90, Parwaz-94 and UQAB varieties were also
used in the work which was done by [<xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. LASANI possess the
genes like that. The present study performed to characterize
genes for rust resistance and this investigation could be helpful
in predicting the occurrence of rust disease according to
changing virulence of pathogen. Single gene could be enough
for newly evolved races of pathogen but varieties containing
efficient resistance are used economically and generally to
avoid production instability [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. It is necessary for plant
breeders to choose suitable rust resistance gene or combination
of these genes for avoiding rust attacks [<xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p>
      <p>The present study offers a way of making the breeding process
simpler and rust resistance more long lasting. And it provides
an insight to the rust resistance genes that should facilitate
efficient utilization and management of genetic stocks. It allows
plant breeders to better understand the rust resistance diseases
among wheat genotypes in a more systematic fashion, and to
develop strategies to incorporate rust resistance genes in their
breeding programs to protect crop stability. There is an urgent
need to incorporate several resistance genes against major
diseases into the new wheat cultivars. Marker assisted selection
along with precise artificial field tests provide new and efficient
possibilities for geneticists and breeders to achieve these goals.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>The data obtained in this experiment will help in accelerating
the breeding program in future, including pyramiding of
different wheat resistant genes in wheat varieties and in gene
stacking that is beneficial for improving the plant's immune
response by having multiple lines of defence for different
strains of rust.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary material</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
        <caption>
          <title>Data 1</title>
        </caption>
        <media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="97320630010371S1.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e429" position="anchor"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="FN1" fn-type="other">
        <p><bold>Citation:</bold>Haque <italic>et al</italic>, Bioinformation 10(6): 371-377 (2014)</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Babar</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Afr J Biotechnol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>1144</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mumtaz</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Afr J Biotechnol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>1188</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dayteg</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tuvesson</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Molecular Techniques in Crop Improvement, Ed. 2<sup>nd</sup></source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>143</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kolmer</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>441</fpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 15922652?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15922652</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Iqbal</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>139</fpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 19352756?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19352756</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nei</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <fpage>5269</fpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 291943?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">291943</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>175</volume>
          <fpage>351</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Begum</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Curr Res J Biol Sci</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>226</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>SB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>1007</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <fpage>1027</fpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 16896713?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16896713</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sui</surname>
              <given-names>XX</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>1209</fpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 19740035?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19740035</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lillemo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>116</volume>
          <fpage>1155</fpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 18347772?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18347772</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>111</volume>
          <fpage>846</fpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 16025305?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16025305</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Deynze</surname>
              <given-names>Van</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>125</fpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 19840401?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19840401</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hussain</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Afr J Biotechnol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>8578</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Che&#x142;kowski</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stepie&#x144;</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>117</fpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 14564046?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14564046</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kuraparthy</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <fpage>1379</fpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 17356867?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17356867</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vanzetti</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Elect J Biotech</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>267</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R19">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Pak J Bot</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>383</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>An example of SSR banding pattern obtained from
primer Xgwm-234 on 20 genotypes of wheat, which are linked
to the Leaf rust resistance gene Lr 52. M is DNA size markers.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="97320630010371F1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>An example of SSR banding pattern obtained from
primer Xbrac-352 on 20 genotypes of wheat which are linked to
the Leaf rust &amp; Stripe rust genes Lr 34/Yr18. M is DNA size
markers.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="97320630010371F2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>An example of SSR banding pattern obtained from
primer STM-773-2 on 20 genotypes of wheat which are linked
to the Stem rust genes Sr32 &amp; Sr36. M is DNA size markers.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="97320630010371F3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
      <label>Figure 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Dendrogram Constructed from Phylogenetic Software</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="97320630010371F4"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
