<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4111509</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25061748</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-19825</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103223</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Enzymology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Enzymes</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Transferases</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biosynthesis</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genome Analysis</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Transcriptome Analysis</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Next-Generation Sequencing</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Molecular Biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Molecular Biology Techniques</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Artificial Gene Amplification and Extension</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Polymerase Chain Reaction</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                    <subject>Reverse Transcriptase-Polymerase Chain Reaction</subject>
                  </subj-group>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Cloning</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Vector Cloning</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                    <subject>Plasmid Cloning</subject>
                  </subj-group>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Plant Science</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plant Biochemistry</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Phytochemicals</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Cloning and Characterization of a Norbelladine 4&#x2032;-<italic>O-</italic>Methyltransferase Involved in the Biosynthesis of the Alzheimer&#x2019;s Drug Galanthamine in <italic>Narcissus</italic> sp. <italic>aff. pseudonarcissus</italic></article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Cloning and Characterization of a Norbelladine 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-Methyltransferase</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kilgore</surname>
            <given-names>Matthew B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Augustin</surname>
            <given-names>Megan M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Starks</surname>
            <given-names>Courtney M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>O&#x2019;Neil-Johnson</surname>
            <given-names>Mark</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>May</surname>
            <given-names>Gregory D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Crow</surname>
            <given-names>John A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kutchan</surname>
            <given-names>Toni M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Donald Danforth Plant Science Center, St. Louis, Missouri, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Sequoia Sciences, St Louis, Missouri, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>National Center for Genome Resources, Santa Fe, New Mexico, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Neilan</surname>
            <given-names>Brett</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>University of New South Wales, Australia</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>tmkutchan@danforthcenter.org</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>A provisional patent application has been filed on the norbelladine &#x2019;-Omethyltransferase gene sequence and enzyme activity reported in this manuscript. Co-authors from Sequoia Sciences are collaborators who provided NMR spectroscopic analysis of the enzymatic product. These interests will not alter the authors' adherence to PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MBK TMK. Performed the experiments: MBK MMA CMS. Analyzed the data: MBK MMA CMS MOJ GDM JAC TMK. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MOJ GDM TMK. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: MBK MMA CMS MOJ GDM JAC TMK.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <elocation-id>e103223</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Kilgore et al</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Galanthamine is an Amaryllidaceae alkaloid used to treat the symptoms of Alzheimer&#x2019;s disease. This compound is primarily isolated from daffodil <italic>(Narcissus</italic> spp.<italic>)</italic>, snowdrop (<italic>Galanthus</italic> spp.), and summer snowflake (<italic>Leucojum aestivum)</italic>. Despite its importance as a medicine, no genes involved in the biosynthetic pathway of galanthamine have been identified. This absence of genetic information on biosynthetic pathways is a limiting factor in the development of synthetic biology platforms for many important botanical medicines. The paucity of information is largely due to the limitations of traditional methods for finding biochemical pathway enzymes and genes in non-model organisms. A new bioinformatic approach using several recent technological improvements was applied to search for genes in the proposed galanthamine biosynthetic pathway, first targeting methyltransferases due to strong signature amino acid sequences in the proteins. Using Illumina sequencing, a <italic>de novo</italic> transcriptome assembly was constructed for daffodil. BLAST was used to identify sequences that contain signatures for plant <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferases in this transcriptome. The program HAYSTACK was then used to identify methyltransferases that fit a model for galanthamine biosynthesis in leaf, bulb and inflorescence tissues. One candidate gene for the methylation of norbelladine to 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methylnorbelladine in the proposed galanthamine biosynthetic pathway was identified. This methyltransferase cDNA was expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> and the protein purified by affinity chromatography. The resulting protein was found to be a norbelladine 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase (<italic>Np</italic>N4OMT) of the proposed galanthamine biosynthetic pathway.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>The results presented herein were supported by the National Institutes of Health award number 1RC2GM092561 (NIGMS) and by the National Science Foundation Major Research Instrumentation award number DBI-0521250. The web sites for these funding sources are <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nih.gov/">http://www.nih.gov/</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nsf.gov/">http://www.nsf.gov/</ext-link>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="11"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta id="data-availability">
          <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
          <meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All data is currently available in the paper, the paper's Supporting Information files, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.medplantrnaseq.org">http://www.medplantrnaseq.org</ext-link> or being held by NCBI until publication (accession numbers KJ584561, KJ584562, KJ584563, KJ584564 and KJ584565).</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability</title>
      <p>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All data is currently available in the paper, the paper's Supporting Information files, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.medplantrnaseq.org">http://www.medplantrnaseq.org</ext-link> or being held by NCBI until publication (accession numbers KJ584561, KJ584562, KJ584563, KJ584564 and KJ584565).</p>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Amaryllidaceae alkaloids are a group of alkaloids with many documented biological activities. This makes them valuable potential medicines several examples are the anti-cancer compounds hemanthamine and lycorine and the anti-viral compound pancratistatin <xref rid="pone.0103223-Gabrielsen1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0103223-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. One example of an Amaryllidaceae alkaloid already used medically to treat Alzheimer&#x2019;s disease is galanthamine. Galanthamine is an alkaloid discovered in 1953 that is produced by members of the Amaryllidaceae family <xref rid="pone.0103223-Uyeo1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. It reduces the symptoms of Alzheimer&#x2019;s disease through acetylcholine esterase inhibition and nicotinic receptor binding. These activities are thought to compensate for reduced acetylcholine sensitivity in Alzheimer&#x2019;s disease by increasing acetylcholine levels and perhaps increasing acetylcholine sensitivity <xref rid="pone.0103223-Barik1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0103223-Irwin1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Until now, no committed biosynthetic genes have been identified <xref rid="pone.0103223-Wilcock1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0103223-Wilcock2" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Limited enzyme kinetic characterization has been done on plant protein extracts enriched for the norbelladine 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase (N4OMT) of <italic>Nerine bowdenii</italic>, but the underlying gene was never identified <xref rid="pone.0103223-Mann1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The putative galanthamine biosynthetic pathway has been studied in detail and intermediates in the pathway have been determined. This knowledge is based on radiolabeling experiments. Work on other Amaryllidaceae alkaloids including lycorine and hemanthamine studying steps prior to 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methylnorbelladine can be applied to galanthamine biosynthesis because 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methylnorbelladine is a universal substrate for these alkaloids <xref rid="pone.0103223-Ejchhorn1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. The proposed pathway starts with the amino acids phenylalanine and tyrosine <xref rid="pone.0103223-Barton1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. In <italic>Narcissus incomparabilis</italic> phenylalanine was established as a precursor that contributes the catechol portion of norbelladine. This was done using radiolabeling experiments to trace incorporation of [3-<sup>14</sup>C]phenylalanine into lycorine and degradation experiments on the resulting lycorine to determine the location of the <sup>14</sup>C label <xref rid="pone.0103223-Suhadolnik1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Similar experiments with phenylalanine were performed in <italic>Nerine browdenii</italic> monitoring hemanthamine incorporation <xref rid="pone.0103223-Wildman1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. As a follow up radiolabeling experiments were used to determine that phenylalanine probably proceeds sequentially through the intermediates <italic>trans</italic>-cinnamic acid, <italic>p</italic>-hydroxycinnamic acid and 3,4-dihydroxycinnamic acid or <italic>p</italic>-hydroxybenzaldehyde before conversion into 3,4-dihydroxybenzaldehyde <xref rid="pone.0103223-Suhadolnik2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Tyrosine has been established as a precursor of galanthamine that in contrast to phenylalanine contributes only to the non-catechol half of the norbelladine intermediate. This was done by observing [2-<sup>14</sup>C]tyrosine incorporation into galanthamine and degradation experiments of galanthamine <xref rid="pone.0103223-Barton1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Tyrosine decarboxylase converts tyrosine into tyramine and is well characterized in other plant families <xref rid="pone.0103223-Lehmann1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. 3,4-Dihydroxybenzaldehyde and tyramine condense into a Schiff-base and are reduced to form the first alkaloid in the proposed pathway, norbelladine. Norbelladine has been documented to incorporate into galanthamine and all major Amaryllidaceae alkaloid types in <sup>14</sup>C radiolabeling studies <xref rid="pone.0103223-Barton1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0103223-Battersby1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0103223-Barton2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methylnorbelladine is then formed by <italic>O</italic>-methylation of norbelladine <xref rid="pone.0103223-Barton1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. A phenol-coupling reaction, followed by spontaneous oxide bridge formation, creates <italic>N</italic>-demethylnarwedine, which is then reduced and <italic>N</italic>-methylated to yield galanthamine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103223-g001">Figure 1</xref>) <xref rid="pone.0103223-Ejchhorn1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. In one study, Barton et al. fed <italic>O</italic>-methyl[1-<sup>14</sup>C]norbelladine to flower stalks of King Alfred daffodils, but it was not incorporated into galanthamine. The authors concluded that the intermediate in the pathway must be 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methyl-<italic>N</italic>-methylnorbelladine despite low incorporation of this compound when the equivalent experiment was conducted with 4&#x2032;-O-methyl-[N-methyl-<sup>14</sup>C]norbelladine <xref rid="pone.0103223-Barton1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. A recent revision of the proposed pathway by Eichhorn et al. contradicted this conclusion and placed the <italic>N</italic>-methylation step at the end of the proposed pathway instead of before the phenol-coupling reaction. In that study, [OC<sup>3</sup>H<sub>3</sub>]4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methylnorbelladine was applied to ovary walls of <italic>Leucojum aestivum.</italic> Incorporation into products indicated that the pathway produced <italic>N</italic>-demethylated intermediates up until the penultimate step to galanthamine. <italic>N</italic>-methylation was proposed as the final step of biosynthesis <xref rid="pone.0103223-Ejchhorn1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0103223-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103223.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Proposed biosynthetic pathway for galanthamine.</title>
          <p>3,4-Dihydroxybenzaldehyde derived from phenylalanine and tyramine derived from tyrosine are condensed to form norbelladine. Norbelladine is methylated by <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT to 4&#x2032;-<italic>O-</italic>methylnorbelladine. 4&#x2032;-<italic>O-</italic>Methylnorbelladine is oxidized to <italic>N-</italic>demethylnarwedine. <italic>N-</italic>demethylnarwedine is then reduced to <italic>N-</italic>demethylgalanthamine. In the last step, <italic>N-</italic>demethylgalanthamine is methylated to galanthamine.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pone.0103223.g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The discovery of genes involved in metabolism is essential to metabolic engineering and synthetic biology. The elucidation of plant biochemical pathways can take decades. In fact, the biosynthesis of morphine, an important opiate analgesic, is still not completely elucidated at the gene level, even though the first enzyme specific to morphine biosynthesis was discovered more than 20 years ago in 1993 <xref rid="pone.0103223-Gerardy1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. Reports on the enzymatic activities of poppy extracts to describe the morphine biosynthetic pathway go even farther back to 1971 <xref rid="pone.0103223-Roberts1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. After more than 40 years of enzymology and reverse genetics, the morphine biosynthetic pathway is still incomplete at the gene level. Traditionally, plant biochemical pathway enzymes have been identified either directly by purification from plant extracts or indirectly by examining enriched cDNA libraries and functionally expressing clones <xref rid="pone.0103223-Mann1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0103223-Raman1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0103223-Widiez1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. To reduce pathway discovery from a 20+ year process to a more reasonable time frame, new methods must be developed and embraced. The previous work on galanthamine biosynthesis makes the prediction of enzyme classes involved in the proposed pathway possible, thereby rendering the galanthamine pathway a suitable system for development of an omic methodology for biochemical pathway discovery.</p>
      <p>In this study, using galanthamine biosynthesis as proof-of-concept, a novel workflow is presented to streamline the identification of biosynthetic pathway genes. A <italic>de novo</italic> transcriptome is created for <italic>Narcissus</italic> sp. <italic>aff. pseudonarcissus</italic> using illumina sequencing. HAYSTACK, a program that utilizes the Pearson correlation, is used to find genes that co-express with galanthamine accumulation in this transcriptome. This set of candidates is interrogated for homologs to methyltransferases. An OMT that converts norbelladine to 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methylnorbelladine (<italic>Np</italic>N4OMT) in the proposed biosynthesis of galanthamine is identified in this manner and characterized.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Plant tissue and chemicals</title>
        <p>Daffodil plants were collected from an outdoor plot in St. Louis, MO, with the GPS coordinates (38.659305, &#x2212;90.410203), during peak flowering and separated into leaf, bulb and inflorescence tissues. Inflorescence is considered all tissues above the spathe. The plants were collected with the permission of the corresponding author who is the owner of the private property. No endangered species were involved in this collection.</p>
        <p>Formic acid, potassium phosphate monobasic, potassium phosphate dibasic, tris(hydroxymethyl)aminomethane, glycerol, sodium acetate, sodium chloride, tetramethylethylenediamine, calcium chloride, magnesium chloride and &#x3B2;-mercaptoethanol were obtained from Acros Organics. Glycine, papaverine hydrochloride, <italic>S</italic>-adenosyl methionine (AdoMet), cobalt chloride, zinc chloride and manganese chloride were obtained from Fisher Scientific. Other chemicals include acetonitrile, JT Baker; InstaPAGE, IBI Scientific; ethanol 200 proof, KOPTEC; Bradford reagent, Bio-Rad; <italic>S</italic>-adenosyl-L-homocysteine, Sigma-Aldrich; deoxynucleotide triphosphates (dNTPs), New England BioLabs, Inc. (NEB); and isopropyl &#x3B2;-D-1-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG), Gold Biotechnology. The norbelladine <italic>N</italic>-methylnorbelladine, 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methyl-<italic>N</italic>-methylnorbelladine and 4&#x2032;-<italic>O-</italic>methylnorbelladine were synthesized previously <xref rid="pone.0103223-Ejchhorn1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. NotI, NdeI, T4 DNA ligase, Taq DNA Polymerase and Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase enzymes were from NEB. M-MLV reverse transcriptase and RNaseOUT were obtained from Invitrogen.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Alkaloid extraction and quantification</title>
        <p>Daffodil leaf, bulb and inflorescence tissues were extracted by grinding tissue with a mortar and pestle cooled with liquid nitrogen. Each ground sample was split into three technical replicates. Two volumes of 70% ethanol were added followed by vortexing 5 min and centrifuging at 14,000&#xD7;g for 10 min. The supernatant was filtered through a 0.2 &#xB5;m low protein binding hydrophilic LCR (PTFE, millex-LG) membrane. For galanthamine quantitation, samples were diluted 1000 fold. Liquid chromatography samples were injected (10 &#xB5;l) onto an LC-20AD (Shimadzu) with a Waters Nova Pak C-18 (300&#xD7;3.9 mm 4 &#xB5;m) column coupled to a 4000 QTRAP (AB Sciex Instruments) for MS/MS analysis. The gradient program had a flow rate of 0.8 ml/min; solvent A was 0.1% formic acid in H<sub>2</sub>O and solvent B was 0.1% formic acid in acetonitrile. At the beginning of the program, solvent B was held at 15% for 2 min, followed by a linear gradient to 43% B at 15 min, 90% B at 15.1 min, 90% B at 20 min, 15% B at 21 min and 15% B at 26 min. A Turbo Ion Spray ionization source temperature of 500&#xB0;C was used with low resolution for Q1 and Q3. All multiple reaction monitoring (MRM) scans were performed in positive ion mode. The ion fragment used for quantitation of galanthamine was 288.00 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>/213.00 [M-OH-C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>7</sub>N]<sup>+&#x2022;</sup><italic>m/z</italic>. Galanthamine was identified by comparison of retention time and fragmentation pattern to authentic galanthamine standard. The Analyst 1.5 software was used to quantitate galanthamine using a comparison of peak area of the unknown to authentic galanthamine.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Illumina sequencing and transcriptome assembly</title>
        <p>The transcriptome was generated via data cleaning, short read assembly, final assembly, and post processing steps. A modified TRIzol RNA isolation method found as protocol number 13 in Johnson et al. was used to obtain RNA for cDNA library preparation <xref rid="pone.0103223-Johnson1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Illumina RNA-Seq was used to generate 100 base pair paired-end reads from the cDNA library. The resulting data was monitored for overrepresented reads. Having found no such reads, adaptor sequences and sections of the standard phi X genome were identified and removed. Reads were then trimmed for quality using the FASTX toolkit version 0.0.8 with a Q value cutoff of 10 as is default for PHRAP <xref rid="pone.0103223-FASTXToolkit1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Reads were assembled in the following manner. ABySS was used to run multiple assemblies of the reads with a range of kmers 24&#x2264;k&#x2264;54. The resulting assemblies were assembled into scaffolds using ABySS scaffolder <xref rid="pone.0103223-Birol1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. Gaps in the sequences were resolved using GapCloser from the SOAPdenovo suit <xref rid="pone.0103223-Luo1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. A final assembly was conducted on the resulting synthetic ESTs using Mira in EST assembly mode <xref rid="pone.0103223-Chevreux1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. All sequences with over 98% identity were considered redundant and removed using CD-Hit <xref rid="pone.0103223-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. The resulting contigs &gt;100 base pairs long were included in the final assembly. Protein products for these contigs were predicted using ESTScan <xref rid="pone.0103223-Iseli1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0103223-Lottaz1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>; all peptides over 30 amino acids were reported. Burrows-Wheeler Aligner was used to align the original reads to the assembled transcriptome to generate relative expression data for the contigs in leaf, bulb and inflorescence tissues <xref rid="pone.0103223-Li2" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. The daffodil assembly and the raw read data can be found at the MedPlant RNA Seq Database, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.medplantrnaseq.org">http://www.medplantrnaseq.org</ext-link>. Anomalies in the number of reads per contig and abnormally long or short contigs were manually curated. To normalize for read depth, each expression value for each contig was divided by the total reads for the respective tissue and multiplied by 1 million.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Candidate gene identification</title>
        <p>Relative expression data was compared to the levels of galanthamine in daffodil tissues using HAYSTACK with a background cutoff of 1, correlation cutoff 0.8, fold cutoff 4 and p-value 0.05 <xref rid="pone.0103223-Mockler1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Using BLASTP, a list of known methyltransferases were queried against the daffodil transcriptome peptide list with an E-value of e<sup>&#x2212;9</sup> to identify methyltransferase homologs <xref rid="pone.0103223-Altschul1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. Accession numbers from NCBI for these methyltransferases are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s008">Table S1</xref>. Overlap between the methyltransferase homologs and contigs that pass the HAYSTACK criteria were considered candidate genes. The candidate daffodil norbelladine 4&#x2032;-OMT has the designation medp_9narc_20101112|62361 in the contigs.fa file in the Narcissus_spp.tar file on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.medplantrnaseq.org">http://www.medplantrnaseq.org</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Phylogenetic tree</title>
        <p>Sequences found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s009">Table S2</xref> were aligned using MUSCLE in the MEGA 5.2 software with default parameters <xref rid="pone.0103223-Tamura1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. For the phylogeny, this alignment was provided as input into the Maximum-Likelihood algorithm also found in MEGA 5.2. Default parameters were used except the Gaps/Missing Data treatment was set to partial deletion.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>PCR and Cloning</title>
        <p>The 5&#x2032; and 3&#x2032; ends of the <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT sequence were completed using Rapid Amplification of cDNA Ends (RACE) with the Invitrogen RACE kit. For gene specific primers (GSP) see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s010">Table S3</xref>. The same PCR program was used for both 5&#x2032; and 3&#x2032;RACE. This applies to both cycles of nested PCR as well. The PCR program parameters were 30 s 98&#xB0;C 1 cycle; 10 s 98&#xB0;C, 30 s 60&#xB0;C, 1 min 72&#xB0;C 30 cycles; 5 min 72&#xB0;C 1 cycle. The outer-primer PCR was a mixture of 4.6 ng/&#xB5;l RACE ready bulb cDNA, 0.3 mM dNTPs, 0.3 &#xB5;M GSP primer, 0.9 &#xB5;M kit provided RACE primer, 1 U NEB Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase and Invitrogen recommended quantity of buffer in a 50 &#xB5;l reaction. The inner-primer PCR used the product of the outer-primer PCR as template with 0.2 &#xB5;M of the inner RACE GSP and Invitrogen primers and 0.2 mM dNTPs.</p>
        <p>Amplification of the <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT open reading frame was performed with 5.1 ng/&#xB5;l daffodil bulb oligo(dT) primed cDNA, 0.4 mM dNTPs, 0.4 &#xB5;M each forward and reverse outer-primer, 1 UNEB Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase and recommended buffer in a 50 &#xB5;l reaction. With the following PCR program parameters: 30 s 98&#xB0;C 1 cycle; 10 s 98&#xB0;C, 30 s 52&#xB0;C, 1 min 72&#xB0;C for 30 cycles; 5 min 72&#xB0;C 1 cycle. The inner-primer PCR used 1 &#xB5;l of the outer-primer PCR product and used the inner-primers in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s010">Table S3</xref>. The same PCR time program was used except the annealing temperature was increased to 53&#xB0;C.</p>
        <p><italic>Np</italic>N4OMT was cloned into the pET28a vector with the NotI and NdeI restriction sites that were added to the 5&#x2032; and 3&#x2032; ends of the open reading frame using the inner PCR primers. PCR product and pET28a were digested with NotI and NdeI enzymes, followed by gel purification and ligation with the T4 DNA ligase. The resulting construct was transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5&#x3B1; cells and screened on Luria-Bertani agar plates with 50 &#xB5;g/ml kanamycin. Resulting colonies were screened by colony PCR with T7 sequencing and T7 terminator primers and Taq DNA Polymerase. The following cycle program was used: 3 min 94&#xB0;C 1 cycle; 30 s 94&#xB0;C, 30 s 52&#xB0;C, 2 min 72&#xB0;C 30 cycles; 7 min 72&#xB0;C 1 cycle. Plasmid minipreps were obtained using the QIAGEN QIAprep Spin Miniprep Kit. After Sanger sequencing of constructs (Genewiz), the desired plasmids were transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21(DE3) Codon Plus RIL competent cells. The sequences of the resulting five variants have the following accession numbers KJ584561(NpN4OMT1), KJ584562(<italic>Np</italic>N4OMT2), KJ584563(<italic>Np</italic>N4OMT3), KJ584564(<italic>Np</italic>N4OMT4) and KJ584565(<italic>Np</italic>N4OMT5).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Protein purification</title>
        <p>Recombinant protein production in 1 L of <italic>E. coli</italic> and purification with TALON resin followed the protocol found in <xref rid="pone.0103223-Higashi1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. No proteases were added to the protein extract, and desalting was performed with PD-10 columns from GE Healthcare. Protein quantity was determined according to Bradford; purity was monitored by SDS-PAGE. The <italic>E. coli</italic> cell line containing the hexahistidine-tagged methylthioadenosine/<italic>S</italic>-adenosylhomocysteine nucleosidase (Pfs) construct from Choi-Rhee and Cronan&#x2019;s work was used to purify Pfs protein <xref rid="pone.0103223-ChoiRhee1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Screening enzyme assays</title>
        <p>Enzyme assays for initial testing of <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT1 contained 10 &#xB5;g of pure protein with 200 &#xB5;M AdoMet, 100 &#xB5;M norbelladine and 30 mM potassium phosphate buffer pH 8.0 in 100 &#xB5;l. The assays were incubated for 2 hr at 30&#xB0;C. The vector control was an <italic>E. coli</italic> extract purified with TALON in the same way as the methyltransferase protein. For the vector control assay, an equal volume of the pure vector control extract was substituted for the <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT1 protein in the enzyme assay. These assays were quenched by adjusting the pH to 9.5 with two volumes of sodium bicarbonate and extracted with two volumes ethyl acetate two times. After drying, the extracts were re-suspended in the initial mobile phase of the HPLC program. The HPLC separation of the assays was performed using a phenomenex Luna C8(2) 5 &#xB5;m 250&#xD7;4.6 mm column with solvent A (0.1% formic acid in H<sub>2</sub>O) and solvent B (acetonitrile). The program started with 10% solvent B and a flow rate of 0.8 ml/min, a linear gradient began at 2 min to 30% at 15 min, 90% at 15.1 min, 90% at 20 min, 10% at 21 min and 10% at 28 min. Injection volume was 20 &#xB5;l using a Waters Autosampler. Waters UV detector was set to 277 nm.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2i">
        <title>Kinetic characterization</title>
        <p>After optimization of the assay, the buffer was changed to 100 &#xB5;M glycine at pH 8.8, with 5 mM of MgCl<sub>2</sub> added and the temperature was increased to 37&#xB0;C in 100 &#xB5;l total reaction volume. When performing kinetic assays, the <italic>E. coli</italic> enzyme Pfs was added to break down SAH and prevent product inhibition. Product formation in kinetic experiments was quantified by comparing product peak area to a standard curve of the expected product or equivalent. Papaverine was used as an internal standard.</p>
        <p>With the same solvent system as for screening enzyme assays, the HPLC program started with 20% B and a flow rate of 0.8 ml/min, a linear gradient began at 2 min to 25.4% B at 7 min, 90% at 7.2 min, 90% at 9 min, 20% at 9.1 min and 20% at 14 min. A 4000 QTRAP mass spectrometer coupled to the same LC column and time program as used in HPLC was used to collect all compound mass and fragmentation data. For fragmentation data and program setting details see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s011">Table S4</xref>. For norbelladine kinetics an MRM program in positive ion mode was used to monitor the following fragments 260.00 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>/138.00 [M-C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>9</sub>O]<sup>+&#x2022;</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic>, 260.00 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>/121.00 [M-C<sub>7</sub>H<sub>8</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+&#x2022;</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic>, 274.00 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>/137.00 [M+H-C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>9</sub>O<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic>, 274.00 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>/122.00 [M+H-C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>10</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic>. The fragments with 260.00 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic> and 274.00 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic> molecular ions were replaced when looking at <italic>N</italic>-methylnorbelladine for 274.00 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>/152.10 [M-C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>9</sub>O]<sup>+&#x2022;</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic>, 274.00 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>/121.00 [M-C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>12</sub>NO<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+&#x2022;</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic>, 288.00 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>/150.10 [M-C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>9</sub>O<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+&#x2022;</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic> and 288.20 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>/137.00 [M-C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>12</sub>NO]<sup>+&#x2022;</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic>. Papaverine internal standard was monitored with the following fragments 340.40[M+H]<sup>+</sup>/324.20 [M-CH<sub>3</sub>]<sup>+&#x2022;</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic> and 340.40 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>/202.10 [M-C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>9</sub>O<sub>2</sub>]<sup>+&#x2022;</sup>
<italic>m/z.</italic> When conducting dopamine kinetics, galanthamine was used as the internal standard and samples were not ethyl acetate extracted prior to LC/MS/MS analysis. To remove protein, two volumes of acetonitrile were added followed by 1 hr at &#x2212;20&#xB0;C and 10 min centrifugation at 16,100&#xD7;g, 4&#xB0;C. The supernatant was dried under vacuum and re-suspended in the starting mobile phase before analysis. The HPLC time program was changed to start at 5% solvent B with solution going to waste until 3.9 min, at 5 min start linear gradient to 25% B at 25 min, 90% B at 9.5 min, 90% B at 11 min, 5% B at 11.1 min and 5% B at 16 min. Ions monitored in the MRM were 168.00 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>/151.00 [M+H-OH]<sup>+</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic> and 168.00 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>/119.00 [M-OH-OCH<sub>3</sub>]<sup>+&#x2022;</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic>. AdoMet steady state kinetic parameters were determined with norbelladine as the saturated substrate. Product was quantitated using HPLC with the 28 min program used for screening enzyme assays. Product for assays on the additional <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT variants was detected with this same 28 min program on HPLC.</p>
        <p>When conducting kinetic experiments the <italic>K<sub>m</sub></italic> was at least five fold higher than the minimum concentration of substrate and fivefold lower than the maximum concentration of substrate tested. <italic>K<sub>m</sub></italic> and <italic>k<sub>cat</sub></italic> were calculated by nonlinear regression to the Michaelis-Menten kinetics equation with the GraphPad PRISM 5.0 software.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2j">
        <title>NMR</title>
        <p>NMR spectra were acquired for 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methylnorbelladine in CD<sub>3</sub>OD at 600 MHz on a BrukerAvance 600 MHz spectrometer equipped with a BrukerBioSpin TCI 1.7 mm MicroCryoProbe. Proton, gCOSY, ROESY, gHSQC, and gHMBC spectra were acquired; <sup>13</sup>C chemical shifts were obtained from the HSQC and HMBC spectra. Chemical shifts are reported with respect to the residual non-deuterated MeOD signal (&#x3B4;<sub>H</sub> 3.31) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s001">Figure S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s002">S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s003">S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s004">S4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s005">S5</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2k">
        <title>Quantitative Real Time-PCR (qRT-PCR)</title>
        <p>cDNA for leaf, bulb and inflorescence tissues of daffodil were created using 1 &#xB5;g RNA from the respective tissues, random primers and M-MLV reverse transcriptase according to the Invitrogen protocol. qRT-PCR was conducted with a TaqMan designed gene expression assay for the methyltransferase with ribosomal RNA as a reference according to manufacture protocol. Reactions (5 &#xB5;l) were performed in quadruplicate with outlier exclusion using Applied Biosystems StepOnePlus Real-Time PCR system. Methyltransferase relative expression values were determined by calculating &#x394;&#x394;C<sub>T</sub> values relative to standard ribosomal RNA and leaf tissue <xref rid="pone.0103223-Livak1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The Illumina sequencing of daffodil leaf, bulb and inflorescence tissues resulted in 65 million paired-end reads that were used to make the daffodil transcriptome assembly. The transcriptome assembly consisted of 106,450 sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103223-g002">Figure 2A</xref>) with a mean length of 551 base pairs and a maximum length of 13,381 base pairs. A similar number of &gt;100 base pair sequences were found in the transcriptome of <italic>Chlorophytum borivilianum</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0103223-Kalra1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. This mean length indicates a high number of the sequences are long enough for homology searches and cloning work. Of these sequences, 79,980 were predicted to have open reading frames and were translated into peptides. After determining the reads coming from the three tissues, several homologs of genes with predictable expression patterns were used to evaluate the quality of the expression estimations. The RuBisCO large and small subunits have high amounts of expression in the photosynthetic leaf and inflorescence tissues compared to the non-photosynthetic bulb tissue. A homolog to the MADS62 floral development transcription factor is exclusively expressed in the inflorescence tissue as would be expected <xref rid="pone.0103223-Kwantes1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. The read counts were thus determined to produce expected expression patterns.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0103223-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103223.g002</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Identification of <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT in the daffodil transcriptome.</title>
          <p>(A) Venn diagram of all sequences, all OMTs and all galanthamine correlating sequences according to HAYSTACK. (B) Accumulation level of galanthamine in daffodil (C) Candidate <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT expression profile in leaf, bulb and inflorescence with the relative initial read estimate and qRT-PCR &#x394;&#x394;Ct on the y-axis with leaf tissue set to 1.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pone.0103223.g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The LC/MS/MS data for leaf, bulb, and inflorescence tissues resulted in a pronounced accumulation pattern of galanthamine. The largest concentration was found in bulb tissue, with a lower level found in leaf and the lowest level in inflorescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103223-g002">Figure 2B</xref>).</p>
      <p>Using BLAST to seek homologs to the methyltransferases found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s008">Table S1</xref> yielded 298 methyltransferase candidate genes <xref rid="pone.0103223-Raman1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Separately, HAYSTACK identified 9,505 contigs that co-express with galanthamine accumulation. A comparison of the two resulting lists revealed one methyltransferase <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT that fits the HAYSTACK model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103223-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). This methyltransferase was chosen for functional analysis. After RACE, <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT was found to be a 239 amino acid protein with a predicted molecular weight (MW) of 27 kDa. When expressed using the pET28a vector, the added <italic>N</italic>-terminal Histidine tag increased the MW to 29 kDa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103223-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). In the course of cloning, five unique clones were obtained with &gt;96% identity to each other. Due to the two-toned yellow flower color, single flower and size, the daffodil variety used in this study is likely Carlton. Based on genome size estimates, Carlton is thought to be a domesticated form of <italic>Narcissus pseudonarcissus</italic> with a genome duplication event that resulted in a tetraploid <xref rid="pone.0103223-Zonneveld1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. A high number of paralogs is, therefore, expected. In addition, these bulbs have been propagated vegetatively. For these reasons, the existence of multiple similar sequences is not surprising.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0103223-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103223.g003</object-id>
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Recombinant <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT1 purification, enzyme assay and NMR structure elucidation of the 4&#x2032;-<italic>O-</italic>methylnorbelladine product.</title>
          <p>(A) SDS-PAGE gel 10% including fractions from crude extract and the desalted protein prep. This is shown for vector only, <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT1 and Pfs preparations. (B) Enzyme assays (top to bottom): Norbelladine standard; 4&#x2032;-<italic>O-</italic>Methylnorbelladine standard; Assay with <italic>E. coli</italic> vector-only crude extract added; Assay without AdoMet added; Complete methyltransferase assay. (C) NMR structure elucidation: proton chemical shifts are black, carbon chemical shifts are blue, key HMBC correlations are black arrows, and key ROESY correlations are red arrows.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pone.0103223.g003"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Due to the high similarity of the clones, the first to be cloned was selected for thorough characterization. The clone selected for characterization is 92.5% identical on the amino acid level to the original sequence in the transcriptome assembly (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s006">Figure S6</xref>). The recombinant protein was purified with a yield of 16.7 mg protein/L <italic>E. coli</italic> culture. SDS-PAGE analysis revealed the protein to be of apparent homogeneity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103223-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Initial enzyme assays with <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT1 yielded, upon HPLC analysis, a peak with the retention time of 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methylnorbelladine. The vector only control lacks <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT1 but has all other assay components. Therefor the absence of product in the vector control assay excludes the possibility of a background reaction. The absence of product in the assay lacking AdoMet shows that the methyltransferase uses AdoMet as a co-substrate and cannot form product without AdoMet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103223-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). The pH optimum was found to be 8.8 and the temperature optimum 45&#xB0;C (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s007">Figure S7B</xref>&#x2013;C). The Pfs protein, shown purified in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103223-g003">Figure 3A</xref>, was added to prevent SAH inhibition in kinetic enzyme assays, through the Pfs catalyzed hydrolysis of SAH to adenine and <italic>S</italic>-ribosyl-homocysteine <xref rid="pone.0103223-ChoiRhee1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>.</p>
      <p>An alternative methylation product, 3&#x2032;-<italic>O-</italic>methylnorbelladine, has the same retention time on HPLC, the same UV profile and MS/MS fragmentation pattern as 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methylnorbelladine. Thus, NMR analysis was performed to determine the regiospecificity of <italic>O</italic>-methylation. HMBC correlations from both the methoxyl protons (&#x3B4;<sub>H</sub> 3.88) and H-6&#x2032; (&#x3B4;<sub>H</sub> 6.90) to the same carbon (&#x3B4;<sub>C</sub> 149.9) placed the methoxyl group at C-4&#x2032;. Its location was further supported by a ROESY correlation from the methoxyl protons to H-5&#x2032; (&#x3B4;<sub>H</sub> 6.98). The NMR data thus confirmed that 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methylnorbelladine is the product of the enzyme reaction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103223-g003">Figure 3C</xref>).</p>
      <p>To determine the substrate specificity of this methyltransferase, several similar substrates were tested. Activity comparable to that found with norbelladine was observed using <italic>N</italic>-methylnorbelladine as the substrate. Dopamine also served as a substrate. Under the assay conditions used, product was not detected with caffeic acid, vanillin, 3,4-dihydroxybenzaldehyde, and tyramine as substrates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0103223-t001">Table 1</xref>). To determine if the other 4 variants show similar activity, they were purified, and enzymatic activity was confirmed for all variants using norbelladine as the substrate. When monitoring <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT1 norbelladine assays allowed to proceed to completion, no sign of double methylation products were observed as expected.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0103223-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103223.t001</object-id>
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Substrate specificity of <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT1.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0103223-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0103223.t001"/>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substrate</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> (&#xB5;M)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub> (1/min)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub>/<italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> (1/&#xB5;M*min)</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">norbelladine</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6&#xB1;0.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3&#xB1;0.06</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AdoMet</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5&#xB1;1.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5&#xB1;0.01</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N-</italic>methylnorbelladine</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9&#xB1;0.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6&#xB1;0.15</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dopamine</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3&#xB1;2.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6&#xB1;0.15</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">caffeic acid</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">vanillin</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,4-dihydroxybenzaldehyde</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tyramine</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt101">
            <label/>
            <p>ND, Not detected.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt102">
            <label/>
            <p>&#xB1;, Standard error.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Phylogenetic analysis of the <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT1 placed it in the class I OMT group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103223-g004">Figure 4</xref>). <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT1 has a length consistent with the 231&#x2013;248 amino acid range found in class I OMTs. This is in contrast to other known plant catechol 4-OMTs which all group in the class II OMTs as their length and cofactor requirements reported in previous work would predict. All these methyltransferases are significantly longer than the standard class I OMTs and none are reported to have the characteristic divalent cation dependence of class I OMTs <xref rid="pone.0103223-Schrder1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0103223-Joshi1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. When testing <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT1 for cation dependence, enzymatic activity improved upon the addition of cobalt. Enzymatic activity increased four-fold more with the addition of magnesium instead of cobalt (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s007">Figure S7A</xref>). This preference for magnesium over other divalent cations is also to be expected from a class I OMT <xref rid="pone.0103223-Joshi1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. It is, furthermore, consistent with previous work on enzyme extracts enriched for this OMT <xref rid="pone.0103223-Mann1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0103223-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103223.g004</object-id>
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT1.</title>
          <p>A maximum-likelihood phylogenetic tree of characterized methyltransferases listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103223.s009">Table S2</xref>
<xref rid="pone.0103223-Takeshita1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0103223-Widiez1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0103223-Schrder1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0103223-Gang1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0103223-Kopycki1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0103223-Day1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0103223-Kato1" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>. Alignment constructed using MUSCLE.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pone.0103223.g004"/>
      </fig>
      <p>To validate the expression profiles predicted based on read counts; qRT-PCR was conducted with the same RNA preparation used to prepare the cDNA libraries for Illumina sequencing. The resulting expression profile is slightly different from that obtained from Illumina sequencing. The qRT-PCR expression profile has a higher quantity of inflorescence transcript relative to bulb transcript (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103223-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). This minor difference is potentially due to cross amplification, during qRT-PCR, with other close homologs in the plant.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The expression pattern, product formation and low <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> for norbelladine all indicate <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT methylates norbelladine in the proposed galanthamine biosynthetic pathway. Two differing orders of methylation have been proposed for galanthamine biosynthesis <xref rid="pone.0103223-Ejchhorn1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. The methylation of <italic>N</italic>-methylnorbelladine was tested to determine if a preference for the <italic>N</italic>-methylation state could be observed at <italic>O</italic>-methylation. Similar <italic>K<sub>m</sub></italic> and <italic>k<sub>cat</sub></italic> values for <italic>N</italic>-methylnorbelladine and norbelladine indicate that a preference for the <italic>N</italic>-methylation state does not occur at <italic>O</italic>-methylation. The results presented here support both proposed galanthamine biosynthetic pathways. Future work on additional enzymes in the pathway will be needed to enzymatically validate one pathway or the other. The lack of enzymatic activity when testing 3,4-dihydroxybenzaldehyde suggests that methylation does not occur prior to formation of norbelladine. The methylation of dopamine is expected considering structural similarity to the methylated moiety of norbelladine. Tyramine was not methylated; this is as expected for a class I OMT (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0103223-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      <p>Several aspects of the candidate gene selection approach proved important for this successful identification. One is the selection of a variety of methyltransferases for the homology search. If only the known 4-OMTs had been used in the homology search, the gene would have been missed due to the large difference in sequence between known 4-OMTs and <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT. It has been shown that catechol 4&#x2032;-OMT and catechol 3&#x2032;-OMT can differ by as little as one amino acid <xref rid="pone.0103223-Wils1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>. Because of this potential for a conversion form catechol 3&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methylation to 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methylation though evolution, OMTs of both positions were used in the homology search. Also, both class I and class II OMTs were used in the search because both classes are known to methylate catechols. Considering the multiple branches of the <italic>N</italic>-methyltransferases in the OMT phylogeny, it is worth investigating enzymes that annotate as <italic>N</italic>-methyltransferases <xref rid="pone.0103223-Raman1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. For these reasons, the sequences used in the initial BLAST search consisted of representatives of known <italic>O-</italic> and <italic>N</italic>-methyltransferases of small metabolites. The <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT turned out to be a member of the class I OMTs. Class I OMTs show closer homology to human catechol OMT than to all known plant catechol 4-OMTs in class II, as demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103223-g004">Figure 4</xref>
<xref rid="pone.0103223-Ibdah1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. The closest known catechol 4-OMT to <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT is bacterial, has 34% identity to <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT and is a class I OMT from <italic>Cyanobacterium Synechocystis</italic> sp. Strain PCC 6803 (<italic>Syn</italic>OMT) <xref rid="pone.0103223-Kopycki1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. Many 3-OMTs show even higher homology to <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT than <italic>Syn</italic>OMT. It is probable that the 4-OMT activity of <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT was acquired independently of <italic>Syn</italic>OMT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103223-g004">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
      <p>The second selection criterion, co-expression with galanthamine accumulation, was also of great value. It reduced the number of candidate OMTs from hundreds to one. There are a variety of methods for the prioritization of candidate genes <xref rid="pone.0103223-Moreau1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0103223-Saito1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>. Many of these methods are oriented towards species and systems for which there are extensive databases or prior knowledge regarding a gene involved in the pathway or process. In one study, a collection of &#x223C;500 microarrays was used to demonstrate the co-expression of genes in the same pathway in Arabidopsis <xref rid="pone.0103223-Wei1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. However, extensive gene expression data are typically not available for non-model systems. There have been several studies that use co-expression analysis to find genes in a pathway and produce promising candidate gene lists. These studies often lack biochemical validation of the in <italic>silico</italic> candidates <xref rid="pone.0103223-Sun1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. If a novel function is proposed, this type of analysis is incomplete without biochemical validation of enzyme activity. Enzymes that are homologous to functionally equivalent enzymes in a different species can be corroborated by co-expression analysis <xref rid="pone.0103223-Sun1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. There are several studies that use a simple differential expression model and microarrays to find biosynthetic genes by comparing biosynthetically active and inactive accessions in rose and strawberry <xref rid="pone.0103223-Aharoni1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0103223-Guterman1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>. Differential expression analysis lacks algorithms to use data with differing levels of metabolism occurring in more than two samples. The Pearson correlation can compare data from multiple samples. Mercke et al. have used a Pearson correlation-based method to identify gene expression with microarrays that correlate with levels of specific terpenes in cucumber <xref rid="pone.0103223-Mercke1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>. Illumina-based transcriptomes are, however, more sensitive to minor variants in the sequences and to splice variants. Illumina-based gene expression data also have a far greater dynamic range, limited only by sequence depth, than microarrays <xref rid="pone.0103223-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. Subtleties in the sequences that could be missed with microarrays can now be detected with Illumina sequencing.</p>
      <p>The use of HAYSTACK as a platform to use the Pearson correlation is ideal because it is designed to receive a hypothesis for gene expression and look for gene expression that correlates with that hypothesis. This is in contrast to an approach in which gene expression patterns are clustered based on similarity to each other. The search for a defined pattern in the data allows the number of required expression data points to be reduced compared to an approach that needs to define clusters of gene expression patterns based on similarity. In HAYSTACK, the shared expression pattern is already defined. HAYSTACK applies additional screening criteria including a p-value test for significance, a fold cutoff and background cutoff. The approach chosen in our study used knowledge of known chemical intermediates, a transcriptome with expression profiles for three tissues, and metabolite levels to identify a candidate gene product to validate with <italic>in vitro</italic> enzyme activity. Little prior knowledge of a pathway is required to use this approach, making this workflow ideal for the identification of genes in unknown biochemical pathways.</p>
      <p>There are several modifications to this approach that could be used to improve its power. It could be applied to more tissues, environmental conditions or time points to provide even greater statistical power to correlate co-expression of biosynthetic genes with the biosynthesis of their products. The method could also be modified to include analysis of multiple end products. If the pathway in which the enzyme participates branches, several end products could be equally important to co-expression analysis. This combined consideration of multiple end products could lead to more informative models <xref rid="pone.0103223-Yamazaki1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>. Another potential source of information on the metabolite level could be the concentrations of intermediates made during synthesis. Correlations between biosynthetic gene expression, and perhaps the accumulation of metabolites as well, tend to decrease as distance in a pathway increases <xref rid="pone.0103223-Wei1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. Experiments that quantitate metabolic intermediates could be useful for finding biosynthetic genes if the flux through the pathway is not so high that intermediates do not accumulate. The latter would be the case in a pathway assembled into a metabolon.</p>
      <p>The discovery of this enzyme enables the future elucidation of other enzymes in the proposed galanthamine biosynthetic pathway and other novel pathways. Genes that co-express with <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT can be identified and used as candidate genes for other steps in the proposed galanthamine biosynthetic pathway. This will potentially be useful for earlier steps in the pathway, considering the tendency of expression correlations to decrease as distance in metabolic pathways increase <xref rid="pone.0103223-Wei1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. This enzyme discovery also validates the utility of this workflow to characterize metabolic pathways and provides a valuable method for pathway discovery in orphan species.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103223.s001">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>
              <italic>Np</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>N4OMT1 product 4&#x2032;-</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>O</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>-methylnorbelladine proton NMR spectra with peak assignments.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0103223.s001.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103223.s002">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>
              <italic>Np</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>N4OMT1 product 4&#x2032;-</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>O</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>-methylnorbelladine COSY spectra.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0103223.s002.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103223.s003">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>
              <italic>Np</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>N4OMT1 product 4&#x2032;-</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>O</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>-methylnorbelladine HMBC spectra.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0103223.s003.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103223.s004">
        <label>Figure S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>
              <italic>Np</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>N4OMT1 product 4&#x2032;-</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>O</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>-methylnorbelladine ROESY spectra.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0103223.s004.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103223.s005">
        <label>Figure S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>
              <italic>Np</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>N4OMT1 product 4&#x2032;-</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>O</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>-methylnorbelladine HSQC spectra.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0103223.s005.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103223.s006">
        <label>Figure S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Protein sequence alignment of </bold><bold><italic>Np</italic></bold><bold>N4OMT variants.</bold> Five unique variants of the <italic>Np</italic>N4OMT sequence are aligned against the original sequence predicted by the <italic>de novo</italic> assembled transcriptome using CLC software. Dots are identical residues.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0103223.s006.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103223.s007">
        <label>Figure S7</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Effect of divalent cations, temperature and pH on </bold><bold><italic>Np</italic></bold><bold>N4OMT1 enzyme activity.</bold> (A) Divalent cations tested with 5 min assays with 5 &#xB5;M of cation Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Co<sup>2+</sup>, Zn<sup>2+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup> or Mn<sup>2+</sup>. (B) pH optimum 15 min assays with 5 &#xB5;M Mg<sup>2+</sup>. (C) Temperature optimum 15 min assays with 5 &#xB5;M Mg<sup>2+</sup>. Divalent cation and pH testing reactions are 100 &#xB5;l reactions at 37&#xB0;C. The divalent cation test contained 4 &#xB5;M norbelladine, while pH and temperature optimum tests contained 100 &#xB5;M norbelladine in the assay mix.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0103223.s007.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103223.s008">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Methyltransferases used in BLAST search.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0103223.s008.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103223.s009">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Methyltransferases used in phylogeny.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0103223.s009.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103223.s010">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Primers used in RACE, cloning and colony PCR.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0103223.s010.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103223.s011">
        <label>Table S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Parameters used for LC/MS/MS analysis.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0103223.s011.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Judy Coyle for figure preparation, Robin S. Kramer (National Center for Genome Resources) for contributing to the transcriptome assembly, Bradley S. Evans (Donald Danforth Plant Science Center) for assistance in mass spectral interpretation and John E. Cronan (Department of Microbiology, University of Illinois) for the <italic>E. coli</italic> culture with the <italic>pfs</italic> construct.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Gabrielsen1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gabrielsen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monath</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huggins</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kefauver</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pettit</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Antiviral (RNA) activity of selected Amaryllidaceae isoquinoline constituents and synthesis of related substances</article-title>. <source>J Nat Prod</source>
<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>1569</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1581</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1336040</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Havelek1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Havelek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seifrtova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kralovec</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bruckova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cahlikova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The effect of Amaryllidaceae alkaloids haemanthamine and haemanthidine on cell cycle progression and apoptosis in p53-negative human leukemic Jurkat cells</article-title>. <source>Phytomedicine</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>479</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>490</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24182986</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Liu1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>WX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Effects of lycorine on HL-60 cells via arresting cell cycle and inducing apoptosis</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>
<volume>578</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>250</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15589827</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Uyeo1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Uyeo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1953</year>) <article-title>Lycoris alkaloids. XXIV. Isolation and characterization of lycoremine</article-title>. <source>Pharm Bull</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13155122</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Barik1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dajas-Bailador</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wonnacott</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Cellular responses to nicotinic receptor activation are decreased after prolonged exposure to galantamine in human neuroblastoma cells</article-title>. <source>Br J Pharmacol</source>
<volume>145</volume>: <fpage>1084</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1092</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15937519</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Irwin1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name> (<year>1960</year>) <article-title>Cholinesterase inhibition by galanthamine and lycoramine</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>147</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>148</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13853036</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Wilcock1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lilienfeld</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaens</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Efficacy and safety of galantamine in patients with mild to moderate Alzheimer&#x2019;s disease: multicentre randomised controlled trial. Galantamine International-1 Study Group</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>
<volume>321</volume>: <fpage>1445</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1449</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11110737</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Wilcock2">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lilienfeld</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Truyen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A long-term comparison of galantamine and donepezil in the treatment of Alzheimer&#x2019;s disease</article-title>. <source>Drugs Aging</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>789</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12875613</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Mann1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>1963</year>) <article-title>Alkaloids and plant metabolism. VI. <italic>O</italic>-Methylation <italic>in vitro</italic> of norbelladine, a precursor of Amaryllidaceae alkaloids</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>238</volume>: <fpage>3820</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3823</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14109227</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Ejchhorn1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ejchhorn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zenk</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Biosynthesis of the amaryllidaceae alkaloid galanthamine</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>
<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1037</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1047</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Barton1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Barton DHR, Kirby GW, Thomas GM (1963) Phenol oxidation and biosynthesis. Part VI. The biogenesis of Amaryllidaceae alkaloids. J Chem Soc: 4545&#x2013;4558.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Suhadolnik1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Suhadolnik</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>FIscher</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zulalian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1962</year>) <article-title>The biogenic origin of the C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>1</sub> unit of lycorine</article-title>. <source>J Am Chem Soc</source>
<volume>84</volume>: <fpage>4348</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4349</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Wildman1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wildman</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Battersby</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Breuer</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name> (<year>1962</year>) <article-title>Biosynthesis in the Amaryllidaceae. Incorporation of 3-C14-Tyrosine and phenylalanine in <italic>Nerine browdenii</italic> W. Wats</article-title>. <source>J Am Chem Soc</source>
<volume>84</volume>: <fpage>4599</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4600</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Suhadolnik2">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Suhadolnik</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zulalian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1963</year>) <article-title>Biogenesis of the Amaryllidaceae alkaloids. II. Studies with whole plants, floral primordia and cell free extracts</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>208</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>212</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13979157</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Lehmann1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pollmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Gene expression and characterization of a stress-induced tyrosine decarboxylase from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>
<volume>583</volume>: <fpage>1895</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1900</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19450582</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Battersby1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Battersby</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fales</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wildman</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name> (<year>1961</year>) <article-title>Biosynthesis in the Amaryllidaceae. Tyrosine and norbelladine as precursors of haemanthamine</article-title>. <source>J Am Chem Soc</source>
<volume>83</volume>: <fpage>4098</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4099</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Battersby2">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Battersby AR, Bink R, Breuer SW (1961) Biosynthesis in the Amaryllidaceae: incorporation of norbelladine into lycorine and norpluvine. Proc Chem Soc July: 243.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Barton2">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Barton DHR, Kirby GW, Taylor JB, Thomas GM (1961) The biosynthesis of Amaryllidaceae alkaloids. Proc Chem Soc July: 254&#x2013;255.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Gerardy1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gerardy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zenk</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Purification and characterization of salutaridine: NADPH 7-oxidoreductase from <italic>Papaver somniferum</italic></article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>
<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>132</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Roberts1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>Polyphenolases in the 1000 g fraction of <italic>Papaver somniferum</italic> latex</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>3021</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3027</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Raman1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rathinasabapathi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>beta-alanine <italic>N</italic>-methyltransferase of <italic>Limonium latifolium</italic>. cDNA cloning and functional expression of a novel <italic>N</italic>-methyltransferase implicated in the synthesis of the osmoprotectant beta-alanine betaine</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>132</volume>: <fpage>1642</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1651</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12857843</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Takeshita1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takeshita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mimura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fitchen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Molecular cloning and characterization of <italic>S</italic>-adenosyl-L-methionine: scoulerine-9-<italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase from cultured cells of <italic>Coptis japonica</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7719631</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Ounaroon1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ounaroon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Decker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lottspeich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kutchan</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>(<italic>R,S</italic>)-Reticuline 7-<italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase and (<italic>R,S</italic>)-norcoclaurine 6-<italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase of <italic>Papaver somniferum</italic> - cDNA cloning and characterization of methyl transfer enzymes of alkaloid biosynthesis in opium poppy</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>808</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>819</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14675446</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Nomura1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kutchan</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Three new <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferases are sufficient for all <italic>O</italic>-methylation reactions of ipecac alkaloid biosynthesis in root culture of <italic>Psychotria ipecacuanha</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>285</volume>: <fpage>7722</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7738</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20061395</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Morishige1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morishige</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dubouzet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yazaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Molecular cloning of columbamine <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase from cultured <italic>Coptis japonica</italic> cells</article-title>. <source>Eur J Biochem</source>
<volume>269</volume>: <fpage>5659</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5667</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12423366</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Frick1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Frick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kutchan</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Molecular cloning and functional expression of <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferases common to isoquinoline alkaloid and phenylpropanoid biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>339</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10205892</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Widiez1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Widiez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hartman</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dudai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Functional characterization of two new members of the caffeoyl CoA <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase-like gene family from <italic>Vanilla planifolia</italic> reveals a new class of plastid-localized <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferases</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>76</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>488</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21629984</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Johnson1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bruskiewich</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burris</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Evaluating methods for isolating total RNA and predicting the success of sequencing phylogenetically diverse plant transcriptomes</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e50226</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23185583</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-FASTXToolkit1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">FASTX-Toolkit website. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hannonlab.cshl.edu/fastx_toolkit">http://hannonlab.cshl.edu/fastx_toolkit</ext-link>. Accessed 2014 Jul 2.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Birol1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Birol</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jackman</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Varhol</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title><italic>De novo</italic> transcriptome assembly with ABySS</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>2872</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2877</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19528083</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Luo1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>SOAPdenovo2: an empirically improved memory-efficient short-read <italic>de novo</italic> assembler</article-title>. <source>Gigascience</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23587118</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Chevreux1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chevreux</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pfisterer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drescher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Driesel</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>M&#xFC;ller</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Using the miraEST assembler for reliable and automated mRNA transcript assembly and SNP detection in sequenced ESTs</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1147</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1159</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15140833</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Li1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Godzik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Cd-hit: a fast program for clustering and comparing large sets of protein or nucleotide sequences</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1658</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1659</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731699</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Iseli1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Iseli C, Jongeneel CV, Bucher P (1999) ESTScan: a program for detecting, evaluating, and reconstructing potential coding regions in EST sequences. Proc Int Conf Intell Syst Mol Biol: 138&#x2013;148.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Lottaz1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lottaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iseli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jongeneel</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bucher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Modeling sequencing errors by combining Hidden Markov models</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>Suppl 2</issue><fpage>ii103</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>112</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14534179</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Li2">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1754</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1760</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Mockler1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mockler</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Priest</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The DIURNAL project: DIURNAL and circadian expression profiling, model-based pattern matching, and promoter analysis</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harb Symp Quant Biol</source>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>363</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18419293</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Altschul1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#xE4;ffer</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>3389</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3402</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Tamura1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MEGA5: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>2731</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2739</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546353</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Higashi1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Higashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kutchan</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Crystallization and preliminary X-ray diffraction analysis of salutaridine reductase from the opium poppy <italic>Papaver somniferum</italic></article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr Sect F Struct Biol Cryst Commun</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>166</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-ChoiRhee1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Choi-Rhee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cronan</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A nucleosidase required for in <italic>vivo</italic> function of the <italic>S-</italic>adenosyl-L-methionine radical enzyme, biotin synthase</article-title>. <source>Chem Biol</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>589</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>593</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15911379</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Livak1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>408</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Kalra1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kalra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Puniya</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kulshreshtha</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title><italic>De novo</italic> transcriptome sequencing reveals important molecular networks and metabolic pathways of the plant, <italic>Chlorophytum borivilianum</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e83336</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24376689</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Kwantes1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kwantes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liebsch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verelst</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>How MIKC* MADS-box genes originated and evidence for their conserved function throughout the evolution of vascular plant gametophytes</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>302</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21813465</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Zonneveld1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zonneveld</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The involvement of <italic>Narcissus hispanicus</italic> Gouan in the origin of <italic>Narcissus bujei</italic> and of cultivated trumpet daffodils (Amaryllidaceae)</article-title>. <source>Anales del Jard&#xED;n Bot&#xE1;nico de Madrid</source>
<volume>67</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Schrder1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schr&#xF6;der</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wehinger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lukacin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wellmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seefelder</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Flavonoid methylation: a novel 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase from <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic>, and evidence that partially methylated flavanones are substrates of four different flavonoid dioxygenases</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>1085</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1094</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15110688</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Akashi1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>cDNA cloning and biochemical characterization of <italic>S</italic>-adenosyl-L-methionine: 2,7,4&#x2032;-trihydroxyisoflavanone 4&#x2032;-<italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase, a critical enzyme of the legume isoflavonoid phytoalexin pathway</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>112</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12610212</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Kim1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Regiospecific methylation of naringenin to ponciretin by soybean <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase expressed in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biotechnol</source>
<volume>119</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>162</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15961179</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Gang1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gang</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lavid</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zubieta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beuerle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Characterization of phenylpropene <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferases from sweet basil: facile change of substrate specificity and convergent evolution within a plant <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase family</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>505</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>519</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11884690</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Joshi1">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Conserved sequence motifs in plant <italic>S</italic>-adenosyl-L-methionine-dependent methyltransferases</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>663</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>674</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9687070</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Wils1">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wils</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A single amino acid determines position specificity of an <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> CCoAOMT-like <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>
<volume>587</volume>: <fpage>683</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>689</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23416302</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Ibdah1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ibdah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A novel Mg(2+)-dependent <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase in the phenylpropanoid metabolism of <italic>Mesembryanthemum crystallinum</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>278</volume>: <fpage>43961</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>43972</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12941960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Kopycki1">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kopycki</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stubbs</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hagemann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Porzel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Functional and structural characterization of a cation-dependent <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase from the cyanobacterium <italic>Synechocystis</italic> sp. strain PCC 6803</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>283</volume>: <fpage>20888</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>20896</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18502765</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Moreau1">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tranchevent</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Computational tools for prioritizing candidate genes: boosting disease gene discovery</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>536</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22751426</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Saito1">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yonekura-Sakakibara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Decoding genes with coexpression networks and metabolomics &#x2013; &#x2018;majority report by precogs&#x2019;</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>36</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18160330</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Wei1">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Srinivasasainagendra</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional coordination of the metabolic network in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>142</volume>: <fpage>762</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>774</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16920875</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Sun1">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Pyrosequencing of the <italic>Camptotheca acuminata</italic> transcriptome reveals putative genes involved in camptothecin biosynthesis and transport</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>533</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22035094</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Aharoni1">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aharoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keizer</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alvarez-Huerta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Identification of the SAAT gene involved in strawberry flavor biogenesis by use of DNA microarrays</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>647</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>662</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10810141</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Guterman1">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guterman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shalit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Menda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piestun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dafny-Yelin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Rose scent: genomics approach to discovering novel floral fragrance-related genes</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>2325</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2338</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368489</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Mercke1">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mercke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kappers</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verstappen</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vorst</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dicke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Combined transcript and metabolite analysis reveals genes involved in spider mite induced volatile formation in cucumber plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>135</volume>: <fpage>2012</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2024</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15310834</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Wang1">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>RNA-Seq: a revolutionary tool for transcriptomics</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015660</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Yamazaki1">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mochida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Asano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakabayashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Coupling deep transcriptome analysis with untargeted metabolic profiling in <italic>Ophiorrhiza pumila</italic> to further the understanding of the biosynthesis of the anti-cancer alkaloid camptothecin and anthraquinones</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>54</volume>: <fpage>686</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>696</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23503598</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Day1">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neutelings</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nolin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grec</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Habrant</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Caffeoyl coenzyme A <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase down-regulation is associated with modifications in lignin and cell-wall architecture in flax secondary xylem</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source>
<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>19</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19004632</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Eswaran1">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eswaran</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parameswaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sathram</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anantharaman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar G</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Yeast functional screen to identify genetic determinants capable of conferring abiotic stress tolerance in <italic>Jatropha curcas</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Biotechnol</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20302659</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Ibrahim1">
        <label>65</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bruneau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bantignies</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Plant <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferases: molecular analysis, common signature and classification</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9484457</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Hugueney1">
        <label>66</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hugueney</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Provenzano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verri&#xE8;s</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferrandino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meudec</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A novel cation-dependent <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase involved in anthocyanin methylation in grapevine</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>150</volume>: <fpage>2057</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2070</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19525322</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Nestor1">
        <label>67</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nestor A, Craig BS, Jack O, Ke Z (2008) Modulating lignin in plants. Google Patents.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Kopycki2">
        <label>68</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kopycki</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rauh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chumanevich</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Biochemical and structural analysis of substrate promiscuity in plant Mg<sup>2+</sup>-dependent <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferases</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>378</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>164</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18342334</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Choi1">
        <label>69</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morishige</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shitan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yazaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Molecular cloning and characterization of coclaurine <italic>N</italic>-methyltransferase from cultured cells of <italic>Coptis japonica</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>277</volume>: <fpage>830</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>835</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11682473</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0103223-Kato1">
        <label>70</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crozier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ashihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Caffeine synthase gene from tea leaves</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>406</volume>: <fpage>956</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>957</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10984041</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
