<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3521742</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-15511</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049718</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Agriculture</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Agricultural Biotechnology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Marker-Assisted Selection</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Crops</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cereals</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Wheat</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Crop Diseases</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genetics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Molecular Genetics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Gene Identification and Analysis</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plant Genetics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Crop Genetics</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Gene Expression</subject>
              <subject>Gene Function</subject>
              <subject>Gene Splicing</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Plant Science</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plant Pathology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Plant Pathogens</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Diagnostic Medicine</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Pathology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>General Pathology</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Biomarkers</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Cloning of a Conserved Receptor-Like Protein Kinase Gene and Its Use as a Functional Marker for Homoeologous Group-2 Chromosomes of the <italic>Triticeae</italic> Species</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">A Conserved Receptor-Like Protein Kinase Gene</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Qin</surname>
            <given-names>Bi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Tingting</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cao</surname>
            <given-names>Aizhong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Haiyan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xing</surname>
            <given-names>Liping</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ling</surname>
            <given-names>Hongqing</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Daowen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>Chunmei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xiao</surname>
            <given-names>Jin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ji</surname>
            <given-names>Jianhui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Xueluan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Peidu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Dajun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Xiue</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>The State Key Laboratory of Crop Genetics and Germplasm Enhancement, Cytogenetics Institute, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>The State Key Laboratory of Plant Cell and Chromosome Engineering, National Center for Plant Gene Research, Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Key Laboratory of Biology and Genetic Resources of Rubber Tree, Ministry of Agriculture, Rubber Research Institute, Chinese Academy of Tropical Agricultural Sciences, Danzhou, Hainan, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            <given-names>Wengui</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>National Rice Research Center, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>xiuew@njau.edu.cn</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: BQ XW. Performed the experiments: BQ TC HW LX JX JJ XC CY. Analyzed the data: BQ AC DW PC DL XW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: HL. Wrote the paper: BQ AC XW.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <elocation-id>e49718</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Qin et al</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Receptor-like kinases (RLKs) play broad biological roles in plants. We report on a conserved receptor-like protein kinase (<italic>RPK</italic>) gene from wheat and other <italic>Triticeae</italic> species. The <italic>TaRPK1</italic> was isolated from the <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> cv. Prins - <italic>Triticum timopheevii</italic> introgression line IGVI-465 carrying the powdery mildew resistance gene <italic>Pm6</italic>. The <italic>TaRPK1</italic> was mapped to homoeologous chromosomes 2A (<italic>TaRPK1-2A</italic>), 2D (<italic>TaRPK1-2D</italic>) and the <italic>Pm6</italic>-carrier chromosome 2G (<italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic>) of IGVI-465. Under the tested conditions, only the <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> allele was actively transcribed, producing two distinct transcripts via alternative splicing. The predicted 424-amino acid protein of TaRPK1-2G contained a signal peptide, a transmembrane domain and an intracellular serine/threonine kinase domain, but lacked a typical extracellular domain. The expression of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> gene was up-regulated upon the infection by <italic>Blumeria graminis</italic> f.sp. <italic>tritici</italic> (<italic>Bgt</italic>) and treatment with methyl jasmonate (MeJA), but down-regulated in response to treatments of SA and ABA. Over-expression of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> in the powdery mildew susceptible wheat variety Prins by a transient expression assay showed that it slightly reduced the haustorium index of the infected <italic>Bgt</italic>. These data indicated that <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> participated in the defense response to <italic>Bgt</italic> infection and in the JA signaling pathway. Phylogenetic analysis indicated that <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> was highly conserved among plant species, and the amino acid sequence similarity of TaRPK1-2G among grass species was more than 86%. Based on its conservation, the <italic>RPK</italic> gene-based STS primers were designed, and used to amplify the <italic>RPK</italic> orthologs from the homoeologous group-2 chromosomes of all the tested <italic>Triticeae</italic> species, such as chromosome 2G of <italic>T. timopheevii</italic>, 2R of <italic>Secale cereale</italic>, 2H of <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>, 2S of <italic>Aegilops speltoides</italic>, 2S<sup>l</sup> of <italic>Ae. longissima</italic>, 2M<sup>g</sup> of <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic>, 2S<sup>p</sup> and 2U<sup>p</sup> of <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic>. The developed STS markers serve as conserved functional markers for the identification of homoeologous group-2 chromosomes of the <italic>Triticeae</italic> species.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This research was supported by grants from the Chinese High Tech Program of China (No. 2011AA1001), the Natural Science Foundation of Jiangsu Province (No. BK2006720), Important National Science and Technology Specific Projects of Transgenic Research (No. 2011ZX08002-001), the Program of Introducing Talents of Discipline to Universities (No. B08025) and A Project Funded by the Priority Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions (PAPD). Research in Daowen Wang's group is supported in part by a grant (2011BAD07B02-2) from the Ministry of Science and Technology of China. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="11"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Receptor protein kinases (RPKs) play essential roles in the signal perception in animals in response to various growth factors and hormones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Fantl1">[1]</xref>. These receptors generally have an extracellular domain, a single transmembrane domain, and an intracellular catalytic kinase domain. Ligands bound by the extracellular domain stimulates receptor autophosphorylation on tyrosine residues within the cytoplasmic protein kinase domain. Then the binding of the ligand to the extracellular domain causes receptor dimerization thereby activating the cytoplasmic kinase domain by intermolecular phosphorylation and transduction of the signal to the downstream effectors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Song1">[2]</xref>. Based on the primary structure, plants also have a large gene family named as receptor-like kinases (RLKs) similar to the animal's RPKs, however, the auto-phosphorylation in plant RLKs is mostly specific to the serine and/or threonine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Walker1">[3]</xref>. Plant RLKs include receptor kinases and receptor-like cytoplasmic kinases (RLCKs) with no typical signal sequence or transmembrane domain, which have been implicated in the perception and transduction of extracellular signals into the cell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Shiu1">[4]</xref>. The RLKs are usually encoded by hundreds of genes in plant genomes, for example, <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> has more than 600 predicted RLKs representing nearly 2.5% of all the coding genes, and rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) has nearly twice as many RLKs members as <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> does <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Shiu2">[5]</xref>. Due to the large gene family, RLKs vary greatly for both their domain organization and the extracellular domains, and the RLK family can be divided into more than 40 sub-families based on their distinct extracellular domains <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Shiu1">[4]</xref>. The diversity in the ligand binding domain endows the RLKs a wide range of biological function, such as growth and development, responses to biotic and abiotic stresses, and nodulation and rhizobial symbiosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Shiu2">[5]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Plant RLKs have been implicated their roles in diverse signaling pathways. For example, <italic>Pto</italic> provides resistance against <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> in tomato <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Martin1">[6]</xref>, <italic>SLG</italic> of <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> may be required for self-incompatibility in the recognition between pollen and stigma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Walker2">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Torii1">[8]</xref>, and the rice <italic>Xa21</italic> confers broad spectrum resistance to <italic>Xanthomonas oryzae</italic> pv. <italic>oryzae</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Song2">[9]</xref>. Several RLKs have also been identified in wheat. The WLRK (wheat leaf rust kinase) gene family, which is located at the <italic>Lr10</italic> locus and conserved in wheat and related species, confers resistance to leaf rust disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Feuillet1">[10]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Feuillet3">[12]</xref>. Three receptor-like kinase genes (<italic>TaRLK-R1</italic>, <italic>2</italic> and <italic>3</italic>) were found to participate in the wheat hypersensitive response to the stripe rust fungus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Zhou1">[13]</xref>. A recent research in our lab showed that a putative serine and threonine protein kinase gene, <italic>Stpk-V</italic>, which located to the <italic>Pm21</italic> locus from <italic>Haynaldia villosa</italic>, conferred broad-spectrum powdery mildew resistance in wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Cao1">[14]</xref>. However, compared to the large population of the RLK genes in wheat, information on their biological role is still very limited. Thus, the identification of more wheat RLK genes is critical for better understanding of their biological roles in wheat.</p>
      <p>In our previous studies, a barley RFLP probe BCD135 was found to be closely linked with the powdery mildew resistance gene <italic>Pm6</italic>, which has been introduced from the tetraploid wheat <italic>T. timopheevii</italic> into the hexaploid common wheat. The sequence of BCD135 was highly conserved among several species including barley, wheat, rye, and rice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Tao1">[15]</xref>. At the genome region of BCD135 in barley and rice, there were two conserved genes, one was a putative receptor-like protein kinase gene (<italic>HvRPK</italic>), and the other had no putative function <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Park1">[16]</xref>. Based on the sequence of the second gene in barley, Ji et al. developed two STS markers closely linked to the gene <italic>Pm6</italic> in common wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Ji1">[17]</xref>. In the present study, the conserved <italic>TaRPK1</italic> gene in this region was explored in grass species based on the barley <italic>HvRPK</italic>, and a functional marker was developed for the identification of the homoeologous group-2 chromosomes of <italic>Triticeae</italic> species. The <italic>TaRPK1</italic> genes belonging to this conserved family were further cloned and characterized from hexaploid wheat, and the putative biological function of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> was investigated.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Plant materials</title>
        <p>Different <italic>Triticeae</italic> species with various genome constitution including <italic>Secale cereale</italic> L. cv. &#x2018;BLANCO&#x2019; (2n&#x200A;=&#x200A;2x&#x200A;=&#x200A;14, RR), <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L. cv. &#x2018;BETZES&#x2019; (2n&#x200A;=&#x200A;2x&#x200A;=&#x200A;14, HH), <italic>Aegilops speltoides</italic> Tausch (2n&#x200A;=&#x200A;2x&#x200A;=&#x200A;14, SS), <italic>Ae. longissima</italic> Schw. et Musch (2n&#x200A;=&#x200A;2x&#x200A;=&#x200A;14, S<sup>l</sup>S<sup>l</sup>), <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic> Roth (2n&#x200A;=&#x200A;2x&#x200A;=&#x200A;14, M<sup>g</sup>M<sup>g</sup>), and <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> (Hack.) Maire &amp; Weiller (2n&#x200A;=&#x200A;4x&#x200A;=&#x200A;28, S<sup>p</sup>S<sup>p</sup>U<sup>p</sup>U<sup>p</sup>]), and their genetic stocks, i.e. addition lines with the alien chromosomes added in the background of wheat variety &#x2018;Chinese spring&#x2019; (CS) (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L., 2n&#x200A;=&#x200A;6x&#x200A;=&#x200A;42, AABBDD) were introduced from Wheat Genetics &amp; Genomic Resources Center (WGGRC), Kansas State University, USA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0049718-t001">Table 1</xref>). The Swedish common wheat variety Prins, which is susceptible to powdery mildew, one <italic>T. timopheevii</italic> (2n&#x200A;=&#x200A;4x&#x200A;=&#x200A;28, AAGG) accession with the powdery mildew resistance gene <italic>Pm6</italic>, two <italic>Pm6</italic>-carrying <italic>T. aestivum</italic>-<italic>T. timopheevii</italic> introgression lines (IGVI-465 [FAO 163b/7*Prins] and IGVI-466 [Kenya Lemphi 50-13596/7*Prins]) were kindly provided by Dr. J. MacKey, Swedish Agricultural University, Uppsala, Sweden, and were used for gene cloning. A set of CS nulli-tetrasomic lines of homoeologous group-2 were also provided by the WGGRC and were used for mapping of wheat <italic>RPK</italic> genes.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0049718-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049718.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Plant materials introduced from the WGGRC, KSU, USA.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0049718-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0049718.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accession number</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Materials</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genome or Chromosome constitution</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA9001</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>H. vulgare</italic> L. cv. &#x2018;BETZES&#x2019;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HH</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA3698</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- BETZES DA 2H</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+t&#x2033;[2H arm unknown]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA3699</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- BETZES DA 3H</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[3H]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA3700</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- BETZES DA 4H</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[4H]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA3701</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- BETZES DA 5H</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[5H]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA3702</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- BETZES DA 6H</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[6H]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7591</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS-<italic>H. chilense</italic> DA 7H<sup>&#x2227;</sup>ch<sup>&#x2227;</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[7H<sup>&#x2227;</sup>ch<sup>&#x2227;</sup>]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA9020</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Secale</italic> L.cv.&#x2018;BLANCO&#x2019;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7501</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- BLANCO DA 1R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[1R]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7502</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- BLANCO DA 2R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[2R]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7503</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- BLANCO DA 3R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[3R]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7505</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- BLANCO DA 4R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[4R]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7506</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- BLANCO DA 5R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[5R]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7507</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- BLANCO DA 6R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[6R]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7508</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- BLANCO DA 7R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[7R]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA1910</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Ae. longissima</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S<sup>l</sup>S<sup>l</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7543</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. longissima</italic> DA 1S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[1S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#3]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7544</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. longissima</italic> DA 2S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[2S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#3]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7545</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. longissima</italic> DA 3S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[3S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#3]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7546</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. longissima</italic> DA 4S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[4S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#3]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7547</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. longissima</italic> DA 5S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[5S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#3]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7548</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. longissima</italic> DA 6S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[6S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#3]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7550</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. longissima</italic> DA 2S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[2S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#4]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA3579</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS-<italic>Ae. longissima</italic> DA 7/4S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[7/4S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>l<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#2]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA2899</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M<sup>g</sup>M<sup>g</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7655</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic> DA 1M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[1M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7656</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic> DA 2M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[2M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7657</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic> DA 3M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[3M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7658</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic> DA 4M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[4M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7659</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic> DA 5M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[5M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7660</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic> DA 6M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[6M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7661</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic> DA 7M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[7M<sup>&#x2227;</sup>g<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA2775</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U<sup>p</sup>U<sup>p</sup>S<sup>p</sup>S<sup>p</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7594</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA 1S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[1S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7595</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA 2S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[2S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7596</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA 3S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[3S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7597</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA 4S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[4S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7598</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA 5S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[5S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7600</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA 7S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[7S<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7614</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA 1U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[1U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7615</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA 2U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[2U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7616</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA 3U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[3U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7617</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA 4U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[4U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7618</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA 5U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[5U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7619</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA 6U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[6U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7620</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA 7U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[7U<sup>&#x2227;</sup>v<sup>&#x2227;</sup>#1]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA2780</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Ae. speltoides</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SS</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7689</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. speltoides</italic> DA 1S#3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[1S#3]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7690</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. speltoides</italic> DA 2S#3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[2S#3]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7691</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. speltoides</italic> DA 3S#3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[3S#3]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7692</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. speltoides</italic> DA 4S#3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[4S#3]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7693</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. speltoides</italic> DA 5S#3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[5S#3]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7694</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. speltoides</italic> DA 6S#3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[6S#3]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA7695</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS- <italic>Ae. speltoides</italic> DA 7S#3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x2033;+1&#x2033;[7S#3]</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Development of STS markers based on the sequence of the barley <italic>RPK</italic> gene <italic>HvRPK</italic></title>
        <p>The sequence of the barley gene <italic>HvRPK</italic> from the barley BAC clone AF474072 was downloaded from the Genbank <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Park1">[16]</xref>. Two SSRs (simple sequence repeats) were identified within the <italic>HvRPK</italic> sequence using the SSRHUNTER <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Li1">[18]</xref>, and several primers flanking the two SSR motifs were designed using Primer 3 Software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.wi.mit.Edu/cgi-bin/primer/primer3.cgi">http://www.genome.wi.mit.Edu/cgi-bin/primer/primer3.cgi</ext-link>). The detailed information on all the primers used in this study is given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0049718-t002">Table 2</xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0049718-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049718.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Information of primers used in this study.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0049718-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0049718.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer name</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer sequence (5&#x2032;-3&#x2032;)</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">RPK-F1/F2 as forward primers were combined with the reverse primers RPK-R1&#x223C;R4 and annealing temperatures were 65&#x223C;68&#xB0;C.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RPK-F1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">CGACTACGTGACGCTCAAGA</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RPK-F2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">CAAGAGCCTCGACAAGATCC</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RPK-R1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">GCGAAGAGGATCTTGTCGAG</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RPK-R2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">ACTTGTCGTCGAGGAGGATG</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RPK-R3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">ACACCAGCATCACCTCCTTC</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RPK-R4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">AGGCGTCATCATCCAGTAGC</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Primers were used to amplify the full length of <italic>TaRPK1</italic> and the annealing temperature was 61&#xB0;C.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TaRPK-ORF-F</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">ATGGCAGCCCGAGACACCAGTTCAA</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TaRPK-ORF-R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">TCATTTGCCGAAGCTCATGTCGTAG</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Primers were used in the Q-RT-PCR analyses and the annealing temperature was 65&#xB0;C.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RPK-QPCR-F</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">TACTTCAGCGGCAACATGAG</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RPK-QPCR-R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">AAATCCTTGGTGGCCTTCTT</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18S rRNA-F</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">AACACTTCACCGGACCATTCA</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18S rRNA-R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">CGTCCCTGCCCTTTGTACAC</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Primers were used to amplify the ORF of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> to construct the over-expression vector and the annealing temperature was 61&#xB0;C.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TaRPK1-2G-F</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">CGGGATCCATGGCAGCCCGAGACA</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TaRPK1-2G-R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">TCCCCCGGGTCATTTGCCGAAGCTC</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>PCR amplification</title>
        <p>For polymorphic analysis of the STS markers and chromosomal location of <italic>TaRPK1</italic>, PCR was performed following the procedure of Ji et al. (2008) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Ji1">[17]</xref>. The PCR products were separated in the 8% non-denaturing polyacrylamide gels (Acr: Bis&#x200A;=&#x200A;19: 1 or 39: 1) at room temperature with 1&#xD7;TBE buffer and visualized by silver staining <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Bassam1">[19]</xref>. High fidelity Taq DNA polymerases (QIAGEN, HotStar HiFidelity Polymerase Kit) were used for PCR amplifications for cloning of the gene <italic>TaRPK1</italic>. Amplification was performed at 94&#xB0;C for 5 min; 32 cycles of 94&#xB0;C for 15 s, 65 to 68&#xB0;C for 1 min, and 72&#xB0;C for 2 min; followed by 10 min at 72&#xB0;C. PCR products were analyzed in 1% agarose gels.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>BAC library screening and <italic>RPK</italic> gene cloning in wheat</title>
        <p>The BAC library of an elite common wheat variety Xiaoyan 54, kindly provided by Dr. Hongqing Ling, Institute of Genetics and Development Biology Chinese Academy of Sciences, China, was used to isolate the <italic>TaRPK</italic> gene. The positive BAC clone was identified by PCR using a STS marker STS<sub>RPK-F1/R4</sub> specific to the <italic>RPK</italic> sequence following the procedure of Dong et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Dong1">[20]</xref>. <italic>HvRPK</italic> was located in a 4.3 kb fragment when the BAC clone AF474072 was digested by <italic>Xba</italic> I <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Park1">[16]</xref>. To sub-clone the <italic>TaRPK</italic> from the positive BAC clone of Xiaoyan 54, the BAC was also digested with <italic>Xba</italic> I and the expected full-length DNA sequence of <italic>TaRPK</italic> gene was obtained. Based on the <italic>TaRPK</italic> sequence obtained from Xiaoyan 54, PCR primers flanking the ORF of <italic>TaRPK</italic> were designed and used to clone the full-length genomic DNA and cDNA sequences of the <italic>TaRPK1</italic> gene from IGVI-465 and <italic>T. timopheevii</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Splicing feature, protein architecture and phylogenetic analyses</title>
        <p>To characterize the splicing feature of the gene <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic>, the genomic DNA and cDNA sequences of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> were used for alignment and similarity analysis by DNAMAN version 5.2.2. TMHMM (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TMHMM-2.0/">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TMHMM-2.0/</ext-link>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Krogh1">[21]</xref> and SMART (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de/">http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de/</ext-link>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Letunic1">[22]</xref> were used to identify the architectures of the protein domain.</p>
        <p>The kinase domain of TaRPK1-2G was used as query sequence for identifying the TaRPK1-2G orthologs by the BLASTP searches in the Phytozome proteome database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phytozome.net/search.php?show=blast&amp;method=Org_Cpapaya">http://www.phytozome.net/search.php?show=blast&amp;method=Org_Cpapaya</ext-link>), and the best hits in various plant species were used for further analysis when the amino acid identity was &gt;50% identical (e-values&lt;e<sup>&#x2212;60</sup>) for at least 100 amino acid of the query sequence. The amino acid sequences of identified orthologs in fasta format were retrieved from the Phytozome proteome database, and the kinase domains of these orthologs were identified by the SMART protein domain prediction server <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Letunic1">[22]</xref>. The kinase domain sequences of TaRPK1-2G and its orthologs were aligned using the CLUSTALX <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Thompson1">[23]</xref>. Phylogenetic analysis was conducted and viewed using MEGA version 4.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Kumar1">[24]</xref> based on the Neighbor&#x2013;Joining method with a Poisson correction model and a bootstrap test of 1000 replicates.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Expression analysis of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> by quantitative RT-PCR</title>
        <p>Seedlings of the &#x2018;IGVI-465&#x2019; were grown in a growth chamber at 16/8 h light/dark and 25/20&#xB0;C temperature regime until the second leaf stage, when inoculation of <italic>Blumeria graminis</italic> f.sp. <italic>tritici</italic> (<italic>Bgt</italic>) was conducted by dusting the conidia from a susceptible wheat variety Sumai 3 onto the surface of the leaves of &#x2018;IGVI-465&#x2019;. The source of <italic>Bgt</italic> inoculum was a local natural mixture collected in the wheat fields of Nanjing, Jiangsu province, China. For chemical treatments, the seedlings of &#x2018;IGVI-465&#x2019; at the first leaf stage were sprayed with 5 mM salicylic acid (SA), 100 &#xB5;M methyl jasmonate (MeJA), 100 &#xB5;M abscisic acid (ABA), and 7 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, respectively. Total RNA of each sample was extracted using the TRIZOL reagent (Invitrogen, USA), and 2 &#xB5;g of RNA per sample was used for synthesizing the first-strand cDNA by the AMV reverse transcriptase (Takara) following the manufacturer's instruction.</p>
        <p>Responses of the <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> upon infection with <italic>Bgt</italic> and the application of chemical agents were analyzed by the real-time quantitative RT-PCR (Q-RT-PCR) with the specific primer pair of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> (RPK-QPCR-F and RPK-QPCR-R), and the 18S rRNA (amplified with primers 18rRNA-F and 18S rRNA-R) was used as a control. The PCR reaction was performed in a 25 &#xB5;l reaction mixture containing 1&#xD7;SYB Premix Ex Taq (Takara), 0.2 &#xB5;M of each primer, 1&#xD7; Rox Reference Dye, and about 30 ng cDNA per sample using the ABI Prism 7000 system (Applied Biosystems, USA). The program used was as follows: 1 min at 94&#xB0;C; followed by 40 cycles of 5 s at 94&#xB0;C, 15 s at 68&#xB0;C and 30 s at 72&#xB0;C. After completion of the reactions, the cycle threshold (C<sub>T</sub>) value was calculated and subsequently, the &#x394;&#x394;C<sub>T</sub> algorithm was used <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Livak1">[25]</xref>. The final value of relative gene quantification was expressed as <italic>n</italic>-fold change in <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> transcript level in tested samples in comparison with the untreated controls. The results are presented as the mean &#xB1; standard deviation (SD) of three independent analyses.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Single-cell transient expression assay</title>
        <p>The ORF of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic>, amplified using the primer pair TaRPK1-2G-F and TaRPK1-2G-R, was inserted into the expression vector pBI220 by placing the <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> under the control of the CaMV35S promoter. The recombinant vector pBI220-<italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> was used for single-cell transient expression assay according to Shirasu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Shirasu1">[26]</xref> and Cao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Cao1">[14]</xref>. The reporter plasmid pAHC25 containing the &#x3B2;-glucuronidase (<italic>GUS</italic>) gene and the expression plasmid pBI220-<italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> were mixed before coating of the particles (molar ratio of 1&#x2236;1; 1 &#xB5;g of total DNA). The bombarded leaves were transferred to 1% agar plates supplemented with 85 &#xB5;M benzimidazole and incubated at 18&#xB0;C for 8 h before high density inoculation with <italic>Bgt</italic> spores. Leaves were stained for GUS to identify the <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> transformed cells at 48 h after <italic>Bgt</italic> inoculation. The haustorium index (percentage of GUS-staining cells with haustoria in the total GUS-staining cells attacked by <italic>Bgt</italic>) was computed based on mean of three independent experiments, each based at least 50 independent interaction events.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>For the results of Q-RT-PCR and single-cell transient expression assay, the obtained data were analyzed by using SPSS analytical software package (version 19.0, IBM Corporation, New York, USA), and presented as the mean &#xB1; standard deviation (SD) of three independent replicates (<italic>n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;3). Comparisons between the controls and the tested samples were made ANOVA test and the statistical differences between the groups were tested by the Duncan's test. All statistically significant differences were tested at the level of <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05. Figures were drawn by Origin Data Analysis and Graphing Software, OriginPro8 (Version8.5.1, OriginLab Corporation, Massachusetts, USA).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Development of <italic>RPK</italic> gene-based STS markers and analysis of their potential use as functional marker in wheat and other <italic>Triticeae</italic> species</title>
        <p>The barley <italic>RPK</italic> gene (<italic>HvRPK</italic>) and the RFLP marker BCD135, which closely linked with gene <italic>Pm6</italic> in wheat, are both present in the barley BAC clone AF474072. To detect whether the orthologs of <italic>HvRPK</italic> was also linked with <italic>Pm6</italic> in wheat, two forward (RPK-F1 and RPK-F2) and four reverse (RPK-R1, RPK-R2, RPK-R3, and RPK-R4) primers, which flanked the SSR motifs of the <italic>HvRPK</italic> gene, were designed. Eight primer pairs were combined and used to test the polymorphism between the <italic>Pm6</italic>-carrying lines and their susceptible recurrent parent &#x2018;Prins&#x2019;. It was found that four primer combinations, STS<sub>RPK-F1/R1</sub>, STS<sub>RPK-F1/R2</sub>, STS<sub>RPK-F2/R3</sub> and STS<sub>RPK-F1/R4</sub> could produce clear polymorphism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g001">Figure 1A and B</xref>). They produced distinct specific bands for both the <italic>Pm6</italic>-carrying lines and &#x2018;Prins&#x2019;, indicating they could serve as co-dominant markers. Linkage analysis in a previous study has shown that the wheat <italic>RPK</italic> gene is closely linked to the <italic>Pm6</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Qin1">[27]</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0049718-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049718.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Polymorphic analysis of <italic>HvRPK</italic>-based STS primer pair amplicons and chromosome location of the <italic>RPK</italic> amplicons in common wheat.</title>
            <p>A. Polymorphisms between the <italic>Pm6</italic>-carrying powdery mildew resistant lines and susceptible lines (Arrows indicate the polymorphic bands). M: DNA fragment marker DL2000; 1 and 2: <italic>Triticum timopheevii</italic> (with <italic>Pm6</italic>); 3 and 4: <italic>Pm6</italic>-carrying <italic>T. aestivum</italic>-<italic>T. timopheevii</italic> introgression line IGVI-465; 5 and 6: susceptible wheat variety Prins. B. Chromosome location of the <italic>RPK</italic> gene using the homoeologous group-2 &#x2018;Chinese spring&#x2019; (CS) nulli-tetrasomic (NT) lines and <italic>Pm6</italic>-carrying <italic>T. aestivum</italic>-<italic>T. timopheevii</italic> introgression lines. The left arrows show the specific bands from chromosomes 2A or 2D and 2B, and arrow on the right shows the specific band from the chromosome 2G of <italic>Pm6</italic>-carrying lines. 1: Nulli2A/Tetra2B; 2: Nulli2A/Tetra2D; 3: Nulli2B/Tetra2A; 4: Nulli2B/Tetra2D; 5: Nulli2D/Tetra 2A; 6: Nulli2D/Tetra2B; 7: CS; 8: Prins; 9: <italic>Pm6</italic>-carrying <italic>T. aestivum</italic>-<italic>T. timopheevii</italic> introgression line IGVI-465; 10: <italic>Pm6</italic>-carrying <italic>T. aestivum</italic>-<italic>T. timopheevii</italic> introgression line IGVI-466; 11: <italic>T. timopheevii</italic> (with <italic>Pm6</italic>).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0049718.g001"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The amplification of STS<sub>RPK-F1/R4</sub> in the Chinese Spring (CS) nulli-tetrasomic lines involving homoeologous group-2 chromosomes enabled the clear discrimination of the <italic>RPK</italic> genes on the chromosomes 2G and 2B, while the two <italic>RPK</italic> gene copies on chromosomes 2A and 2D could not be discriminated due to their similar size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). The presence of <italic>RPKs</italic> in the 2A, 2B and 2D indicated their conservation in the three wheat genomes. To further demonstrate the conservation of the <italic>RPK</italic> gene in homoeologous group-2 chromosomes in the genomes of wheat relatives, the <italic>RPK</italic> genes were amplified using the above four STS markers in wheat relatives and their corresponding alien addition lines in the background of Chinese Spring. The results showed that all these STS markers could produce specific fragments in the alien species and the addition lines involving the group-2 chromosomes. For example, STS<sub>RPK-F1/R1</sub> produced a &#x223C;1900 bp specific band from chromosome 2G of <italic>T. timopheevii</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g001">Figure 1B</xref>), a &#x223C;400 bp specific band from chromosome 2H of barley (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g002">Figure 2A</xref>), a &#x223C;1000 bp specific band from 2R of rye (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g002">Figure 2B</xref>), three specific bands (&#x223C;480 bp, &#x223C;500 bp, and &#x223C;1000 bp) from 2S of <italic>Ae. speltoides</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>), two specific bands (&#x223C;1200 bp and &#x223C;500 bp) from 2S<sup>l</sup> of <italic>Ae. longissima</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g002">Figure 2D</xref>), two specific bands (&#x223C;1000 bp and &#x223C;600 bp) from 2M<sup>g</sup> of <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g002">Figure 2E</xref>), a &#x223C;500 bp and a &#x223C;1000 bp specific band from 2S<sup>p</sup> and 2U<sup>p</sup> of <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic>, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g002">Figure 2F</xref>). STS<sub>RPK-F1/R1</sub> could clearly discriminate the chromosomes 2S<sup>p</sup> and 2U<sup>p</sup> in the tetraploid <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic>. All these indicated highly conservation of <italic>RPK</italic> genes among diverse species, and the STS markers derived from <italic>RPK</italic> gene can be served as conserved functional markers to identify specific homoeologous group-2 chromosomes or chromosome segments of wheat relatives.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0049718-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049718.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Conserved <italic>RPK</italic> genes identified by the STS marker STS<sub>RPK-F1/R1</sub> from the homoeologous group-2 chromosomes of a series of wheat and <italic>Triticeae</italic> species.</title>
            <p>Arrows indicate the <italic>RPKs</italic> specific to each species. A: Barley and &#x2018;Chinese spring&#x2019; (CS)-barley disomic chromosome addition (DA) lines. Lanes 1 and 2: Barley variety BETZES; 3 and 4: DA2H; 5 and 6: DAt&#x201D;[2H] (ditelosomic chromosome addition line); 7: DA3H; 8: DA4H; 9: DA5H; 10: DA6H; 11: DA7H. B: Rye and CS-rye DA lines. Lanes 1 and 2: Rye variety BLANCO; 3: DA1R; 4 and 5: DA2R; 6: DA3R; 7: DA4R; 8: DA5R; 9: DA6R; 10: DA7R. C. <italic>Ae. speltoides</italic> and CS-<italic>Ae. Speltoides</italic> DA lines. Lanes 1 and 2: <italic>Ae. speltoides</italic>; 3: DA1S; 4 and 5: DA2S; 6: DA3S; 7: DA4S; 8: DA5S; 9: DA6S; 10: DA7S. D. <italic>Ae. longissima</italic> and CS-<italic>Ae. longissima</italic> DA lines. Lanes 1 and 2: <italic>Ae. longissima</italic>; 3: DA1S<sup>l</sup>; 4: DA2S<sup>l</sup>#3-1; 5: DA2S<sup>l</sup>#3-2; 6: DA3S<sup>l</sup> ; 7: DA4S<sup>l</sup>; 8:DA5S<sup>l</sup>; 9: DA6S<sup>l</sup>; 10: DA7/4S<sup>l</sup>. E. <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic> and CS-<italic>Ae. geniculata</italic> DA lines. Lanes 1 and 2: <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic>; 3: DA1M<sup>g</sup>; 4 and 5: DA2M<sup>g</sup>; 6: DA3M<sup>g</sup>; 7: DA4M<sup>g</sup>; 8: DA5M<sup>g</sup>; 9: DA6M<sup>g</sup>; 10: DA7M<sup>g</sup>. F: <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> and CS-<italic>Ae. peregrina</italic> DA lines. Lanes 1 and 2: <italic>Ae. peregrina</italic>; 3: DA1S<sup>p</sup>; 4 and 5: DA2S<sup>p</sup>; 6: DA3S<sup>p</sup>; 7: DA4S<sup>p</sup>; 8: DA5S<sup>p</sup>; 9: DA7S<sup>p</sup>; 10: DA1U<sup>p</sup>; 11 and 12: DA2U<sup>p</sup>; 13: DA3U<sup>p</sup>; 14: DA4U<sup>p</sup>; 15: DA5U<sup>p</sup>; 16: DA6U<sup>p</sup>; 17: DA7U<sup>p</sup>; 18: CS.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0049718.g002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Isolation of <italic>TaRPK</italic> gene in the common wheat variety Xiaoyan 54</title>
        <p>The fragment amplified by the STS<sub>RPK-F1/R4</sub> only included a 1,032 bp region of the CDS of barley <italic>HvRPK</italic>, which was totally 1,281 bp in length. To obtain the full length of the <italic>HvRPK</italic> homologs in hexaploid wheat, STS<sub>RPK-F1/R4</sub> was used to screen the BAC library constructed from the wheat variety Xiaoyan 54. Ten positive clones were identified. Based on the digestion results of the BAC clone AF474072 using <italic>Xba</italic> I <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Park1">[16]</xref>, the <italic>HvRPK</italic> was located in a 4.3 kb digested fragment. Accordingly, the positive clones were digested by <italic>Xba</italic> I, and an expected &#x223C;4.3 kb target fragment was sub-cloned into the pBluescript vector for sequencing. It was found that this 4,305 bp fragment (BAC-xiaoyan54, GenBank accession number JX065225) included two putative genes with opposite transcript directions, one was a putative PLA IIB/PLP6 (Patatin-like protein 6) gene of 1,166 bp in length, and the other was the target <italic>RPK</italic> gene of 1,644 bp in length. We designated the two genes from wheat as <italic>TaPLP6</italic> and <italic>TaRPK</italic>, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Cloning of <italic>TaRPK</italic> homologs from different genomes, analysis of its splicing feature and putative protein domain architectures in the <italic>Pm6</italic>-carrying line IGVI-465</title>
        <p>As <italic>TaRPK</italic> was tightly linked with <italic>Pm6</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Qin1">[27]</xref>, and mapped to the introgression segment of 2G. It is interesting to isolate the <italic>TaRPK</italic> homologous gene from the <italic>Pm6</italic>-carrying line IGVI-465 and to figure out its putative biological function. Based on the sequence of <italic>TaRPK</italic> from Xiaoyan 54, PCR primers (TaRPK-ORF-F and TaRPK-ORF-R) flanking the ORF (open reading frame) of <italic>TaRPK</italic> were used to clone the full-length genomic DNA and cDNA sequences of the <italic>TaRPK</italic> homologs from IGVI-465 and <italic>T. timopheevii</italic>. Sequence analysis indicated that three <italic>TaRPK</italic> homologs were present in IGVI-465 on chromosomes 2A (<italic>TaRPK1-2A</italic>, 1,691 bp, GenBank accession number JX065226), 2D (<italic>TaRPK1-2D</italic>, 1,692 bp, GenBank accession number JX065228), and the introgressed chromosome segment of 2G (<italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic>, 1,650 bp, GenBank accession number JX065231). Two <italic>TaRPK</italic> homologs were present in <italic>T. timopheevii</italic>, one each on chromosomes 2A<sup>t</sup> (<italic>TaRPK1-2A<sup>t</sup></italic>, 1,692 bp, GenBank accession number JX065227) and 2G (<italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic>, 1,650 bp). This indicated that in wheat variety CS, there were also three copies of <italic>RPK</italic>, and the two copies from chromosomes 2A and 2D in both CS and IGVI-465 were hard to separate and visualized as a single band in the non-denaturing polyacrylamide gels (as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g001">Figure 1B</xref>) due to their similar sequence size (with only one base pair difference in size as shown in IGVI-465). The 100% identity of the two <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> from IGVI-465 and <italic>T. timopheevii</italic> further proved that <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> was located on the introgressed chromosomal fragment of 2G in IGVI-465. Multiple sequence alignment showed that the <italic>TaRPK</italic> from Xiaoyan 54 and <italic>TaRPK1-2A</italic> had the highest similarity (being 93.27% identity) indicating that <italic>TaRPK</italic> was originally from the chromosome 2A in Xiaoyan 54.</p>
        <p>The comparison of the genomic DNA of the three <italic>TaRPK1</italic> homologs with their corresponding cDNA sequence in IGVI-465 showed that <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> was the gene actively transcribed under the tested conditions. <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> produced two different transcripts, probably due to alternative splicing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g003">Figure 3</xref>). One type (<italic>TaRPK1-2G -1</italic>, GenBank accession number JX065229) had the complete ORF and generated the putative functional protein, whereas the other (<italic>TaRPK1-2G-2</italic>, GenBank accession number JX065230) had 13 bp intronic sequence from the second intron, and resulted in a truncated protein due to premature termination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g003">Figure 3</xref>, indicated by the star). Alignment of the <italic>TaRPK1-2G-1</italic> and <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> indicated that <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> had 4 introns and 5 extrons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g003">Figure 3</xref>), and <italic>TaRPK1-2G -1</italic> coded for a predicted protein of 424 amino acids. Based on structural properties indicated by the TMHMM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Krogh1">[21]</xref> and SMART programs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Letunic1">[22]</xref>, the predicted protein was a receptor protein kinase (RPK). The predicted protein TaRPK1-2G has a transmembrane domain (TM, from the 7<sup>th</sup> to 29<sup>th</sup> amino acid), an N-terminal hydrophobic signal peptide (from the 1<sup>st</sup> to 26<sup>th</sup> amino acid), and a cytoplasmic serine/threonine protein kinase domain (from the 80<sup>th</sup> to 358<sup>th</sup> amino acid), but does not have the typical extracellular structure such as eLRRs. We found that, in the transmembrane domain and the signal peptide, there were 20 amino acids overlapping, which has not been found in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> RLKs.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0049718-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049718.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Schematic diagram of the <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> gene and its alternative splicing feature.</title>
            <p>Exons are shown as boxes. Introns are shown as black lines. The alternative splicing site is shown as diagonal lines. The star represents the premature stop codons in the alternative transcript.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0049718.g003"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Analysis of TaRPK1-2G orthologs in plant species</title>
        <p>To reveal the relationship of TaRPK1-2G with other RPKs, BLASTP was performed against the Phytozome proteome database for identifying TaRPK1-2G orthologs based on the similarity in their kinase domains, which was considered to be the most conserved domain among the RPKs. Orthologs were identified from 30 plant species with available genomic information, and together with the barley HvRPK, a total of 31 orthologs were used for phylogenetic analysis. These orthologs share a conserved serine/threonine protein kinase domain and belong to serine/threonine protein kinase by KOG classification (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0049718.s001">Form S1</xref>). The results indicated that TaRPK1-2G was highly conserved among the 32 selected species, and the amino acid sequence identity in the kinase domain was more than 86% among the RPKs from various grass species, including wheat (TaRPK1-2G), barley (HvRPK), <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> (OsRPK), <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> (BdRPK), <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> (SbRPK), <italic>Setaria italica</italic> (SiRPK), <italic>Zea mays</italic> (ZmRPK), and <italic>Panicum virgatum</italic> (PavRPK) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g004">Figure 4</xref>, detail information on these orthologs were provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0049718.s001">Form S1</xref>). Comparative genome mapping of the <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> orthologs in grass species showed that they were well retained in the collinear regions of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> which have been revealed by whole-genome comparison <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Salse1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-The1">[29]</xref>, such as <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> and <italic>Pm6</italic> co-located on 2BL [fraction length (FL) 0.50&#x2013;1.00 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Qin1">[27]</xref>, <italic>HvRPK</italic> on chromosome 2H: 140.1 cM, <italic>OsRPK</italic> on Chr4: 33,594,296 bp&#x2013;33,596,099 bp, <italic>BdRPK</italic> on Bd5: 26,167,244 bp&#x2013;26,168,882 bp, and <italic>SbRPK</italic> on chromosome_6: 59,793,399 bp&#x2013;59,795,140 bp (The locations of these <italic>RPKs</italic> in their corresponding genomes are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0049718.s001">Form S1</xref>). Moreover, these orthologs from the grass species formed into a group, which was separate from the dicots, with a high bootstrap support value (99%). However, TaRPK1-2G was most similar (with 97% identity) to the putative HvRPK from the barley BAC clone AF474072 (AAM13439). In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, the putative LRR-RLK (AT1G56140) showed the highest identity (53.8%) with TaRPK1-2G. AT1G56140 has been classified as the LRR protein of the VIII-2 subfamily <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Shiu1">[4]</xref>, suggesting that TaRPK1-2G, although without the LRR motifs at its extracellular structure, also belongs to the VIII-2 subfamily (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g004">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0049718-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049718.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Phylogenetic tree of TaRPK1-2G and its orthologs.</title>
            <p>Neighbor Joining phylogenetic tree of the kinase domains of TaRPK1-2G and its orthologs from other 31 plant species was constructed using MEGA4.1. Bootstrap support on the left of each node was inferred from 1,000 replicates. The full names of all species and accession number or locus name of each sequence used for phylogenetic analysis were provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0049718.s001">Form S1</xref>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0049718.g004"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title>Expression profiling of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> under stress and hormone treatments</title>
        <p>Since a large number of <italic>RPKs</italic> were proved to participate in plant defense response. To investigate whether <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> also participates in the defense response in wheat, the expression patterns of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> upon the attack of <italic>Bgt</italic> infection and different hormone applications were analyzed by Q-RT-PCR. It was found that expression of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> was up-regulated by the <italic>Bgt</italic> infection in the <italic>Pm6</italic>-containing line IGVI-465 at 1 h after inoculation (hai), but then reduced its expression at 6 hai and maintained at a low level from 24 hai to 72 hai (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g005">Figure 5A</xref>), suggesting that <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> might take part in the active defense response to <italic>Bgt</italic>. Expression of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> was significantly induced by MeJA, but down-regulated by SA and ABA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). Application of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> also regulated the <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> expression, although not dramatically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). The induction of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> transcription by <italic>Bgt</italic> and MeJA treatments in IGVI-465 suggested that this gene played a role in defense response to the infection by <italic>Bgt</italic> or other biotic or abiotic stresses via the JA pathway.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0049718-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049718.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Expression of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> in the leaves of IGVI-465.</title>
            <p>(A) inoculated with <italic>Bgt</italic>. (B) treated with 100 &#xB5;M MeJA, 5 mM SA and 100 &#xB5;M ABA. (C) treated with 7 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Bars with different letters show significant differences at the <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05 level.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0049718.g005"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3f">
        <title><italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic>-mediated resistance to <italic>Bgt</italic> revealed by single-cell transient expression assay</title>
        <p>The localization of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> to the same chromosome region of <italic>Pm6</italic> on the chromosome 2G fragment and its up-regulation by <italic>Bgt</italic> infection hinted the possible correlation of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> with powdery mildew resistance. This assumption was tested using a single-cell transient expression assay. Single-cell transient expression assay is highly efficient in assessing the function of defense-related genes in response to <italic>Bgt</italic> both in wheat and barley, especially for those genes with pre-haustorium resistance. Haustorium is a key structure for nutrient extraction during <italic>Bgt</italic> development. The haustorium index (HI) can be used as a criterion to estimate the compatibility of interaction between the host and <italic>Bgt</italic>. In the single-cell transient assay, the epidermal cells expressing <italic>GUS</italic> gene and challenged by the <italic>Bgt</italic> were selected as the targets. If <italic>Bgt</italic> failed to penetrate into the cell and no haustorium formed, the interaction was considered to be incompatible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g006">Figure 6A-a</xref>); on the other hand, if the haustorium and elongating secondary hyphae were observed, the interaction was considered to be compatible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g006">Figure 6A-b, c, d</xref>). In the susceptible variety Prins, the HI was 64.16% when transformed with the <italic>GUS</italic> gene alone, and 59.53% when co-transformed with <italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic>. In the resistant line IGVI-465, the HI was 37.47% when transformed with the <italic>GUS</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0049718-g006">Figure 6B</xref>). Statistical analysis indicated that there was no significant difference for the HI between the <italic>GUS</italic> alone transformation and the <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic>+<italic>GUS</italic> co-transformation in the susceptible variety Prins, while significant difference was observed for the HI between the <italic>GUS</italic> alone transformation in Prins and IGVI-465. These indicated that transciently over-expression of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> could prevent the formation of haustoria to a certain extent, but it could not improve the resistance level of the susceptible variety to <italic>Bgt</italic>. We deduced that the <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> play a role in the powdery mildew resistance pathway of IGVI-465, but it should not be the best candidate for the <italic>Pm6</italic> gene.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0049718-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049718.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Functional analysis of the <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> by single cell transient expression assay in interaction with <italic>Bgt</italic>.</title>
            <p>A. The compatible and incompatible interactions between the positive transformed cells of the target gene with <italic>Bgt</italic> fungus. a: incompatible interaction in which the formation of haustorium failed. b, c, d: compatible interaction in which the formation of haustorium succeeded. co: conidia; pp: penetration peg; ha: haustorium; hy: hyphae. B. The haustorium index in the <italic>GUS</italic> transformed cells or in the <italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> co-transformed cells. Bars with different letters show significant differences at the <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05 level; differences of the haustorium index were compared between the <italic>GUS</italic> transformed cells and the <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic>+<italic>GUS</italic> co-transformed cells using Prins (susceptible) as the receptors, and between the <italic>GUS</italic> transformed cells using IGVI-465 (resistant) as the receptor.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0049718.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this study, a conserved wheat <italic>RPK</italic> gene associated with the introgressed <italic>Pm6</italic> from <italic>T. timopheevii</italic> was cloned and characterized. Based on the <italic>HvRPK</italic> gene, STS markers were developed and they could be used to identify the alien chromosomes belonging to the homoeologous group-2 in the wheat background. Molecular mapping and bioinformatics analysis revealed orthologous copies of <italic>RPK</italic> in the <italic>Triticeae</italic> and apparent orthologs were present in various plant species. The orthologs of <italic>RPK</italic> were conserved in the collinear regions of rice, <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, <italic>S. bicolor</italic>, and <italic>Z. mays</italic> (The locations of these <italic>RPKs</italic> in their corresponding genomes are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0049718.s001">Form S1</xref>), and the collinear regions of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> orthologs in these grass species have been revealed by whole-genome comparison <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Salse1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-The1">[29]</xref>. This implied that the conserved <italic>RPK</italic> gene may confer important biological roles in plant species.</p>
      <p>The presence of a putative hydrophobic signal peptide, a hydrophobic membrane-spanning segment, and a highly conserved kinase domain supported that TaRPK1-2G is a receptor like protein kinase. Although the kinase domain-based multiple sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis supported the TaRPK1-2G could be classified into the LRR VIII-2 subfamily, the fact that it lacks of the LRR motifs at the extracellular structure implied that TaRPK1-2G may be a new member of the LRR VIII-2 subfamily. Among those genes closely related to TaRPK1-2G, none of their function has been elucidated. <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> was found to be up-regulated by both <italic>Bgt</italic> and MeJA treatments, suggesting that it might be involved in the defense response. However, the exact function of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> and its orthologs in the grass species remains to be further elucidated.</p>
      <p>Alternative splicing of pre-mRNA is a prominent post-transcriptional mechanism, which contributes to increased protein diversity and the regulation of gene function in eukaryotic cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Stamm1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Lareau1">[31]</xref>. It was estimated that about 40&#x2013;60% genes in human, at least 42% in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and 56% in maize undergo alternative splicing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Modrek1">[32]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Li2">[34]</xref>. The impact of the alternative splicing has been frequently reported in human, which sometimes leads to many diseases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Soleymanlou1">[35]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Venables1">[38]</xref>. In plants, alternative splicing was reported to partake in the regulation of flowering, disease resistance, stress tolerance, grain quality and so on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Reddy1">[39]</xref>. For example, the photoperiod gene <italic>Ppd-B1</italic>, which plays a major role in controlling of the heading time, yield, and adaptability in wheat, was alternatively spliced <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Guo1">[40]</xref>. The disease resistance gene <italic>RPS4</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> produces multiple transcripts via alternative splicing, and <italic>RPS4</italic>-mediated resistance requires the combined presence of transcripts encoding both the full-length and the truncated ORFs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Zhang1">[41]</xref>. In wheat, the transcription factor <italic>DREB2</italic> in response to different abiotic stresses can produce three types of transcripts in varying amounts through alternative splicing. Alternative splicing of <italic>RPS4</italic> undergoes dynamic changes specifically during the resistance response <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Zhang2">[42]</xref>, and alternative splicing of <italic>DREB2</italic> was regulated by the ABA-dependent (response to drought and salt stress) and ABA independent pathway (response to low temperature stress) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0049718-Egawa1">[43]</xref>. These findings indicate the importance of alternative splicing in regulation of responses to various stresses. In this study, we found that <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> was also an alternative splicing gene producing two different transcripts, <italic>TaRPK1-2G-1 and TaRPK1-2G-2</italic>, however, only the <italic>TaRPK1-2G-1</italic> encoded the full-length ORF, and it was mainly up-regulated by the MeJA. The relationship between the alternative splicing of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> and JA signaling defense pathway is still unknown, and it will be important to characterize the function of <italic>TaRPK1-2G</italic> and its regulation at the post-transcriptional level.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0049718.s001">
        <label>Form S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>The information of TaRPK1-2G orthologs.</bold> The kinase domain of TaRPK1-2G was used as query sequence for identifying the TaRPK1-2G orthologs by BLASTP searches in the Phytozome proteome database. The best hits in each species were retrieved. This form provided the information about the species of the orthologs, accession number &amp; locus name, location in corresponding genome, description of putative protein, and scores, e-values, identities, and positives of the BLAST results.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0049718.s001.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Fantl1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fantl</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Signalling by receptor tyrosine kinases</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><volume>62</volume>: <fpage>453</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7688944</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Song1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carraway</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eck</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Catalytic specificity of protein-tyrosine kinases is critical for selective signalling</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>373</volume>: <fpage>536</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7845468</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Walker1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Structure and function of the receptor-like protein kinases of higher plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source><volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1599</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7858206</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Shiu1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shiu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bleecker</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Receptor-like kinases from Arabidopsis form a monophyletic gene family related to animal receptor kinases</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>98</volume>: <fpage>10763</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11526204</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Shiu2">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shiu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karlowski</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tzeng</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Comparative analysis of the receptor-like kinase family in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1220</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15105442</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Martin1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brommonschenkel</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chunwongse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frary</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ganal</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Map-based cloning of a protein kinase gene conferring disease resistance in tomato</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>262</volume>: <fpage>1432</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7902614</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Walker2">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Receptor-like protein kinase genes of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>451</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8220453</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Torii1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Torii</surname><given-names>KU</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Receptor-like kinases in plant development</article-title>. <source>Advances in Botanical Research</source><volume>32</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>267</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Song2">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pi</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>A receptor kinase-like protein encoded by the rice disease resistance gene, <italic>Xa21</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>270</volume>: <fpage>1804</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8525370</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Feuillet1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Feuillet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reuzeau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kjellbom</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization of a new type of receptor-like kinase (wlrk) gene family in wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source><volume>37</volume>: <fpage>943</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>953</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9700067</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Feuillet2">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Feuillet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schachermayr</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Molecular cloning of a new receptor-like kinase gene encoded at the <italic>Lr10</italic> disease resistance locus of wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9025301</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Feuillet3">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Feuillet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Penger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gellner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mast</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Molecular evolution of receptor-like kinase genes in hexaploid wheat. Independent evolution of orthologs after polyploidization and mechanisms of local rearrangements at paralogous loci</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>125</volume>: <fpage>1304</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11244111</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Zhou1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular analysis of three new receptor-like kinase genes from hexaploid wheat and evidence for their participation in the wheat hypersensitive response to stripe rust fungus infection</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>52</volume>: <fpage>420</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17764502</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Cao1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Serine/threonine kinase gene <italic>Stpk-V</italic>, a key member of powdery mildew resistance gene <italic>Pm21</italic>, confers powdery mildew resistance in wheat</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>108</volume>: <fpage>7727</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21508323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Tao1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Genetic mapping of the powdery mildew resistance gene <italic>Pm6</italic> in wheat by RFLP analysis</article-title>. <source>TAG Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>100</volume>: <fpage>564</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>568</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Park1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dixit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennetzen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Further evidence of microcolinearity between barley and rice genomes at two orthologous regions</article-title>. <source>Mol Cells</source><volume>17</volume>: <fpage>492</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15232225</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Ji1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>STS markers for powdery mildew resistance gene <italic>Pm6</italic> in wheat</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>163</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>165</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Li1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>SSRHunter: development of a local searching software for SSR sites</article-title>. <source>Yi Chuan</source><volume>27</volume>: <fpage>808</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16257914</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Bassam1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bassam</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caetano-Anolles</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gresshoff</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Fast and sensitive silver staining of DNA in polyacrylamide gels</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source><volume>196</volume>: <fpage>80</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1716076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Dong1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>New insights into the organization, recombination, expression and functional mechanism of low molecular weight glutenin subunit genes in bread wheat</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e13548</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20975830</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Krogh1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Predicting transmembrane protein topology with a hidden Markov model: application to complete genomes</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>305</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152613</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Letunic1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Letunic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Copley</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ciccarelli</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doerks</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>SMART 4.0: towards genomic data integration</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>32</volume>: <fpage>D142</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681379</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Thompson1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Multiple sequence alignment using ClustalW and ClustalX</article-title>. <source>Curr Protoc Bioinformatics Chapter</source><volume>2</volume>: <fpage>Unit 2 3</fpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Kumar1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jakobsen</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>MEGA2: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis software</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1244</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751241</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Livak1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2<sup>-&#x25B5;&#x25B5;CT</sup> Method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Shirasu1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shirasu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piffanelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schulze-Lefert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Cell-autonomous complementation ofmloresistance using a biolistic transient expression system</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>17</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>299</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Qin1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>You</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Collinearity-based marker mining for the fine mapping of Pm6, a powdery mildew resistance gene in wheat</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>123</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21468676</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Salse1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Salse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bolot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Throude</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jouffe</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piegu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterization of shared duplications between rice and wheat provide new insight into grass genome evolution</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18178768</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-The1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>The International Brachypodium Initiative</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genome sequencing and analysis of the model grass <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>463</volume>: <fpage>763</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20148030</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Stamm1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stamm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ben-Ari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rafalska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Function of alternative splicing</article-title>. <source>Gene</source><volume>344</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15656968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Lareau1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lareau</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bhatnagar</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The evolving roles of alternative splicing</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>273</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15193306</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Modrek1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Modrek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A genomic view of alternative splicing</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source><volume>30</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11753382</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Filichkin1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Filichkin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Priest</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Givan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide mapping of alternative splicing in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19858364</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Li2">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ponnala</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gandotra</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Si</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The developmental dynamics of the maize leaf transcriptome</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source><volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1060</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1067</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21037569</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Soleymanlou1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Soleymanlou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Todros</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ietta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A novel Mtd splice isoform is responsible for trophoblast cell death in pre-eclampsia</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source><volume>12</volume>: <fpage>441</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15775999</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Tan1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fook-Chong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Differential expression of splice variant and wild-type parkin in sporadic Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source>Neurogenetics</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>179</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16086186</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Agrawal1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Differential expression of novel naturally occurring splice variants of <italic>PTEN</italic> and their functional consequences in Cowden syndrome and sporadic breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source><volume>15</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16436456</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Venables1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Venables</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Unbalanced alternative splicing and its significance in cancer</article-title>. <source>Bioessays</source><volume>28</volume>: <fpage>378</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16547952</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Reddy1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Alternative splicing of pre-messenger RNAs in plants in the genomic era</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source><volume>58</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17222076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Guo1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Alternative splicing of photoperiod response gene <italic>Ppd-B1</italic> in wheat</article-title>. <source>Acta Agronomica Sinica</source><volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1764</fpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Zhang1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gassmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title><italic>RPS4</italic>-mediated disease resistance requires the combined presence of <italic>RPS4</italic> transcripts with full-length and truncated open reading frames</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2333</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14523247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Zhang2">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gassmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Alternative splicing and mRNA levels of the disease resistance gene <italic>RPS4</italic> are induced during defense responses</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>145</volume>: <fpage>1577</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17951452</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0049718-Egawa1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Egawa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ishibashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Differential regulation of transcript accumulation and alternative splicing of a <italic>DREB2</italic> homolog under abiotic stress conditions in common wheat</article-title>. <source>Genes Genet Syst</source><volume>81</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16755132</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
