<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jexbot</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3617820</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ert004</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Paper</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Enhanced stability of thylakoid membrane proteins and antioxidant competence contribute to drought stress resistance in the <italic>tasg1</italic> wheat stay-green mutant</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name>
            <surname>Tian</surname>
            <given-names>Fengxia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name>
            <surname>Gong</surname>
            <given-names>Jiangfeng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Jin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Meng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Guokun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Aixiu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Wei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="AF0001"><sup>1</sup><institution>State Key Laboratory of Crop Biology, College of Life Sciences, Shandong Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Tai&#x2019;an, Shandong, 271018</addr-line>, <country>PR China</country></aff>
        <aff id="AF0002"><sup>2</sup><institution>State Key Laboratory of Tree Genetics and Breeding, Research Institute of Forestry, Chinese Academy of Forestry</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing, 100091</addr-line>, <country>PR China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1"><sup>*</sup>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>wangw@sdau.edu.cn</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>64</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>1509</fpage>
      <lpage>1520</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(2) [2013].</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>A wheat stay-green mutant, <italic>tasg1</italic>, was previously generated via mutation breeding of HS2, a common wheat cultivar (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.). Compared with wild-type (WT) plants, <italic>tasg1</italic> exhibited delayed senescence indicated by the slower degradation of chlorophyll. In this study, the stability of proteins in thylakoid membranes was evaluated in <italic>tasg1</italic> under drought stress compared with WT plants in the field as well as in seedlings in the laboratory. Drought stress was imposed by controlling irrigation and sheltering the plants from rain in the field, and by polyethylene glycol (PEG)-6000 in the laboratory. The results indicated that <italic>tasg1</italic> plants could maintain higher Hill activity, actual efficiency (&#x3A6;<sub>PSII</sub>), maximal photochemical efficiency of PSII (<italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>), and Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase and Mg<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase activities than the WT plants under drought stress. Furthermore, the abundance of some polypeptides in thylakoid membranes of <italic>tasg1</italic> was greater than that in the WT under drought stress. Expression levels of <italic>TaLhcb4</italic> and <italic>TaLhcb6</italic> were higher in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT. Under drought stress, the accumulation of superoxide radical (O<sub>2</sub>&#xB7;<sup>&#x2013;</sup>) and hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) was lower in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT not only at the senescence stage but also at the seedling stages. These results suggest greater functional stability of thylakoid membrane proteins in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT, and the higher antioxidant competence of <italic>tasg1</italic> may play an important role in the enhanced drought tolerance of <italic>tasg1</italic>.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Key words:</title>
        <kwd>Antioxidant competence</kwd>
        <kwd>drought stress</kwd>
        <kwd>stability</kwd>
        <kwd>stay-green mutant</kwd>
        <kwd>thylakoid membrane proteins</kwd>
        <kwd>wheat</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Drought stress is a serious environmental factor that can severely limit the growth, performance, and productivity of wheat, one of the most important food crops worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0006">Chaves and Oliveira, 2004</xref>). The photosynthetic activity of the chloroplast is one of the most sensitive physiological processes to drought stress, which damages the thylakoid membrane, disturbs its functions, and ultimately decreases photosynthesis and crop yield (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0034">Shah and Paulsen, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0017">Huseynova <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0046">Zhao <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). Thus, preservation of the photosynthetic apparatus is an important strategy for enhancing photosynthetic activity under drought stress.</p>
      <p content-type="indent">Leaf senescence in plants is an internally programmed degeneration process, during which the photosynthetic apparatus is gradually disorganized, leading to death. The most prominent visible change in leaf senescence is associated with chlorophyll degradation and a progressive decline in photosynthetic capability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0020">Matile <italic>et al</italic>., 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0021">1999</xref>). Stay-green or non-yellowing mutations in various plant species have been reported to maintain leaf greenness longer than their wild-type (WT) counterpart during senescence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0039">Thomas and Smart, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0035">Spano <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0014">H&#xF6;rtensteiner, 2009</xref>). Some &#x2018;functional stay-green&#x2019; mutants can photosynthesize for longer and may therefore be expected to give a higher yield (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0038">Thomas and Howarth, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0043">Yoo <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0047">Zheng <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). It has been estimated that a delay in the onset of senescence in <italic>Lolium temulentum</italic> by just 2 d increases the amount of carbon fixed by the plant by 11% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0038">Thomas and Howarth, 2000</xref>). In contrast, so-called &#x2018;non-functional stay-green&#x2019; mutants, for example type C, remain green as a result of lesions in chlorophyll catabolism but lack photosynthetic competence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0038">Thomas and Howarth, 2000</xref>).</p>
      <p content-type="indent">With type C mutants, the pathways involved in chlorophyll degradation have been well established in recent years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0031">Sato <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0033">Schelbert <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). Two types of chlorophyll are found in higher plants, Chl <italic>a</italic> and Chl <italic>b</italic>. Chl <italic>a</italic> is a component of all chlorophyll&#x2013;protein complexes, while Chl <italic>b</italic> is contained only in PSI-associated light-harvesting complex I (LHCI) and PSII-associated LHCII. LHCI and LHCII are localized in thylakoid membranes and function in energy harvest and transfer. LHCII is mainly localized in grana, the stacking region of the thylakoid membranes, and is thought to play an important role in the formation and maintenance of grana stacks due to intermolecular forces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001">Allen and Forsberg, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0036">Standfuss <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>). The apoproteins of LHCI and LHCII are encoded by the <italic>Lhca</italic> and <italic>Lhcb</italic> gene families, respectively. <italic>Lhca1&#x2013;Lhca4</italic> genes encode the polypeptides of LHCI associated with PSI. <italic>Lhcb1</italic>, <italic>Lhcb2</italic>, and <italic>Lhcb3</italic> genes encode the polypeptides of trimeric LHCII. Lhcb4, Lhcb5, and Lhcb6 proteins (often called CP29, CP26, and CP24, respectively) are suggested to be monomeric proteins that are present as one copy per PSII unit. The expression of <italic>Lhca</italic> and <italic>Lhcb</italic> and the stability of LHCI and LHCII are of great importance for keeping the photosynthetic activity at a high level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0036">Standfuss <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0031">Sato <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>).</p>
      <p content-type="indent">In a previous study, a functional stay-green wheat mutant <italic>tasg1</italic> with improved drought tolerance was generated. The net photosynthetic rate (<italic>P</italic><sub>n</sub>) of <italic>tasg1</italic> was consistently higher than that of the WT during water senescence induced by drought stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0040">Tian <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). In the present experiments, the stability and activity of proteins in thylakoid membranes involved in photosynthesis, as well as the expression of select LHC genes, were detected. The accumulated levels of superoxide radical (O<sub>2</sub>&#xB7;<sup>&#x2013;</sup>) and hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) were found to be lower in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT under drought stress. These data contribute to the better understanding of stay-green mechanisms for the improvement of drought resistance in wheat cultivars.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Plant materials</title>
        <p>The wheat stay-green mutant, <italic>tasg1</italic>, was previously generated via mutation breeding by applying the ethyl methane sulphonate (EMS) mutagen to HS2, a common wheat cultivar (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.), as the WT. All the experiments were conducted in two sets: one, in the field and the other in the laboratory.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4">
        <title>Field experiments</title>
        <p>Wheat plants were grown in the fields of Shandong Agricultural University, China, during the growing seasons October&#x2013;June 2011. Six 4 m<sup>2</sup> interspersed plots were established via random block design in the field, with three replicate plots for each genotype. Wheat seeds were hand-sown in eight lines, with rows spaced 25cm apart. Seeds were planted at ~1&#x2013;2cm depth and 5cm spacing. Conventional agricultural management was maintained during growth and development of the seedlings.</p>
        <p content-type="indent">Drought stress treatment was imposed by controlling irrigation and sheltering the plants from rain, with conventional normal water conditions for controls.</p>
        <p content-type="indent">Physiological parameters were measured using intact flag leaves of both <italic>tasg1</italic> and WT plants on 20 May 2011 (~14 d after flowering) and on 4 June 2011 (~6 d before harvest), ~10 d (the early stage of drought stress) and 25 d (the later stage of drought stress) after the drought stress was imposed, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s5">
        <title>Laboratory experiments</title>
        <p>For the hydroponic seedlings, seeds of both the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> were germinated on filter paper moistened with water for 24h at 25&#xB1;1 &#xB0;C after being sterilized with 0.2% sodium hypochlorite. The seeds were then placed in a well-ordered fashion on a nylon gauze sheet at the appropriate density and cultured in trays (25 cm&#xD7;18 cm&#xD7;5cm) containing Hoagland solution. These trays were placed in a growth chamber at 25&#xB1;1 &#xB0;C under a 12h light (300 &#xB5;mol m<sup>&#x2013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2013;1</sup>)&#x2013;dark cycle and a relative humidity of 70%. After complete unfolding, second leaves were harvested for senescence-inducing treatments as described below. Osmotic stress was induced using 20% polyethylene glycol (PEG)-6000 solution (&#x2013;1.45MPa) with water as a control. The solution was changed every 12h.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s6">
        <title>Determining the water content of soil</title>
        <p>Water conditions were assessed by measuring the water content of the soil at 10 d and 25 d after drought stress treatments were imposed. A statistically significant difference in soil water content between drought treatment plots and normal water control plots was achieved (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Soil water content (%) in the field under both drought stress (DS) and normal water (CK) conditions. Values are mean &#xB1;SE (<italic>n</italic>=3). The letters next to the values demonstrate significant difference at 0.05 thresholds. </p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="vsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Date</th>
                <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">0&#x2013;20cm depth</th>
                <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">20&#x2013;40cm depth</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DS</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DS</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 May 2011</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.88&#xB1;0.20 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32&#xB1;0.20 a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.13&#xB1;0.03 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.58&#xB1;0.14 a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 June 2011</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.78&#xB1;0.22 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.43&#xB1;0.29 a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.08&#xB1;0.12 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.55&#xB1;0.19 a</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s7">
        <title>Determining the Hill activity of the chloroplast</title>
        <p>Chloroplast isolation and Hill activity assays were determined following the procedure of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0046">Zhao <italic>et al</italic>. (2007)</xref>, which was modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0042">Ye and Qian (1985</xref>). The chlorophyll content of the chloroplast suspension was measured according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0003">Arnon (1949</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s8">
        <title>Chlorophyll a fluorescence analysis</title>
        <p>The actual PSII efficiency under irradiance (&#x3A6;<sub>PSII</sub>) and the maximal photochemical efficiency of PSII (<italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>) were measured with a portable pulse-modulated fluorometer FMS-2 (Hansatech Instruments Ltd, King&#x2019;s Lynn, UK). For quenching analyses, the leaves were illuminated with actinic light intensities of 800 &#xB5;mol m<sup>&#x2013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> for 16min (which was found to be sufficient for the induction of steady-state light conditions) and subsequently kept for a further 10min in the dark.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s9">
        <title>Determinations of thylakoid membrane Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase and Mg<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase activities</title>
        <p>Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase activity and Mg<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase activity were determined following the procedure of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0041">Wang <italic>et al</italic>. (2010)</xref>, which was modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0015">Huang (1985</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s10">
        <title>Detection of thylakoid polypeptides</title>
        <p>Thylakoid membranes were prepared according to the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0045">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>. (1999)</xref>. Fresh leaves (1g) were homogenized in an ice-cold 5ml solution of HMSN buffer containing 0.4M sucrose, 0.01M NaCl, 5mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 0.01M HEPES (pH 7.8) in a tissue homogenizer. The homogenate was filtered through four layers of gauze and centrifuged at 5000 <italic>g</italic> at 4 &#xB0;C for 10min. The supernatants and most of the loose pellets were discarded. The remaining chloroplast deposit was suspended in 5ml of HMSN buffer and centrifuged at 5000 <italic>g</italic> at 4 &#xB0;C for 10min. The supernatants and most of the loose pellets were discarded. The remaining chloroplast deposit suspended in 1ml of HMSN buffer was used to examine the thylakoid polypeptides.</p>
        <p content-type="indent">Chlorophyll contents in thylakoid suspension were estimated using 80% acetone following the equation of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0019">Lichtenthaler (1987</xref>).</p>
        <p content-type="indent">Thylakoid polypeptides were separated by urea and SDS&#x2013;PAGE according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0025">Parida <italic>et al</italic>. (2003)</xref> with minor modification to the 15% separating gel and were detected after staining and de-staining as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0025">Parida <italic>et al</italic>. (2003)</xref>. In total, 20 &#xB5;g of chlorophyll was loaded per lane.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s11">
        <title>Semi-quantitative RT&#x2013;PCR of pigment-binding protein-related gene expression</title>
        <p>Six genes related to pigment-binding proteins were selected to examine the different expression in <italic>tasg1</italic> and the WT. First, total RNA from wheat leaves, which were grown under normal conditions and drought stress treatments for 0, 12, 24, 36, and 48h, was isolated according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s protocol (Trizol, Takara, China), and subsequently used for reverse transcription&#x2013;polymerase chain reaction (RT&#x2013;PCR). Then, total RNA was treated with DNase I (RNase-free; Promega USA) to remove genomic DNA, and reverse transcription was performed using the primer oligo(dT)<sub>18</sub> and Moloney murine leukaemia virus (M-MLV) reverse transcriptase (Promega) at 42 &#xB0;C for 60min. Subsequently, a PCR with equal aliquots of cDNA samples was performed using special primers. The specific primers for genes encoding LHCI (<italic>TaLhca1</italic>, <italic>TaLhca2</italic>, and <italic>TaLhca3</italic>) and LHCII (<italic>TaLhcb1</italic>, <italic>TaLhcb4</italic>, and <italic>TaLhcb6</italic>) subunits were designed based on published wheat expressed sequence tags (ESTs): <italic>TaLhca1</italic>, F (5&#x2019;-CAACCTGCCGACCATCCTG-3&#x2019;) and R (5&#x2019;-CAGCCGCCCGTTCTTGAT-3&#x2019;); <italic>TaLhca2</italic>, F (5&#x2019;-CCCC AACCGCAAGAACC-3&#x2019;) and R (5&#x2019;-CCGACGAAGGCGAG CAT-3&#x2019;); <italic>TaLhca3</italic>, F (5&#x2019;-CCTCACCAGCCTCAAGTTCC-3&#x2019;) and R (5&#x2019;-CGCACGCTCACGTTTCC-3&#x2019;); <italic>TaLhcb1</italic>, F (5&#x2019;-GG AGAACACACAATACACC-3&#x2019;) and R (5&#x2019;-CCCATTATGTGT GCAGTTC-3&#x2019;); <italic>TaLhcb4</italic>: F (5&#x2019;-AAAGGCCGAGGAGGAC AA-3&#x2019;) and R (5&#x2019;-CCACCGACCACTTAAGAGG-3&#x2019;); and <italic>TaLhcb6</italic>, F (5&#x2019;-TCAGCGACCTCACCGTCA-3&#x2019;) and R (5&#x2019;-CC CCAAAGAAGTCACGGACA-3&#x2019;).</p>
        <p content-type="indent">Amplification of the <italic>T. aestivum tubulin</italic> gene (using primers <italic>TubulinF</italic>, 5&#x2019;-ACCGCCAGCTCTTCCACCCT-3&#x2019; and <italic>TubulinR</italic>, 5&#x2019;-TCACTGGGGCATAGGAGGAA-3&#x2019;) exhibiting constitutive expression was used as a positive control, from which a linear relationship between the amount of RNA used for amplification and the amount of cDNA fragment amplified, as well as the quality of both extracted RNA and RT&#x2013;PCRs were determined.</p>
        <p content-type="indent">The amplification conditions were as follows: 30 s at 94 &#xB0;C, 30 s at 56 &#xB0;C, and 30 s at 72 &#xB0;C. The cycle was repeated 28 times. The RT&#x2013;PCR products were separated on a 1.0% (m/v) agarose gel. The experiments were independently repeated three times under identical conditions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s12">
        <title>Detection of pigment-binding proteins by immunoblotting</title>
        <p>Total protein was extracted from wheat leaves. Protein content was determined by the dye binding assay according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0005">Bradford (1976</xref>). Proteins were separated by SDS&#x2013;PAGE on a 12% gel and transferred to a polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membrane (Millipore, Saint-Quentin, France). Proteins were routinely detected with the Lhca2, Lhcb4, and Lhab6 antibody (Sigma), and with the Rubisco large subunit as control.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s13">
        <title>Detection of protein carbonylation by immunoblotting</title>
        <p>Total protein was extracted from wheat leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">Dalle-Donna <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0029">Qiu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Proteins were separated by SDS&#x2013;PAGE following the procedures of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0044">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>. (2012)</xref>, which were modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">Dalle-Donna <italic>et al</italic>. (2002)</xref>. Protein carbonylation was routinely detected with the anti-dinitrophenyl (DNP) antibody (Sigma).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s14">
        <title>Staining detection of O<sub>2</sub>&#xB7;<sup>&#x2013;</sup> accumulation</title>
        <p>O<sub>2</sub>&#xB7;<sup>&#x2013;</sup> accumulation was visualized with nitroblue tetrazolium (NBT). Detached leaves were infiltrated with 6mM NBT. Chlorophyll was removed from the leaves prior to imaging by infiltrating them with lacto-glycerol-ethanol (1:1:4, v/v/v) and boiling in water for 5min. The location of formazan deposits was visualized by subtracting background (non-formazan) pixels from the leaf image.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s15">
        <title>H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> staining with diaminobenzidine</title>
        <p>Detached leaves were infiltrated with 6&#x2013;8ml of diaminobenzidine (DAB) solution (1mg ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> DAB, Sigma pH 3.8) with NaOH according to the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0011">Giacomelli <italic>et al</italic>. (2007)</xref> with slight modification. Leaves were then left in the solution overnight in the dark. The following day, the solution containing the leaves was brought to the boil for a few minutes, and then incubated at room temperature for 3h under mild agitation. The leaves were then cleared with chlorhydrate (10ml of water added to 25g of chlorhydrate).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s16">
        <title>Relative electric conductivity</title>
        <p>Six leaf discs (0.8cm in diameter) were put into 10ml of distilled water and a vacuum was applied for 30min, and then surged for 3h to measure the initial electric conductance (S1) (25 &#xB0;C). A test tube was filled with leaf discs and distilled water, the the mixture was cooked (100 &#xB0;C) for 30min and then reduced to room temperature (25 &#xB0;C) to determine the final electric conductance (S2). The relative electric conductivity (REC) was evaluated as: REC=S1&#xD7;100/S2.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s17">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>The statistical significance of differences in measured parameters was tested by using the procedures of DPS (Zhejiang University, China). All pairwise comparisons were analysed using Duncan&#x2019;s test. Differences between the means among wheat lines or treatments were compared using Duncan&#x2019;s multiple range tests at 0.05 probability levels.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s18">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s19">
        <title>Stay-green phenotype of tasg1 in the field</title>
        <p>Under normal field conditions, no significant difference between <italic>tasg1</italic> and the WT was observed in plant development or phenotype before the flag leaves appeared. However, flag leaves of the WT generally emerged on 28 April, while those of <italic>tasg1</italic> did not appear until 1 d or 2 d later. The flowering date of <italic>tasg1</italic> was also delayed by 1 d or 2 d compared with the WT. The stay-green phenotype of <italic>tasg1</italic> was expressed at the beginning of anthesis and was especially apparent with late natural senescence. Drought stress accelerated the plant senescence in both wheat varieties, but it was delayed in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">C</xref>). Meanwhile, the areas of the flag leaves of <italic>tasg1</italic> were 28% and 23% larger than those of WT leaves under normal water and drought stress conditions, respectively, at the grain filling stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>).</p>
        <fig fig-type="fig" id="F1" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Naturally senescent WT (left) and <italic>tasg1</italic> (right) plants were maintained with normal water (A) or induced with drought stress (B) at the late filling stage in the field. (C) Naturally senescent flag leaves of WT (right) and <italic>tasg1</italic> (left) plants at the late filling stage in the field. The images in A&#x2013;C were obtained on 2 June 2011. (D) Flag leaves of WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> plants under normal water and drought stress conditions at the filling stage in the field. Photos in D were taken on 25 May 2011.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert004_f0001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s20">
        <title>Differential effects of drought stress on activity and abundance of the photosynthesis protein complexes in the thylakoid membrane of tasg1 and WT plants</title>
        <p>In a previous study, photosynthetic activity was found to be higher in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT, and the duration of the high photosynthesis period was longer in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT under drought conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0040">Tian <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). In the current study, the protein activity and components involved in photosynthesis were detected in the thylakoid membrane of the flag leaves. The results are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> and are described below.</p>
        <fig fig-type="fig" id="F2" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Hill activity of chloroplasts in flag leaves of WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> plants in the early and later stages of drought stress in the field. Each bar is the mean &#xB1;SD of four replications. Bars with the same letter were not significantly different at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert004_f0002"/>
        </fig>
        <sec id="s21">
          <title>Hill reaction activity</title>
          <p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>, under normal water conditions, there was no obvious difference in the Hill reaction activity between the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> at 10 d under drought. The Hill reaction activity was reduced by 31.4% and 47.9% in leaves of <italic>tasg1</italic> and WT plants, respectively, under normal water conditions due to senescence. Meanwhile, the Hill reaction activity was reduced by 44.1% and 51.1% in leaves of <italic>tasg1</italic> and WT plants, respectively, at 25 d under drought. These results suggest that the Hill reaction activity was less affected by drought stress in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s22">
          <title>PSII photochemistry</title>
          <p>The actual PSII efficiency under irradiance (&#x3A6;<sub>PSII</sub>) and the maximal photochemical efficiency of PSII (<italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>) are commonly used as sensitive indicators of plant photosynthetic performance responding to stress conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0022">Maxwell and Johnson, 2000</xref>), and both of these parameters represent a measure of the functional status of PSII. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">B</xref>, no significant difference in &#x3A6;<sub>PSII</sub> and <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> of PSII photochemistry was observed between <italic>tasg1</italic> and the WT in the early stage of drought stress. In the later stage of drought stress, <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> was decreased, but not significantly, while &#x3A6;<sub>PSII</sub> decreased significantly. However, &#x3A6;<sub>PSII</sub> in leaves of <italic>tasg1</italic> was 52.1% and 47.9% higher than in the WT under normal and drought stress conditions, respectively. These findings suggest that the PSII complex in <italic>tasg1</italic> could better withstand drought stress than the WT.</p>
          <fig fig-type="fig" id="F3" position="float">
            <label>Fig. 3.</label>
            <caption>
              <p><italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> (A), &#x3A6;<sub>PSII</sub> (B), and the activities of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase (C) and Mg<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase (D) in the thylakoid membrane in WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> flag leaves in the early and later stages of drought stress. Each bar is the mean &#xB1;SD of four replications. Bars with the same letter were not significantly different at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert004_f0003"/>
          </fig>
          <p content-type="indent">As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">D</xref>, under normal water conditions and at 10 d under drought, differences in the activities of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase and Mg<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase between <italic>tasg1</italic> and the WT were not significant, but they were significantly higher in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT at 25 d under drought. Drought stress decreased the activities of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase and Mg<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase in both <italic>tasg1</italic> and WT plants, but both activities were consistently higher in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT during drought stress, with significant differences observed at 25 d under drought. These results suggest greater stability of ATPases in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT under drought stress.</p>
          <p content-type="indent">From the results shown above (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">3</xref>), it can be deduced that the activity of thylakoid membrane proteins, including PSII and ATPase, were better maintained in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT under drought stress.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s23">
          <title>Polypeptide abundance in thylakoid membrane</title>
          <p>Next, the changes in protein abundance in the thylakoid membrane under drought stress were investigated. In flag leaves under field conditions, the level of the 28kDa polypeptide in <italic>tasg1</italic> was higher than that in the WT under both normal and drought stress conditions on both days of the drought, 10 d and 25 d (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). The polypeptides were similarly detected in WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> wheat seedlings at the second-leaf stage in the laboratory, and the three observed polypeptides of ~28, 38, and 50kDa in <italic>tasg1</italic> were consistently higher than those in the WT after treatment with 20% PEG-6000 solution with water as control for 24h and 48h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>).</p>
          <fig fig-type="fig" id="F4" position="float">
            <label>Fig. 4.</label>
            <caption>
              <p>Effects of drought stress on thylakoid polypeptides in WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> flag leaves in the field (A) and in the leaves of WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> seedlings (B). M represents the molecular mass marker. Lanes to the left of M represent the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> under normal conditions (CK) and in the early stage under drought stress (DS) by treatment with 20% PEG-6000 solution for 24h. Lanes to the right of M represent the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> under normal conditions and in the later stage under drought stress by treatment with 20% PEG-6000 solution for 48h. The graphs on the right show the relative density of signals in the corresponding samples of the SDS&#x2013;PAGE in the left panels. Quantitative analysis was performed using the Tanon GIS system (Tanon, Shanghai China).</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert004_f0004"/>
          </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s24">
          <title>Transcriptional levels of genes involved in LHCI and LHCII</title>
          <p>Six genes encoding pigment-binding proteins were selected to determine the different transcriptional responses to drought stress between <italic>tasg1</italic> and the WT. RNA was obtained from wheat seedlings in which PEG-6000 was used to simulate water stress. As revealed by semi-quantitative RT&#x2013;PCR, the expression of genes encoding pigment-binding proteins showed distinct responses to drought stress, and the expression patterns varied for different genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
          <fig fig-type="fig" id="F5" position="float">
            <label>Fig. 5.</label>
            <caption>
              <p>Expression of LHCI and LHCII genes in response to drought stress in wheat. Total RNA from leaves of wheat grown under normal and drought stress conditions for 0, 12, 24, 36, and 48h was isolated and reverse transcribed. RT&#x2013;PCR products amplified using specific primers were separated on a 1.0% (m/v) agarose gel. The constitutively expressed <italic>T. aestivum tubulin</italic> gene was amplified as a positive control. Three independent experiments were performed under identical conditions. The right panel shows the corresponding relative densities of the RT&#x2013;PCR signals in the left panel. Quantitative analysis was performed using the Tanon GIS system.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert004_f0005"/>
          </fig>
          <p content-type="indent">Expression levels of genes involved in LHCI, namely <italic>TaLhca1</italic>, <italic>TaLhca2</italic>, and <italic>TaLhca3</italic>, were down-regulated gradually during drought stress in both the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). The mRNA levels of all three <italic>TaLhca</italic> genes tested were reduced to the minimum at 48h after water stress treatment. For example, <italic>TaLhca3</italic> was the most sensitive gene to drought stress, and it was significantly repressed by 48h of drought stress in both the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic>. Meanwhile, <italic>TaLhca2</italic>, at the last tested time point of 48h, still remained at a higher level in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT.</p>
          <p content-type="indent">Expression levels of genes involved in LHCII, namely <italic>TaLhcb1</italic>, <italic>TaLhcb4</italic>, and <italic>TaLhcb6</italic>, were not consistent with those involved in LHCI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). The expression levels of <italic>TaLhcb4</italic> and <italic>TaLhcb6</italic> were higher in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT, especially at the last tested time point (48h). The degradation of <italic>TaLhcb4</italic> and <italic>TaLhcb6</italic> was inhibited in <italic>tasg1</italic>, decreasing slowly as the period of drought stress was extended. Even at the last tested time point (48h), the transcript levels of <italic>TaLhcb4</italic> and <italic>TaLhcb6</italic> did not decrease significantly and still remained high. The expression level of <italic>TaLhcb4</italic> was significantly different between the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> in the early stage during drought stress, while that of <italic>TaLhcb6</italic> was largely different between the two plant types in the later stage during drought stress. However, the expression levels of <italic>TaLhcb1</italic> were similar between the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> over the course of drought stress treatment.</p>
          <p content-type="indent">To analyse pigment-binding proteins further, the abundance of TaLhca2, TaLhcb4, and TaLhcb6 was detect by western blotting with the Rubisco large subunit as a control. The expression levels of these three genes were different to a certain extent between the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic>, especially at the last tested time point (48h) according to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>. Immunoblot analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>) revealed that the accumulation of TaLhca2, TaLhcb4, and TaLhcb6 was decreased in both the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> at 48h after treatment under drought stress. There was no significant difference in accumulation of TaLhca2 between the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic>. However, the contents of TaLhcb4 and TaLhcb6 were higher in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT under drought stress. The protein accumulation of TaLhcb6 was 2.15-fold higher in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT at 48h after treatmenet under drought stress, while the mRNA accumulation of <italic>TaLhcb6</italic> was 1.97-fold higher in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). These observations suggest that TaLhcb4 and TaLhcb6 could be maintained at a higher level in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT under drought stress.</p>
          <fig fig-type="fig" id="F6" position="float">
            <label>Fig. 6.</label>
            <caption>
              <p>Immunoblot analysis of degradation of photosynthesis-related proteins (Lhca2, Lhcb4, and Lhcb6) during induced drought stress in the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> by 20% PEG for 0, 24, and 48h. Rubisco L, the Rubisco large subunit. The lower panel shows the corresponding relative densities of the western blotting signals in the upper panel. The amounts of band signal by densitometry and normalized to that of the loading control (Rubisco L). Quantitative analysis was performed using the Tanon GIS system.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert004_f0006"/>
          </fig>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s25">
        <title>Effects of drought stress on antioxidant activity</title>
        <p>To study the mechanisms underlying differences in senescence and drought resistance, the antioxidant activities in <italic>tasg1</italic> and the WT were compared, and the results are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>. First, protein carbonylation was detected by immunoblotting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). Drought stress increased protein carbonylation in the leaves of <italic>tasg1</italic> and the WT. However, the amount of protein carbonylation products accumulated in the WT was greater than that in <italic>tasg1</italic> under both normal and drought stress conditions. Meanwhile, in the control experiment using PVDF membranes treated with HCl only without 2, 4-dinitrophenylhydrazine (DNPH), no protein carbonylation was found (data not shown).</p>
        <fig fig-type="fig" id="F7" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 7.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Protein carbonylation levels were detected with anti-DNP antibodies in WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> flag leaves in the early and later stages of drought stress in the field. Protein gel blot analysis of protein carbonylation following derivatization of protein carbonyls with DNPH in HCl.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert004_f0007"/>
        </fig>
        <fig fig-type="fig" id="F8" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 8.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Changes in O<sub>2</sub>&#xB7;<sup>&#x2013;</sup> (A, B) and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (C, D) accumulation in WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> flag leaves. The top row shows samples from plants after drought stress at the earlier stage. The bottom row shows samples from plants after drought stress at the later stage. Changes in O<sub>2</sub>&#xB7;<sup>&#x2013;</sup> (E, F, G) and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (H, I, J) accumulation in WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> leaves of third-leaf stage seedlings. Drought stress was induced using 20% PEG-6000 solution with water as a control for 0, 24, and 48h. Leaves were detached after drought treatment and vacuum infiltrated with NBT or DAB solution. The presence of the purple formazan precipitate indicates the location and content of O<sub>2</sub>&#xB7;<sup>&#x2013;</sup> accumulation. The brown polymerization product is the result of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert004_f0008"/>
        </fig>
        <fig fig-type="fig" id="F9" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 9.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Effects of water stress on relative electrical conductivity in <italic>tasg1</italic> and the WT. The results are means &#xB1;SD of five independent measurements on each of five plants per experiment.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert004_f0009"/>
        </fig>
        <p content-type="indent">O<sub>2</sub>&#xB7;<sup>&#x2013;</sup> accumulation was detected by monitoring the precipitation of purple formazan when reacting NBT with O<sub>2</sub>&#xB7;<sup>&#x2013;</sup>. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A</xref>, under normal conditions and in the early stage of drought stress, little NBT precipitation was detected in <italic>tasg1</italic>, but obvious NBT staining was observed in the WT. In the later stage of drought stress (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8B</xref>), NBT precipitation was significantly increased in both the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic>, but, compared with the WT, the accumulation of O<sub>2</sub>&#xB7;<sup>&#x2013;</sup> was less than in <italic>tasg1</italic>. DAB staining also showed less accumulation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">D</xref>).</p>
        <p content-type="indent">To confirm further differences in antioxidant activities between the two wheat varieties, wheat seedlings at the third-leaf stage were also used to detect accumulation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) accumulation by water stress treatment with 20% PEG-6000 solution or water as a control for 0, 24, and 48h. The O<sub>2</sub>&#xB7;<sup>&#x2013;</sup> accumulation was lower in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT at all three observed time points, but no obvious difference in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation was observed at this stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8H</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">J</xref>). The results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>) collectively show that the accumulation of ROS in <italic>tasg1</italic> was lower than in the WT under both normal and drought stress conditions not only at the senescence stage but also at the seedling stages.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s26">
        <title>Effect of drought stress on relative electrical conductivity</title>
        <p>At 10 d under drought, the REC of the WT was higher than that of <italic>tasg1</italic> under normal water conditions. Drought stress increased the REC in both wheat varieties, but it was lower in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT. At 25 d under drought, leaf senescence increased the REC in both wheat varieties compared with that at 10 d under drought, and drought stress inhibited this increase. However, compared with the WT, the REC in <italic>tasg1</italic> was consistently lower over the course of the experiment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>). The less severe membrane damage in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT was consistent with the greater antioxidant competence of <italic>tasg1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s27">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s28">
        <title>Improved functions of protein complexes in the thylakoid membrane in tasg1 facilitate photosynthesis and drought resistance</title>
        <p>In a previous study, <italic>tasg1</italic> was shown to retain photosynthetic competence, consistent with its delayed progression of chlorophyll degradation compared with WT plants at 30 d after anthesis. Therefore, <italic>tasg1</italic> is a functional stay-green wheat mutant with the Type B phenotype (in which senescence is initiated on schedule but progresses at a rate lower than the WT) or the combination of Type B and Type A (in which senescence is initiated late but proceeds at a normal rate) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0016">Hui <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). In this current work, compared with the WT, <italic>tasg1</italic> exhibited markedly delayed senescence with retention of leaf colour, and the stay-green phenotype of <italic>tasg1</italic> was also maintained under drought stress (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), suggesting improved drought resistance in <italic>tasg1</italic>.</p>
        <p content-type="indent">Photosynthesis in the chloroplast is one of the most stress-sensitive physiological processes. Stress damages the thylakoid membrane, disturbs its functions, and ultimately decreases photosynthesis and crop yield (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0034">Shah and Paulsen, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0017">Huseynova <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0046">Zhao <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). In a previous study, the <italic>P</italic><sub>n</sub> of <italic>tasg1</italic> was found to be greater than that of the WT under drought stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0040">Tian <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). However, the functions of the protein complexes in the thylakoid membrane of <italic>tasg1</italic> and how <italic>tasg1</italic> protects the thylakoid membrane from damage under drought stress was still unclear. To determine the stability of the protein complexes in the thylakoid membrane in <italic>tasg1</italic> under drought stress in this study, the Hill reaction activity, &#x3A6;<sub>PSII</sub> and <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> of PSII photochemistry, ATPase activity, as well as the abundance of polypeptides in the thylakoid membrane were examined. The expression levels of several genes and proteins involved in LHCI and LHCII were also detected.</p>
        <p content-type="indent">The Hill reaction activity is an important index for oxygen-evolving centre (OEC) activity in thylakoid membranes. As can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>, in the early stage of drought stress (at 10 d under drought), the Hill reaction activity was reduced in leaves of both <italic>tasg1</italic> and WT plants by drought stress, but it remained at a higher level in <italic>tasg1</italic>. About 2 weeks later (at 25 d under drought), a steep decrease in the Hill reaction activity was observed under both normal and drought stress conditions, suggesting that severe damage to the OEC occurred due to leaf senescence as well as drought stress, but the decrease was smaller in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT.</p>
        <p content-type="indent">The reduction in photosynthetic activity under drought stress can be the cause or result of photoinhibition. PSII is believed to play a key role in the response of leaf photosynthesis to environmental perturbations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0037">Swiatek <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">Dubey, 2005</xref>). Both &#x3A6;<sub>PSII</sub> and <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> represent a measure of the functional status of PSII and have been used as a sensitive indicator of plant photosynthetic performance responding to stress conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0022">Maxwell and Johnson, 2000</xref>). In this study, under non-stress conditions, no significant differences in &#x3A6;<sub>PSII</sub> and <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> of PSII photochemistry were observed between <italic>tasg1</italic> and the WT, while drought stress significantly decreased &#x3A6;<sub>PSII</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>) and <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). However, compared with the WT, those decreases in <italic>tasg1</italic> were attenuated under drought stress, indicating that the PSII complex in <italic>tasg1</italic> could better withstand photoinduced inactivation than the WT under drought stress. Furthermore, drought stress significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) decreased the activities of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase and Mg<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase in the thylakoid membrane, but the decreases in the WT were more drastic than those in <italic>tasg1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">D</xref>), suggesting the better drought tolerance of ATPase in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT. All these results were consistent with observations from a previous study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0041">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>).</p>
        <p content-type="indent">The function of the thylakoid membrane is dependent upon its fluidity and integrity, which are affected by its components, such as lipids, membrane proteins, pigments, and ions. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0012">Gillet <italic>et al</italic>. (1998)</xref> reported that drought induces an increase in the concentration of a 34kDa thylakoid protein. Similar studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0017">Huseynova <italic>et al</italic>. (2007)</xref> showed that the concentration of a 40.5kDa thylakoid membrane protein is increased under water stress. It was found here that the abundance of polypeptides from the thylakoid membrane with molecular masses of ~25&#x2013;35kDa, especially a 28kDa polypeptide, was affected by drought stress (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Meanwhile, the levels of three polypeptides of 28, 38, and 50kDa were consistently higher in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in WT wheat seedlings at the third-leaf stage when treated with 20% PEG-6000 solution with water as a control for 24h and 48h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Of these three polypeptides detected in wheat seedlings, only the 28kDa polypeptide was retained in mature plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). This difference suggested that some polypeptides were degraded during leaf development and senescence. Compared with the WT, <italic>tasg1</italic> could maintain the thylakoid membrane protein complexes with better stability against damage by drought stress.</p>
        <p content-type="indent">Stay-green mutants are characterized by increased stability of chloroplast membranes and chlorophyll&#x2013;protein complexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0018">Kusaba <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0026">Park <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0032">Sato <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). In a previous report, it was also suggested that the chloroplast and thylakoid structures in the <italic>tasg1</italic> mutant are protected from drought stress-induced damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0040">Tian <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). Under drought stress conditions in <italic>tasg1</italic>, it had been found that the thylakoid stacks in the grana were nearly unchanged and also a fusion ultrastructure of several grana stacks was observed, which was consistent with other reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0018">Kusaba <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0033">Schelbert <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). The retention of LHCII is thought to play an important role in the formation and maintenance of grana stacks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0036">Standfuss <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>). In this study, the expression levels of two genes encoding LHCII proteins, <italic>TaLhcb4</italic> and <italic>TaLhcb6</italic>, were found to be higher in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT, especially at the 48h time point under drought stress (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). Immunoblot analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>) also revealed that the accumulation of TaLhca2, TaLhcb4, and TaLhcb6 was decreased in both the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> after 48h under drought stress. However, some inconsistencies were also found between the mRNA level and protein abundance in the three detected proteins. Expression levels of <italic>TaLhca2</italic> mRNA still remained at a higher level in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT at the last tested time point of 48h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). However, the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> have almost the same protein content of TaLhca2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). At 48h after drought stress treatment, the mRNA level of <italic>TaLhcb6</italic> was 1.97-fold higher in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT, while protein accumulation of TaLhcb6 was changed 2.15-fold. Previous outcomes indicate that further levels of regulation based on post-transcriptional and post-translational mechanisms are involved in the abiotic stress response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0024">Oksman-Caldentey and Saito, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0030">Reinders and Sickmann, 2007</xref>). Beyond protein phosphorylation, other post-translational modifications such as ubiquitination and sumoylation regulate the activation and stability of pre-existing molecules to ensure a prompt response to stress. However, the exact mechanisms of post-transcriptional and post-translational regulatory systems in the WT and <italic>tasg1</italic> need to be studied further. In a previous study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0040">Tian <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>), <italic>tasg1</italic> showed 52.0% and 72.5% higher contents of Chl <italic>b</italic> on the 30th day after anthesis compared with the WT under normal and drought stress conditions, respectively. Chl <italic>b</italic> is known to play an important role in LHCII stability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0004">Bellemare <italic>et al</italic>., 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0027">Paulsen <italic>et al</italic>., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0013">Horn and Paulsen, 2004</xref>), which may contribute to the maintenance of grana stacks in <italic>tasg1</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s29">
        <title>Enhanced antioxidant activities in tasg1 may contribute to delayed senescence and drought resistance</title>
        <p>Abiotic stresses such as drought, cold, and salinity result in the production and accumulation of ROS, which are highly reactive and toxic to plants, and can lead to senescence and cell death by causing damage to proteins, lipids, DNA, and carbohydrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0023">Noctor and Foyer, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0002">Apel and Hirt, 2004</xref>). Although a variety of enzymatic and non-enzymatic antioxidants can remove the ROS continuously generated by aerobic metabolism and environmental stressors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0010">Foyer and Noctor, 2005</xref>), a substantial fraction of cellular proteins is irreversibly damaged (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0028">Poppek and Grune, 2006</xref>), and the accumulated oxidized proteins can be toxic to plant cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007">Cohen <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>).</p>
        <p content-type="indent">Derivatization of protein carbonyls with DNPH, followed by immunoblotting with an anti-DNP antibody, is a sensitive and specific method for the detection of oxidatively modified proteins and is generally regarded as an indicator of oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0029">Qiu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). The lower amounts of accumulated protein carbonylation products observed in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT under both normal and drought stress conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>) suggested less oxidative damage to proteins in <italic>tasg1</italic>. The lower levels of electrolyte leakage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>) in <italic>tasg1</italic> were also indicative of less cell membrane damage induced by drought stress compared with the WT plant.</p>
        <p content-type="indent">Meanwhile, the accumulation of O<sub>2</sub>&#xB7;<sup>&#x2013;</sup> and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> was lower in <italic>tasg1</italic> than in the WT under normal and drought stress conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>), which may be related to the higher activity of antioxidative enzymes in <italic>tasg1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0040">Tian <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). Furthermore, this lower ROS accumulation in <italic>tasg1</italic> was found not only in the senescence stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">D</xref>), but also in the seedling stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8E</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">J</xref>), suggesting the native greater antioxidant competence in <italic>tasg1</italic>.</p>
        <p content-type="indent">In previous research, <italic>tasg1</italic> accumulated more soluble sugars and proteins under water stress, which could also contribute to protection from cell membrane damage in <italic>tasg1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0040">Tian <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>).</p>
        <p content-type="indent">In summary, the stay-green wheat mutant <italic>tasg1</italic> could stably maintain thylakoid membrane polypeptides at high levels, while its expression of some LHCI- and LHCII-related genes remained steady under drought stress. The improved Hill reaction activity, &#x3A6;<sub>PSII</sub> and <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> of PSII photochemistry, and ATPase activity resulted in the high photosynthesis activity in <italic>tasg1</italic> compared with the WT plant. Thus, the results in this study combined with previous observations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0016">Hui <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0040">Tian <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>) suggest that greater antioxidant competence may contribute to the delayed senescence and drought resistance of <italic>tasg1</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>This work was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 30671259).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Molecular recognition in thylakoid structure and function</article-title>. <source>Trends in Plant Science</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>317</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11435171</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Reactive oxygen species: metabolism, oxidative stress, and signal transduction</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source><volume>55</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>399</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnon</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><year>1949</year><article-title>Copper enzymes in isolated chloroplasts: polyphenoloxidase in <italic>Beta vulgaris</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>24</volume>, <fpage>l</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>15</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellemare</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1982</year><article-title>Biosynthesis of chlorophyll <italic>a/b</italic>-binding polypeptides in wild type and the chlorina-f2 mutant of barley</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>257</volume>, <fpage>7762</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7045113</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1976</year><article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein&#x2013;dye binding</article-title>. <source>Analytical Biochemistry</source><volume>72</volume>, <fpage>248</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Mechanisms underlying plant resilience to water deficits: prospects for water-saving agriculture</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>55</volume>, <fpage>2365</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15475377</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieschke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Perciavalle</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Opposing activities protect against age-onset proteotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>313</volume>, <fpage>1604</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16902091</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dalle-donne</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Giustarini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagliano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Simplicio</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Milzani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Methionine oxidation as a major cause of the functional impairment of oxidized actin</article-title>. <source>Free Radical Biology and Medicine</source><volume>32</volume>, <fpage>927</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11978495</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Photosynthesis in plants under stressful conditions</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pessarakli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, ed. <source>Handbook of photosynthesis</source>, <edition>2nd edn</edition><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press, Taylor and Francis Group</publisher-name>, <fpage>717</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>737</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foyer</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Noctor</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Redox homeostasis and antioxidant signaling: a metabolic interface between stress perception and physiological responses</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1866</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15987996</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0011">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giacomelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Masi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ripoll</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wijk</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> deficient in two chloroplast ascorbate peroxidases shows accelerated light-induced necrosis when levels of cellular ascorbate are low</article-title>. <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source><volume>65</volume>, <fpage>627</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17823777</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0012">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Peltier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Molecular characterization of CDSP 34, a chloroplastic protein induced by water deficit in <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L. plants, and regulation of CDSP 34 expression by ABA and light illumination</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>16</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9839468</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0013">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Early steps in the assembly of light harvesting chlorophyll <italic>a/b</italic> complex</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>279</volume>, <fpage>44400</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>44406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15304514</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0014">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#xF6;rtensteiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Stay-green regulates chlorophyll and chlorophyll-binding protein degradation during senescence</article-title>. <source>Trends in Plant Science</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>155</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19237309</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0015">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1985</year><source>Techniques of plant physiological experiment</source>. <publisher-loc>Shanghai</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Shanghai Scientific &amp; Technical Publishers</publisher-name>, <fpage>111</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>115</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0016">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>The antioxidative defense system is involved in the delayed senescence in a wheat mutant <italic>tasg1</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Reports</source><volume>31</volume>, <fpage>1073</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1084</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22262312</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0017">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huseynova</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Suleymanov</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Aliyev</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Structural functional state of thylakoid membranes of wheat genotypes under water stress</article-title>. <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source><volume>1767</volume>, <fpage>869</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17321491</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0018">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kusaba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Rice NON-YELLOW COLORING1 is involved in light-harvesting complex II and grana degradation during leaf senescence</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1362</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17416733</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0019">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichtenthaler</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year><article-title>Chlorophylls and carotenoids: pigments of photosynthetic biomembranes</article-title>. <source>Methods in Enzymology</source><volume>148</volume>, <fpage>350</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>382</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0020">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matile</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#xF6;rtensteiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kra&#xFC;tler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Chlorophyll breakdown in senescent leaves</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>112</volume>, <fpage>1403</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12226455</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0021">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matile</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#xF6;rtensteiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Chlorophyll degradation</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology and Plant Molecular Biology</source><volume>50</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>95</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0022">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Chlorophyll fluorescence&#x2014;a practical guide</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>51</volume>, <fpage>659</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10938857</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0023">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noctor</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Foyer</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Ascorbate and glutathione: keeping active oxygen under control</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology and Plant Molecular Biology</source><volume>49</volume>, <fpage>249</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>279</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0024">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oksman-Caldentey</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2005 Integrating genomics and metabolomics for engineering plant metabolic pathways</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Biotechnology</source><volume>16</volume>, <fpage>174</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15831383</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0025">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parida</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Effects of NaCl stress on the structure, pigment complex composition, and photosynthetic activity of mangrove <italic>Bruguiera parviflora</italic> chloroplasts</article-title>. <source>Photosynthetica</source><volume>41</volume>, <fpage>191</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>200</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0026">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>The senescence-induced stay green protein regulates chlorophyll degradation</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1649</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17513504</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0027">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Finkenzeller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#xFC;hlein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Pigments induce folding of light-harvesting chlorophyll <italic>a/b</italic>-binding protein</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Biochemistry</source><volume>215</volume>, <fpage>809</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>816</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8354287</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0028">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poppek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Grune</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Proteasomal defense of oxidative protein modifications</article-title>. <source>Antioxidants and Redox Signaling</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16487051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0029">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>QS</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Booker</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Leakey</surname><given-names>ADB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiscus</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yau</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ort</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Increased protein carbonylation in leaves of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and soybean in response to elevated [CO<sub>2</sub>]</article-title>. <source>Photosynthesis Research</source><volume>97</volume>, <fpage>155</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18506594</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0030">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinders</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sickmann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2007 Modificomics: posttranslational modifications beyond protein phosphorylation and glycosylation</article-title>. <source>Biomolecular Engineering</source><volume>24</volume>, <fpage>169</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17419095</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0031">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsuma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusaba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Two short-chain dehydrogenase/reductases, NON-YELLOW COLORING1 and NYC1-LIKE, are required for chlorophyll <italic>b</italic> and light-harvesting complex II degradation during senescence in rice</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>57</volume>, <fpage>120</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18778405</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0032">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusaba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Mendel&#x2019;s green cotyledon gene encodes a positive regulator of the chlorophyll degrading pathway</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>104</volume>, <fpage>14169</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>14174</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0033">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schelbert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Burla</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Agne</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupinska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#xF6;rtensteine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Pheophytin pheophorbide hydrolase (pheophytinase) is involved in chlorophyll breakdown during leaf senescence in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>21</volume>, <fpage>767</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19304936</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0034">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Interaction of drought and high temperature on photosynthesis and grain-filling of wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant and Soil</source><volume>257</volume>, <fpage>219</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>226</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0035">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Fonzo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrotta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Platani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronga</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawlor</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Napier</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shewry</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Physiological characterization of &#x2018;stay green&#x2019; mutants in durum wheat</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>54</volume>, <fpage>1415</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12709488</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0036">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Standfuss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Scheltinga</surname><given-names>ACT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamborghini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#xFC;hlbrandt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Mechanisms of photoprotection and nonphotochemical quenching in pea light-harvesting complex at 2.5 &#xC5; resolution</article-title>. <source>EMBO Journal</source><volume>24</volume>, <fpage>919</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15719016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0037">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swiatek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuras</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokolenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>The chloroplast gene <italic>ycf9</italic> encodes a photosystem II (PSII) core subunit, PsbZ, that participates in PSII supramolecular architecture</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>13</volume>, <fpage>1347</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402165</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0038">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Howarth</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Five ways to stay green</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>51</volume>, <fpage>329</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10938840</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0039">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Smart</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Crops that stay green</article-title>. <source>Annals of Applied Biology</source><volume>123</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>223</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0040">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Improved drought resistance in a wheat stay-green mutant <italic>tasg1</italic> under field conditions</article-title>. <source>Biologia Plantarum</source><volume>56</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>515</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0041">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Overaccumulation of glycine betaine enhances tolerance to drought and heat stress in wheat leaves in the protection of photosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Photosynthetica</source><volume>48</volume>, <fpage>117</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>126</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0042">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1985</year><article-title>Detection of Hill reaction with spectrophotometer</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Plant physiology experiment handbook</source>. <publisher-loc>Shanghai</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Shanghai Science and Technology Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>104</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>107</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0043">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Paek</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Quantitative trait loci associated with functional stay-green <italic>SNU-SG1</italic> in rice</article-title>. <source>Molecules and Cells</source><volume>24</volume>, <fpage>83</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17846502</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0044">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>QF</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Manipulation of monoubiquitin improves salt tolerance in transgenic tobacco</article-title>. <source>Plant Biology</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>315</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22187972</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0045">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name><name><surname>Paakkarinen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wijk</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Aro</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Cotranslational assembly of the D1 protein into photosystem II</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>274</volume>, <fpage>16062</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>16067</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10347157</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0046">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>QQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Effect of glycinebetaine on function of thylakoid membranes in wheat flag leaves under drought stress</article-title>. <source>Biologia Plantarum</source><volume>51</volume>, <fpage>584</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>588</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0047">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>QTL mapping of maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) stay-green traits and their relationship to yield</article-title>. <source>Plant Breeding</source><volume>128</volume>, <fpage>54</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>62</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
