<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jexbot</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3638834</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23536608</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ert070</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Paper</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Novel insights into the composition, variation, organization, and expression of the low-molecular-weight glutenin subunit gene family in common wheat</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaofei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Dongcheng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Jianghua</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>Wei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>Guangbin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Wenlong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Jiazhu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tong</surname>
            <given-names>Yiping</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cui</surname>
            <given-names>Dangqun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Aimin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">
            <sup>&#x2020;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="AF0001"><sup>1</sup><institution>State Key Laboratory of Plant Cell and Chromosome Engineering, National Center for Plant Gene Research, Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology, Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>1 West Beichen Road, Chaoyang District, Beijing 100101</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff>
        <aff id="AF0002"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Agronomy/Key Laboratory of Physiological Ecology and Genetic Improvement of Food Crops in Henan Province, Henan Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>63 Nongye Road, Zhengzhou 450002</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1"><sup>&#x2020;</sup> To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>amzhang@genetics.ac.cn</email></corresp>
        <corresp id="c2">*These authors contributed equally to this work.
</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>64</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <fpage>2027</fpage>
      <lpage>2040</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(2) [2013].</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="creative-commons">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Low-molecular-weight glutenin subunits (LMW-GS), encoded by a complex multigene family, play an important role in the processing quality of wheat flour. Although members of this gene family have been identified in several wheat varieties, the allelic variation and composition of LMW-GS genes in common wheat are not well understood. In the present study, using the LMW-GS gene molecular marker system and the full-length gene cloning method, a comprehensive molecular analysis of LMW-GS genes was conducted in a representative population, the micro-core collections (MCC) of Chinese wheat germplasm. Generally, &gt;15 LMW-GS genes were identified from individual MCC accessions, of which 4&#x2013;6 were located at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus, 3&#x2013;5 at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus, and eight at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus. LMW-GS genes at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus showed the highest allelic diversity, followed by the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> genes, while the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> genes were extremely conserved among MCC accessions. Expression and sequence analysis showed that 9&#x2013;13 active LMW-GS genes were present in each accession. Sequence identity analysis showed that all i-type genes present at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus formed a single group, the s-type genes located at <italic>Glu-B3</italic> and <italic>Glu-D3</italic> loci comprised a unique group, while high-diversity m-type genes were classified into four groups and detected in all <italic>Glu-3</italic> loci. These results contribute to the functional analysis of LMW-GS genes and facilitate improvement of bread-making quality by wheat molecular breeding programmes.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Key words:</title>
        <kwd>Allele</kwd>
        <kwd>common wheat</kwd>
        <kwd>composition</kwd>
        <kwd>low-molecular-weight glutenin subunits.</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="14"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Common wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) is one of the &#x2018;big three&#x2019; cereal crops used for human food (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Shewry, 2009</xref>) since wheat grains confer their viscoelastic properties to wheat dough (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Shewry <italic>et al</italic>., 1995</xref>). These viscoelastic properties allow dough to be incorporated into a wide range of daily food products, which are affected by glutenin and gliadin proteins in wheat seeds (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Shewry <italic>et al</italic>., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">D&#x2019;Ovidio and Masci, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Juh&#xE1;sz and Gianibelli, 2006</xref>). Glutenin proteins are composed of two groups of subunits, namely high-molecular-weight and low-molecular-weight glutenin subunits (HMW-GS, 65&#x2013;90kDa; LMW-GS, 30&#x2013;45kDa) (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Payne, 1987</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">D&#x2019;Ovidio and Masci, 2004</xref>). The LMW-GS account for about one-third of the seed protein and 60% of glutenin proteins, and play an important role in determining dough properties and the quality of wheat food products (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Gupta <italic>et al</italic>., 1991</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Branlard <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Eagles <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Howitt <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). Thus, elucidating the composition and variation of LMW-GS genes in common wheat and investigating the relationship between allelic variants and end-use quality are of interest for wheat quality improvement (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Gupta <italic>et al</italic>., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">He <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Bekes <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Juh&#xE1;sz and Gianibelli, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>).</p>
      <p content-type="indent">LMW-GS genes form a multigene family in common wheat, generally located at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic>, <italic>Glu-B3</italic>, and <italic>Glu-D3</italic> loci on the short arms of homoeologous group 1 chromosomes (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Jackson <italic>et al</italic>., 1983</xref>). The copy number of LMW-GS genes was estimated to range from 10&#x2013;20 to 30&#x2013;40 (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Ikeda <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">D&#x2019;Ovidio and Masci, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Juh&#xE1;sz and Gianibelli, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Cloutier, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>). In Norin 61, 12 groups of LMW-GS genes were identified by screening the cDNA library (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Ikeda <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). In Glenlea, among the 12 active genes, one was assigned to chromosome 1A, two to chromosome 1B, and nine to chromosome 1D (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Cloutier, 2008</xref>). In Xiaoyan 54, 14 unique LMW-GS genes were identified using BAC (bacterial artificial chromosome) library screening and proteomics analysis, of which four were located at <italic>Glu-A3</italic>, three at <italic>Glu-B3</italic>, and seven at <italic>Glu-D3</italic>. Of the 11 active genes, two, two, and seven were i-, s-, and m-type genes, respectively (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). The above three varieties contained different LMW-GS gene compositions, suggesting that this gene family has high molecular diversity among wheat varieties (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Moreover, these LMW-GS proteins had similar physical and chemical properties and molecular weights to the gliadins, which are a type of alcohol-soluble, monomeric seed storage protein. The high copy number and their co-migration with gliadins by SDS&#x2013;PAGE (sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis) and MALDI-TOF MS (matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization-time of flight mass spectrometry) made separation of LMW-GS proteins and isolation of all LMW-GS genes from a particular wheat variety difficult (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Howitt <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). Thus, characterization of the allelic variation of LMW-GS genes in wheat germplasm remains challenging.</p>
      <p content-type="indent">To dissect the LMW-GS complex, a nomenclature system was developed based on their relative mobility in SDS-PAGE (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Singh <italic>et al</italic>., 1991</xref>). Recently, their encoding genes were isolated using PCR with gene-specific primers. One m- and two i-type LMW-GS genes (<italic>GluA3-1</italic>, <italic>GluA3-2</italic>, and <italic>GluA3-3</italic>) were isolated from each <italic>Glu-A3</italic> allele (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). At the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus, four LMW-GS genes (<italic>GluB3-1</italic>, <italic>GluB3-2</italic>, <italic>GluB3-3</italic>, and <italic>GluB3-4</italic>) and their allelic variants were isolated from nine <italic>Glu-B3</italic> alleles (<italic>Glu-B3a</italic>&#x2013;<italic>Glu-B3i</italic>) (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). Also, six <italic>Glu-D3</italic> genes were identified from individual wheat varieties containing <italic>Glu-D3a&#x2013;Glu-D3e</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Zhao <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Meanwhile, allele-specific markers were developed to discriminate LMW-GS genes and their allelic variants in common wheat (<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Zhao <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Appelbee <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). These markers facilitated identification of the known <italic>Glu-A3</italic> and <italic>Glu-B3</italic> alleles used in breeding programmes (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). However, <italic>Glu-D3</italic> genes were highly conserved, and allelic identification using PCR markers was difficult (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). In contrast, these allele-specific primers characterized only one or two genes in individual alleles, and could not be used to determine the exact composition of LMW-GS genes in individual varieties.</p>
      <p content-type="indent">To determine the composition of LMW-GS genes in individual wheat varieties, the LMW-GS gene molecular marker system and the full-length gene-cloning method were developed (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>), which enabled identification and characterization of the complete sequences of all LMW-GS genes in any wheat variety. In the present study, using both methods, LMW-GS genes were investigated in the micro-core collections (MCC) of Chinese wheat germplasm, which covers &gt;70% of the genetic diversity of Chinese wheat germplasm (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Hao <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). The composition, organization, allelic variation, and expression of LMW-GS genes in 262 MCC accessions were comprehensively investigated.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Wheat germplasm</title>
        <p>The MCC of Chinese wheat germplasm were obtained from the Institute of Crop Science, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences (CAAS). This was a representative sample of Chinese wheat diversity. This collection consisted of 262 accessions including 88 modern varieties, 157 landraces, and 17 foreign varieties, which accounted for &gt;70% of the genetic diversity of the national collection.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4">
        <title>LMW-GS gene analysis</title>
        <p>Genomic DNAs of 262 MCC accessions were extracted from young leaves of seedlings with the cetyltrimethyl ammonium bromide (CTAB method) following <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Saghai-Maroof <italic>et al</italic>. (1984)</xref>. The LMW-GS genes in all the MCC accessions were separated using the LMW-GS gene molecular marker system (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011b</xref>). Based on data from the marker system, 45 accessions containing almost all allelic variants were selected for RNA analysis. Total RNA was prepared from developing seeds at 15&#x2013;21 dpa (day post anthesis) using TRIzol<sup>&#xAE;</sup> Reagent, according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s protocol (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). The RNA was converted into cDNA using Moloney murine leukemia virus (M-MLV) reverse transcriptase (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). The expressed LMW-GS genes were detected using the molecular marker system (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011<italic>b</italic>
</xref>). To obtain the full-length sequence of these LMW-GS genes, 30 representative varieties containing all the main allelic variants of each gene were selected. All genes were cloned and identified using the full-length gene cloning method (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>). To clone rare allelic variants, gene-specific primers were developed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> available at <italic>JXB</italic> online). Sequence analysis and characterization were performed using Lasergene software (DNAStar; <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dnastar.com/">http://www.dnastar.com/</uri>), ClustalW2 (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/</uri>), and MEGA 5 software (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Kumar <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s6">
        <title>Composition and variation of LMW-GS genes in MCC accessions</title>
        <p>LMW-GS genes in the MCC of Chinese wheat germplasm were amplified using the LMW-GS gene molecular marker system consisting of three independent sets of conserved primers (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>). In general terms, at least 15 LMW-GS genes were identified in each wheat variety (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). To characterize these LMW-GS genes further, 30 representative accessions containing the main allelic variants were selected, and all of their LMW-GS genes were cloned and sequenced using the full-length gene cloning method and gene-specific primers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online) (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>). In total, 466 LMW-GS gene sequences were identified and deposited in GenBank (JX877778&#x2013;JX878243).</p>
        <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>LMW-GS genes and their allelic variants identified from MCC accessions using the LMW-GS gene molecular marker system.</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="vsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Genes and allelic variants<sup><italic>a</italic></sup>
</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">LMWGS1<sup><italic>b</italic></sup>
</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">LMWGS2<sup><italic>b</italic></sup>
</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">LMWGS3<sup><italic>b</italic></sup>
</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-391</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-353</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-370</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-373</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">391.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">353.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">370.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">373.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">484.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">460.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">477.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">480.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">375.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">350.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">368.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">371.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-400</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-374</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-388</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-394</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">400.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">374.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">388.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N<sup><italic>c</italic></sup>
</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">506.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">481.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">494.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">399.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">387.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-402</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-408</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-411</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">402.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">408.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">411.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">509.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">514.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">517.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">402.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">408.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">411.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-502</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-480</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-484</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-487</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">484.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">590.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">538.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">513.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">522.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-508</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">543.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-565</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">565.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">671.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">606.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-568</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-567</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">568</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">567.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">674.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">673.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">609.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">607.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-620</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-590</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-626</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-640</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">620.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">589.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">626.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/640.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">725.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">693.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">730.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/745.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">666.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">632.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">673.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">619.4/688.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-643</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-646</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-649</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">643.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">646</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">649.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">750.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">753.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">691</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">695.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">698.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A3-662</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">662.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">766.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">715.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-530</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-510</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-516</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">530.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">510.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">516</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">636.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">616.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">622.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">538.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">516.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">522.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-548</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-557</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">548.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">557.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">654.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">663.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">556.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">565.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-570</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">570.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">676.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-578</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">577.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">683.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">587.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-544</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-590</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-593</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-596</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">544.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">590.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">593.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">596.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">650.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">696.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">699</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">701.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">554.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">605.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">608.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">611.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-598</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-601</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-604</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">598.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">601.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">604.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">704.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">706.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">709.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">615.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">618.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">621.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-607</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-610</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">607.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">610.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">712.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">715.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">625</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">628.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-688</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-621</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-624</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">688.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">621.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">624.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">791.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">726.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">729.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">707.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">635.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">638.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-691</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>B3-813</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">691.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">813.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">794.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">916.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">710.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">855.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-385</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">385.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">492.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">383.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-393</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-385&#x2019;</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">393.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">499.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">390.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-394</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-397</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">394.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">397.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">503.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">393.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-441</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-432</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-444</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">441.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">432.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">444.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">547.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">538.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">550.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">441.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">432.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">444.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-525</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-522</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-528</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">525.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">522.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">528.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">631.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">628.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">634.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">532.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">529.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">535.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-575</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">575</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">681</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">584</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-578</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">577.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">683.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">587.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-586</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-583</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-589</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D3-591</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">586.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">583.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">589</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">591.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">691.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">688.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">694</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">696.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">597.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">594.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">601</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">604.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-594</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>D3-597</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">594.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">597.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">699.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">702.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">607.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">610.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn fn-type="other">
              <p><sup><italic>a</italic></sup> LMW-GS genes and allelic variants were named according to the size of the DNA fragments amplified using the primer LMWGS1. For each gene, the major allelic variant was designated as the LMW-GS gene and the remainder as its variants.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn fn-type="other">
              <p><sup><italic>b</italic></sup> Three sets of conserved primers in the LMW-GS gene molecular marker system (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011<italic><italic>b</italic></italic>
</xref>).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn fn-type="other">
              <p><sup><italic>c</italic></sup> Not detected with the specific primers.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p content-type="indent">For each LMW-GS gene, several allelic variants were detected from the MCC (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), some of which were identified previously (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Ikeda <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Zhao <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Cloutier, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>). Using available mapped LMW-GS genes and their allelic relationship with the genes identified from the MCC, all these genes were assigned to specific wheat chromosomes. In individual accessions, 4&#x2013;6 genes were located at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus, 3&#x2013;5 at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus, and eight at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). These genes were named according to their DNA fragment size and chromosomal location. For example, the gene corresponding to DNA fragment 441.5, located at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus, was designated <italic>D3-441</italic>. Most of these genes contained several allelic variations across the MCC. To simplify description, the major allelic variant was selected to represent each LMW-GS gene and it was named according to the following scheme: &#x2018;DNA fragment+gene&#x2019; (e.g. the <italic>A3-402</italic> gene), while the allelic variants of each gene were named according to &#x2018;DNA fragment+allele&#x2019; (e.g. the <italic>A3-402</italic> allele).</p>
        <sec id="s7">
          <title>LMW-GS genes at the Glu-A3 locus</title>
          <p>At the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus, 4&#x2013;6 LMW-GS genes were detected in each accession and several allelic variants were identified for each gene in the MCC (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). With regard to the <italic>A3-391</italic> gene, five allelic variants, <italic>A3-353</italic>, <italic>A3-370a</italic>, <italic>A3-370b</italic>, <italic>A3-373</italic>, and <italic>A3-391</italic>, shared &gt;97% identity (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). The <italic>A3-391</italic> allele predominated in 196 accessions, while <italic>A3-353</italic> and <italic>A3-373</italic> were rare variants, each present in only two MCC accessions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>). Sequence analysis of the <italic>A3-391</italic> genes of 30 varieties confirmed that allelic variants showed length polymorphisms in the repetitive regions, and that each variant contained its own single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link>). <italic>A3-353</italic>, <italic>A3-373</italic>, and <italic>A3-391</italic> were highly conserved across the MCC population, whereas the <italic>A3-370</italic> allele could be further divided into two variants (<italic>A3-370a</italic> and <italic>A3-370b</italic>) due to SNPs in all available sequences (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link>). <italic>A3-353</italic>, <italic>A3-370a</italic>, <italic>A3-370b</italic>, and <italic>A3-391</italic> alleles contained immature stop codons, and only the rare allele <italic>A3-373</italic> possessed an intact open reading frame (ORF) encoding an m-type subunit (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>). Thus, the <italic>A3-391</italic> gene was universal in common wheat, even though only five sequences with &gt;98% identities were deposited in GenBank.</p>
          <fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" position="float">
            <label>Fig. 1.</label>
            <caption>
              <p>Composition of LMW-GS genes at the <italic>Glu-3</italic> loci in micro-core collections (MCC) of Chinese wheat germplasm. The diagrams illustrate the LMW-GS genes and their allelic variants at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic>, <italic>B3</italic>, and <italic>D3</italic> loci identified from MCC accessions. The horizontal axis of each diagram shows the allelic variants of individual genes or haplotypes identified from the MCC. The vertical axis displays the composition of unique genes and haplotypes in individual accessions. The length of line segments represents the number of accessions containing the corresponding allelic variants. Underlined allelic variants were rare in the MCC, and allelic variants in red were active in common wheat. The allelic variants indicated by numbers and letters, such as 370a and 370b, shared the same DNA fragment but had different nucleotide sequences. (A) The compositions of genes and their allelic variants at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus. The i-type genes showed high diversity and were tightly linked, forming specific haplotypes. (B) The compositions of genes and their allelic variants at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus. The s-type genes were tightly linked and formed specific haplotypes. (C) The composition of eight genes and their allelic variants at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert070_f0001"/>
          </fig>
          <p content-type="indent">The <italic>A3-400</italic> gene was also common in wheat varieties. Seven allelic variants with different repetitive region lengths, <italic>A3-374</italic>, <italic>A3-388</italic>, <italic>A3-394</italic>, <italic>A3-400</italic>, <italic>A3-402</italic>, <italic>A3-408</italic>, and <italic>A3-411</italic>, were identified from MCC accessions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>). Sequence alignments suggested that the <italic>A3-374</italic>, <italic>A3-388</italic>, <italic>A3-400</italic>, <italic>A3-408</italic>, and <italic>A3-411</italic> alleles were conserved among wheat varieties, whereas both <italic>A3-394</italic> and <italic>A3-402</italic> comprised two variants, <italic>A3-394a</italic> and <italic>A3-394b</italic>, and <italic>A3-402a</italic> and <italic>A3-402b</italic>, respectively, due to indels and SNPs in the available sequences (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). Sequence analysis also demonstrated that <italic>A3-402a</italic> and <italic>A3-400</italic> shared the same SNP, containing a premature stop codon, while all remaining allelic variants (i.e. <italic>A3-374</italic>, <italic>A3-388</italic>, <italic>A3-394a</italic>, <italic>A3-394b</italic>, <italic>A3-402b</italic>, <italic>A3-408</italic>, and <italic>A3-411</italic>) contained intact coding sequences that might encode m-type LMW-GS in common wheat (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link>).</p>
          <p content-type="indent">Except for the m-type genes above, all the others identified at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus were i-type genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). The coding sequences of alleles <italic>A3-480</italic>, <italic>A3-484</italic>, <italic>A3-487</italic>, <italic>A3-502</italic>, and <italic>A3-508</italic> contained a specific length of repetitive regions and unique SNPs. For the major variant <italic>A3-502</italic>, eight allelic variants (<italic>A3-502a</italic>&#x2013;<italic>A3-502h</italic>) were recognized due to SNPs and indels in the coding sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S3</ext-link>). For the other i-type genes, eight genes/haplotypes, <italic>A3-620</italic>, <italic>A3-626</italic>, <italic>A3-643</italic>, <italic>A3-646</italic>, <italic>A3-649</italic>, <italic>A3-573</italic>/<italic>A3-640</italic>, <italic>A3-567</italic>/<italic>A3-590</italic>, and <italic>A3-565</italic>/<italic>A3-568</italic>/<italic>A3-662</italic>, were detected, of which alleles <italic>A3-626</italic> and <italic>A3-646</italic> were further divided into two allelic variants, respectively, due to SNPs in the coding sequences. Moreover, two genes, <italic>A3-649-1</italic> and <italic>A3-649-2</italic> with unique SNPs and indels, which shared a 649bp DNA fragment, were identified from individual accessions; the <italic>A3-567-1</italic> and <italic>A3-567-2</italic> genes exhibited similar commonality. After analysing the composition of i-type genes in 262 MCC accessions, it was found that all <italic>A3-502</italic> variants were tightly linked with other unique i-type genes. The <italic>A3-502a</italic> and <italic>A3-502b</italic> alleles were coupled with <italic>A3-620</italic>, <italic>A3-502c</italic> with <italic>A3-626a</italic>, <italic>A3-502d</italic> with <italic>A3-643</italic>, <italic>A3-502e</italic> with <italic>A3-646a</italic>, <italic>A3-502f</italic> with <italic>A3-646b</italic>, <italic>A3-502g</italic> with <italic>A3-573</italic> and <italic>A3-640</italic>, and <italic>A3-502h</italic> with <italic>A3-649-1</italic> and <italic>A3-649-2</italic>. In total, 12 i-type haplotypes were identified in MCC accessions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s8">
          <title>LMW-GS genes at the Glu-B3 locus</title>
          <p>Generally, excluding 11 1BL/1RS translocation lines, 3&#x2013;5 <italic>Glu-B3</italic> genes were identified in each MCC accession, and <italic>B3-530</italic> and <italic>B3-548</italic> genes were universal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>). With regard to the <italic>B3-530</italic> gene, three allelic variants, <italic>B3-510</italic>, <italic>B3-516</italic>, and <italic>B3-530</italic>, were identified (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>), and shared high sequence identity (&gt;99%). The <italic>B3-530</italic> allele was further divided into three variants (<italic>B3-530a</italic>, <italic>B3-530b</italic>, and <italic>B3-530c</italic>) due to the unique SNPs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S4</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). All allelic variants of the <italic>B3-530</italic> gene possessed intact ORFs and their deduced proteins belonged to m-type LMW-GS. For the <italic>B3-548</italic> gene, the <italic>B3-548</italic> allele predominated in 241 accessions, while the rare allelic variant <italic>B3-557</italic> was detected in only one (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>). However, both variants contained premature stop codons in their coding sequences, suggesting them to be pseudogenes.</p>
          <p content-type="indent">The other <italic>Glu-B3</italic> genes were identified only in partial MCC accessions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The <italic>B3-570</italic> gene was identified in 44 MCC accessions, and its intact ORF contained 344 amino acid residues and encoded an m-type gene with the novel N-terminal sequence, METSQIPGLEKPS. The <italic>B3-578</italic>, <italic>B3-621</italic>, and <italic>B3-544</italic> genes were tightly linked at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus and formed several haplotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>). The <italic>B3-578</italic> gene was classified into two variants (<italic>B3-578a</italic> and <italic>B3-578b</italic>) based on two SNPs. The <italic>B3-544</italic> genes were conserved among accessions, and the allelic variants <italic>B3-544</italic> and <italic>B3-587&#x2013;B3-607</italic> shared &gt;99% sequence identity (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S5</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). Also, <italic>B3-621</italic> and <italic>B3-624</italic> differed in only a CAA indel and an SNP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S6</ext-link>). Moreover, <italic>B3-578</italic> contained two premature stop codons in its coding sequences, while the other genes possessed intact ORFs, which might be active in common wheat. Sequence analysis showed that all three genes were s-type, the deduced protein sequences of which contained a MENSHIPGLERPS peptide at the N-terminus. <italic>B3-688</italic> could be divided into three groups (<italic>B3-688a</italic>, <italic>B3-688b</italic>, and <italic>B3-688c</italic>) in MCC accessions, although several irregular SNPs were found in the coding sequences (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S6</ext-link>). These irregular SNPs were tightly linked with <italic>B3-691</italic> or <italic>B3-813</italic> at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus, forming different haplotypes, namely <italic>B3-688a</italic>/<italic>B3-691</italic>, <italic>B3-688b</italic>/<italic>B3-813</italic>, and <italic>B3-688c</italic>/<italic>N</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>). <italic>B3-688a</italic> was coupled with <italic>B3-691</italic>, and shared &gt;99% identity, the only differences being a CAA indel and an SNP. <italic>B3-813</italic> was identified for the first time in common wheat and contained a premature stop codon in the ORF, while both <italic>B3-688</italic> and <italic>B3-691</italic> had unbroken ORFs encoding s-type LMW-GS in common wheat.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s9">
        <title>LMW-GS genes at the Glu-D3 locus</title>
        <p>Eight LMW-GS genes (<italic>D3-385</italic>, <italic>D3-393</italic>, <italic>D3-394</italic>, <italic>D3-441</italic>, <italic>D3-525</italic>, <italic>D3-575</italic>, <italic>D3-578</italic>, and <italic>D3-586</italic>) were detected at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus in individual wheat varieties (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>). Neither <italic>D3-385</italic> nor <italic>D3-575</italic> preserved any allelic variants and were universal in all MCC accessions. In terms of the <italic>D3-393</italic> gene, the <italic>D3-3</italic>93 allele was present in 259 MCC accessions, while the other rare allelic variant, <italic>D3-385&#x2019;</italic>, was found in only three (Fengkang 2, Guinong 10, and Lovrin 10). For the <italic>D3-394</italic> gene, both allelic variants, <italic>D3-394</italic> and <italic>D3-397</italic>, shared &gt;99% sequence identities, the difference being an indel (CAA) and two SNPs; the latter allele was detected in only a single landrace, Yizhimai. Three conserved allelic variants of <italic>D3-441</italic> (<italic>D3-432</italic>, <italic>D3-441</italic>, and <italic>D3-444</italic>) were identified with CAA indels in the repetitive region (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S7</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). The three allelic variants of the <italic>D3-525</italic> gene, namely <italic>D3-522</italic>, <italic>D3-525</italic>, and <italic>D3-528</italic>, exhibited a similar phenomenon (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S8</ext-link>). For the <italic>D3-578</italic> gene, <italic>D3-578a</italic> was identical in length but had a different nucleotide sequence from that of the the <italic>D3-578b</italic> variant (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S9</ext-link>). This gene encoded the only s-type LMW-GS at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus in common wheat. The nucleotide sequences of <italic>D3-586</italic> and its allelic variants were identical, except for the CAA indels in the repetitive region that contributed to the length polymorphism (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S10</ext-link>). Among the eight LMW-GS genes at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus, <italic>D3-393</italic> was a pseudogene due to a frameshift mutation and <italic>D3-586</italic> was a pseudogene due to a premature stop codon. The remaining six genes contained intact ORFs that encoded one s-type (<italic>D3-578</italic>) and five m-type LMW-GS at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus, which contained the largest number of active genes of all the <italic>Glu-3</italic> loci.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s10">
        <title>Organization of LMW-GS genes in MCC accessions</title>
        <p>Using the LMW-GS gene molecular marker system and the full-length gene cloning method (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>), almost all LMW-GS genes were detected in the MCC and were cloned and characterized in 30 MCC accessions, which facilitated investigation of the organization of LMW-GS genes and their linkage relationship.</p>
        <p content-type="indent">At the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus, 4&#x2013;6 genes were generally isolated from individual MCC accessions, including <italic>A3-391</italic>, <italic>A3-400</italic>, and 2&#x2013;4 i-type genes (e.g. <italic>A3-502a</italic> and <italic>A3-620</italic>; <italic>A3-502g</italic>, <italic>A3-573</italic>, and <italic>A3-640</italic>; and <italic>A3-484</italic>, <italic>A3-565</italic>, <italic>A3-568</italic>, and <italic>A3-662</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref>). Although several allelic variants were identified for each gene, only 11 main types of <italic>Glu-A3</italic> genotypes were detected in MCC accessions, suggesting that these genes were tightly linked (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). Two genotypes containing <italic>A3-391</italic>, <italic>A3-400</italic> or <italic>A3-402a</italic>, <italic>A3-502</italic>, and <italic>A3-620</italic> accounted for ~70% of the MCC accessions, while each of the remaining genotypes accounted for &lt;7% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). Moreover, concerning the distribution of different genotypes in foreign accessions, Chinese modern varieties, and landraces, genotypes containing the <italic>A3-649-1</italic>/<italic>-2</italic> genes were detected only in landraces, while those containing <italic>A3-394a</italic>/<italic>b</italic> were present in both foreign accessions and Chinese modern varieties (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>).</p>
        <fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Main genotypes of LMW-GS genes at <italic>Glu-3</italic> loci identified from the MCC. Genotypes present in more than three MCC accessions are shown. LMW-GS genes at the same locus were generally linked and formed limited types of genotypes. Genes in red were active in common wheat. Moreover, the modern varieties, landraces, and foreign varieties are indicated by different colours. The genotypes most common in landraces are indicated by red asterisks, and those found only in modern and foreign varieties by blue asterisks. (A) Eleven genotypes at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus. (B) Thirteen genotypes at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus. Of these, 11 accessions without LMW-GS genes belong to 1B/1R translocation lines. (C) Fourteen genotypes at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus.</p>
          </caption>
          <?source 960.87646484375?>
          <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert070_f0002"/>
        </fig>
        <p content-type="indent">Based on the genotype data of MCC accessions, the linkage relationship among LMW-GS genes at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus was analysed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). First, four main haplotypes of i-type genes were detected in MCC accessions, namely <italic>A3-502a</italic>/<italic>b</italic>/<italic>A3-620</italic>, <italic>A3-502</italic>/<italic>A3-646</italic>, <italic>A3-502h</italic>/<italic>A3-649-1</italic>/<italic>A3-649-2</italic>, and <italic>A3-484</italic>/<italic>A3-565</italic>/<italic>A3-568</italic>/<italic>A3-662</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref>). The i-type genes were completely linked and formed specific haplotypes in common wheat. Secondly, the <italic>A3-391</italic> allele was coupled with alleles <italic>A3-400</italic> and <italic>A3-402a</italic>, and the <italic>A3-370a</italic>/<italic>b</italic> alleles co-segregated with <italic>A3-394b</italic>, <italic>A3-402b</italic>, <italic>A3-408</italic>, and <italic>A3-411</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). m-Type genes may have been tightly linked with each other at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus. Thirdly, the <italic>A3-370a</italic>/<italic>b</italic> alleles were generally coupled with <italic>A3-502</italic>(<italic>e</italic>/<italic>f</italic>)/<italic>A3-646</italic> and <italic>A3-484</italic>/<italic>A3-565</italic>/<italic>A3-568</italic>/<italic>A3-662</italic>, while the <italic>A3-391</italic> allele was linked with <italic>A3-502</italic>(<italic>a</italic>/<italic>b</italic>)/<italic>A3-620</italic>, <italic>A3-502h</italic>/<italic>A3-649-1</italic>/<italic>A3-649-2</italic>, and <italic>A3-502</italic>g/<italic>A3-573</italic>/<italic>A3-640</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). Thus, the <italic>A3-391</italic> gene generally linked with i-type genes in MCC accessions.</p>
        <p content-type="indent">At the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus, although 3&#x2013;5 genes were present in individual accessions, their allelic variants consisted of 12 main genotypes in the MCC accessions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>). Genotypes containing allelic variants <italic>B3-621</italic>, <italic>B3-624</italic>, or <italic>B3-688</italic> covered all MCC accessions, excluding 11 1BL/1RS translocation lines, and genotypes containing the haplotypes <italic>B3-688</italic>/<italic>N</italic> or <italic>B3-688</italic>/<italic>B3-691</italic> accounted for 54% of the MCC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). Tight linkage of LMW-GS genes at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus was also observed. The <italic>B3-510</italic> allele was tightly coupled with the <italic>B3-570</italic> gene, forming the haplotype <italic>B3-510</italic>/<italic>B3-570</italic>, which was generally linked with another haplotype <italic>B3-688</italic>/<italic>B3-691</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). In contrast, s-type genes consisted of two groups of haplotypes at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus; one contained the <italic>B3-621</italic> gene and the other the <italic>B3-688</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>). The former group formed various haplotypes, which contained three unique LMW-GS genes, namely <italic>B3-578</italic>, <italic>B3-544</italic> and <italic>B3-621</italic>, as well as their allelic variants. Alleles <italic>B3-544</italic>, <italic>B3-601</italic>, <italic>B3-604</italic>, and <italic>B3-607</italic> regularly co-segregated with <italic>B3-621</italic>, while the other variants <italic>B3-590</italic>, <italic>B3-593</italic>, and <italic>B3-596</italic> were usually coupled with <italic>B3-624</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). In terms of the distribution of these genes in MCC, 1BL/1RS lines and genotypes containing <italic>B3-601</italic> and <italic>B3-604</italic> were identified only in foreign or modern varieties, whereas the genotypes containing <italic>B3-624</italic> and the genotype <italic>B3-530</italic>/<italic>B3-548</italic>/<italic>B3-688</italic>/<italic>B3-691</italic> were detected mostly in landraces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>).</p>
        <p content-type="indent">At the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus, although eight LMW-GS genes were identified from individual accessions, few haplotypes were characterized throughout the entire MCC population because of the high conservation of LMW-GS genes at this locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). Among them, <italic>D3-578a</italic> was linked with the <italic>D3-432</italic> allele, whereas <italic>D3-578b</italic> was generally coupled with <italic>D3-441</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). The <italic>D3-586</italic> gene showed high length polymorphisms among MCC accessions for six allelic variants <italic>D3-583</italic>/<italic>586</italic>/<italic>589</italic>/<italic>591</italic>/<italic>594</italic>/<italic>597</italic>, which resulted in detection of 14 main genotypes at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus in MCC accessions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). Two genotypes, <italic>D3-385</italic>/<italic>D3-393</italic>/<italic>D3-394</italic>/<italic>D3-441</italic>/<italic>D3-525</italic>/<italic>D3-575</italic>/<italic>D3-578</italic>/<italic>D3-586</italic> and <italic>D3-385</italic>/<italic>D3-393</italic>/<italic>D3-394</italic>/<italic>D3-441</italic>/<italic>D3-525</italic>/<italic>D3-575</italic>/<italic>D3-578</italic>/<italic>D3-589</italic>, differed only in the pseudogene <italic>D3-586</italic>, which accounted for 64.8% of the MCC accessions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s11">
        <title>Expression of LMW-GS genes in the MCC accessions</title>
        <p>Since only the active genes in this family affected bread-making quality, the mRNA of the developing seeds was investigated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) and active LMW-GS genes were identified by comparing the mRNA and genomic DNA data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
        <fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Expression analysis of LMW-GS genes in MCC accessions. Electropherograms show the patterns of DNA fragments detected in genomic DNA and cDNA of individual accessions using the LMWGS1 primers. The results of four of 45 representative accessions are shown. The horizontal axis shows the size of the detected DNA fragments, while the vertical axis displays the signal intensity (i.e. the concentration of DNA fragments in the PCR products). The orange peaks indicate the GeneScan 1200 LIZ size standard fragments, while the blue peaks represent the DNA fragments in the PCR products. In the genomic DNA electropherogram, peaks indicated by arrows and numbers were detected only in genomic DNA, all of which were pseudogenes. Peaks in the cDNA electropherograms indicated by numbers correspond to active LMW-GS genes. <italic>Glu-A3</italic> genes are shown in black, <italic>Glu-B3</italic> genes in green, and <italic>Glu-D3</italic> genes in pink.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert070_f0003"/>
        </fig>
        <p content-type="indent">At the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus, among the 4&#x2013;6 genes detected in genomic DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>), the <italic>A3-370a</italic>/<italic>b</italic> and <italic>A3-391</italic> alleles were not detected in mRNA of developing seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>), while their allelic variant <italic>A3-373</italic> may have been active in the intact ORF. In terms of the <italic>A3-400</italic> gene, the <italic>A3-400</italic> and <italic>A3-402a</italic> alleles were inactive, whereas both <italic>A3-402b</italic> and <italic>A3-408</italic> were expressed during seed filling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Also, the rare allelic variants <italic>A3-374</italic>, <italic>A3-388</italic>, <italic>A3-394a</italic>/<italic>b</italic>, and <italic>A3-411</italic> may encode LMW-GS proteins in their intact ORFs. None of the allelic variants of the <italic>A3-502</italic> gene was expressed due to premature stop codons, except for the active allele <italic>A3-502h</italic>. Among the other i-type genes, <italic>A3-573</italic>, <italic>A3-620</italic>, <italic>A3-646</italic>, <italic>A3-649-2</italic>, <italic>A3-568</italic>, and <italic>A3-662</italic> were detected in developing seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>), and the rare allelic variants <italic>A3-626a</italic>/<italic>b</italic>, <italic>A3-643</italic>, <italic>A3-567-1</italic>, <italic>A3-567-2</italic>, and <italic>A3-590</italic> contained intact ORFs, which might also be active in common wheat. Thus, in a particular wheat variety, 1&#x2013;3 LMW-GS genes might be active at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). For example, accessions with the genotype <italic>A3-391</italic>/<italic>A3-400</italic>/<italic>A3-502</italic>/<italic>A3-620</italic> contained only one active LMW-GS gene, <italic>A3-620</italic>, while those with the i-type haplotype <italic>A3-484</italic>/<italic>A3-565</italic>/<italic>A3-568</italic>/<italic>A3-662</italic> possessed three active genes at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>).</p>
        <p content-type="indent">At the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus, 3&#x2013;5 genes were detected in the genomic DNA of individual accessions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). Based on the electropherogram of the LMW-GS gene marker system, the <italic>B3-548</italic>, <italic>B3-578a</italic>/<italic>b</italic>, and <italic>B3-813</italic> genes were not detected in developing seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>), while the remaining m-type genes (<italic>B3-530</italic> and the newly identified <italic>B3-570</italic>) and s-type genes (<italic>B3-544</italic>, <italic>B3-621</italic>, and <italic>B3-688</italic>) were generally expressed in wheat varieties, although <italic>B3-570</italic> was only present in partial MCC accessions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). With regard to active genes of different haplotypes, the number of active <italic>Glu-B3</italic> genes varied from two to four in one wheat variety, including one or two m-type-encoding genes and one or two s-type-encoding genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>).</p>
        <p content-type="indent">At the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus, of the eight LMW-GS genes detected in genomic DNA, <italic>D3-385</italic>, <italic>D3-394</italic>, <italic>D3-441</italic>, <italic>D3-525</italic>, <italic>D3-575</italic>, and <italic>D3-578</italic> were detected in developing seeds of MCC accessions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>), and the rare allelic variants <italic>D3-397</italic>, <italic>D3-444</italic>, and <italic>D3-522</italic> might be active in their intact ORF. The remaining two genes, <italic>D3-393</italic> and <italic>D3-586</italic>, were not identified in the developing seeds probably due to premature stop codons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Thus, one s-type (<italic>D3-578</italic>) and five m-type genes (<italic>D3-385</italic>, <italic>D3-394</italic>, <italic>D3-441</italic>, <italic>D3-525</italic>, and <italic>D3-575</italic>) were generally expressed at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus in individual wheat varieties (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). These expression analyses revealed that individual accessions with different allelic variants or haplotypes might possess different numbers of active genes. Generally, none or one m-type and one or two i-type active genes were detected at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus, and one or two m-type and one or two s-type genes at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus were expressed, whereas one s-type and five m-type genes comprised the active genes at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus. Thus, the number of active genes in individual MCC accessions varied from nine to 13.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s12">
        <title>Characteristics of LMW-GS genes identified from MCC accessions</title>
        <p>All proteins encoded by the genes identified in the present study were typical of LMW-GS, which had similar structures to previously characterized LMW-GS (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">D&#x2019;Ovidio and Masci, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Juh&#xE1;sz and Gianibelli, 2006</xref>). Each deduced protein contained four main structural domains: a signal peptide, a short conserved N-terminal domain, a repetitive domain, and a C-terminal domain, except for i-type proteins, which lacked the N-terminal domain (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S11</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). Based on the N-terminal sequence of mature proteins, three types of LMW-GS (m-, s-, and i-types) were recognized. The m-type proteins were the most abundant in all genotypes analysed, and their molecular mass varied from 31.8kDa (D3-385) to 39.6kDa (D3-575). The s-type proteins generally had a higher molecular mass than did m-type subunits, which ranged from 37.0kDa (B3-544) to 42.5kDa (B3-691). Also, the i-type proteins had higher molecular weights (39.2&#x2013;43.0kDa), despite lacking the N-terminal sequences.</p>
        <p content-type="indent">Cysteine residues played a vital role in determining the structural and functional characteristics of wheat proteins (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Shewry <italic>et al</italic>., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">D&#x2019;Ovidio and Masci, 2004</xref>). All deduced proteins identified in this study possessed eight cysteine residues, except the putative amino acid sequences from pseudogenes <italic>A3-502d</italic> and <italic>D3-385&#x2019;</italic>, which contained seven and nine cysteine residues, respectively. However, both pseudogenes do not play a role in glutenin polymers and bread-making quality. The locations of the first (or third for i-type genes) and seventh cysteines were highly diverse, while the remaining six cysteines were conserved among all LMW-GS genes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S11</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). Based on the relative locations of cysteines, LMW-GS proteins were divided into six groups (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S11</ext-link>).</p>
        <p content-type="indent">All LMW-GS genes and their allelic variants were subjected to cluster analysis using ClustalW2 and MEGA 5. Also, the six main groups were further divided, which was consistent with the grouping data based on the cysteine positions of the deduced proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). The i-type genes located at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus formed a single group (i<sub>A</sub>), and all the s-type genes at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus and <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus were located in a single branch (s<sub>BD</sub>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). All the remaining LMW-GS genes were m-type, which were further divided into four groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Variants of both the <italic>D3-441</italic> and <italic>D3-525</italic> genes formed single groups (m<sub>D</sub>-2 and m<sub>D</sub>-1, respectively), which were unique at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus. The m<sub>BD</sub> group was composed of three genes (<italic>B3-530</italic>, <italic>B3-548</italic>, and <italic>B3-570</italic>) from the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus and two (<italic>D3-575</italic> and <italic>D3-586</italic>) from the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus. In contrast, the m<sub>AD</sub> group contained five m-type genes, two of which were located at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus and three at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus. Collectively, genes from the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus contained all the i-type genes (i<sub>A</sub>) and m-type genes (m<sub>AD</sub>), genes from the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus were associated with two groups, including s-type (s<sub>BD</sub>) and m-type (m<sub>BD</sub>) genes, and genes from the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus were distributed into five of the six groups and showed higher diversity than those at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> and <italic>Glu-B3</italic> loci (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p>
        <fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Phylogenetic reconstruction of all LMW-GS genes and their allelic variants identified from MCC accessions. The phylogenetic tree of LMW-GS genes was constructed using MEGA 5 (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Kumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). All LMW-GS genes were divided into six groups. The i-type genes located at <italic>Glu-A3</italic> were special and formed a single group (i<sub>A</sub>). The s-type genes at <italic>Glu-B3</italic> and <italic>Glu-D3</italic> shared high identity and were located in a single branch (s<sub>BD</sub>). The other LMW-GS genes were of the m-type, and were divided into four groups (m<sub>AD</sub>, m<sub>D-1</sub>, m<sub>BD</sub>, and m<sub>D-2</sub>). LMW-GS genes at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus were assigned to five groups, and showed a higher diversity than those at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> and <italic>Glu-B3</italic> loci. (This figure is available in colour at <italic>JXB</italic> online.)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert070_f0004"/>
        </fig>
        <p content-type="indent">Of the LMW-GS genes, i-type genes were the most complex and 12 haplotypes were detected, each of which contained unique LMW-GS genes. Sequence alignments and phylogenetic analysis of all i-type genes demonstrated that the <italic>A3-502</italic> gene was conserved (&gt;85% diversity) among the haplotypes, whereas the other genes could be divided into five subgroups (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S12</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). <italic>A3-626</italic> and <italic>A3-643</italic> shared high identity (&gt;98%) and formed the subgroup i<sub>A</sub>-1 with the <italic>A3-502</italic> gene. The haplotypes <italic>A3-502e/f</italic> and <italic>A3-646</italic> were named i<sub>A</sub>-2. The <italic>A3-502g</italic>/<italic>A3-573</italic>/<italic>A3-640</italic> and <italic>A3-502h</italic>/<italic>A3-649-1</italic>/<italic>A3-649-2</italic> haplotypes contained three i-type genes and were classified into subgroups i<sub>A</sub>-3 and i<sub>A</sub>-4, respectively. <italic>A3-484</italic>/<italic>A3-565</italic>/<italic>A3-568</italic>/<italic>A3-662</italic> and <italic>A3-487</italic>/<italic>A3-567-1</italic>/<italic>A3-567-2</italic>/<italic>A3-590</italic> represented a unique i-type genotype (i<sub>A</sub>-5) in common wheat (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S12</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s13">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>LMW-GS genes in common wheat are complex, and their exact copy number remains unclear (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Cassidy <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Ikeda <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Juh&#xE1;sz and Gianibelli, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Cloutier, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Recently, using BAC library screening, 14 and 19 genes were isolated from the common wheat varieties Xiaoyan 54 and Glenlea, respectively (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Cloutier, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Meanwhile, LMW-GS genes at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic>, <italic>Glu-B3</italic>, and <italic>Glu-D3</italic> loci were identified using gene-specific primers, which suggested that at least 12 genes are present in the common wheat genome (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Zhao <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Based on the conserved and polymorphic structures of these genes, the LMW-GS gene marker system and the full-length gene cloning method were developed, which can identify &gt;15 members of this gene family in common wheat (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>). In the present study, both methods were used to investigate the MCC of Chinese wheat germplasm, and the complex LMW-GS gene family in common wheat was successfully dissected.</p>
      <sec id="s14">
        <title>Dissection of LMW-GS genes at individual Glu-3 loci</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Glu-A3 locus</title>
          <p>Two m-type genes and 2&#x2013;4 i-type LMW-GS genes were generally identified at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus, which was the highest number reported for this locus in individual wheat varieties (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref>). The m-type gene, <italic>A3-391</italic>, and its allelic variants shared high identities (&gt;99%) with a few sequences in GenBank derived from <italic>T. macha</italic>, <italic>T. durum</italic>, and <italic>T. timopheevii</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online), which suggests that <italic>A3-391</italic> might be widely present in <italic>Triticum</italic>. The other m-type gene at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus, <italic>A3-400</italic>, was reported by several groups, corresponding to <italic>GluA3-2</italic> genes from Aroona near-isogenic lines (NILs) (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>), the group 6 type IV gene from Norin 61 (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Ikeda <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>), and <italic>A3-1</italic> from Xiaoyan 54 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>) (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). The present results provided direct evidence for the presence of m-type genes at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus in common wheat, and this gene showed high diversity among MCC accessions with several novel allelic variants (i.e. <italic>A3-374</italic>, <italic>A3-388</italic>, <italic>A3-394a</italic>, and <italic>A3-411</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>). Moreover, the new allelic variants, <italic>A3-388</italic>, <italic>A3-394a</italic>/<italic>b</italic>, <italic>A3-408</italic>, and <italic>A3-411</italic>, contained intact ORFs and may make specific contributions to wheat bread-making quality.</p>
          <sec id="s15">
            <title/>
            <p content-type="indent">In the present study, using conserved primers, 2&#x2013;4 i-type genes were identified in individual wheat varieties. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). In previous studies, 1&#x2013;3 i-type genes in only a few wheat varieties were characterized (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>) (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Ikeda <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Cloutier, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>), which made it difficult to analyse the relationships among haplotypes of these genes. Here, the MCC of Chinese wheat germplasm were investigated in terms of LMW-GS gene composition. The i-type genes were present in the wheat genome as haplotypes rather than single genes, and 12 haplotypes of i-type genes were detected in the MCC. Nucleotide sequence comparisons showed that genes in six of 12 haplotypes identified in this study were similar (&gt;99%) to those isolated from seven <italic>Glu-A3</italic> alleles, for example haplotype <italic>A3-502d</italic>/<italic>643</italic> corresponding to <italic>GluA3-32</italic>/<italic>Glu-A3-12</italic> from <italic>Glu-A3b</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>) (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). In addition, haplotype <italic>A3-484</italic>/<italic>A3-565</italic>/<italic>A3-568</italic>/<italic>A3-662</italic> contained the three i-type genes identified in Norin 61 and Xiaoyan 54 (<italic>A3-2</italic>, <italic>A3-3</italic>, and <italic>A3-4</italic>), and the haplotype <italic>A3-502f</italic>/<italic>646b</italic> covered the i-type gene detected in Glenlea (EU189087) (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Cloutier, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). This confirms that i-type genes in common wheat exist as haplotypes at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus and exhibit high genetic diversity. The identification and characterization of these haplotypes will facilitate the functional analysis of i-type genes and the selection of specific genes using haplotype-specific markers.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="s16">
            <title>Glu-B3 locus</title>
            <p>Three to five <italic>Glu-B3</italic> genes were detected in individual varieties, of which 1&#x2013;3 were s-type and two or three were m-type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>). The m-type gene <italic>B3-530</italic> shared &gt;99% sequence identity with <italic>GluB3-4</italic> genes from Aroona and its near-isogenic lines, the <italic>B3-1</italic> gene from Xiaoyan 54 and Jing 411, <italic>1557N24-M</italic> from Glenlea, and the group 2 type I gene from Norin 61 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online) (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Ikeda <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Cloutier, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>), while <italic>B3-548</italic> has been reported only rarely since it is a pseudogene. The third m-type gene, <italic>B3-570</italic>, was newly identified from wheat varieties and was detected in partial MCC accessions containing <italic>B3-510</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). Thus, at least two m-type genes were present at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus, rather than the one reported previously (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Ikeda <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Cloutier, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). The other genes at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus were of s-type, and were divided into two subgroups based on their gene composition; one containing the <italic>B3-688</italic> gene and the other containing <italic>B3-621</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>). The <italic>B3-688</italic> subgroup of s-type haplotypes corresponded to <italic>B3-2</italic> from Xiaoyan 54 as well as Jing 411 and <italic>GluB3-3</italic> from Aroona-<italic>Glu-B3c</italic>, <italic>B3d</italic>, <italic>B3h</italic>, and <italic>B3i</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>) (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). The other subgroup contained two active genes, <italic>B3-544</italic> and <italic>B3-621</italic>, and one pseudogene, <italic>B3-578</italic>. <italic>B3-544</italic> had 99% sequence identity with <italic>GluB3-1</italic> from Aroona-<italic>Glu-B3a</italic>, <italic>B3b</italic>, <italic>B3f</italic>, and <italic>B3g</italic>. Also, <italic>B3-621</italic> genes were present in Aroona<italic>-Glu-B3a</italic>, <italic>B3b</italic>, <italic>B3f</italic>, and <italic>B3g</italic>, corresponding to <italic>GluB3-2</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>). Thus, s-type genes existed as haplotypes in common wheat. However, both subgroups of s-type genes displayed significant differences in terms of gene composition and sequences, and thus might make different contributions to dough quality. Overall, evaluation of <italic>Glu-B3</italic> genes/haplotypes will enable development of haplotype-specific primers for marker-assisted selection.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s17">
          <title>Glu-D3 locus</title>
          <p>One s-type and seven m-type genes were identified at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus from a single wheat genotype, which was by far the highest number of LMW-GS genes reported for this locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). Pseudogene <italic>D3-586</italic> was newly detected in common wheat, whereas the other seven genes have been investigated extensively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online), and covered all <italic>Glu-D3</italic> genes identified in wheat varieties, including Norin 61, Glenlea, Xiaoyan 54, Jing 411, and Aroona NILs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>) (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Ikeda <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Zhao <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Cloutier, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>). These <italic>Glu-D3</italic> genes were highly conserved, with only a few allelic variants (&gt;99% identities), of which three novel active allelic variants (<italic>D3-397</italic>, <italic>D3-444</italic>, and <italic>D3-522</italic>) were detected with unique SNPs or indels in MCC, but functional analysis of these variants has been limited. Moreover, these <italic>Glu-D3</italic> genes shared &gt;97% identities with LMW-GS genes isolated from <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Johal <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>), which further confirmed the conservation of <italic>Glu-D3</italic> genes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s18">
          <title>Relative genetic locations of LMW-GS genes at the Glu-3 loci</title>
          <p>Typical LMW-GS genes were located at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic>, <italic>Glu-B3</italic>, and <italic>Glu-D3</italic> loci on the homoeologous group 1 chromosomes. However, little is known about the relative location of LMW-GS genes at individual loci due to the complexity of gene composition and the lack of appropriate methods of investigating this gene family. Recently, the recombination of 14 LMW-GS genes at <italic>Glu-3</italic> loci was analysed and the relative genetic position of these genes was determined (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Subsequently, four more genes were detected and sequenced in Xiaoyan 54 (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>). In the present study, based on the allelic relationship with the genes in Xiaoyan 54, all the LMW-GS genes in the MCC were located at a specific position in homoeologous group 1 chromosomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). At the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus, two groups of LMW-GS genes, m<sub>AD</sub> and i<sub>A</sub> gene clusters, were found and little recombination was detected within groups, of which the i<sub>A</sub> group was distal and the m<sub>AD</sub> group was proximal to the centromere (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). At the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus, although the relative position of <italic>A3-548</italic> was not determined, the m- and s-type genes might exist as two gene clusters (m<sub>BD</sub> and s<sub>BD</sub>). Also, m-type genes were more proximal to the centromere than s-type genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). At the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus, tight linkage was identified only between <italic>D3-441</italic> and <italic>D3-578a</italic> or <italic>D3-432</italic> and <italic>D3-578b</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>), which could be explained by the close physical proximity (15.9kb) of these genes (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Additionally, <italic>D3-385</italic>, <italic>D3-393</italic>, <italic>D3-394</italic>, and <italic>D3-525</italic> genes were located in close proximity and had a high identity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Based on the location and sequence analysis, LMW-GS genes that show high identity or belong to the same group may be tightly linked and located at the same position in the <italic>Glu-3</italic> loci.</p>
          <fig fig-type="figure" id="F5" position="float">
            <label>Fig. 5.</label>
            <caption>
              <p>Organization of the LMW-GS genes in homoeologous group 1 chromosomes. The relative locations of genes or haplotypes were determined based on <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>. (2010)</xref>. The main allelic variants are displayed as representatives. The distances among genes do not represent the genetic or physical distances. (A) Relative genetic positions of LMW-GS genes at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus. The i-type genes were tightly linked at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus and formed five haplotype subgroups, and both m-type genes also generally co-segregated in the MCC. (B) Relative genetic positions of LMW-GS genes at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus. The s-type genes were coupled at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus and were of two principal haplotypes. (C) Relative genetic positions of the eight LMW-GS genes at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus. Of these, only <italic>D3-411</italic> and <italic>D3-578</italic> were tightly linked.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert070_f0005"/>
          </fig>
          <p content-type="indent">In addition, twelve i-type haplotypes at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus could be divided into five subgroups (i<sub>A</sub>-1 to i<sub>A</sub>-5; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S12</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online), and s-type haplotypes at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus were divided into two subgroups, revealing the high diversity of the i- and s-type genes/haplotypes among wheat varieties. These subgroups were significantly different in terms of gene numbers and sequences, which suggests that the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> and <italic>Glu-B3</italic> loci in common wheat might be derived from several unique ancestors or have been involved in significant mutational or recombination events during the course of their evolution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">5</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s19">
          <title>The complex LMW-GS gene family in Chinese wheat germplasm</title>
          <p>The LMW-GS gene family was investigated using the MCC of Chinese wheat germplasm, which consists of 262 accessions with an estimated 70% genetic diversity compared with the full collection (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Hao <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). Using the MCC, most (&gt;15) LMW-GS genes were identified in individual wheat varieties. This allowed investigation of the classification and relationship of these genes in Chinese wheat germplasm.</p>
          <p content-type="indent">The i-type genes were reported only at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Ikeda <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Cloutier, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>) or the A genome, for example <italic>T. urartu</italic> and <italic>T. monococcum</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">An <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Ma <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Caballero <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Long <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). The findings also indicate that all i-type genes detected in MCC accessions were located at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Since i-type genes lacked the sequences encoding the N-terminal domain, m- and s-type genes without the N-terminal domain-coding sequences were used for the phylogenetic analysis. It was found that i-type genes had a closer relationship with s-type genes (s<sub>BD</sub>) than m-type genes, excluding the m<sub>D</sub>-2 group (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S13</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). This results confirmed that the i-type genes may be the result of a deletion event of s-type genes (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>), and the i-type genes comprised a relatively young group of LMW-GS genes (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Juh&#xE1;sz and Gianibelli, 2006</xref>). The s-type genes were distributed at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> and <italic>Glu-D3</italic> loci in common wheat and the progenitor of the wheat A genome, <italic>T. urartu</italic> (data not shown), but not at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus in common wheat (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). This suggests that their disappearance from the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus might be the result of elimination at the polyploid level. The m-type genes were common at the <italic>Glu-3</italic> loci, and the difference between the s- and m-types was not significant (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">D&#x2019;Ovidio and Masci, 2004</xref>). The <italic>D3-441</italic> gene (m<sub>D</sub>-2) and s-type genes were located at the same main branch, although they belonged to different groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). These data confirm that the s-type genes probably originated from m-type genes due to mutation of MET to MEN in the N-terminal region (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Masci <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">D&#x2019;Ovidio and Masci, 2004</xref>). This also suggests that the m-type genes might be the oldest type of LMW-GS gene.</p>
          <p content-type="indent">Genome sequence analysis of <italic>Glu-3</italic> loci revealed that both i-type and s-type genes/haplotypes existed together with the <italic>Pm3</italic> analogue and genetic marker <italic>SFR159</italic>, while most m-type genes, m<sub>AD</sub>, m<sub>D</sub>-1, and m<sub>BD</sub>, were tightly linked with another genetic marker, <italic>WHS179</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Wicker <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Moreover, at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> and <italic>B3</italic> loci, i-type and s-type genes were distal, while the m<sub>AD</sub> and m<sub>BD</sub> groups of genes were proximal to the centromere (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>) (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). At the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus, the s-type gene <italic>D3-578</italic> was also more distal to the centromere than the m<sub>BD</sub> gene, <italic>D3-575</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>) (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Thus, the phylogenetic analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S13</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online), together with the linked genes/markers and their relative locations on chromosomes, suggest that i-type and s-type genes may have been derived from similar ancestral genes, and the m<sub>AD</sub> (only <italic>Glu-A3</italic> genes) and m<sub>BD</sub> groups of genes were orthologues among the A, B, and D subgenomes.</p>
          <p content-type="indent">After sequence alignment and clustering analysis, the LMW-GS genes detected in MCC accessions were divided into six groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). The genes at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus were assigned to the i<sub>A</sub> and m<sub>AD</sub> groups, and those at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus were divided into the s<sub>BD</sub> and m<sub>BD</sub> groups, whereas those at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus were distributed widely among the m<sub>D-1</sub>, m<sub>D-2</sub>, s<sub>BD</sub>, m<sub>BD</sub>, and m<sub>AD</sub> groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Thus, the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> genes showed higher diversity than those at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> or <italic>Glu-B3</italic> loci in individual wheat varieties. The <italic>Glu-A3</italic> locus did not share the same group of LMW-GS genes as the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>), which suggested that genes at the <italic>Glu-A3</italic> and <italic>Glu-B3</italic> loci evolved through different routes and had a distant evolutionary relationship. All genes at the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> locus and three <italic>Glu-D3</italic> genes comprised two groups (s<sub>BD</sub> and m<sub>BD</sub>); these homoeoalleles showed close relationships between the <italic>Glu-B3</italic> and <italic>Glu-D3</italic> loci, which were consistent with the derivation of BB and DD subgenomes from <italic>Aegilops</italic>.</p>
          <p content-type="indent">Analysis of the LMW-GS gene family was performed using MCC accessions, consisting of foreign varieties, Chinese modern varieties, and landraces. The novel i-type haplotype, <italic>A3-502h</italic>/<italic>A3-649-1</italic>/<italic>A3-649-2</italic> was detected only in landraces and were absent from Chinese modern or foreign wheat varieties (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). This also occurred for genotypes containing <italic>B3-624</italic> and the genotype <italic>B3-530</italic>/<italic>B3-548</italic>/<italic>B3-688</italic>/<italic>B3-691</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). Although these haplotypes possessed an equal number of active genes to other haplotypes, they have not been selected for use in modern wheat breeding programmes. This may be because these genes or those linked to them have a detrimental effect on bread-making quality or yield potential. In contrast, <italic>A3-394a</italic>/<italic>b</italic>, <italic>B3-601</italic>/<italic>604</italic>, and the genotypes <italic>D3-385</italic>/<italic>D3-376</italic>/-/<italic>D3-432</italic>/-/<italic>D3-575</italic>/<italic>D3-578a</italic>/-, and 1BL/1RS lines were present only in modern or foreign varieties. The presence of these genes/genotypes in Chinese modern varieties might be the result of incorporation of foreign germplasm in breeding programmes in the past several decades. For example, the elite 1BL/1RS translocation lines were introduced into China in the 1970s and were exploited in modern wheat breeding since they contain several disease resistance and yield improvement genes. Also, the other genes/genotypes were probably introduced into Chinese wheat germplasm since they (or linked genes) increased the yield potential or bread-making quality.</p>
          <p content-type="indent">Using the LMW-GS gene marker system and full-length gene cloning method, a representative population (MCC) was investigated, and the composition, organization, variation, and expression of LMW-GS genes were evaluated. Furthermore, the LMW-GS genes corresponding to all DNA fragments from the LMW-GS gene marker system were identified (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Supplementary S1</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). The expression profile of these genes was revealed by comparing the genomic DNA and cDNA data. These data will facilitate the update of the LMW-GS gene marker system which can be used to separate, identify, and characterize LMW-GS genes efficiently in common wheat.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s20">
      <title>Supplementary data</title>
      <p>Supplementary data are available at <italic>JXB</italic> online.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Figure S1.</ext-link> Sequence alignments of the <italic>A3-391</italic> gene identified in the MCC.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Figure S2.</ext-link> Sequence alignments of the <italic>A3-400</italic> gene identified in the MCC.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Figure S3.</ext-link> Sequence alignments of the <italic>A3-502</italic> gene identified in the MCC.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Figure S4.</ext-link> Sequence alignments of the <italic>B3-530</italic> gene identified in the MCC.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Figure S5.</ext-link> Sequence alignments of the <italic>B3-544</italic> gene identified in the MCC.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Figure S6.</ext-link> Sequence alignments of the <italic>B3-621</italic> and <italic>B3-688</italic> genes identified in the MCC.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Figure S7.</ext-link> Sequence alignments of the <italic>D3-441</italic> gene identified in the MCC.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Figure S8.</ext-link> Sequence alignments of the <italic>D3-525</italic> gene identified in the MCC.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Figure S9.</ext-link> Sequence alignments of the <italic>D3-578</italic> gene identified in the MCC.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Figure S10.</ext-link> Sequence alignments of the <italic>D3-586</italic> gene identified in the MCC.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Figure S11.</ext-link> Sequence alignments of the deduced proteins of 15 representative LMW-GS genes from MCC accessions.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Figure S12.</ext-link> Phylogenetic reconstruction of all i-type LMW-GS genes and their allelic variants identified from MCC accessions.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Figure S13.</ext-link> Phylogenetic reconstruction of all LMW-GS genes and their allelic variants with removed sequences coding for N-terminal domains.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Table S1.</ext-link> Gene-specific primers used for cloning rare allelic variants.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert070/-/DC1">Table S2.</ext-link> Nucleotide sequence identities of LMW-GS genes from MCC to the previously reported <italic>Glu-A3</italic>, <italic>B3</italic>, and <italic>D3</italic> alleles/genes.</p>
      <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Data</title>
        </caption>
        <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_64_7_2027__index.html"/>
        <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_ert070_jexbot089565_file001.pdf"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank Professor Moshe Feldman (The Weizmann Institute of Science, Rehovot, Israel) for constructive suggestions on this work. This work was supported by the Ministry of Science and Technology of China (2009CB118300) and the Ministry of Agriculture of China for transgenic research (2013ZX08009-003-004 and 2013ZX08002-004).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Cloning and molecular characterization of three novel LMW-i glutenin subunit genes from cultivated einkorn (<italic>Triticum monococcum</italic> L.)</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>113</volume>,
<fpage>383</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>395</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16775696</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Appelbee</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekuria</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagasandra</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonneau</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Eagles</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eastwood</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mather</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Novel allelic variants encoded at the <italic>Glu-D3</italic> locus in bread wheat</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Cereal Science</source><volume>49</volume>,
<fpage>254</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>261</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bekes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemeny</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Morell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>An integrated approach to predicting end-product quality of wheat</article-title>.
<source>European Journal of Agronomy</source><volume>25</volume>,
<fpage>155</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>162</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Branlard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dardevet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saccomano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagoutte</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gourdon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Genetic diversity of wheat storage proteins and bread wheat quality</article-title>.
<source>Euphytica</source><volume>119</volume>,
<fpage>59</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>67</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caballero</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Allelic variation for the high- and low-molecular-weight glutenin subunits in wild diploid wheat (<italic>Triticum urartu</italic>) and its comparison with durum wheats</article-title>.
<source>Australian Journal of Agricultural Research</source><volume>59</volume>,
<fpage>906</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>910</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cassidy</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dvorak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>The wheat low-molecular-weight glutenin genes: characterization of six new genes and progress in understanding gene family structure</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>96</volume>,
<fpage>743</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>750</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x2019;Ovidio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Masci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>The low-molecular-weight glutenin subunits of wheat gluten</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Cereal Science</source><volume>39</volume>,
<fpage>321</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>339</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>New insights into the organization, recombination, expression and functional mechanism of low molecular weight glutenin subunit genes in bread wheat</article-title>.
<source>PLoS One</source><volume>5</volume>,
<fpage>e13548</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20975830</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eagles</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollamby</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gororo</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Eastwood</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Estimation and utilisation of glutenin gene effects from the analysis of unbalanced data from wheat breeding programs</article-title>.
<source>Australian Journal of Agricultural Research</source><volume>53</volume>,
<fpage>367</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>377</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Rapid evolution and complex structural organization in genomic regions harboring multiple prolamin genes in the polyploid wheat genome</article-title>.
<source>Plant Molecular Biology</source><volume>65</volume>,
<fpage>189</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>203</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17629796</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0011">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bekes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wrigley</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Prediction of physical dough properties from glutenin subunit composition in bread wheats&#x2014;correlation studies</article-title>.
<source>Cereal Chemistry</source><volume>68</volume>,
<fpage>328</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>333</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0012">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornish</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bekes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathjen</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Allelic variation at glutenin subunit and gliadin loci, <italic>Glu-1, Glu-3</italic> and <italic>Gli-1</italic>, of common wheat. 1. Its additive and interaction effects on dough properties</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Cereal Science</source><volume>19</volume>,
<fpage>9</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>17</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0013">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Genetic diversity and linkage disequilibrium in Chinese bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) revealed by SSR markers</article-title>.
<source>PLoS One</source><volume>6</volume>,
<fpage>e17279</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21365016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0014">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pena</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Composition of HMW and LMW glutenin subunits and their effects on dough properties, pan bread, and noodle quality of Chinese bread wheats</article-title>.
<source>Cereal Chemistry</source><volume>82</volume>,
<fpage>345</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>350</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0015">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howitt</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Juh&#xE1;sz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Diagnostic markers for quality</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Wrigley</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#xE9;k&#xE9;s</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bushuk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Gliadin and glutenin. The unique balance of wheat quality</source>.
<publisher-loc>St Paul, MN</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>AACCI Press</publisher-name>,
<fpage>333</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>361</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0016">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cloutier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Molecular characterization and genomic organization of low molecular weight glutenin subunit genes at the <italic>Glu-3</italic> loci in hexaploid wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>116</volume>,
<fpage>953</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>966</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18305921</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0017">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Characterization of low-molecular-weight glutenin subunit genes and their protein products in common wheats</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>112</volume>,
<fpage>327</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>334</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16283233</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0018">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagamine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Identification of new low-molecular-weight glutenin subunit genes in wheat</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>104</volume>,
<fpage>680</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>687</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12582674</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0019">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name></person-group><year>1983</year><article-title>Characterization of high molecular-weight gliadin and low-molecular-weight glutenin subunits of wheat endosperm by two-dimensional electrophoresis and the chromosomal localization of their controlling genes</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>66</volume>,
<fpage>29</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>37</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24263628</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0020">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gianibelli</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Morell</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Characterization of low-molecular-weight glutenin genes in <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>
</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>109</volume>,
<fpage>1028</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1040</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15164175</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0021">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juh&#xE1;sz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gianibelli</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Low-molecular-weight glutenin subunits: insights into this abundant subunit group present in glutenin polymers</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Wrigley</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#xE9;k&#xE9;s</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bushuk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Gliadin and glutenin. The unique balance of wheat quality</source>.
<publisher-loc>St Paul, MN</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>AACCI Press</publisher-name>,
<fpage>171</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>212</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0022">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>MEGA: a biologist-centric software for evolutionary analysis of DNA and protein sequences</article-title>.
<source>Briefings in Bioinformatics</source><volume>9</volume>,
<fpage>299</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>306</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417537</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0023">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Branlard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Comparison of low molecular weight glutenin subunits identified by SDS&#x2013;PAGE, 2-DE, MALDI-TOF-MS and PCR in common wheat</article-title>.
<source>BMC Plant Biology</source><volume>10</volume>,
<fpage>124</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20573275</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0024">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>ZC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Length variation of i-type low-molecular-weight glutenin subunit genes in diploid wheats</article-title>.
<source>Russian Journal of Genetics</source><volume>44</volume>,
<fpage>429</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>435</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0025">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>ZC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Characterization of low-molecular-weight i-type glutenin subunit genes from diploid wheat in relation to the gene family structure</article-title>.
<source>Molecular Biology</source><volume>40</volume>,
<fpage>897</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>906</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0026">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x2019;Ovidio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafiandra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasarda</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Characterization of a low-molecular-weight glutenin subunit gene from bread wheat and the corresponding protein that represents a major subunit of the glutenin polymer</article-title>.
<source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>118</volume>,
<fpage>1147</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1158</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9847089</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0027">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year><article-title>Genetics of wheat storage proteins and the effect of allelic variation on bread-making quality</article-title>.
<source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology and Plant Molecular Biology</source><volume>38</volume>,
<fpage>141</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>153</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0028">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saghai-Maroof</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Soliman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1984</year><article-title>Ribosomal DNA spacer-length polymorphisms in barley: mendelian inheritance, chromosomal location, and population dynamics</article-title>.
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>81</volume>,
<fpage>8014</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8018</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0029">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shewry</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Wheat</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>60</volume>,
<fpage>1537</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1553</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19386614</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0030">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shewry</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatham</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Barro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Barcelo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazzeri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Biotechnology of breadmaking: unraveling and manipulating the multi-protein gluten complex</article-title>.
<source>Nature Biotechnology</source><volume>13</volume>,
<fpage>1185</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1190</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0031">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornish</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>A simplified SDS&#x2013;PAGE procedure for separating LMW subunits of glutenin</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Cereal Science</source><volume>14</volume>,
<fpage>203</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>208</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0032">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Pena</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Development of STS markers and establishment of multiplex PCR for <italic>Glu-A3</italic> alleles in common wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Cereal Science</source><volume>51</volume>,
<fpage>305</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>312</lpage>.
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0033">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Appels</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pena</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Characterization of low-molecular-weight glutenin subunit <italic>Glu-B3</italic> genes and development of STS markers in common wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>118</volume>,
<fpage>525</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>539</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18989655</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0034">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wicker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yahiaoui</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlagenhauf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubcovsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Rapid genome divergence at orthologous low molecular weight glutenin loci of the A and A(m) genomes of wheat</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>15</volume>,
<fpage>1186</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1197</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724543</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0035">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gianibelli</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rampling</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Characterisation and marker development for low molecular weight glutenin genes from <italic>Glu-A3</italic> alleles of bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>. L)</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>108</volume>,
<fpage>1409</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1419</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14727031</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0036">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>HQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011a</year><article-title>PCR-based isolation and identification of full-length low-molecular-weight glutenin subunit genes in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>123</volume>,
<fpage>1293</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1305</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21830110</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0037">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Composition and functional analysis of low-molecular-weight glutenin alleles with Aroona near-isogenic lines of bread wheat</article-title>.
<source>BMC Plant Biology</source><volume>12</volume>,
<fpage>243</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23259617</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0038">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>HQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011b</year><article-title>Development of a new marker system for identifying the complex members of the low-molecular-weight glutenin subunit gene family in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>122</volume>,
<fpage>1503</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1516</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21344181</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0039">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name><surname>Appels</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Characterization of three low-molecular-weight <italic>Glu-D3</italic> subunit genes in common wheat</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>113</volume>,
<fpage>1247</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1259</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16941095</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0040">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name><surname>Appels</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>QX</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Novel DNA variations to characterize low molecular weight glutenin <italic>Glu-D3</italic> genes and develop STS markers in Common Wheat</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>114</volume>,
<fpage>451</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>460</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17106734</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
