<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3637298</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-08221</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Agriculture</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Agricultural Production</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Green Revolution</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Crops</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cereals</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Triticale</subject>
                <subject>Wheat</subject>
                <subject>Wheats</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Plant Science</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Agronomy</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Plant Breeding</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Botany</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Plant Morphology</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plants</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Flowers</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plant Genetics</subject>
              <subject>Plant Growth and Development</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>GA-Responsive Dwarfing Gene <italic>Rht12</italic> Affects the Developmental and Agronomic Traits in Common Bread Wheat</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Rht12 Affects the Agronomic Traits in Wheat</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Liang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Phillips</surname>
            <given-names>Andrew L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Condon</surname>
            <given-names>Anthony G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Parry</surname>
            <given-names>Martin A. J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>Yin-Gang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Crop Stress Biology for Arid Areas and College of Agronomy, Northwest A&amp;F University, Yangling, Shaanxi, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Plant Biology and Crop Science, Rothamsted Research, Harpenden, Herts, United Kingdom</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>CSIRO Plant Industry, Canberra, Australia</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff4">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line>Institute of Water Saving Agriculture in Arid Regions of China, Northwest A&amp;F University, Yangling, Shaanxi, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Blazquez</surname>
            <given-names>Miguel A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Instituto de Biolog&#xED;a Molecular y Celular de Plantas, Spain</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>huyingang@nwsuaf.edu.cn</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: YGH AGC LC. Performed the experiments: LC YGH AGC. Analyzed the data: LC YGH ALP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YGH LC AGC. Wrote the paper: LC YGH ALP MAJP.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <elocation-id>e62285</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Chen et al</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title/>
          <p>Opportunities exist for replacing reduced height (<italic>Rht</italic>) genes <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> with alternative dwarfing genes, such as the gibberellin-responsive gene <italic>Rht12</italic>, for bread wheat improvement. However, a comprehensive understanding of the effects and mode of action of <italic>Rht12</italic> is lacking. In the present study, the effects of <italic>Rht12</italic> were characterized by analyzing its effects on seeding vigour, seedling roots, leaf and stem morphology, spike development and carbohydrate assimilation and distribution. This was carried out in the four genotypes of F<sub>2:3</sub> lines derived from a cross between Ningchun45 and Karcagi (12) in two experiments of autumn sowing and spring sowing. <italic>Rht12</italic> significantly decreased stem length (43%&#x223C;48% for peduncle) and leaf length (25%&#x223C;30% for flag leaf) while the thickness of the internode walls and width of the leaves were increased. Though the final plant stature was shortened (40%) by <italic>Rht12</italic>, the seedling vigour, especially coleoptile length and root traits at the seedling stage, were not affected adversely. <italic>Rht12</italic> elongated the duration of the spike development phase, improved the proportion of spike dry weight at anthesis and significantly increased floret fertility (14%) in the autumn sowing experiment. However, <italic>Rht12</italic> delayed anthesis date by around 5 days and even the dominant <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> allele could not compensate this negative effect. Additionally, grain size was reduced with the ability to support spike development after anthesis decreased in <italic>Rht12</italic> lines. Finally, grain yield was similar between the dwarf and tall lines in the autumn sowing experiment. Thus, <italic>Rht12</italic> could substantially reduce plant height without altering seeding vigour and significantly increase spikelet fertility in the favourable autumn sowing environment. The successful utilization of <italic>Rht12</italic> in breeding programs will require careful selection since it might delay ear emergence. Nonetheless, the potential exists for wheat improvement by using <italic>Rht12</italic>.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by the sub-project of the 863 Program (2011AA100504, 2013AA102902) of the Ministry of Science and Technology, the key project of Chinese Universities Scientific Fund, Northwest A&amp;F University (ZD2012002) and the China 111 Project (B12007), P. R. China, as well as the ACIAR Project (CIM/2005/111) of Australia. ALP and MAJP are supported by the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council (BBSRC) of the UK under the 20&#x2236;20 Wheat&#xAE; Institute Strategic Programme. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="16"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The introduction of semi-dwarfing genes into wheat was a major event in breeding high yielding varieties during the Green Revolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Hedden1">[1]</xref>. The greater grain yields were associated with improved lodging resistance and the resulting ability to tolerate higher rates of chemical fertilizers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Worland1">[2]</xref>, and also with increased harvest index <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Miralles1">[3]</xref>. The gibberellin acid (GA) insensitive semi-dwarfing genes <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> (<italic>Rht1</italic>) and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> (<italic>Rht2</italic>) are widely used to reduce plant height and increase grain yield in wheat breeding programs. <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> reduce stem internode length and therefore overall plant height by decreasing the sensitivity of vegetative and reproductive tissues to endogenous GA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Keyes1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke1">[5]</xref>. However, reduced stature also contributes to reduced seedling vigour and coleoptile length and may reduce crop water-use efficiency <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Allan1">[6]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Botwright1">[9]</xref>, and performance in unfavourable environments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Butler1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Chapman1">[11]</xref>. Longer coleoptiles may permit crops to be sown at the optimal time to increase biomass and yield <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Shackley1">[12]</xref> while deep sowing of short coleoptile <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> alleles commonly results in fewer, later emerging seedlings with low relative growth rates, leaf area and biomass <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke3">[13]</xref>, and ultimately lower final biomass, fewer spikes and yield <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke3">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Mahdi1">[14]</xref>. But, in irrigated and fertilised environments, the height reduction associated with <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> may not be sufficient. Excessive height and severe lodging can occur in semi-dwarf varieties carrying these alleles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Berry1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Stapper1">[16]</xref>. Further, genetic reductions in plant height of the <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>+<italic>Rht-D1b</italic> doubled-dwarfs usually produce much less biomass and result in slow development of seedling leaf area though they significantly reduced lodging and have a greater harvest index <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Richards1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Butler1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Flintham1">[17]</xref>. A range of dwarfing genes is needed at our disposal to achieve the appropriate height reduction for different environments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Richards1">[7]</xref>. The modest height-reducing gene <italic>Rht8</italic> may be suitable to reduce final plant height without compromising early plant growth. <italic>Rht8</italic> has been used in breeding programs in different environments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Worland2">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Zhang1">[19]</xref> as it has no effect on coleoptile length or seedling vigour <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke4">[20]</xref> and there is potential for developing shorter <italic>Rht8</italic>+<italic>Rht-B1b</italic>/<italic>D1b</italic> sesqui-dwarfs with reduced lodging susceptibility and without limiting crop establishment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke5">[21]</xref>. Preliminary evidence indicates the potential of several other GA-responsive dwarfing genes, including <italic>Rht4</italic>, <italic>Rht5</italic>, <italic>Rht9</italic>, <italic>Rht12</italic>, <italic>Rht13</italic> and <italic>Rht14</italic>, to reduce plant height without affecting seedling vigour <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Ellis1">[22]</xref>. It is currently not clear whether these alternative dwarfing genes can be used to improve wheat yield and lodging tolerance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Ellis2">[23]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The life cycle of wheat can be divided into phases based on the main organs being differentiated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Slafer1">[24]</xref>. The pre-anthesis late reproductive phase (from terminal spikelet initiation to anthesis) of stem elongation is particularly important for yield <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Fischer1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Gonzalez1">[26]</xref> because the number of fertile florets at anthesis will be determined during this phase. Wheat yield can be improved through increasing the duration of the late reproductive phase by manipulation of spike developmental rates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Slafer2">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Slafer3">[28]</xref>. The developmental phases prior to anthesis may be sensitive to the environment (photoperiod or temperature) that they encounter or the concentrations of different endogenous hormones (gibberellin, auxin or cytokinin) associated with development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Yamaguchi1">[29]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Fleet1">[32]</xref>. Indeed, several dwarfing genes are associated with lesions in GA biosynthesis or signalling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Pearce1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Gasperini1">[34]</xref>. The possibility exists that the duration of spike development phases can be optimised using dwarfing genes, as done with genes affecting photoperiod or vernalization requirement <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Gonzalez1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Cockram1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Prasil1">[36]</xref>. Previous reports have shown that GA-insensitive dwarfing genes have no effect on the initiation of leaf and spikelet primordia at the shoot apex nor on the number of leaves and internodes. The primary effect of these dwarf genes on growth is to reduce the rate of leaf expansion, stem elongation and vegetative dry matter accumulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Youssefian1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Calderini1">[38]</xref>. However, the effects of GA-responsive dwarfing genes on plant growth and spike development have not been investigated and the potential of optimising the duration of late reproductive phase to improve ear fertility using GA-responsive dwarfing genes is unknown. Additionally, winter wheat requires several weeks at low temperature to flower. This process, vernalization, is controlled by three major genes, <italic>Vrn-A1</italic>, <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> and <italic>Vrn-D1</italic> which locate to the long arm of chromosomes 5A, 5B, and 5D, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Iwaki1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Law1">[40]</xref>. The spring habit alleles at these loci are dominant while recessive alleles at all three loci determine winter growth habit <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Yan1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Chen1">[42]</xref>. The dominant <italic>Vrn-A1</italic> allele provides complete insensitivity to vernalization (achieving the double ridge stage without low temperature) whereas the dominant <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> and <italic>Vrn-D1</italic> alleles each provide a reduced vernalization requirement compared to winter alleles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Pugsley1">[43]</xref>. Thus, these genes can be used to modify the flowering time in wheat.</p>
      <p><italic>Rht12</italic>, a dominant GA-responsive dwarfing gene from the gamma ray induced mutant Karcagi 522M7K of winter wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Viglasi1">[44]</xref>, has been shown to be located distally in the long arm of chromosome 5A, approximately 5.4 cM from locus Xwms291 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Sutka1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Korzun1">[46]</xref>. <italic>Rht12</italic> has been described as having few negative effects on yield components and, with a reduction of height by around 46% <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Viglasi1">[44]</xref>, it has a stronger effect on height than either <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> or <italic>Rht-D1b.</italic> Worland et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Worland1">[2]</xref> reported that <italic>Rht12</italic> reduced height without altering ear size and significantly increased spikelet fertility, but this was always accompanied by delayed ear emergence. There was no significant difference in early root growth and root architecture between <italic>Rht12</italic> dwarf lines and the control lines, but the effects on total root length were still unclear due to the different background or experimental methodology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Wojciechowski1">[47]</xref>. Recently, it was found that <italic>Rht12</italic> increased grain yield, harvest index and lodging resistance while reducing grain weight <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke5">[21]</xref>. However, it is still difficult to evaluate the effects of <italic>Rht12</italic> comprehensively, which would include effects on vegetative organs, spike development or other agronomic traits. Moreover, <italic>Rht12</italic> has not been used in wheat breeding, and its full potential remains uncertain.</p>
      <p>The objectives of this work were to analyse the effect of <italic>Rht12</italic> on leaf and stem morphology, phenological development up to anthesis and on agronomic traits and yield components. Due to the late ear emergence associated with the <italic>Rht12</italic> allele, the dominant <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> gene was introduced from a tall, spring-habit parent to analyse the effect of <italic>Rht12</italic> on spike development.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>General Description</title>
        <p>The experiments were carried out during the two growing seasons of 2010&#x2013;2011 and 2011&#x2013;2012 in the experimental field of the Institute of Water Saving Agriculture in Arid Regions of China, Northwest A&amp;F University, Yangling, Shaanxi, China (34&#xB0;17&#x2032; N, 108&#xB0;04&#x2032; E, at an elevation of 506 m). To avoid water stress, supplemental irrigation was provided as needed. Weeds were manually removed where necessary, and fungicides and insecticides were applied to prevent diseases and insect damage. Weather data were recorded at an automated weather station at the site.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Plant Material</title>
        <p>A cross was made using Ningchun 45 as the female and Karcagi (12) as pollen donor in May, 2009. Wheat seeds of Karcagi (12) (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.), a gamma ray-induced mutant carrying the dominant GA-responsive dwarfing gene <italic>Rht12</italic> and strong winter habit as detected with the recessive loci for all three <italic>Vrn-1</italic> genes, were generously provided by the Australian Winter Cereal Collection. Ningchun 45 (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.), is a tall Chinese spring wheat cultivar widely used in the semi-arid areas of Northwest Spring Wheat Region of China, which carries the dominant vernalization gene <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> and lacks any known dwarfing genes as detected by molecular markers.</p>
        <p>The F<sub>2</sub> population was sown as spaced plants in the field in October, 2010. The individuals of the F<sub>2</sub> population were numbered, the plant height and other agronomic traits of each individual were recorded, and the presence or absence of the loci for the dwarfing gene <italic>Rht12</italic> and vernalization gene <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> in each numbered individual was determined using the corresponding molecular markers (see below for details). The individuals with the four kinds of homozygous genotypes of <italic>Rht12Rht12Vrn-B1Vrn-B1</italic> (abbreviated as RRBB), <italic>Rht12Rht12vrn-B1vrn-B1</italic> (RRbb), <italic>rht12rht12Vrn-B1Vrn-B1</italic> (rrBB) and <italic>rht12rht12vrn-B1vrn-B1</italic> (rrbb) were then selected and used to develop the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines for further analysis.</p>
        <p>The two parents and 57 F<sub>2:3</sub> homozygous lines were used in experiments to evaluate the effects of dwarfing gene <italic>Rht12</italic> in the 2011&#x2013;2012 growing season. There were two sowing dates: October 6, 2011 (Autumn Sowing, AS) and February 6, 2012 (Spring Sowing, SS). Among those F<sub>2:3</sub> homozygous lines, 15, 13, 17 and 12 lines had the genotypes <italic>Rht12Rht12Vrn-B1Vrn-B1</italic>, <italic>Rht12Rht12vrn-B1vrn-B1</italic>, <italic>rht12rht12Vrn-B1Vrn-B1</italic>, and <italic>rht12rht12vrn-B1vrn-B1</italic>, respectively, as identified in the F<sub>2</sub> population. The lines and parents were sown in plots of four rows 2 m long and 25 cm apart, with seeds spaced 5 cm apart within rows. The parents and the 28 dwarf and 29 tall F<sub>2:3</sub> lines were randomly arranged to avoid competitive effects with two replications.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Genotyping of <italic>Rht12</italic> and <italic>Vrn-B1</italic></title>
        <p>The molecular markers WMS291 (Xgwm291) and Intr1-B-F/Intr1-B-R3/Intr1-B-R4 were used to determine the genotypes of individuals for the presence or absence of the dwarfing gene <italic>Rht12</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Korzun1">[46]</xref> and the vernalization gene <italic>Vrn-B1</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Fu1">[48]</xref> in the individual plants of the F<sub>2</sub> population, respectively.</p>
        <p>Genomic DNA from young leaves was isolated from the two parents and each F<sub>2</sub> individual using the CTAB method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Aldrich1">[49]</xref>. DNA concentrations were measured using a spectrophotometer and normalized to 50 ng/&#xB5;L. The PCR protocols for the three markers were as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Korzun1">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Fu1">[48]</xref>. The PCR profiles were: an initial denaturation at 95&#xB0;C for 2 min was followed by 40 cycles at 94&#xB0;C for 20 s, 55&#xB0;C, 63&#xB0;C and 58&#xB0;C (for the three markers, respectively) for 30 s, 72&#xB0;C for 90 s and a final extension of 72&#xB0;C for 5 min. PCR products for SSR marker Xgwm291 were visualized on a 8% polyacrylamide gel (19&#x2236;1 of Acrylamide to bis ratio) in 1&#xD7;TBE buffer at 250V for 1.5 h, then stained by silver buffer using a modified procedure described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Chen2">[50]</xref>. PCR products for Intr1-B-F and Intr1-B-R3 or R4 were separated on 1% agarose gels with 1&#xD7;TAE buffer at 115 V for 40 min, stained in an ethidium bromide buffer for 15 min, and then visualized by Gel Doc XR (BioRad Laboratories, Inc.).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Coleoptile Length and Seedling Root Traits</title>
        <p>Coleoptile length from the seed to the tip of the coleoptile was measured with a ruler after germination in a darkened growth chamber at 20&#xB0;C after 200&#xB0;Cd using the method described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Botwright2">[51]</xref>. Seedling root growth characteristics were assessed using a &#x2018;Cigar&#x2019; method as follows. Five grains of each line were arranged in a line (3 cm from the upper edge) on a 32&#xD7;29 cm germination paper (Anchor, USA), and then rolled as a cigar with the seeds at the top. Then the cigar was stood vertically in a tank (50&#xD7;35&#xD7;30 cm) containing Hoagland solution (10 cm depth) at 20&#xB0;C until 200&#xB0;Cd. The number of seminal roots, maximum root length, and total root length were measured. Root and shoot dry mass were also investigated after drying at 60&#xB0;C for 72 h. Seedling vigour was evaluated as the area of the first two leaves, coleoptile length and the seedling root length.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Spike Development and Fertility</title>
        <p>Spike differentiation was investigated on three randomly selected plants from each field plot. Beginning from the three leaf stage (Z12), plants were sampled every 3 days and the main shoot was dissected to determine the timing of the double ridge formation (DR) and the terminal spikelet initiation (TS) in the apical meristem, as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Gardner1">[52]</xref> using a digital Stereo Microscope (Nikon, SMZ1500). The timing of other stages of spike differentiation was also recorded successively. Pictures were taken using a digital camera linked to the microscope. The timing of heading (Z55) and anthesis (Z65) was visually determined when 50% of the plants per plot had reached these stages.</p>
        <p>At anthesis, five plants in the central row of each plot were harvested and the number of fertile florets in the main shoot spike was counted before drying. Florets were considered fertile when the stigmatic branches were spread wide, with either pollen grains present on them or with green anthers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Waddington1">[53]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Carbohydrate Assimilation and Distribution</title>
        <p>After investigation of fertility, the five plants harvested at anthesis were partitioned to investigate the dry weight of the main shoot (PDM), dry weight of the main shoot spike (SDM), dry weight of tiller spikes (SDT) and the total dry matter excluding roots (TDP). The partitioning of total dry matter to reproductive organs (dry weight of total spike including main shoot and tiller spikes) and the spike to stem ratio in main shoots were then calculated. The number of green leaves on the main shoot was counted from the flag leaf down and included fractions of leaves that were partially yellow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Zadoks1">[54]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Also from these samples, the dry weights of flag leaf, the second leaf, the third leaf, the peduncle, the fifth internode, the fourth internode, the basal three internodes on the main shoot stems and leaves including leaf sheaths were determined. Samples were also collected at the 14th, 18th, 22nd and 30th day after anthesis as described above to analyse the dynamic changes of the dry weight of spike, stem and leaf of the main shoot between different genotypes. All samples were oven-dried at 60&#xB0;C for 72 h and weighed separately <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Gonzalez1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Miralles2">[55]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Plant Height, Leaf and Internode Character</title>
        <p>Plant height was determined at maturity as the distance from the soil surface to the top of the ear (awns excluded) of ten plants for each plot. Seedling height was measured as the distance from the soil surface to the ligule of the last fully emerged leaf of ten plants for each plot and was used to analyze the growth rate of different lines (capacity to produce biomass) weekly from Z12 until heading. At the three leaf stage (Z13) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Zadoks1">[54]</xref>, five plants per plot were randomly selected and tagged, and the number of leaves emerging on the main shoot was noted two or three times a week until anthesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Haun1">[56]</xref>. The length and width of each leaf were measured when the leaf was fully elongated.</p>
        <p>All of the genotypes have six internodes, the first internode of more than 1 cm was defined as internode1, although internodes shorter than 1 cm were occasionally observed in some individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Berry2">[57]</xref>. Subsequent internodes up the stem were numbered as 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 (peduncle), respectively. The lengths of internodes (mm) were measured from the mid-point of their subtending nodes. Stem diameter (mm) was measured at the middle of each internode using digital calipers (TESA Etalon). Internodes were then cut at their centre point and digital calipers were used to measure the stem wall thickness (mm). Two measurements of stem wall thickness were taken on opposite sides of the stem from which a mean value was calculated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Berry2">[57]</xref>. Characters of each internode were measured when they fully developed.</p>
        <p>Lodging was scored at maturity from the fraction of the area affected and the severity of lodging in those areas noted, on a scale of 0 for a standing crop to 90 for a crop flat on the ground <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Zadoks1">[54]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Yield Components and Yield</title>
        <p>The main shoot ears of ten plants of each line at maturity were measured for assessment of spike length, spikelets per spike, grains per spike, total grains in the uppermost three spikelets and in the bottom three spikelets of the spike. The fertile shoots per plant were also measured in the same plants.</p>
        <p>Due to the frequent sampling prior to harvest and the limited number of plants in each plot (seeds from individual F<sub>2</sub> plants were limited), only 25 to 40 plants remained in each plot at harvest. Plants were hand-cut at ground level and the number of plants harvested in each plot was recorded. The total above-ground dry biomass of each line was determined before threshing, and then the average biomass per plant, average yield per plant, harvest index (calculated as the ratio of grain to total above-ground biomass) and 1000-grain weight were determined.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2i">
        <title>Data Analysis</title>
        <p>For each parameter measured, the mean value for each line (15 RRBB, 13 RRbb, 17 rrBB and 12 rrbb lines) was calculated and statistical evaluation of the data was carried out by ANOVA analysis with multiple comparisons (LSD test at the 0.05 level) using the statistical package SPSS18.0. Association analysis was also made with SPSS18.0. Whenever thermal time was used to measure developmental progress, 0&#xB0;C was chosen as base temperature.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>The Pleiotropic Effects of <italic>Rht12</italic> in F<sub>2</sub> Progeny</title>
        <p>Among the F<sub>2</sub> segregating population, 228 plants were genotyped using the SSR markers linked with <italic>Rht12</italic> and <italic>Vrn-B1</italic>, respectively. Individuals homozygous at those two loci were selected and classified into four groups. Thus the F<sub>2</sub> individuals composing 15 with RRBB (<italic>Rht12Rht12Vrn-B1Vrn-B1</italic>), 13 with RRbb (<italic>Rht12Rht12vrn-B1vrn-B1</italic>), 17 with rrBB (<italic>rht12rht12Vrn-B1Vrn-B1</italic>) and 12 with rrbb (<italic>rht12rht12vrn-B1vrn-B1</italic>) were identified.</p>
        <p>All progenies segregated into two distinct height classes, due to the strong effects of <italic>Rht12</italic>, and the homozygous recessive <italic>rht12</italic> progeny could be clearly identified by their tall stature. The primary and pleiotropic effects of <italic>Rht12</italic> are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t001">Table 1</xref>. Plant height was significantly decreased from an average of 106 cm in the rr genotypes to 76 cm in the RR genotypes; a reduction of 28% in plant height was thus observed. The individuals with heterozygous genotype (Rr) were approximately 4 cm taller than RR (data not shown). The spike length, number of spikelets per spike and 1000-grain weight were also reduced after introducing the dwarfing gene <italic>Rht12</italic>. Whereas, the grain number per spike, the effective spike number, and the fertility of the top three spikelets were increased in the homozygous dwarf plants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t001">Table 1</xref>). Moreover, the ear emergence time and flowering time of the homozygous dwarf individuals were significantly delayed, for flowering by an average of 4 days (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t001">Table 1</xref>), but with some plants by as much as 10 days compared with the tall plants.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0062285-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of <italic>Rht12</italic> on plant height, spike traits and yield components in the F<sub>2</sub> progeny.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0062285-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0062285.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype/variety</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant height(cm)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spike length(cm)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of spikeletsspike<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of grainsin thetop three spikelets</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of grainsin thebasal three spikelets</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grain numberspike<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000-grainweight (g)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effective Tiller number</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW-AN<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref> (&#xB0;C d)</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.5&#xB1;6.97b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2&#xB1;0.89b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5&#xB1;1.01ab</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5&#xB1;0.23a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2&#xB1;0.35a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.4&#xB1;4.65a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.6&#xB1;3.41b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4&#xB1;2.94a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216.0 (1585)a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.4&#xB1;7.43b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.8&#xB1;0.90b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9&#xB1;1.12b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4&#xB1;0.25a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9&#xB1;0.40a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.6&#xB1;4.87a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.3&#xB1;2.31b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0&#xB1;3.21a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216.3 (1592)a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.2&#xB1;4.62a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1&#xB1;0.82a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1&#xB1;0.74a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4&#xB1;0.21b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2&#xB1;0.29a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.6&#xB1;4.29b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.6&#xB1;3.75a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7&#xB1;2.68b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212.0(1479)b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rrbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.2&#xB1;4.61a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9&#xB1;0.76ab</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6&#xB1;1.04ab</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1&#xB1;0.14b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3&#xB1;0.24a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.5&#xB1;3.85b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5&#xB1;3.29a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6&#xB1;2.56b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212.5 (1500)b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karcagi</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.0&#xB1;2.48</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7&#xB1;0.66</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0&#xB1;0.77</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2&#xB1;0.15</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9&#xB1;0.23</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.6&#xB1;3.29</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9&#xB1;1.39</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7&#xB1;1.43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221.0 (1633)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nchun45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.0&#xB1;1.94</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4&#xB1;0.58</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.6&#xB1;0.70</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0&#xB1;0.19</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9&#xB1;0.19</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5&#xB1;4.11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.2&#xB1;2.40</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0&#xB1;1.16</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211.7 (1471)</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label>*</label>
              <p>Data are the duration days (d) with calculated thermal time (&#xB0;C d) in parenthesis; SW: sowing date; AN: anthesis date. Karcagi and Nchun45 represent the two parents Karcagi (12) and Ningchun45, respectively. Data are means &#xB1;SD (standard deviation) of each genotype. Data of the two parents were not considered in the statistical significance testing. Different letters within columns indicate statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Seedling Vigour and Seedling Root Characters</title>
        <p>In the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines, no significant difference was observed for the length or width of the first leaf between the tall and dwarf groups, while the length of the second leaf of the dwarf group was shorter than that of the tall group (with a 1.6 cm reduction) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t002">Table 2</xref>). The total area of the first two leaves in the dwarf group were less than that of the tall group by 1.1 cm<sup>2</sup> (9%) and 0.55 cm<sup>2</sup> (11%) in the AS and SS experiments, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t002">Table 2</xref>). Although the area of individual leaves at seedling stage of the dwarf group was slightly reduced, the emergence of new leaves was advanced 3 days earlier than the tall group (data not shown), which may benefit seedling growth. However, genotype rrBB achieved the largest leaf area while RRbb had the smallest leaf area in both the AS and SS experiments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t002">Table 2</xref>), indicating that the combination of RR and bb may affect seedling leaf growth. Additionally, no significant difference in coleoptile length was observed between the dwarf and tall groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t003">Table 3</xref>), suggesting that <italic>Rht12</italic> may confer a semi-dwarf height in wheat, while allowing no reduction in coleoptile length.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0062285-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Seedling vigour of different groups of the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines in the autumn-sown (AS) and spring-sown (SS) experiments.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0062285-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0062285.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experiment</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype/variety</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of the 1<sup>st</sup> leaf (cm)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Width of the 1<sup>st</sup> leaf (cm)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area of the 1<sup>st</sup> leaf (cm<sup>2</sup>)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of the 2<sup>nd</sup> leaf (cm)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Width of the 2<sup>nd</sup> leaf (cm)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area of the 2<sup>nd</sup> leaf (cm<sup>2</sup>)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total area of two leaves (cm<sup>2</sup>)</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1&#xB1;0.31a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0&#xB1;0.58a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0&#xB1;0.70b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2&#xB1;0.81b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2&#xB1;1.36b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0&#xB1;0.22a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0&#xB1;0.47a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8&#xB1;0.72b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1&#xB1;0.83b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1&#xB1;1.23b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5&#xB1;0.54a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2&#xB1;0.66a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0&#xB1;1.44 a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2&#xB1;1.24a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4&#xB1;1.61a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2&#xB1;0.52a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5&#xB1;0.03a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1&#xB1;0.59a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4&#xB1;1.32a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6&#xB1;0.03a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9&#xB1;1.18a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0&#xB1;1.32ab</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karcagi</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0&#xB1;0.19</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5&#xB1;0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6&#xB1;0.43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0&#xB1;0.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6&#xB1;0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3&#xB1;0.54</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9&#xB1;0.89</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nchun45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3&#xB1;0.39</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5&#xB1;0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9&#xB1;0.54</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9&#xB1;0.70</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6&#xB1;0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6&#xB1;0.77</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5&#xB1;1.36</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5&#xB1;0.85a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0&#xB1;0.97a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4&#xB1;0.58ab</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5&#xB1;0.89a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5&#xB1;0.93a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2&#xB1;0.87a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0&#xB1;1.05a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9&#xB1;0. 47b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4&#xB1;0.72a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4&#xB1;0.90a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0&#xB1;0.82a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2&#xB1;0.91a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6&#xB1;1.15a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8&#xB1;1.28a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0&#xB1;1.57a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7&#xB1;0.80a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#xB1;0.03a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1&#xB1;090a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3&#xB1;0.87a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#xB1;0.03a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7&#xB1;0.94a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8&#xB1;1.14a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karcagi</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1&#xB1;0.31</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#xB1;0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7&#xB1;0.43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3&#xB1;0.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#xB1;0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0&#xB1;0.58</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7&#xB1;0.89</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nchun45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5&#xB1;0.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#xB1;0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3&#xB1;0.58</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2&#xB1;0.58</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4&#xB1;0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9&#xB1;0.77</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2&#xB1;1.01</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label/>
              <p>All data are means &#xB1;SD of each genotype. Data of the two parents were not considered in the statistical significance testing. Different letters within columns indicate statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0062285-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285.t003</object-id>
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of <italic>Rht12</italic> on coleoptile length and root traits of different groups of the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines at the seedling stage.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0062285-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0062285.t003"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coleoptile length (cm)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of seminal roots</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum root length<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">*</xref> (cm)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total root length (cm)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root dry mass (mg)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shoot dry mass (mg)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root to shoot Ratio of dry mass</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.87&#xB1;0.56a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0&#xB1;0.08b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.25&#xB1;1.90a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.46&#xB1;3.29b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.57&#xB1;0.35b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.32&#xB1;1.20b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49&#xB1;0.01a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.96&#xB1;0.52a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0&#xB1;0.14b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.97&#xB1;1.62a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.14&#xB1;2.74b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.51&#xB1;0.29b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.15&#xB1;1.26b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.20&#xB1;0.49a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1&#xB1;0.16a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.42&#xB1;1.44b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.39&#xB1;4.33a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.28&#xB1;0.37a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.29&#xB1;1.81a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44&#xB1;0.02b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.13&#xB1;0.60a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0&#xB1;0.21a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.65&#xB1;1.52b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.20&#xB1;3.15 a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.26&#xB1;0.24a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.33&#xB1;1.66a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44&#xB1;0.01b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karcagi(12)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1&#xB1;0.22</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0&#xB1;0.08</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.47&#xB1;0.93</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.67&#xB1;2.52</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.64&#xB1;0.23</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.43&#xB1;0.97</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44&#xB1;0.01</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nchun45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2&#xB1;0.29</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3&#xB1;0.08</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.28&#xB1;1.98</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.42&#xB1;4.80</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.23&#xB1;0.50</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.58&#xB1;2.05</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50&#xB1;0.03</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label>*</label>
              <p>Mean value of the longest root length in each set of lines. Data are means &#xB1;SD of each genotype. Data of the two parents were not considered in the statistical significance testing. Different letters within columns indicate statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Based on the &#x2018;Cigar&#x2019; test for the root characters at the seedling stage, the total number of seminal roots was significantly decreased in the dwarf group (2 roots fewer) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062285-g001">Fig. 1</xref>), while the total root length in the dwarf group was reduced by 6 cm (9%) compared to that of the tall group (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t003">Table 3</xref>). The maximum root length of the dwarf group was 3 cm (15%) longer than that of the tall group, which may be beneficial for water acquisition in deeper soil in dry environments, assuming this seedling trait is expressed in adult plants.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0062285-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Seminal root morphology of the dwarf and tall lines at the seedling stage determined by the Cigar method.</title>
            <p>Panel A shows the dwarf lines and B shows the tall lines. The tall lines always have two more seminal roots than the dwarf lines (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0062285.g001"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The difference between the total root length of the tall and dwarf genotypes was mainly determined by the difference in total number of roots and not by the root elongation rate. The root dry mass was decreased by 0.7 mg (11%) in the dwarf lines. While, the dry mass ratio of root to shoot of the dwarf lines (0.49) was significantly greater than that of the tall lines (0.44). It suggested that <italic>Rht12</italic> did not greatly affect the seedling root growth although it significantly reduced the total number of roots. There was no significant difference in root architecture between BB and bb genotypes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Spike Development, Spike Dry Weight at Anthesis and Floret Fertility</title>
        <p>Spike development was significantly delayed and the duration of the spike development phase was elongated in the <italic>Rht12</italic> dwarf lines compared to that of tall lines under both AS and SS experiments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t004">Table 4</xref>). In the AS experiment, spike development of the dwarf lines with <italic>Rht12</italic> either with <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> or <italic>vrn-B1</italic> was delayed by 16 days to reach the double ridge stage, which meant that an additional thermal time of 45&#xB0;Cd was needed compared to the tall lines with the winter growth habit. The effect of the dominant vernalization gene <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> was masked in the dwarf lines, while in the tall lines without <italic>Rht12</italic>, the lines with <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> reached double ridge stage about 60 days (30&#xB0;Cd) earlier than those with <italic>vrn-B1</italic>. However, the anthesis date of the dwarf lines was about 5 days (110&#xB0;Cd) later than that of the tall lines (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t004">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062285-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). In the SS experiment, the RRBB lines required an additional 9 days (140&#xB0;Cd) to reach the double ridge stage compared to the rrBB lines and needed a further 6 days (135&#xB0;Cd) to reach anthesis compared to the tall lines. Whereas, rrBB lines reached double ridge stage about 5 days (60&#xB0;Cd) faster than rrbb lines (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t004">Table 4</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0062285-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Spike development of the tall (rrBB, A1&#x2013;A3) and dwarf (RRBB, B1&#x2013;B3) genotypes in the AS experiment.</title>
            <p>A1 and B1 show spike development at the early double ridge stage of tall genotypes and at metaphase of single ridge stage of the dwarf genotypes at 630&#xB0;Cd (75d after sowing), respectively; A2 and B2 show spike development at terminal spikelet initiation stage of the tall genotypes and at anaphase of double ridge stage of the dwarf genotypes at 770&#xB0;Cd (165d after sowing), respectively; A3 and B3 show the floret morphology at yellow anther stage/anthesis of the tall genotypes and at green anther stage of the dwarf genotypes at 1430&#xB0;Cd (209d after sowing), respectively. Scale bars&#x200A;=&#x200A;100 &#xB5;m.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0062285.g002"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0062285-t004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285.t004</object-id>
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Duration days (d) and thermal time (&#xB0;C d) of different pre-anthesis developmental phases of different groups of the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines in the autumn-sown (AS) and spring-sown (SS) experiments.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0062285-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0062285.t004"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experiment</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype/variety</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW-AN</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW-DR</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR-TS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TS-AN</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total leaf number</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214.0(1555.8)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153.0(702.2)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0(160.1)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0(693.5)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215.5(1584.6)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154.0(705.0)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5(168.3)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0(711.3)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209.0(1437.7)b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.0(629.0)b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.0(144.3)b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.0(664.4)b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4c</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210.5(1468.4)b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.0(658.2)d</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.0(136.2)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5(674.0)b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karcagi</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220.0(1661.6)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162.0(747.1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0(194.0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.0(720.5)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nchun45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210.0(1458.9)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.0(615.7)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.0(156.1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.0(687.1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.0(1367.5)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.0(566.0)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0(217.2)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0(543.3)b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115.0(1385.1)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.0(582.1)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0(234.0)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0(566.0)b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108.0(1231.6)b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.0(428.0)c</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0(184.4)b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0(619.2)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2c</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.0(1266.6)b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.0(485.3)b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0(181.0)b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0(600.3)a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karcagi</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121.0(1471.5)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.0(650.4)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0(249.0)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.0(572.1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nchun45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.0(1192.8)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.0(413.5)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0(191.2)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.0(588.1)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label/>
              <p>Data are the duration days (d) with calculated thermal time (&#xB0;C d) in parenthesis; SW: sowing date, DR: double ridge formation date, TS: terminal spikelet initiation date, AN: anthesis date. All data are means of each genotype. Statistical analysis was carried out using the thermal time. Data of the two parents were not considered in the statistical significance testing. Different letters within columns indicate statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>In both AS and SS experiments, there was no significant difference between RRBB and RRbb in spike development, suggesting that the dwarfing <italic>Rht12</italic> allele might have an epistatic effect on <italic>Vrn-B1</italic>. The tall spring lines (rrBB) developed faster than the tall winter lines (rrbb) before terminal spikelet stage while they had no difference on flowing time (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t004">Table 4</xref>). This indicated that genotypes having dominant <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> needed less time to undergo vernalization in tall lines. However, the effects of <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> on plant development were not strong enough to promote early flowering in either tall or dwarf genotypes.</p>
        <p>In the AS experiment, spike lengths in RRBB and RRbb groups were significantly decreased (7%) compared with rrBB, while there was no significant difference observed with rrbb (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t005">Table 5</xref>). The number of spikelets per spike in RRbb was significantly reduced (3%) compared to that in rrBB and rrbb groups, while there was no significant difference between RRBB and rrBB/rrbb. The rrBB lines showed the largest number of spikelets per spike while RRbb had the smallest (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t005">Table 5</xref>). The dominant <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> allele likely plays a major role in determining spikelet number in this population and the combination of rr and BB produces more spikelets per spike. This phenomenon was also observed in the SS experiment. But, total florets per spike of RRBB, RRbb and rrbb were significantly decreased compared with that of rrBB in both experiments. This indicates that the BB allele apparently has an effect on initiation of florets in tall plants.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0062285-t005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285.t005</object-id>
          <label>Table 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of <italic>Rht12</italic> on the spike characters and fertility of different groups of the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines in the autumn-sown (AS) and spring-sown (SS) experiments.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0062285-t005-5" xlink:href="pone.0062285.t005"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experiment</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype/variety</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spike length(cm)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spikeletsspike<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Florets initiatedspike<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fertile floretsspike<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fertile florets inthe top threespikelet</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fertility<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6&#xB1;1.05b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.2&#xB1;0.89ab</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197.0&#xB1;16.42b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.8&#xB1;3.60a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1&#xB1;0.19a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25&#xB1;0.01a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5&#xB1;0.71b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9&#xB1;0.79b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194.2&#xB1;14.78b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.3&#xB1;3.52a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3&#xB1;0.32a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25&#xB1;0.01a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6&#xB1;0.99a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.7&#xB1;1.15a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202.9&#xB1;17.03a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.2&#xB1;3.77b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2&#xB1;0.33b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22&#xB1;0.01b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1a&#xB1;0.73a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4&#xB1;1.07a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198.6&#xB1;15.28b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.1&#xB1;4.02b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3&#xB1;0.17b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22&#xB1;0.01b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karcagi</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4&#xB1;0.54</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7&#xB1;0.66</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169.9&#xB1;13.71</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.7&#xB1;3.82</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3&#xB1;0.19</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27&#xB1;0.01</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nchun45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7&#xB1;1.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.5&#xB1;1.39</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204.5&#xB1;18.05</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.1&#xB1;4.76</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2&#xB1;0.08</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24&#xB1;0.01</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4&#xB1;0.97ab</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8&#xB1;1.20b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201.8&#xB1;19.83c</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8&#xB1;2.01b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8&#xB1;0.12a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20&#xB1;0.01b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0&#xB1;1.19b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4&#xB1;1.26b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198.5&#xB1;16.87c</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.7&#xB1;1.98b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4&#xB1;0.18ab</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19&#xB1;0.01b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3&#xB1;0.78a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.6&#xB1;1.11a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215.0&#xB1;20.86a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.0&#xB1;2.60a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1&#xB1;0.08b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0&#xB1;0.83a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4&#xB1;1.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210.0&#xB1;18.46b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9&#xB1;1.97a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3&#xB1;0.10ab</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24&#xB1;0.01a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karcagi</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7&#xB1;0.46</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.2&#xB1;0.62</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181.3&#xB1;15.57</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3&#xB1;1.28</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3&#xB1;0.08</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19&#xB1;0.01</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nchun45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3&#xB1;0.77</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.9&#xB1;1.32</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220.2&#xB1;16.46</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.4&#xB1;3.37</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1&#xB1;0.19</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25&#xB1;0.02</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt105">
              <label>*</label>
              <p>Fertility is estimated as the ratio of fertility florets to total floret per spike of the main shoot spike. All data are means &#xB1;SD of each genotype. Data of the two parents were not considered in the statistical significance testing. Different letters within columns indicate statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>In the AS experiment, <italic>Rht12</italic> significantly increased floret fertility (14%) and produced more fertile florets (10%) compared with the tall genotypes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t005">Table 5</xref>). Correlation analysis showed that the elongated duration of the late reproduction phase pre-anthesis (thermal time accumulated) associated with <italic>Rht12</italic> was highly correlated with the increased number of fertile florets, and the duration of TS-AN explained almost 87% (R<sup>2</sup>&#x200A;=&#x200A;0.865) of variation of the ear fertility. However, possibly due to slow development of the vegetative phase (SW-DR) and early reproductive phase (DR-TS), which shortened the period of time available under favourable conditions prior to flowering (TS-AN), the dwarf lines produced fewer (23%) fertile florets per spike than that of the tall lines in the SS experiment. The decreased duration of late reproduction phase pre-anthesis (thermal time accumulated) was highly correlated with the reduced number of fertile florets (R<sup>2</sup>&#x200A;=&#x200A;0.908) in the SS experiment. There were more fertile florets in the top three spikelets of dwarf plants in both experiments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t005">Table 5</xref>), suggesting that <italic>Rht12</italic> had a stronger production potential in the top spikelets. There was no significant difference between BB and bb in floret fertility.</p>
        <p>Dry matter partitioning to the spikes during the late reproduction phase is particularly important for yield because during this phase the number of fertile florets at anthesis is determined <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Gonzalez1">[26]</xref>. In the AS experiment, the dry weights of the main shoot spikes at anthesis were similar among the four genotypes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t006">Table 6</xref>). Whereas, the dry weight of the tiller spikes per plant in dwarf groups were higher (9%) than that of the tall groups, which might result from the increased number of tiller spikes in dwarf plants rather than bigger tiller spikes. Because of the reduction in plant stature, the dry weight of the main shoot (SDM) and the dry weight of the above-ground biomass (TDP) of the dwarf lines at anthesis were significantly decreased. While, the ratios of main shoot spike dry weight (SDM) to main shoot dry weight (PDM) and the total spike dry weight (SDM+SDT) to plant dry weight (TDP) of the dwarf lines was significantly increased compared to that of the tall lines (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t006">Table 6</xref>). This indicates that <italic>Rht12</italic> could increase the partitioning of dry matter to spikes during the late reproductive phase, potentially advantageous in achieving a greater availability of assimilates to support floret survival in developing spikes and a greater mass per carpel at anthesis, resulting in the greater production of fertile florets. But, in the SS experiment, SDM, SDT, and SDM/PDM of the dwarf genotypes at anthesis were all significantly lower than that of the tall genotypes, while (SDM+SDT)/TDP was not different between the dwarf and tall groups, and a fertility reduction was observed in the dwarf plants. It seemed that the environment effects of sowing date were greater on dwarf lines than on tall lines, and the differences between the two sowing date experiments were more evident in dwarf lines though all lines produced less total dry matter in the SS experiment than in the AS experiment.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0062285-t006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285.t006</object-id>
          <label>Table 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Dry weight of spikes and the whole plant at anthesis of different groups of the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines in the autumn-sown (AS) and spring-sown (SS) experiments.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0062285-t006-6" xlink:href="pone.0062285.t006"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experiment</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype/variety</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDM (g)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDT (g)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDM (g)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDP (g)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDM/PDM</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(SDM+SDT)/TDP</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71&#xB1;0.05a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.17&#xB1;0.54a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.16&#xB1;0.32b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.28&#xB1;1.95b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22&#xB1;0.01a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.20&#xB1;0.58a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05&#xB1;0.38b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.14&#xB1;1.88b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22&#xB1;0.01a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71&#xB1;0.06a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.83&#xB1;0.62b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95&#xB1;0.46a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.09&#xB1;3.10a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18&#xB1;0.01b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15&#xB1;0.03b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.72&#xB1;0.68b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.77&#xB1;0.41a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.78&#xB1;2.85a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19&#xB1;0.01b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14&#xB1;0.02b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karcagi</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64&#xB1;0.03</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.62&#xB1;0.36</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.93&#xB1;0.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.55&#xB1;1.55</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22&#xB1;0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23&#xB1;0.01</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nchun45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88&#xB1;0.05</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17&#xB1;0.30</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18&#xB1;0.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.68&#xB1;2.30</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21&#xB1;0.02</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15&#xB1;0.01</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64&#xB1;0.04b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30&#xB1;0.25b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.45&#xB1;0.30b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.24&#xB1;1.85b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19&#xB1;0.01b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19&#xB1;0.01a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62&#xB1;0.03b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30&#xB1;0.19b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38&#xB1;0.35b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.62&#xB1;1.56b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18&#xB1;0.01b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18&#xB1;0.01a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85&#xB1;0.06a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90&#xB1;0.30a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.10&#xB1;0.54a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.41&#xB1;2.27a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83&#xB1;0.06a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80&#xB1;0.25a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95&#xB1;0.50a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.88&#xB1;2.58a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18&#xB1;0.01a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karcagi</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46&#xB1;0.03</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53&#xB1;0.12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74&#xB1;0.26</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.11&#xB1;1.13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17&#xB1;0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14&#xB1;0.01</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nchun45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91&#xB1;0.03</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00&#xB1;0.18</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.79&#xB1;0.45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.31&#xB1;1.58</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19&#xB1;0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17&#xB1;0.01</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt106">
              <label/>
              <p>Note: SDM is spike dry weight of the main shoot, SDT is spike dry weight of the tillers, PDM is the dry weight of the main shoot, TDP is the total dry weight of one plant. Data are means &#xB1; SD of each genotype. Data of the two parents were not considered in the statistical significance testing. Different letters within columns indicate statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Furthermore, in the AS experiment, spikelet dry weight and number of fertile florets per spikelet of dwarf lines increased by, respectively, 2% and 13% compared with tall lines. Conversely, in the SS experiment, spikelet dry weight and number of fertile florets per spikelet of tall lines were larger than that of dwarf lines by 28% and 27%, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t005">Table 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t006">Table 6</xref>). Despite these contrasting responses, in both experiments spikelet dry weight was highly correlated with the number of fertile florets per spikelet at anthesis with R<sup>2</sup> of 0.81 and 0.99 respectively, in the AS and SS experiment.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Plant Height and Associated Traits</title>
        <p>Plant height was greatly reduced by the <italic>Rht12</italic> dwarfing gene. In the AS experiment, the plant height of dwarf lines carrying <italic>Rht12</italic> was reduced by 45 cm (37%) through reducing the length of internodes, and the peduncle length was reduced by 20 cm (43%) in dwarf lines compared with that of the tall lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062285-g003">Figs 3A, 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0062285.s001">Table S1</xref>). In the SS experiment, plant height was reduced by 50 cm (40%) in the dwarf lines compared with that of the tall lines with the reduction of peduncle length by 23 cm (48%). The pattern of reduced internode length compared with the tall genotypes was thus similar in both the AS and SS experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062285-g003">Fig. 3C</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0062285.s001">Table S1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0062285-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Culm morphology of the four genotypes in the AS and SS experiments.</title>
            <p>A: the mature plant morphology of the four genotypes and the two parents in the AS experiment. B: schematic representation of internode elongation patterns of the four genotypes and the two parents in AS experiment. C: Schematic representation of internode elongation patterns of the four genotypes in the SS experiment.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0062285.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The culm elongated faster in tall lines than in dwarf lines from seedling stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062285-g004">Fig. 4</xref>), with the tall lines reaching jointing stage earlier than the dwarf lines and producing longer internodes and more biomass; this difference was sustained to maturity in both experiments. The shortest individual internode was more often observed in RRbb lines in both AS and SS experiments. However, there was no significant difference in the length of internodes between BB and bb lines (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0062285.s001">Table S1</xref>). Although no significant difference was observed in diameter of the internodes between dwarf and tall lines, the thickness of the internode walls of the dwarf lines was significantly greater than that of tall lines in both experiments (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0062285.s002">Table S2</xref>). In particular, the wall thickness of the first and second internodes of the dwarf lines was increased by 0.25 mm (32%) and 0.22 mm (34%) in the AS experiment and 0.26 mm (28%) and 0.25 mm (31%) in the SS experiment, respectively. These shorter and thicker internodes might confer a greater resistance to lodging in the dwarf plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Berry2">[57]</xref>. Due to the occurrence of storms at anthesis stage and at the middle grain filling stage, lodging occurred twice in the AS experiment; serious lodging was only observed in the tall lines (average lodging score is 39, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0062285.s002">Table S2</xref>), while all of the dwarf lines kept an upright posture. There was no significant difference observed in lodging between BB and bb lines.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0062285-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Development of plant height from the soil surface to the top ligule.</title>
            <p>A: AS experiment, the final height is achieved at week 22. B: SS experiment, the final height is achieved at week 16. C: plants at the 7<sup>th</sup> week in AS experiment, the yellow line shows the site of the top ligule in each genotype and the two parents.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0062285.g004"/>
        </fig>
        <p>There was no significant difference in the number of green leaves (average of 3.6) on main stem at anthesis between the four genotypes in both experiments. Whereas, the leaf length of dwarf lines with <italic>Rht12</italic> was significantly decreased (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0062285.s003">Table S3</xref>). In the AS experiment, the leaves of the dwarf lines were significantly shorter than those of the tall lines by as much as 6 cm (30%), and their widths were greater (10%&#x223C;25%) than those of the tall lines. Thus the total area of the uppermost three leaves on the main stem of the dwarf lines was only slightly (3%) less than that of the tall lines (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0062285.s003">Table S3</xref>). This may enable the dwarf lines to have a similar ability to produce sufficient photosynthate for the development of the kernels. Additionally, in both sowings, RRBB lines had significantly larger leaf area (4% and 6%, respectively) than RRbb whereas there was no effect of <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> in tall lines, suggesting that the dominant <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> could promote leaf growth in dwarf lines.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title>Dry Matter Accumulation and Distribution of the Main Shoot after Anthesis</title>
        <p>Dynamic changes in the dry weight of different organs in the main shoot after anthesis were different between the dwarf and tall genotypes. In the AS experiment, the dry weight of the flag leaf, the second last leaf, the fourth internode and the fifth internode increased until the 14<sup>th</sup> day (18<sup>th</sup> day for peduncle) after anthesis in the dwarf lines, while the dry weight of the leaves and internodes were all increased until the 18<sup>th</sup> day after anthesis, except the dry weight of the second last leaf, in the tall lines. The dry weight of the third last leaf decreased after anthesis in both dwarf and tall lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062285-g005">Fig. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0062285.s004">Table S4</xref>). However, assimilates stored in leaves and stems of dwarf lines were transferred to spikes earlier than in the tall plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062285-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). Similar results were also observed in the SS experiment on the dynamic change of dry weight of the leaves and stems (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062285-g006">Fig. 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0062285.s005">Table S5</xref>). In both AS and SS experiments, the maximum dry weights of the flag leaf were larger than that of the peduncle or the fifth internode in the dwarf plants while the opposite was observed in the tall plants. This indicated that <italic>Rht12</italic> affected internode growth more than leaf expansion. Finally, the total dry weight of the main shoot (excluding the spike) decreased by 0.67 g (30%) from its maximum to that measured at 30 days after anthesis in dwarf lines while it decreased by 1.37 g (35%) in tall lines in AS experiment; in the SS experiment the dry weight decreased by 0.87 g (33%) and 1.61 g (39%) in dwarf and tall lines, respectively. This suggests that the capability to support grain-filling (translocate shoot dry matter to the ear) was greatly reduced for dwarf lines, a conclusion supported by the observed greater gain in spike dry weight of tall lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062285-g005">Figs. 5C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062285-g006">6C</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0062285-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Dynamic changes in dry weight of different organs in the main shoot after anthesis in the AS experiment.</title>
            <p>A: dwarf lines; B: tall lines; C: spike dry weight of the dwarf and tall lines. The main culm comprises 6 internodes, the sixth internode is the peduncle. The leaves are numbered from the flag leaf down on the main stem. RR: dwarf lines; rr: tall lines.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0062285.g005"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0062285-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Dynamic changes in dry weight of different organs in the main shoot in the SS experiment.</title>
            <p>A: dwarf lines; B: tall lines; C: spike dry weight of the dwarf and tall lines. The main culm comprises 6 elongated internodes, the sixth internode is the peduncle. The leaves are numbered from the flag leaf down on the main stem. RR: dwarf alleles; rr: tall alleles.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0062285.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3f">
        <title>Yield and Yield Components</title>
        <p>Seed set and grain numbers were significantly increased in <italic>Rht12</italic> dwarf lines compared to that in tall lines in the AS experiment, while fewer grains per spike were produced in dwarf lines under the conditions encountered in the SS experiment due to lower fertility (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t007">Table 7</xref>). For both sowings, there were more grains in the top three spikelets due to their higher floret fertility in dwarf lines than in tall lines (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t005">Tables 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t007">7</xref>). This suggested that <italic>Rht12</italic> could increase grain numbers at the top of spikes and the top three spikelets in dwarf lines had stronger production potential than in tall plants. There was no significant difference between BB and bb lines for grain numbers.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0062285-t007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062285.t007</object-id>
          <label>Table 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of <italic>Rht12</italic> on yield components and harvest index of different groups of the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines in the autumn-sown (AS) and spring-sown (SS) experiments.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0062285-t007-7" xlink:href="pone.0062285.t007"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experiment</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype/variety</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grain number spike<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000-grain weight (g)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of efficient spikes plant<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant yield<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">*</xref> (g)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant biomass<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">*</xref> (g)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Harvest index</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.8&#xB1;3.95a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9&#xB1;3.37b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4&#xB1;1.24a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4&#xB1;2.32a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.6&#xB1;6.86b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.6&#xB1;3.46a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5&#xB1;3.17b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8&#xB1;1.73a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8&#xB1;2.31a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3&#xB1;6.13b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36&#xB1;0.03a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.6&#xB1;3.63b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.2&#xB1;4.58a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6&#xB1;2.19b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2&#xB1;2.72a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.6&#xB1;8.29a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31&#xB1;0.03b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8&#xB1;3.64b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.0&#xB1;4.47a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4&#xB1;1.42b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1&#xB1;2.08a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.5&#xB1;6.79a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31&#xB1;0.04b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karcagi</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.0&#xB1;3.99</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5&#xB1;2.75</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2&#xB1;2.32</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1&#xB1;2.13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.6&#xB1;7.67</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36&#xB1;0.02</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nchun45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.4&#xB1;4.34</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.3&#xB1;3.02</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4&#xB1;1.28</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5&#xB1;2.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8&#xB1;8.50</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33&#xB1;0.03</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SS</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.3&#xB1;2.59b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0&#xB1;3.14b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6&#xB1;0.50b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7&#xB1;0.46b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8&#xB1;2.56b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32&#xB1;0.01a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.1&#xB1;2.88b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.5&#xB1;3.10b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2&#xB1;0.36b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6&#xB1;0.54b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5&#xB1;2.63b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrBB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.4&#xB1;4.21a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.7&#xB1;3.71a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0&#xB1;0.87a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7&#xB1;1.24a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9&#xB1;5.15a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28&#xB1;0.03b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrbb</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.7&#xB1;3.29a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.2&#xB1;3.53a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5&#xB1;0.62a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1&#xB1;1.32a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1&#xB1;3.83a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26&#xB1;0.02b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karcagi</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.0&#xB1;1.78</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0&#xB1;3.25</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9&#xB1;0.23</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9&#xB1;0.46</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4&#xB1;0.89</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23&#xB1;0.01</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nchun45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.1&#xB1;4.26</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.2&#xB1;3.16</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3&#xB1;0.27</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3&#xB1;1.59</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.5&#xB1;2.13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29&#xB1;0.02</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt107">
              <label>*</label>
              <p>These data are the mean values of 25&#x223C;40 plants. All data are means &#xB1;SD of each genotype. Data of the two parents were not considered in the statistical significance testing. Different letters within columns indicate statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>A significant reduction in 1000-grain weight was found in <italic>Rht12</italic> dwarf lines compared to that in tall lines in both AS and SS experiments, possibly due to a combination of the 5-day delay in time to anthesis and the reduced plant biomass associated with <italic>Rht12</italic>. Whereas, the increase in grain numbers and in the number of fertile ears per plant of the dwarf lines resulted in there being no significant difference in plant yield between the dwarf and tall lines (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t007">Table 7</xref>). Additionally, as reported above, biomass per plant was decreased significantly in the dwarf genotypes, resulting in a net increase in harvest index. This indicates that, if total biomass could be maintained, <italic>Rht12</italic> might have the potential to decrease plant stature while increasing the grain yield. In the SS experiment, due to the lower fertility and less productive tillers of the dwarf lines, the grain yield of dwarf lines was much lower (32%) than that of the tall plants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062285-t007">Table 7</xref>). However, again due to the much-reduced biomass, the harvest index of the dwarf plants was higher than in the tall plants. This suggested that the dwarf genotypes could achieve a higher harvest index more easily than the tall genotypes in different environments. There was no significant difference between BB and bb lines on plant biomass, 1000-grain weight or grain yield.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This study is part of a series of experiments carried out to investigate and obtain a better understanding of the effects of the dwarfing gene <italic>Rht12</italic> on physiological attributes of the wheat crop. To improve the winter habit and the late ear emergence of <italic>Rht12</italic> plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Worland1">[2]</xref>, the dominant vernalization gene <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> was introduced to compensate for these effects. Contrasting homozygous lines with or without <italic>Rht12</italic> and <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> genes (RRBB, RRbb, rrBB and rrbb) were selected in a F<sub>2</sub> segregating population and assessed as F<sub>2:3</sub> lines to evaluate the effects of the dwarfing gene <italic>Rht12</italic>. Although the homozygous F<sub>2:3</sub> lines do not share a common background as with near-isogenic lines (NILs), single chromosome recombinant inbred lines (RILs) or doubled haploid (DH) lines, the large number of lines studied allowed the effects of other loci to be reduced or neutralized, which coupled with the strong phenotypic effect of <italic>Rht12</italic>, gave good resolution between genotypes. A similar strategy could be used to assess the effects of other dwarfing genes with strong effects on plant height (such as <italic>Rht4</italic>, <italic>Rht5</italic>, <italic>Rht13</italic> and <italic>Rht18</italic>) to evaluate their potential use in crop breeding for improving agronomic performance or to determine their effects in different target environments.</p>
      <p>To better understand the effects of <italic>Rht12</italic>, the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines were sown at two sowing dates to provide winter and spring wheat growing environments, which was important for determining the spike development traits associated with <italic>Rht12</italic>. In the AS experiment, all plants should have received adequate vernalization, as around 6 weeks below 5&#xB0;Cd are considered sufficient to complete vernalization of most wheat cultivars <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Griffiths1">[58]</xref>. However, RRbb and even the RRBB group showed a longer duration to double-ridge and flowered later than the rrbb group. Moreover, in the SS experiment, rrBB and even rrbb reached the double ridge stage earlier and showed a higher ear fertility (than in the AS experiment) than RRBB, which still had a significantly elongated duration to double ridge and showed poor ear fertility. Therefore, the effects of <italic>Rht12</italic> on reduction in the rate of spike development and elongation of the duration of spike development phase, as well as its epistatic effects on <italic>Vrn-B1</italic> were revealed in the two sowing date experiments. This finding is different than that of the GA-insensitive <italic>Rht</italic> dwarf genes which had no effect on the duration of phenological development and reduced only the rates of vegetative and reproductive development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Youssefian1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Calderini1">[38]</xref>. The effects of <italic>Rht12</italic> measured in the two experiments are thus very similar except for ear fertility and effective tiller number. The difference in ear fertility and effective tiller number between sowings could be the result of the elongated duration of plant development associated with <italic>Rht12</italic>: due to the slower growth rate and the strong winter growth habit caused by the strong effect of <italic>Rht12</italic>, also interacting with the higher temperature after the initiation of terminal spikelet, the dwarf plants had a shorter period of time under favourable conditions to develop fertile florets prior to flower <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Worland1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Gonzalez1">[26]</xref>, and finally produced fewer competent florets than tall plants in the SS experiment. Additionally, the delayed elongation stage and the shorter time available to initiate new tillers and develop tiller spikes also decreased the number of tillers with fertile spikes after floret initiation stage in the dwarf lines. It is suggested that while floret development and effective tiller development were more sensitive to temperature than other traits in dwarf lines, it is feasible to evaluate other pleiotropic effects of <italic>Rht12</italic> using these two sowing date experiments under winter and spring growth conditions.</p>
      <p>The reduction of plant height by <italic>Rht12</italic> was 47 cm (&#x223C;40%) in this study. A similar result was reported by Rebetzke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke5">[21]</xref> who found that <italic>Rht12</italic> reduced plant height by around 44 cm (&#x223C;45%), which was stronger than the dwarfing genes most widely used in commercial varieties, such as <italic>Rht1</italic> (&#x223C;20%), <italic>Rht2</italic> (&#x223C;20%) or <italic>Rht8</italic> (&#x223C;7%) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke5">[21]</xref>. The reduction of plant height caused by these dwarf or semi-dwarf genes might result from reduced cell elongation rather than cell division <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Keyes1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Gasperini1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Miralles2">[55]</xref>. Additionally, it was observed that while the diameter of the internodes was not affected by <italic>Rht12</italic>, the width of the stem wall was increased significantly in dwarf plants, which probably benefits lodging resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Calderini1">[38]</xref>. Indeed, along with reduced height, thicker stem walls may contribute to the better lodging resistance of the dwarf plants in this study, and confirmed that dwarf genes had been an important factor in lodging resistance of commercial varieties <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Berry1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Flintham1">[17]</xref>.</p>
      <p>During the vegetative phase, the crop initiates leaves until the point of floral initiation, which is generally indicated by the formation of the first double ridge in the apex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Gonzalez1">[26]</xref>. <italic>Rht12</italic> lines developed more leaves than the equivalent tall genotypes due to the longer duration to double ridge. In contrast, previous reports have shown that GA-insensitive dwarfing genes (<italic>Rht1</italic>, <italic>Rht2</italic> and <italic>Rht3</italic>) do not affect the timing of plant developmental events, nor the final numbers of leaves and internodes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Miralles1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Youssefian1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Calderini1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Pugsley1">[43]</xref>. This suggests that the two classes of dwarfing genes may act on plant growth and development via different mechanisms. While, similar with that in the GA-insensitive dwarf genotypes, the number of elongated internodes in <italic>Rht12</italic> lines did not change compared with the tall lines, indicating that <italic>Rht12</italic> affects the number of leaves but not the number of internodes that elongate. Despite initiating more leaves, there was no significant difference either in the number of green leaves at anthesis or the area of the three upper leaves at grain-filling stage between the dwarf and tall groups, which is important for radiation interception and biomass production in <italic>Rht12</italic> lines.</p>
      <p>It is argued that the pre-anthesis late reproductive phase (TS-AN) coinciding with the period of rapid stem elongation, is particularly important for yield <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Fischer1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Gonzalez1">[26]</xref> because the number of fertile florets at anthesis is determined during this phase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke5">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Flintham2">[59]</xref>. Moreover, it has been found that the greater number of fertile florets per spike at anthesis in dwarf lines than in tall lines is due to reduced degeneration of floret primordia in the late reproductive phase pre-anthesis rather than differences in the maximum number of floret primordia initiated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Bancal1">[60]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Kirby1">[61]</xref>. Lengthening the duration of TS-AN in wheat would arguably improve yield potential by increasing the number of fertile florets at anthesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Fischer2">[62]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Slafer4">[63]</xref>. In the AS experiment, <italic>Rht12</italic> lines had a longer TS-AN duration (&#xB0;Cd), which correlated with a significant increase in floret survival, although the total number of florets initiated was similar to the tall lines. The duration of TS-AN was also highly correlated with the number of fertile florets in the SS experiment, although in this case the dwarf lines actually had fewer fertile florets than the tall lines. Allocating a greater proportion of dry mass to the ear may also result in more fertile florets at anthesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Gonzalez1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Gonzalez2">[64]</xref>, but this does not imply that ears of dwarf genotypes are always heavier than those of tall genotypes, because total shoot dry matter has also to be considered <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Youssefian1">[37]</xref>. With reduced competition due to a much shorter stem, <italic>Rht12</italic> could increase the partitioning of dry matter to spikes during the late reproductive phase, leading to a greater mass per carpel at anthesis, which in turn could result in an improved proportion of fertilized florets and finally produce more grains per spikelet and per ear.</p>
      <p>Although the <italic>Rht12</italic> dwarf lines had a slower growth rate during stem elongation, the seeding vigour was similar to tall lines. The coleoptile length of dwarf plants was only about 3 mm (5%) shorter than that of the tall plants. Moreover, the length and width of the first leaves were not significantly different between the four genotypes. It has previously been observed that <italic>Rht12</italic> had no effect on seeding vigour and coleoptile length <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke5">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Addisu1">[65]</xref>, which offers the opportunity to reduce plant stature without compromising on early growth and crop establishment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke4">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Ellis1">[22]</xref>. In contrast, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> or <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> are associated with shorter coleoptiles and smaller seedling leaf area and have a poor emergence when sown deeply <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke3">[13]</xref>.</p>
      <p>It has been reported that <italic>Rht12</italic> had no negative effects on root dry mass <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Wojciechowski2">[66]</xref>. In this study, a reduction in total number of seminal roots and a significant reduction in root dry mass (11%) were observed in <italic>Rht12</italic> dwarf lines at the seedling stage. These different findings may be due to the effect of either different genetic backgrounds or different growing environments, or both. In contrast, a longer maximum root length and a higher dry mass ratio of root to shoot were achieved in <italic>Rht12</italic> dwarf lines. Thus, <italic>Rht12</italic> had both negative and positive effects on root growth attributes. Further work should be conducted to explore the possibility of enhancing aspects of root growth such as root length using <italic>Rht12</italic> to enable crops to grow in drier environments.</p>
      <p>The increase in ear fertility is observed as one the most important advantages of almost all the major height-reducing genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Miralles1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke5">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Youssefian1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Miralles2">[55]</xref>. Kernels per spike, especially the fertility of the top three spikelets were significantly increased in <italic>Rht12</italic> dwarf lines in the AS experiment. Consistent with that, <italic>Rht12</italic> significantly increased ear fertility in different varietal backgrounds, which results in the increase of grain numbers per spike <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Worland1">[2]</xref>. Whereas, spike length, spikelet number per spike and (particularly) grain size were all reduced in the <italic>Rht12</italic> dwarf lines in this study as the lowest spike length and spikelet number per spike were observed in RRbb genotype while the highest in rrBB lines in both AS and SS experiments. <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s1">Introduction</xref> of the dominant vernalization gene can help to compensate some of the effects of <italic>Rht12</italic> on yield parameters. Similar reductions in spikelet numbers have previously been correlated with genes other than height-reducing, particularly with <italic>Ppd1</italic>, where an average of two fewer spikelets per spike were produced <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Worland3">[67]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The reduction in leaf length in lines containing dwarfing or semi-dwarfing <italic>Rht-1</italic> alleles (i.e. <italic>Rht-B1b&#x200A;=&#x200A;Rht1</italic>, <italic>Rht-D1b&#x200A;=&#x200A;Rht2</italic> and <italic>Rhtb1c&#x200A;=&#x200A;Rht3</italic>) is mainly due to shortening of cell length while the number of cells is not modified, and it has been suggested that <italic>Rht-1</italic> alleles may likewise limit cell length in the pericarp to reduce potential grain size <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Keyes1">[4]</xref>. However, Miralles et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Miralles2">[55]</xref> found that <italic>Rht-1</italic> alleles did not modify cell length nor width in the pericarp, but reduced the total number of cells in that tissue, presumably by affecting cell division. It was also observed that the smaller average grain size conferred by <italic>Rht</italic> alleles were not only a consequence of a higher grain number produced in distal florets, but were also due to smaller grains at certain positions within the spike <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Miralles1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Flintham2">[59]</xref>. Additionally, it has been suggested that reduced grain size with <italic>Rht</italic> alleles was associated with a competitive response to the increased spikelet fertility under limiting photosynthate availability, rather than a primary effect of the dwarfing genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Flintham2">[59]</xref>. Furthermore, flowering time can also influence grain size, because delayed flowering shortens the period of time available with favourable conditions prior to harvest <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Worland1">[2]</xref>. In this study, the delay of 5&#x2013;6 days in flowering time associated with <italic>Rht12</italic> could have affected the development and size of grains. Also, the small size of vegetative organs (especially the flag leaf and peduncle) of <italic>Rht12</italic> lines may have limited the assimilates available for producing large grains. Thus, the reduction in grain size of different dwarf genes may be through different modes of action from each other <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Allan1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke5">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Miralles2">[55]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The pleiotropic effects of <italic>Rht12</italic> on several yield components were evaluated in the present study. <italic>Rht12</italic> increased the number of grains per spike and reduced grain size, resulting in an overall reduction in spike yield. Whereas, whole plant yields are dependent on both ear yields and the number of fertile ears produced per plant. Due to the increased number of tillers in dwarf plants (in AS experiment), the final yield per plant was not significantly different between the tall and dwarf plants. Although the plant biomass of dwarf plants was reduced, the harvest index of <italic>Rht12</italic> dwarf plants increased significantly in both AS and SS experiments. The greater harvest index and grain number for <italic>Rht12</italic> alleles was consistent with the effects of other dwarfing genes that reduced competition between growing florets and elongating stems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Rebetzke5">[21]</xref>. <italic>Rht12</italic> has potential for increasing harvest index and total biomass in autumn sowing environment without compromising on establishment and early growth of seedlings, but it should be noted that in this study <italic>Rht12</italic> dwarf lines had lower yields in the spring sowing environment.</p>
      <p><italic>Rht12</italic> has been classified as a GA-responsive dwarfing gene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Worland1">[2]</xref>, but its role, if any, in GA biosynthesis or signalling remains unknown. <italic>Rht12</italic> is located on chromosome 5AL, linked to Xgwm291 at a distance of 5.4 cM. Thus, high resolution mapping should be initiated for eventual map-based cloning of <italic>Rht12</italic>. To date none of the dwarfing genes are cloned except a few GA-insensitive dwarf genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Pearce1">[33]</xref>. More information on these genes is needed for a better understanding of how the dwarf genes act on plant growth and what their roles are in GA biosynthesis or signalling. However, it was found that the effects of the dwarf gene <italic>Rht8</italic> which had been considered as &#x2018;GA-sensitive&#x2019; was possibly not due to the defective gibberellin biosynthesis or signalling, but possibly to a reduced sensitivity to brassinosteroids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Gasperini1">[34]</xref>. Similarly, there may be more complex relations between <italic>Rht</italic> genes and GAs uncovered by future research.</p>
      <p>Previous research has indicated that the main disadvantage of <italic>Rht12</italic> is the long vegetative phase resulting in late ear emergence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062285-Worland1">[2]</xref>. In this study, even the dominant <italic>Vrn-B1</italic>, which accelerates flowering, could not compensate for the negative effect of <italic>Rht12</italic> on flowering time. RRBB and RRbb had a similar duration of SW-DR while rrBB had shorter SW-DR duration than rrbb, suggesting that <italic>Rht12</italic> might be partially epistatic to <italic>Vrn-B1</italic>. Therefore, development-promoting genes need to be combined with <italic>Rht12</italic> to compensate for the delay in ear emergence in order to exploit the potential of <italic>Rht12</italic> in breeding programs. In this study, one dwarf line with earlier ear emergence time (2 days earlier than other dwarf lines) was observed, indicating that selection for early ear emergence may be possible among <italic>Rht12</italic> progeny. We have established other crosses for this purpose and also for further analysing the potential of <italic>Rht12</italic> for crop improvement.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0062285.s001">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Plant height and internode length of different groups of the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines in the autumn-sown (AS) and spring-sown (SS) experiments.</bold> All data are means &#xB1;SD of each genotype. Data of the two parents were not considered in the statistical significance testing. Different letters within columns indicate statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0062285.s001.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0062285.s002">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Diameter and wall thickness of the internodes of different groups of the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines in the autumn-sown (AS) and spring-sown (SS) experiments.</bold> Note: DI is internode diameter at the mid-point; WT is wall thickness. The sixth internode is the peduncle. All data are means &#xB1;SD of each genotype. Data of the two parents were not considered in the statistical significance testing. Different letters within columns indicate statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0062285.s002.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0062285.s003">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>The mean length, width and area of the top three leaves of different groups of the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines in the autumn-sown (AS) and spring-sown (SS) experiments at grain-filling stage.</bold> *, The second and third leaves are from the flag leaf down on the main shoot. All data are means &#xB1;SD of each genotype. Data of the two parents were not considered in the statistical significance testing. Different letters within columns indicate statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0062285.s003.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0062285.s004">
        <label>Table S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Dry weight (mg) of different organs in main shoot after anthesis of different groups of the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines in the autumn-sown (AS) experiment.</bold> *, The main culm comprises 6 internodes, the sixth internode is the peduncle. The leaves are numbered from the flag leaf down on the main stem. RR: dwarf alleles; rr: tall alleles. DDW is the difference between maximum dry weight and minimum dry weight, with its proportion to the maximum dry weight in the parenthesis. Values are given as the mean &#xB1;SD.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0062285.s004.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0062285.s005">
        <label>Table S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Dry weight (mg) of different organs in main shoot after anthesis of different groups of the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines in spring-sown (SS) experiment.</bold> *, The main culm comprises 6 internodes, the sixth internode is the peduncle. The leaves are numbered from the flag leaf down on the main stem. RR: dwarf alleles; rr: tall alleles. DDW is the difference between maximum dry weight and minimum dry weight, with its proportion to the maximum dry weight in the parenthesis. Values are given as the mean &#xB1;SD.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0062285.s005.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We are grateful to Peter Hedden, Stephen Thomas and Yidan Li at Rothamsted Research for their helpful discussion. We also thank OPTICHINA (an EU/CAAS funded project) which aims to link the crop improvement research activities carried out by European and Chinese researchers by providing LC the opportunity of training at Rothamsted Research, UK.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Hedden1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hedden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The genes of the Green Revolution</article-title>. <source>Trends in Genetics</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12493241</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Worland1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Worland</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sayers</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The Genetics and Breeding Potential of Rht12, a Dominant Dwarfing Gene in Wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant Breeding</source><volume>113</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>196</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Miralles1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miralles</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slafer</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Yield, biomass and yield components in dwarf, semi-dwarf and tall isogenic lines of spring wheat under recommended and late sowing dates</article-title>. <source>Plant Breeding</source><volume>114</volume>: <fpage>392</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>396</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Keyes1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Keyes</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paolillo</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>The Effects of Dwarfing Genes Rht1 and Rht2 on Cellular Dimensions and Rate of Leaf Elongation in Wheat</article-title>. <source>Annals of Botany</source><volume>64</volume>: <fpage>683</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>690</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Rebetzke1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rebetzke</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mickelson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Breeding long coleoptile, reduced height wheats</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>106</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>168</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Allan1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Agronomic Comparisons between Rht1 and Rht2 Semidwarf Genes in Winter-Wheat</article-title>. <source>Crop Science</source><volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1103</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1108</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Richards1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>The Effect of Dwarfing Genes in Spring Wheat in Dry Environments.2. Growth, Water-Use and Water-Use Efficiency</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Agricultural Research</source><volume>43</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>539</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Rebetzke2">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rebetzke</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sirault</surname><given-names>XRR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Genetic analysis of coleoptile length and diameter in wheat</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Agricultural Research</source><volume>55</volume>: <fpage>733</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>743</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Botwright1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Botwright</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rebetzke</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Condon</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Influence of the gibberellin-sensitive Rht8 dwarfing gene on leaf epidermal cell dimensions and early vigour in wheat (Triticum aestivum L.)</article-title>. <source>Annals of Botany</source><volume>95</volume>: <fpage>631</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15655105</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Butler1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Agronomic performance of Rht alleles in a spring wheat population across a range of moisture levels</article-title>. <source>Crop Science</source><volume>45</volume>: <fpage>939</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>947</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Chapman1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trethowan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Relationships between height and yield in near-isogenic spring wheats that contrast for major reduced height genes</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>157</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>397</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Shackley1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shackley</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Responses of Wheat Cultivars to Time of Sowing in the Southern Wheat-Belt of Western-Australia</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Experimental Agriculture</source><volume>35</volume>: <fpage>579</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>587</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Rebetzke3">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rebetzke</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fettell</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Condon</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genotypic increases in coleoptile length improves stand establishment, vigour and grain yield of deep-sown wheat</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Research</source><volume>100</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>23</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Mahdi1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mahdi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Establishment and yield of wheat (Triticum turgidum L.) after early sowing at various depths in a semi-arid Mediterranean environment</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Research</source><volume>58</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>196</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Berry1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sylvester-Bradley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Ideotype design for lodging-resistant wheat</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>154</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>179</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Stapper1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stapper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Genotype, sowing date and plant spacing influence on high-yielding irrigated wheat in southern New South Wales. II. Growth, yield and nitrogen use</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Agricultural Research</source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1021</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1041</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Flintham1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Flintham</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Worland</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Optimizing wheat grain yield: Effects of Rht (gibberellin-insensitive) dwarfing genes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural Science</source><volume>128</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Worland2">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Worland</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Korzun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ganal</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Genetic analysis of the dwarfing gene Rht8 in wheat. Part II. The distribution and adaptive significance of allelic variants at the Rht8 locus of wheat as revealed by microsatellite screening</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>96</volume>: <fpage>1110</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1120</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Zhang1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Distribution of the Rht-B1b, Rht-D1b and Rht8 reduced height genes in autumn-sown Chinese wheats detected by molecular markers</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>152</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>116</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Rebetzke4">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rebetzke</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Gibberellic acid-sensitive dwarfing genes reduce plant height to increase kernel number and grain yield of wheat</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Agricultural Research</source><volume>51</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>245</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Rebetzke5">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rebetzke</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bonnett</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mickelson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Condon</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Height reduction and agronomic performance for selected gibberellin-responsive dwarfing genes in bread wheat (Triticum aestivum L.)</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Research</source><volume>126</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>96</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Ellis1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rebetzke</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bonnett</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spielmeyer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The effect of different height reducing genes on the early growth of wheat</article-title>. <source>Functional Plant Biology</source><volume>31</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>589</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Ellis2">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rebetzke</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Azanza</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spielmeyer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Molecular mapping of gibberellin-responsive dwarfing genes in bread wheat</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>111</volume>: <fpage>423</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15968526</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Slafer1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slafer</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rawson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Sensitivity of Wheat Phasic Development to Major Environmental-Factors - a Reexamination of Some Assumptions Made by Physiologists and Modelers</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Plant Physiology</source><volume>21</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>426</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Fischer1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Yield Potential in a Dwarf Spring Wheat and Effect of Shading</article-title>. <source>Crop Science</source><volume>15</volume>: <fpage>607</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>613</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Gonzalez1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slafer</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miralles</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Pre-anthesis development and number of fertile florets in wheat as affected by photoperiod sensitivity genes Ppd-D1 and Ppd-B1</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>146</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>269</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Slafer2">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slafer</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rawson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Responses to photoperiod change with phenophase and temperature during wheat development</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Research</source><volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>13</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Slafer3">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slafer</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abeledo</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miralles</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whitechurch</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Photoperiod sensitivity during stem elongation as an avenue to raise potential yield in wheat</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>119</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>197</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Yamaguchi1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Gibberellin metabolism and its regulation</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source><volume>59</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>251</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Hansen1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grossmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Auxin-induced ethylene triggers abscisic acid biosynthesis and growth inhibition</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>124</volume>: <fpage>1437</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11080318</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Thomas1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Update on gibberellin signaling. A tale of the tall and the short</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>135</volume>: <fpage>668</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15208413</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Fleet1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fleet</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A DELLAcate balance: the role of gibberellin in plant morphogenesis</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15653404</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Pearce1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saville</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Molecular Characterization of Rht-1 Dwarfing Genes in Hexaploid Wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>157</volume>: <fpage>1820</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22013218</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Gasperini1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gasperini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hedden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dreos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Genetic and physiological analysis of Rht8 in bread wheat: an alternative source of semi-dwarfism with a reduced sensitivity to brassinosteroids</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>63</volume>: <fpage>4419</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22791821</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Cockram1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cockram</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leigh</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O&#x2019;Sullivan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Control of flowering time in temperate cereals: genes, domestication, and sustainable productivity</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>58</volume>: <fpage>1231</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17420173</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Prasil1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Prasil</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prasilova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pankova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Relationships among vernalization, shoot apex development and frost tolerance in wheat</article-title>. <source>Annals of Botany</source><volume>94</volume>: <fpage>413</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15277245</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Youssefian1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Youssefian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>EJM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Pleiotropic Effects of the Ga-Insensitive Rht Dwarfing Genes in Wheat.2. Effects on Leaf, Stem, Ear and Floret Growth</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Research</source><volume>28</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>210</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Calderini1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calderini</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miralles</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sadras</surname><given-names>VO</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Appearance and Growth of Individual Leaves as Affected by Semidwarfism in Isogenic Lines of Wheat</article-title>. <source>Annals of Botany</source><volume>77</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>589</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Iwaki1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Iwaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanagisawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Genetic analysis of Vrn-B1 for vernalization requirement by using linked dCAPS markers in bread wheat (Triticum aestivum L.)</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>104</volume>: <fpage>571</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12582660</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Law1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Worland</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giorgi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>The genetic control of ear emergence time by chromosomes 5A and 5D of wheat</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source><volume>36</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>58</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Yan1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Helguera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fukuyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Allelic variation at the VRN-1 promoter region in polyploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and applied genetics</source><volume>109</volume>: <fpage>1677</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15480533</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Chen1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Detection of SNPs in the VRN-A1 gene of common wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) by a modified Ecotilling method using agarose gel electrophoresis</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Crop science</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>329</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Pugsley1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pugsley</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>A genetic analysis of the spring-wheat habit in wheat</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Agricultural Research</source><volume>22</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>23</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Viglasi1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Viglasi P (1968) Short-Strawed Mutants of Karcag 522 Winter Wheat Induced by Gamma Rays. Acta Agronomica Academiae Scientiarum Hungaricae 17: 205-&amp;.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Sutka1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sutka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Chromosomal Location of Dwarfing Gene Rht12 in Wheat</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>36</volume>: <fpage>521</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>523</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Korzun1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Korzun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Worland</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Intrachromosomal mapping of genes for dwarfing (Rht12) and vernalization response (Vrn1) in wheat by using RFLP and microsatellite markers</article-title>. <source>Plant Breeding</source><volume>116</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>232</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Wojciechowski1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wojciechowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gooding</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The effects of dwarfing genes on seedling root growth of wheat</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>60</volume>: <fpage>2565</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19439763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Fu1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Szucs</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Helguera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Large deletions within the first intron in VRN-1 are associated with spring growth habit in barley and wheat</article-title>. <source>Molecular Genetics and Genomics</source><volume>273</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15690172</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Aldrich1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cullis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>RAPD analysis in flax: Optimization of yield and reproducibility using klenTaq 1 DNA polymerase, chelex 100, and gel purification of genomic DNA</article-title>. <source>Plant Molecular Biology Reporter</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>128</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>141</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Chen2">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chen L, Huang LZ, Min DH, Phillips A, Wang SQ, <etal>et al</etal>. (2012) Development and Characterization of a New TILLING Population of Common Bread Wheat (Triticum aestivum L.). Plos One 7.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Botwright2">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Botwright</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rebetzke</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Condon</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Influence of variety, seed position and seed source on screening for coleoptile length in bread wheat (Triticum aestivum L.)</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>119</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>356</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Gardner1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trione</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Development of the Young Wheat Spike - a Sem Study of Chinese Spring Wheat</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Botany</source><volume>72</volume>: <fpage>548</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>559</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Waddington1">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Waddington</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cartwright</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>A Quantitative Scale of Spike Initial and Pistil Development in Barley and Wheat</article-title>. <source>Annals of Botany</source><volume>51</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>130</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Zadoks1">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zadoks</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Konzak</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Decimal Code for Growth Stages of Cereals</article-title>. <source>Weed Research</source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>415</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>421</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Miralles2">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miralles</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colloca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slafer</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Floret development in near isogenic wheat lines differing in plant height</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Research</source><volume>59</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>30</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Haun1">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Haun</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Visual Quantification of Wheat Development</article-title>. <source>Agronomy Journal</source><volume>65</volume>: <fpage>116</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>119</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Berry2">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sylvester-Bradley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spink</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Controlling plant form through husbandry to minimise lodging in wheat</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Research</source><volume>67</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>81</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Griffiths1">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>FEW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lyndon</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>The Effects of Vernalization on the Growth of the Wheat Shoot Apex</article-title>. <source>Annals of Botany</source><volume>56</volume>: <fpage>501</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>511</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Flintham2">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Flintham</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>The Tom Thumb Dwarfing Gene Rht3 in Wheat.2. Effects on Height, Yield and Grain Quality</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>66</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>256</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Bancal1">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bancal</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ney</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Modelling wheat growth and yield losses from late epidemics of foliar diseases using loss of green leaf area per layer and pre-anthesis reserves</article-title>. <source>Annals of Botany</source><volume>100</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17686762</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Kirby1">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>EJM</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Analysis of Leaf, Stem and Ear Growth in Wheat from Terminal Spikelet Stage to Anthesis</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Research</source><volume>18</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>140</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Fischer2">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stockman</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Kernel Number Per Spike in Wheat (Triticum-Aestivum L) - Responses to Preanthesis Shading</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Plant Physiology</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>180</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Slafer4">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slafer</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Satorre</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Genetic-Improvement Effects on Preanthesis Physiological Attributes Related to Wheat Grain-Yield</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Research</source><volume>23</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>263</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Gonzalez2">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slafer</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miralles</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Floret development and spike growth as affected by photoperiod during stem elongation in wheat</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Res</source><volume>81</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>38</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Addisu1">
        <label>65</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Addisu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snape</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gooding</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Reduced height (Rht) and photoperiod insensitivity (Ppd) allele associations with establishment and early growth of wheat in contrasting production systems</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>166</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>267</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Wojciechowski2">
        <label>66</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wojciechowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gooding</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The effects of dwarfing genes on seedling root growth of wheat</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source><volume>60</volume>: <fpage>2565</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19439763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0062285-Worland3">
        <label>67</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Worland</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petrovic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Genetic analysis of chromosome 2D of wheat. II: The importance of this chromosome to Yugoslavian varieties</article-title>. <source>Plant Breeding</source><volume>100</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>259</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
