<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Chem</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Chem</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Chem.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Frontiers in Chemistry</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2296-2646</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4513236</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fchem.2015.00046</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Chemistry</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Original Research</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Seed dormancy is modulated in recently evolved chlorsulfuron-resistant Turkish biotypes of wild mustard (<italic>Sinapis arvensis</italic>)</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Topuz</surname>
            <given-names>Muhamet</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nemli</surname>
            <given-names>Yildiz</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fatima</surname>
            <given-names>Tahira</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mattoo</surname>
            <given-names>Autar K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
          <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/76550/overview"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <sup>1</sup>
        <institution>Sustainable Agricultural Systems Laboratory, Agricultural Research Service, United States Department of Agriculture, Henry A. Wallace Beltsville Agricultural Research Center</institution>
        <country>Beltsville, MD, USA</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <sup>2</sup>
        <institution>Plant Protection Research Station, Department of Plant Protection, Ege University</institution>
        <country>Izmir, Turkey</country>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Edited by: Jimmy R. Botella, University of Queensland, Australia</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Reviewed by: Kenneth Wilson, University of Saskatchewan, Canada; Anirudha R. Dixit, NASA/John F Kennedy Space Center, USA</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Autar K. Mattoo, Sustainable Agricultural Systems Laboratory, Henry A. Wallace Beltsville Agricultural Research Center, USDA-ARS, Building 001, Beltsville, MD 20705-2350, USA <email xlink:type="simple">autar.mattoo@ars.usda.gov</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn002">
          <p>This article was submitted to Agricultural Biological Chemistry, a section of the journal Frontiers in Chemistry</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <elocation-id>46</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>09</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2015 Topuz, Nemli, Fatima and Mattoo.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Topuz, Nemli, Fatima and Mattoo</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Biotypes of the broad-leaved wild mustard (<italic>Sinapis arvensis</italic> L.) found in wheat fields of Aegean and Marmara region of Turkey were characterized and shown to have developed resistance to sulfonylurea (chlorsulfuron), an inhibitor of acetolactate synthase (ALS). DNA sequence analysis of the <italic>ALS</italic> genes from two such resistant (&#x201C;R&#x201D;) biotypes, KNF-R1 and KNF-R2, revealed point mutations, CCT (Pro 197) to TCT (Ser 197) in KNF-R1 and CCT (Pro 197) to ACT (Thr 197) in KNF-R2; these substitutions are consistent with the presence of chlorsulfuron-insensitive ALS enzyme activity in the &#x201C;R&#x201D; <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes. An additional phenotype of chlorsulfuron resistance in the Turkish <italic>S. arvensis</italic> &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes was revealed in the form of an altered seed dormancy behavior over 4&#x2013;48 months of dry storage (after-ripening) compared to the susceptible (&#x201C;S&#x201D;) biotypes. Seeds of the &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes dry stored for 4 months had a higher initial germination, which sharply decreased with storage time, while the seeds of the &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes had lower germination after 4-months storage, rising sharply and peaking thereafter by 24 months' of dry storage. The &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype seeds continued to maintain a higher germination percentage even after 48 months of after-ripening. The seed weight of &#x201C;R&#x201D; and &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes after-ripened for 4 months was similar but those after-ripened for 48 months differed, &#x201C;R&#x201D; seeds were significantly heavier than those of the &#x201C;S&#x201D; seeds. Differential seed germinability between &#x201C;S&#x201D; and &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes was found not a case of differential viability, temperature regimen or non-response to pro-germination hormone GA<sub>3</sub>. These studies are of relevance to ecological fitness of herbicide-resistant biotypes in terms of seed viability and germination.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Sinapis arvensis</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>ALS inhibitor</kwd>
        <kwd>herbicide resistance</kwd>
        <kwd>point mutations</kwd>
        <kwd>seed dormancy</kwd>
        <kwd>germination</kwd>
        <kwd>gibberellins</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source id="cn001">U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA)</funding-source>
        </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="7"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <equation-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="49"/>
        <page-count count="11"/>
        <word-count count="7708"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Maximizing crop yields are vital for feeding the burgeoning population in the world. Major obstacles to increasing crop productivity include weed competition (as high as 100 billion dollars a year or even more), and maintaining seed vigor of the cash crop upon storage since seed germination decreases upon aging (Kocsy, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). For instance, wheat yield losses are proportional to increased weed density (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www1.agric.gov.ab.ca/$department/deptdocs.nsf/all/crop1280">http://www1.agric.gov.ab.ca/$department/deptdocs.nsf/all/crop1280</ext-link>), since the latter compete for soil nutrients, water, space and light. Weeds have therefore been a major management constraint for agriculturists, farmers, and crop biologists alike. The discovery of sulfonylureas as inhibitors of acetolactate synthase (ALS) [EC 4.1.3.18], also known as acetohydroxyacid synthase (AHAS), which catalyzes the first committed step in the biosynthesis of branched-chain amino acids (valine, leucine, and isoleucine), led to sulfonylureas-based herbicides as effective weed management tool for a number of crops including wheat (Umbarger, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">1978</xref>; Tranel and Wright, <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>).</p>
      <p>Chlorsulfuron was formulated as an herbicide and introduced into agriculture worldwide over 30 years ago to control growth of monocot and dicot weed species. Its frequent use, however, led to weed resistant biotypes, such as prickly lettuce (<italic>Lactuca seriola</italic> L.) (Mallory-Smith et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>) and kochia (<italic>Kochia scoparia</italic> L. Schrad.) (Primiani et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>). The resistance to chlorsulfuron was linked to point mutation(s) in the ALS gene, which prevented herbicide binding to the ALS enzyme (Mallory-Smith et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>; Martinez-Ghersa et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>), as well as to enhanced ability to catabolize the herbicide (Primiani et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>). By 2015, 246 plant species (103 monocots and 143 dicot) are reported to have developed resistance to ALS inhibitors (Heap, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).</p>
      <p>The relevance of herbicide resistance is of tremendous concern for weed management including the possibility of their altered ecological fitness in regard to their growth, competitive ability and seed production and seed germination ability (Gressel and Segel, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">1978</xref>; Tranel and Wright, <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Vila-Aiub et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Little information is available on the fitness of chlorsulfuron-resistant weeds, although an early report found seeds of chlorsulfuron-resistant kochia biotype to germinate faster than the susceptible biotype (Dyer et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>).</p>
      <p>Wheat is grown in Turkey in ~9.4 m ha, occupying about 45% of the total arable land (FAOSTAT Database; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org">http://www.fao.org</ext-link>). The application of sulfonylurea herbicides has successfully managed weeds in Turkish agriculture (including wheat, rice, and maize cultivations) in the past for over 30 years. Among these weeds, wild mustard (S<italic>inapis arvensis</italic> L.) is of noted importance causing substantial yield losses in wheat even when present at low seeding rate (60 plants/m<sup>2</sup>) (Gillespie and Nalewaja, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>). Another study conducted on <italic>S</italic>. <italic>arvensis</italic> at seeding rates of 54 and 108 plants m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> found 12&#x2013;20 and 20&#x2013;56% reductions in wheat yields, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www1.agric.gov.ab.ca/$department/deptdocs.nsf/all/crop1280">http://www1.agric.gov.ab.ca/$department/deptdocs.nsf/all/crop1280</ext-link>).</p>
      <p><italic>S. arvensis</italic> is frequently observed in the wheat growing Aegean and Marmara region of Turkey (Boz, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Topuz and Nemli, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). Two of its biotypes, called KNF-R1 and KNF-R2, were identified as being resistant to sulfonylurea application in the Band&#x131;rma-Bal&#x131;kesir province of the latter wheat-growing region. Here, we characterize chlorsulfuron resistance in these Turkish <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes at physiological and molecular levels, linking resistance to known mutation(s) in the <italic>ALS</italic> gene and a chlorsulfuron-insensitive ALS enzyme. Further, we show an additional phenotype of chlorsulfuron resistant <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes in the form of an altered seed dormancy behavior compared to the susceptible biotypes. These studies are of relevance to ecological fitness of herbicide-resistant biotypes in terms of seed viability and germination.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Plant material</title>
        <p>Wild mustard (<italic>S. arvensis</italic>) seeds were collected from surviving weeds in wheat fields sprayed with chlorsulfuron in Band&#x131;rma-Bal&#x131;kesir provinces of Marmara region (latitude 40&#xB0; 19&#x2032; 6&#x2033; N and longitude 27&#xB0; 58&#x2032; 40&#x2033; E), Turkey. Two resistant (R) biotypes (labeled as KNF-R1 and KNF-R2) were collected from wheat fields in Kulefli, ~4 km apart, about 8 km southwest of Band&#x131;rma airport. These fields had a history of chlorsulfuron applications for weed control for several years. Chlorsulfuron-susceptible (&#x201C;S&#x201D;) biotypes (labeled as MR-S biotype for herbicide resistance studies; and MR-S1 and MR-S2 for seed germination studies) were collected from ditch banks next to wheat fields from which KNF-R1 and KNF-R2 biotypes originated. Seeds of each biotype were collected from five plants, bulked, air dried at room temperature, and then stored at 4&#xB0;C until use.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Whole plant herbicide dose-response studies</title>
        <p>Dose-response data for chlorsulfuron were generated from experiments carried out both in Turkey and the USA. The remaining experiments were performed solely in the USA. In Turkey, the experiments were carried out in open net houses covered by polyethylene at the Plant Protection Research Institute, Izmir/Bornova. The seeds were directly seeded in 20 &#xD7; 20 &#xD7; 20 cm pots containing turf (obtained after sieving decomposed tree leaf litter):soil:sand (2:1:1 ratio), at three plants per pot. Experiments in the USA were carried out in a temperature-controlled greenhouse at the USDA, Henry A. Wallace Beltsville Agricultural Research Center, Maryland (latitude 39&#xB0; 1&#x2032; 39.35&#x2033; N and longitude 76&#xB0; 55'35.40W). Seeds were sown in Metro-mix 360 (Scotts-Sierra Horticultural Products, Marysville, OH, USA) in plastic containers. At the cotyledon stage, the seedlings were transplanted into 10 &#xD7; 10 &#xD7; 10 cm plastic pots (1 plant per pot in quadruplicate) on the same media. Temperature regime was 21&#xB0;C/16&#xB0;C day/night with 16 h photoperiod supplemented with 230 &#x3BC;mol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> illumination. Plants were watered daily and treated at 3&#x2013;4 leaf stage with chlorsulfuron (Glean/Glean&#xAE;) using a hand sprayer (Turkey) or pressurized sprayer (USA), both equipped with a flat fan nozzle (8001E), calibrated to deliver 300 L ha-1 of spray solution at 210 kPa. Chlorsulfuron was applied at rates (indicated in the text) that were 0.5&#x2013;8 times the recommended application rates in Turkey (10 g a.i ha<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>), and from 0.25 to 128 times in the USA based on a calculated minimum rate of 10 g a.i ha<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. The untreated controls were sprayed with water instead of the herbicide. The effects of the applied herbicides were evaluated 21 days after the treatment (DAT). The shoots were cut at soil level to collect the biomass, which was then air dried at 65&#xB0;C for 72 h to determine dry weight. Plant pots were arranged in a randomized complete block design, with five replications in Turkey and four replications in USA, and experiments were repeated twice. Whole plant herbicide cross-resistance was studied with trifensulfuron-methyl (doses equivalent to 4.35, 8.7, 17.4, 34.8, and 69.6 g a.i ha<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>; Harmony&#xAE; GT, 750 g a.i kg-1, Du Pont). Chlorsulfuron resistant (KNF-R1 and KNF-R2) and susceptible (MR-S) biotypes were grown as described above and treated at the 3&#x2013;4 leaf stage for cross resistance pattern for trifensulfuron-methyl. In all the experiments, untreated controls were sprayed with water. Herbicides were applied with a pressurized sprayer with a flat fan nozzle as described above.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Acetolactate synthase (ALS) enzyme assay</title>
        <p>Leaves were excised from the resistant KNF-R1 and KNF-R2, and susceptible MR-S <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes, and processed for the preparation of cell-free extracts, protein precipitation with ammonium sulfate and desalting on Sephadex G-25 column as previously described (Ray, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>). ALS [EC 4.1.3.18] activity was determined in 60% ammonium sulfate precipitated protein fraction (after desalting). Total protein content was determined by the Bradford method (Bradford, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">1976</xref>). The ALS enzyme assay was carried out with slight modifications as previously described (Rashid et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). The reaction assay mixture contained, in a final volume of 500 &#x3BC;L, desalted (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>-precipitated protein (100 &#x3BC;g), 300 &#x3BC;L of the assay medium (83.3 mM potassium phosphate, pH 7.0, containing 167 mM sodium pyruvate,16.7 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>,1.67 mM thiamine pyrophosphate and 16.6 &#x3BC;L FAD), and H<sub>2</sub>O or herbicide. The herbicide concentrations were varied from 0 to 100 nM. The reaction mixtures were incubated at 35&#xB0;C for 60 min and the enzymatic reaction stopped by adding 50 &#x3BC;l of 6 N H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. After incubation at 60&#xB0;C for 15 min, 25 &#x3BC;l of 3N NaOH were added to each tube, and pH adjusted to 7.0. The samples were microfuged for 5 min. After adding 500 &#x3BC;l each of creatine (Sigma, C0780, 5.45 g l<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> in water) and 1-napthol (54.5 g l<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> in freshly prepared 2.5 N NaOH), the tubes were incubated at 60&#xB0;C. The samples were microfuged for 1 min and then absorbance of the color developed was measured spectrophotometrically at 525 nm (Molecular Devices Spectra Max Plus<sup>384</sup>). The experiment was repeated 3 times.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>ALS gene sequencing</title>
        <p>Genomic DNA was extracted from young leaves, excised from a total of 5 plants from each biotype, as previously described (Delaporta et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">1983</xref>) and quantified spectrophotometrically. The <italic>ALS</italic> gene from MR-S, KNF-R1, and KNF-R2 biotypes was PCR amplified and the PCR products sequenced to determine the sites where mutations may have arisen. Three overlapping regions were amplified using primer sets (Tan and Medd, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) and conditions as described (Warwick et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). The PCR amplification reaction contained 100 ng genomic DNA, primers (each 0.5 &#x3BC;M), 200 &#x3BC;M dNTP, 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and 2 &#x3BC;l (5 units/&#x3BC;l) Go Taq&#xAE; Flexi DNA Polymerase (Promega cat No: M8291) in a final volume of 100 &#x3BC;l. PCR products were separated on 1.5% low melting agarose gels and purified using Qiaquick&#xAE; Gel Purification Kit (Qiagen, 28704). Direct cycle sequencing was outsourced to MWG, North Carolina (USA). Each PCR product was sequenced with both forward and reverse primers. Nucleotide and amino acid positions were numbered based on the amino acid sequence of <italic>ALS</italic> from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (Sathasivan et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>List of primers used to amplify the <italic>ALS</italic> gene of <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes</bold>.</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Primer sequence 5&#x2032; &#x2013; 3&#x2032;</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALS1F TTCR<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref>TCTCCCGM<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref>TACGCTCCC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALS1R CAARCTGY<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref>TGCTGAATATC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALS2F GATGTTCCTAAGGATATTC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALS2R CTGATGYTGYCCAACACC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALS3F GGR<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref>GAAGCCATTCCTCC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALS3R TCARTACTW<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref>AGTGCK<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref>ACCATC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALS11F AGGGTTACGCTCGTTCCTC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALS11R GAAACTTCCGGAGGCTGAG</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="TN1">
              <label>a</label>
              <p><italic>I.U.P.A.C-I.U.B codes for mixed bases R (AG), M (AC), Y (CT), W (AT), K (GT)</italic>.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Seed preparation for germination studies</title>
        <p>Experiments carried out in the laboratory, growth chamber and greenhouse followed completely randomized design with four replications, and were repeated twice. Seeds were stored at 4&#xB0;C for the times indicated in the text. Prior to use, seeds from <italic>S. arvensis</italic> resistant and susceptible biotypes were surface sterilized for 1 min in 70% ethanol followed by two 5 min immersions in 0.3% sodium hypochlorite and then thoroughly rinsed with sterile water (Yajima et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). The same seed lots and germination chambers were used throughout the germination assays.</p>
        <p>In the laboratory, seeds were placed in 12-well petri dishes with 2 seeds per well (24 seeds petri-dish<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) on sterile double filter paper, previously moistened with sterile water (0.6 ml well<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>). Dormancy and viability tests were carried out in the absence and presence of gibberellic acid (GA<sub>3</sub>) at 0.1&#x2013;10 mM. GA<sub>3</sub> was first dissolved in isopropyl alcohol, and then diluted with water to achieve indicated concentrations. Controls included sterile water. The petri dishes were sealed with parafilm and stored in the dark at 22&#xB0;C &#xB1; 2 &#xB0;C. Germination of seeds (aged 3 and 8 years) was assessed daily, in the dark, for 14 days; germinated seeds were counted and removed. Germination was defined as any seed where the seed coat was found broken and the radicle was visible.</p>
        <p>For experiments carried out in a temperature-controlled greenhouse (Henry A. Wallace Beltsville Agricultural Research Center, MD), seeds were sown on Metro-mix 360 (Scotts-Sierra Horticultural Products, Marysville, OH) in plastic containers (36 seeds replicate<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>), watered daily and germination evaluated for 21 days at 12 h intervals. Temperature regime was 21&#xB0;C/16&#xB0;C day/night with 16 h photoperiod supplemented with 230 &#x3BC;mol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> illumination. The germinated seeds were counted and removed from the containers.</p>
        <p>The effect of different temperature regimes (5, 10, and15&#xB0;C) on seed germination was carried out in a growth chamber under 16 h light/8 h dark photoperiod.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Effect of after-ripening time on seed weight and seed germination rate</title>
        <p>Lots of 100 seeds each were randomly taken from two resistant (&#x201C;R&#x201D;) and two susceptible (&#x201C;S&#x201D;) biotypes for measuring weight of seeds that were dry-stored (after-ripening) for 4 months and 4 years. Seeds of (&#x201C;R&#x201D;) and (&#x201C;S&#x201D;) biotypes were evaluated for germination rates in a greenhouse taking seed lots stored for 4 months, 2 years, and 4 years (after-ripening time). Seeds were sown on Metro-mix 360 (Scotts-Sierra Horticultural Products, Marysville, OH) in plastic containers (36 seeds replicate<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>), watered daily and germination evaluated for 21 days at 12 h intervals.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>The data on percentage of seeds that germinated on each plate were statistically analyzed using SPSS 15.0 for windows. Data were logarithmically transformed and then subjected to analysis of variance to determine the significance of differences between means at the 5% level of probability using the Duncan test. For further analysis, germinating seedlings were scored and converted to mean germination percentage and the standard errors of the means calculated. Dose-response curves (for chlorsulfuron) for the whole plant bioassay were plotted and statistically analyzed by SAS (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>) using a non-linear regression (Seefeldt et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>) since seeds germinated at variable rates.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Establishing herbicide resistance in Turkish <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes</title>
        <p>The shoot dry weight (SDW), used as a measure of growth response, of the sensitive (MR-S) and resistant (KNF-R1 and KNF-R2) Turkish <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes to application of indicated doses of chlorsulfuron was tested both in Turkey (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>) and USA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). In Turkish trials, the MR-S biotype was found sensitive to the lowest applied chlorsulfuron dose while both the resistant biotypes, KNF-R1 and KNF-R2, were recalcitrant to chlorsulfuron concentrations as high as 80 g a.i ha<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. In the USA greenhouse experiments, chlorsulfuron levels used were higher, varying a thousand-fold (0&#x2013;1280 g a.i ha<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>). The MR-S biotype was found highly sensitive to the lowest herbicide concentration of 2.5 g a.i ha<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> as compared to its untreated control while the SDW of KNF-R1 and KNF-R2 biotypes was not affected up to a dose of 80 g a.i ha<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, as also seen in the Turkish trials (compare Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref> with Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). However, a progressive decrease in SDW was apparent even in KNF-R1 and KNF-R2 biotypes at chlorsulfuron concentration of 160 g a.i ha<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> and higher (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="F1" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Differential effects on the shoot dry weight (SDW) of wild mustard (<italic>S. arvensis</italic>) biotypes, MR-S (&#x2022;), KNF-R1 (&#x25E6;), and KNF-R2 (&#x25BE;) in response to sprays with increasing concentrations of the ALS inhibitor, chlorsulfuron (A, B) or trifensulfuron-methyl (C) shown in log values</bold>. <bold>(A)</bold> Net-house in Izmir, Turkey; chlorsulfuron rates tested (0&#x2013;80 g a.i.ha<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>). Seeds used were dry-stored for 6&#x2013;9 months. <bold>(B,C)</bold> Greenhouse at Beltsville, MD, USA; in <bold>(B)</bold> chlorsulfuron rates tested (0&#x2013;320 g.a.i ha<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>). Seeds used were dry stored for 24 months. Vertical bars represent standard error [<italic>n</italic> = 10, for <bold>(A,B)</bold>; <italic>n</italic> = 8, for <bold>(C)</bold>].</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fchem-03-00046-g0001"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Cross resistance of the three biotypes used here was also tested using other related herbicides - trifensulfuron-methyl (thifensulfuron), metsulfuron-methyl and imazamethabenz-methyl (IMI), and an unrelated herbicide 2,4-D (Jugulam et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). The MR-S biotype was found susceptible to all of these inhibitors while the KNF-R1 and KNF-R2 biotypes were found resistant also to the trifensulfuron-methyl (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>) but not to IMI, metsulfuron-methyl, or to the plant growth regulator 2,4-D (data not shown). The dose-response curves for trifensulfuron-methyl on the SDW of the three biotypes paralleled those obtained with chlorsulfuron (compare Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A,B</xref> with Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Acetolactate synthase activity isolated from chlorsulfuron-resistant <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes is insensitive to chlorsulfuron</title>
        <p>Next, acetolactate synthase (ALS) activity was determined in the 60% ammonium sulfate precipitated protein fraction of soluble leaf extracts from KNF-R1, KNF-R2, and MR-S biotypes in the absence and presence of chlorsulfuron (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). The ALS enzyme activity isolated from MR-S biotype was found sensitive to low concentrations of chlorsulfuron, 5 nM herbicide causing 50% inhibition of the enzyme activity. In contrast, ALS enzyme activity isolated from KNF-R1 and KNF-R2 biotypes was completely insensitive to chlorsulfuron, even at concentrations as high as 100 nM (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). These <italic>in vitro</italic> data complement the <italic>in vivo</italic> dose response on the SDW of the three biotypes, and relate chlorsulfuron resistance of KNF-R1 and KNF-R 2 <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes to an altered ALS protein.</p>
        <fig id="F2" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>(A)</bold> Acetolactate synthase (ALS) activity of resistant biotypes, KNF-R1 and KNF-R2, is not inhibited by chlorsulfuron. <bold>(B)</bold> Nucleotide positions, amino acids and ALS gene mutations in <italic>S. arvensis</italic> &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes, KNF-R1 and KNF-R2, in comparison to the &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotype MR-S using <italic>A. thaliana als</italic> sequence as standard. <bold>(C)</bold> Representation of the sequences around the mutation in ALS gene of &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes which results in amino acid substitution. In KNF-R1, the mutation C&#x2013;T represents Pro197 (<bold>C</bold>CT) to Ser (<bold>T</bold>CT) substitution while in KNF-R2 the C&#x2013;A change representing Pro197 (<bold>C</bold>CT) to Thr (<bold>A</bold>CT) substitution. The ALS gene from susceptible MR-S biotype did not harbor any of these mutations.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fchem-03-00046-g0002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>ALS gene from chlorsulfuron-resistant <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes harbors mutations</title>
        <p>To test our contention that the ALS protein in KNF-R1 and KNF-R2 <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes is altered, we carried out molecular analysis by first amplifying the ALS genes of all the three biotypes using PCR, and then the PCR products were sequenced. The sequences we obtained lacked 62&#x2013;64 nucleotides from the 5&#x2032; end of the gene but included all the regions of the ALS gene previously shown to have mutations that confer resistance to chlorsulfuron (Tranel and Wright, <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Overall, DNA sequence analysis showed a total of 16 nucleotide mutations among the <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes, fourteen of which were determined to be silent, i.e., when translated these did not result in a change in the amino acid (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B,C</xref>). ALS gene sequences varied slightly among the three biotypes, with some polymorphism being apparent (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>). The ALS gene of Turkish <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes showed ~1% polymorphism, similar to that detected previously (Warwick et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Amino acid substitution of Glu290 (GAG) to Ser290 (AGT) in MR-S biotype and Gly290 (GGT) in KNF-R1 and KNF-R2 biotypes was apparent but this amino acid change in ALS gene is not known to be associated with resistance phenomenon and is highly variable (Warwick et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Notably, the single point mutation that resulted in an amino acid substitution was found at nucleotide position 589 in the ALS gene from &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes, KNF-R1 and KNF-R2 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>). In the KNF-R1 ALS gene, the mutation C to T represents Pro197 (<bold>C</bold>CT) to Ser (<bold>T</bold>CT) substitution while in KNF-R2 the C to A change represents Pro197 (<bold>C</bold>CT) to Thr (<bold>A</bold>CT) substitution (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>). The ALS gene from susceptible MR-S biotype did not show any of these mutations (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Chlorsulfuron-resistant Turkish <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes are altered in seed dormancy behavior</title>
        <p>Seed dormancy, germination, and emergence are important agronomic characteristics of weeds, which play a key role in agricultural productivity, determining competition and success of a staple crop and its weeds in an agroecosystem (Koger et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Weitbrecht et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Occasional reference to a possible link between herbicide resistance and seed dormancy has appeared in the literature but data are less dense. Therefore, we tested whether newly evolved chlorsulfuron resistance of <italic>S. arvensis</italic>, associated with altered ALS gene/enzyme, has any impact on the seed germination ability as compared to the sensitive biotypes.</p>
        <p>Over a few years during which these studies were conducted, we consistently observed variability in the germination rate of seeds of chlorsulfuron susceptible (S) vs. resistant (R) <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes. Therefore, we carried out controlled, long-term experiments (in the USA) and compared seed germination rates of <italic>S. arvensis</italic> (&#x201C;R&#x201D;) and (&#x201C;S&#x201D;) biotypes after a period of 4 months, and after 2 and 4 years of dry storage. The seeds of &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes, MR-S1 and MR-S2, dry stored for 4-months had, respectively, a germination rate of 38.0 and 23.0% (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>), which decreased to 8 and 18% at 2 years (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>), and after 48-months' dry storage it was 13 and18.5% (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). In contrast, the resistant biotypes, KNF-R1 and KNF-R2, showed an opposite germination trend to that of &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes. The germination rate of 4-months dry stored seeds of R1 and R2 biotypes was, respectively, 12.5 and 30.5% (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>), which increased to 68.0 and 56.7% at 2 years of storage (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>), and by 4 years of dry storage period it was 66.5 and 32.2% (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). It is noted here that the seeds of &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes dry stored for 4 years germinated 24 h sooner than the &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes.</p>
        <fig id="F3" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Cumulative seed germination (%) in relation to progressive emergence of <italic>S. arvensis</italic> chlorsulfuron-resistant &#x201C;R&#x201D; [KNF-R1 (&#x2207;), KNF-R2 (&#x25BE;)], and susceptible &#x201C;S&#x201D; [MR-S1 (&#x2022;) and MR-S2 (&#x25E6;)] biotype seeds</bold>. Seeds used were dry stored for: <bold>(A)</bold>, 4 months; <bold>(B)</bold>, 2 years (24 months); <bold>(C)</bold>, 4 years (48 months). Vertical bars represent standard error (<italic>n</italic> = 6).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fchem-03-00046-g0003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To further confirm the results from experiments carried out in the greenhouse, we compared germination of seeds from the &#x201C;S&#x201D; and &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes, dry stored for 2-3 years, at room temperature in the laboratory and at 22&#xB0;C in the greenhouse. In the laboratory experiments, significantly higher percentage (74&#x2013;75%) of seeds from &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes, KNF-R2 and KNF-R1, germinated compared to low % germination (26.9&#x2013;27.1%) of &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotype counterparts, MR-S2 and MR-S1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). A similar germination pattern was observed under controlled greenhouse conditions where germination of &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes was 81.9 and 75.0% in KNF-R1 and KNF-R2, respectively, compared to respective 26.8 and 24.3% in MR-S1 and MR-S2 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="F4" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Cumulative seed germination (%) of <italic>S. arvensis</italic> chlorsulfuron-resistant &#x201C;R,&#x201D; KNF-R1 and KNF-R2, vs. susceptible &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes, MR-S1 and MR-S2, under controlled laboratory (A) and greenhouse conditions (B)</bold>. In both tests, seeds used had been dry stored for 2&#x2013;3 years. Vertical bars represent standard error [<italic>n</italic> = 12 for <bold>(A)</bold>; <italic>n</italic> = 6 for <bold>(B)</bold>].</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fchem-03-00046-g0004"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Different seed germination potential of &#x201C;S&#x201D; and &#x201C;R&#x201D; <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes is not altered by suboptimal temperature regime</title>
        <p>We next investigated if low temperature regime&#x2014;5, 10, and 15&#xB0;C&#x2014;altered the germination potential of the &#x201C;S&#x201D; and &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes. These experiments were performed in a temperature-controlled growth chamber using seeds that had undergone dry storage for between 2.2 and 3 years. At 5&#xB0;C, seeds from neither <italic>S. arvensis</italic> &#x201C;R&#x201D; and &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes germinated (data not shown). However, at both 10&#xB0;C and 15&#xB0;C the maximum cumulative germination was clearly advantageous in favor of &#x201C;R&#x201D; compared to &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes, being, respectively, 48.2&#x2013;63.8% (10&#xB0;C) and 50.0&#x2013;53.2% (15&#xB0;C) in &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes vs. 15.9&#x2013;17.5% (10&#xB0;C) and 29.1&#x2013;30.7% (15&#xB0;C) in &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A,B</xref>; Supplemental Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="F5" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Emerging progression of chlorsulfuron-resistant &#x201C;R,&#x201D; KNF-R1 (&#x2207;) and KNF-R2 (&#x25BE;), and susceptible &#x201C;S,&#x201D; MR-S1 (&#x2022;) and MR-S2 (&#x25E6;), <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes sowed in a growth chamber held constant at 10&#xB0;C (A) and 15&#xB0;C (B)</bold>. Cumulative seed germination (%) is presented as supplemental material (Supplemental Figure 1). Seed lots used had been dry-stored for 30&#x2013;36 months. Vertical bars represent standard error (<italic>n</italic> = 6).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fchem-03-00046-g0005"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Differential seed germination of &#x201C;S&#x201D; and &#x201C;R&#x201D; <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes is not a question of seed viability or weight difference</title>
        <p>Seed weight of <italic>S. arvensis</italic> &#x201C;S&#x201D; and &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes measured after dry storage (after-ripened) of 4 months and 4 years are given in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A,B</xref>, respectively. The 4-months dry stored seeds from both lines had similar weight. However, seeds of &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotype dry stored for 4 years weighed lesser than the 4-month stored seeds (compare Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref> with A, MR-S1 and MR-S2) whereas during the same duration in dry storage, the &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes weighed more, being significantly heavier than their &#x201C;S&#x201D; counterparts (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A,B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="F6" position="float">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Mean seed mass of <italic>S. arvensis</italic> susceptible (MR-S1 and MR-S2) and resistant (KNF-R1 and KNF-R2) biotypes after 4 months (A) and 4 years (48 months) (B) of dry storage</bold>. Vertical bars represent standard error (<italic>n</italic> = 3; 100 seeds in 3 batches from each of the four biotypes were weighed).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fchem-03-00046-g0006"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To further ensure that the seeds of both &#x201C;S&#x201D; and &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes were viable, we tested the effects of a range, low to high concentrations, of the plant hormone gibberellic acid (GA<sub>3</sub>) on germination of seeds stored for 3 and 8 years. GA<sub>3</sub> application to &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotype seeds dry stored for 3 years effectively increased their ability to germinate, raising it from 38.8% without GA<sub>3</sub> to ~80% and higher at 1&#x2013;5 mM GA<sub>3</sub> reaching % germination value close to the untreated &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype seeds (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>). Since we had the &#x201C;S&#x201D; and &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes in dry storage for 8 years, we also compared the effects of GA<sub>3</sub> on them as well, especially because we had noted a decreasing trend in the germination of even the &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype seeds dry stored for 4 years (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). By 8 years of dry storage, the germination rate of untreated seeds of MR-S2 biotype and KNF-R2 biotype was ~8 and ~26%, respectively. Both these biotypes responded to GA<sub>3</sub> treatment by vigorous germination that increased with each higher dose of the GA<sub>3</sub> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>). The concentration of GA<sub>3</sub> required to generate maximal effect on germination potential in these biotypes was found to vary, 5 mM was saturating for &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype while 10 mM was optimal for the &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotype&#x2014;the curve for &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotype, however, had not reached saturation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="F7" position="float">
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Gibberellic acid (GA<sub>3</sub>) application restores seed germination potential in chlorsulfuron-susceptible <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes</bold>. <bold>(A)</bold> MR-S1 (open bars) and MR-S2 (serrated bars). Germination (%) of chlorsulfuron-resistant seeds (KNF-R1 and KNF-R2) is shown in &#x201C;Control&#x201D; next to the &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes. Seeds used in <bold>(A)</bold> had been dry stored for 3 years. In <bold>(B)</bold> the response curves to increasing concentrations of GA<sub>3</sub> are shown with seeds of MR-S2 (&#x25A0;) and KNF-R2 (&#x25A1;) <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes dry stored for 8 years. Vertical bars represent standard error (<italic>n</italic> = 3).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fchem-03-00046-g0007"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Wild mustard (<italic>S. arvensis</italic> L.) is a prolific weed in wheat fields, causing substantial yield loss to the crop. Field management for <italic>S. arvensis</italic> has involved the use of chlorsulfuron herbicides that inhibit acetolactate synthase (ALS) and impair the synthesis of three prominent branched-chain amino acids&#x2014;valine, leucine, and isoleucine (as stated in the Introduction). However, resistance to this herbicide among weeds has been observed worldwide and generally attributed to amino acid substitutions in the ALS gene (Guttieri et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; Boutsalis et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Gressel, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Weed populations exposed to single-mechanism based herbicides that have longer residual life in the soil develop resistance and, in turn, can incur a fitness cost (Coustau et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Tranel and Wright, <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). The chlorsulfuron-resistant biotypes studied here originated from areas in Turkey, where wheat is mainly grown as a monoculture or in rotation with sunflower. These fields had a history of several years' consecutive use of the chlorsulfuron herbicide. We show and confirm that resistance to chlorsulfuron [ALS (AHAS)-inhibiting herbicides] in Turkish biotypes is associated with altered target site mutations in the ALS gene, corresponding to amino acid substitutions, Pro197 (CCT) to Ser (TCT), or Thr (ACT), as is known for many other species. These findings are consistent with our <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments showing that ALS enzyme activity in <italic>S. arvensis</italic> KNF-R1 and KNFR-2 biotypes, and not the susceptible biotypes, is insensitive to chlorsulfuron. The Pro to Ser (ALS from KNF-R1 biotype) or Thr (ALS from KNF-R2 biotype) substitutions are consistent with previously reported Pro substitution to Ser in Corn poppy (<italic>Papaver rhoeas</italic> L.) (Prado et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>) and wild mustard (<italic>S. arvensis</italic> L.) (Warwick et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>), Ala, Arg, Gln, Leu, Lys, Met, Ser, Thr, or Trp in Kochia (<italic>K. scoparia</italic> L.) (Guttieri et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>; Warwick et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>), or Ala/Thr in wild radish (<italic>R. raphanistrum</italic> L.) (Tan and Medd, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>).</p>
      <p>The newly evolved chlorsulfuron-resistant <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes with mutated ALS gene became a resource to delineate effects on seed germination and weight in comparison to the susceptible biotypes. Interestingly, the time in dry storage (after-ripening) had a major and differential effect on the germinability of seeds from susceptible vs. resistant <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes. The maximum cumulative germination was found to be different between &#x201C;R&#x201D; and &#x201C;S&#x201D; seeds after dry storage periods from 4 months to 4 years. Seeds from both biotypes held for 4 months in dry storage showed the &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotype seeds to record a higher germination than the seed from &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype. However, as the dry storage period was prolonged the germinability of S biotype seeds sharply decreased with longer storage time. Surprisingly, the seeds from &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes recorded highest germination potential at 24 months dry storage, which slightly dropped at 4 years of dry storage and yet was significantly higher than the &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotype seeds. These data on variable germinability of <italic>S. arvensis</italic> being linked to the different biotypes may explain the diverse data on seed germination of this species in the literature. For example, a study on <italic>S. arvensis</italic> seeds immediately after harvest found quite low (7.2%) germinability compared to 28% in those stored for a year (Donald and Hoerauf, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">1985</xref>), while in another study (Andersson and Milberg, <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>) <italic>S. arvensis</italic> seed germination varied as much as 20&#x2013;90%. Although it is known that seed dormancy determines germination timing, little is known about how this process is regulated (Xiang et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p>
      <p>Differential seed germinability between &#x201C;S&#x201D; and &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes was not due to differential viability, temperature regimen, or non-responsiveness to pro-germination hormone GA<sub>3</sub>, and likely associated with the &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype phenotype due to single amino acid substitution, Pro197 (CCT) to Ser (TCT) or Thr (ACT), in the ALS gene. Thus, while the <italic>S. arvensis</italic> seeds dry stored for 4 months weighed the same irrespective of being sensitive (&#x201C;S&#x201D;) or resistant (&#x201C;R&#x201D;) to chlorsulfuron, however, after dry storage for 4 years the &#x201C;R&#x201D; seeds were significantly heavier than the &#x201C;S&#x201D; ones. Interestingly, seed weight and seed germination potential of &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes apparently correlated&#x2014;as the seed weight was lost, the germination capacity also decreased. The &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype seeds showed higher germination capacity at 10 and 15&#xB0;C than the seeds of &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotype. This observation bodes well for the fitness of &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype seeds since wild mustard germinates in two flushes, one in spring and the other in autumn both periods of cooler temperatures (Edwards, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">1980</xref>).</p>
      <p>Final evidence for the viability of &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotype seeds came from the response pattern of their germination upon application of GA<sub>3</sub>. GA<sub>3</sub> treatment of &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotype seeds dry stored for 36 months resulted in high germinability, reaching a capacity near to that seen with untreated &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype seeds. A comparison of germinability of &#x201C;S&#x201D; and &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype seeds dry stored for 8 years demonstrated similar response to exogenous GA<sub>3</sub>, the &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype seed germination saturating at 5 mM GA<sub>3</sub> while the &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotype seeds showed a linear response which appeared to lead them to match the potential of the &#x201C;R&#x201D; seeds. Application of the GA<sub>3</sub> antagonist in seed germination, abscisic acid (ABA), to &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype seeds inhibited their germination (data not shown), suggesting that the germination differences between the two types of seeds may be due to differences in the endogenous ratio of ABA/GA<sub>3</sub>. In preliminary studies, ABA concentrations in the seeds of MR-S1 and MR-S2 <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes were found to be 143&#x2013;237% higher than the corresponding &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype seeds (unpublished data). However, this remains to be further established. Thus, the ABA/GA hormone postulate (Karssen and La&#xE7;ka, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">1986</xref>) might apply to the differential seed germination between &#x201C;S&#x201D; and &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes of <italic>S. arvensis</italic>. In this regard, it is known that GA application is necessary to break dormancy in wild mustard germination (Karssen and La&#xE7;ka, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">1986</xref>; Duran and Retamal, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>). These results are consistent with the findings on chlorsulfuron-resistant lettuce (<italic>Lactuca sativa</italic> L.), where the &#x201C;R&#x201D; near-isogenic line showed faster germination than the &#x201C;S&#x201D; line (Mallory&#x2013;Smith et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>), and on <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic> &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes, which germinated earlier than the &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes at low temperature (5&#xB0;C); however, no differences in germination occurred at higher temperatures (Park et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>).</p>
      <p>The observation that the <italic>S. arvensis</italic> &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotype seeds were significantly heavier than those from the &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes upon dry storage for 4 years might seem intriguing. However, in this regard it is interesting to note that recent molecular studies with &#x201C;dry&#x201D; quiescent seeds showed the latter to be metabolically active as revealed by transcriptomics and protein dynamics (Leubner-Metzger, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Surprisingly, dynamic processes within &#x201C;dry&#x201D; seed seem to characterize germination potential, with after-ripening being associated with specific gene networks (Carrera et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Further, there is sparse information on post-transcriptional regulation and post-translational modification of proteins in dry seeds, which need to be addressed to throw light on the (molecular) mechanisms that regulate after-ripening (Holdsworth et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>).</p>
      <p>Studies on the environmental factors on seed germination/emergence are important for predicting when weeds in the growing season might emerge in order to put an effective weed management in place. To improve their competitive ability in agricultural farms, it is thought that annual weeds adjust the timing and rate of seed germination (Martinez-Ghersa et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). The degree of competition between the weed and the crop is dependent upon the relative time of their emergence, whichever germinates or emerges first is expected to have the upper hand by employing more time to establish and gainfully compete for space, light, and nutrients over the other (Neve et al., <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>).</p>
      <p>The Turkish chlorsulfuron-resistant <italic>S. arvensis</italic> biotypes studied here have the ability to germinate faster in high percentages at cold temperature regimes, and sustain their germinability over a long dry storage time compared to their susceptible counterparts. It would imply that these resistant weeds would be more competitive in the field conditions compared to &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes. Rapid germination at low temperatures may be a characteristic trait associated with ALS target site resistance (Pro-197/-Ser/-Arg/-Thr), which was postulated to turn into either a fitness advantage or disadvantage depending upon the prevailing agroecological conditions (Park et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Moreover, the rapid and high rates of seed germination of chlorsulfuron (ALS inhibitor) resistant <italic>S. arvensis</italic> &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes could also be &#x201C;successfully&#x201D; exploited in weed management strategies to safeguard the crop by draining the &#x201C;R&#x201D; weed seed bank. Relative fitness studies on other weeds have shown that the ALS &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes are not associated with growth penalty, rather under some conditions they may have fitness advantages compared to &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes (Gressel and Segel, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>; Maxwell et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>; Thomson et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; Christoffoleti et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>). Data presented here on comparative seed germination between &#x201C;R&#x201D; and &#x201C;S&#x201D; biotypes of <italic>S. arvensis</italic> suggest that the altered target site trait conferring resistance to ALS inhibitor, chlorsulfuron in particular, in &#x201C;R&#x201D; biotypes does not result in a growth penalty.</p>
      <sec>
        <title>Conflict of interest statement</title>
        <p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Mary Camp (USDA-ARS Beltsville,Md) for statistical analysis of the data, Dr. Ahmet Uluda&#x11F; for technical advice on some dose-response experiments, Prof. Jonathan Gressel for creative discussions, Dr. Vijaya Shukla for help with gene sequence submissions to Genbank, and Dr. Steven Mirsky and Dr. Bhavneet Kaur for constructive comments on the manuscript. The accession numbers of the ALS gene sequences deposited in Genbank are: MR-S (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="FJ655877">FJ655877</ext-link>), KNF&#x2013;R1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="FJ655876">FJ655876</ext-link>), KNF-R2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="FJ655875">FJ 655875</ext-link>). Mention of trade names or commercial products in this article is solely for the purpose of providing specific information and does not imply recommendation or endorsement by the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA). USDA is an Equal Opportunity Provider and Employer.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supplementary material</title>
      <p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fchem.2015.00046">http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fchem.2015.00046</ext-link></p>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1">
        <media xlink:href="Presentation1.PDF">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milberg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Variation in seed dormancy among plants, populations and years of seed collection</article-title>. <source>Seed Sci. Res.</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boutsalis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karotam</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Powles</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Molecular basis of resistance to acetolactate synthase-inhibiting herbicides in <italic>Sisymbrium orientale</italic> and <italic>Brassica tournefortii</italic></article-title>. <source>Pesticide Sci.</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>507</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>516</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boz</surname><given-names>&#xD6;.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The determination of the weed species and their density and frequency in the wheat areas of Ayd&#x131;n province</article-title>. <source>J. Turk. Weed Sci.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantification of microgram quantities of protein using the principle of protein-dye binding</article-title>. <source>Anal. Biochem.</source>
<volume>72</volume>, <fpage>248</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>252</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 942051?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrera</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Medhurst</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Footitt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Theodoulou</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Seed after-ripening is a discrete developmental pathway associated with specific gene networks in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source><volume>53</volume>, <fpage>214</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>224</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03331.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18028281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18028281</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christoffoleti</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westra</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Growth analysis of sulfonylurea resistant and susceptible kochia (<italic>Kochia scoparia</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Weed Sci.</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>691</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>695</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coustau</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevillon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>French-Constant</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Resistance to xenobiotics and parasites: can we count the cost?</article-title>
<source>Trends Ecol Evol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>378</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>383</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-5347(00)01929-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10931680?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10931680</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delaporta</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>A plant DNA minipreparation</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donald</surname><given-names>W. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoerauf</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Enhanced germination and emergence of dormant wild mustard (<italic>S. arvensis</italic>) seed by two substituted phthalimides</article-title>. <source>Weed Sci.</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>894</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>902</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Retamal</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Coat structure and regulation of dormancy in <italic>Sinapis arvensis</italic> L. seeds</article-title>. <source>J. Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>135</volume>, <fpage>218</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chee</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Rapid germination of sulfonylurea&#x2013;resistant <italic>Kochia scoparia</italic> accessions is associated with elevated seed levels of branched-chain amino acids</article-title>. <source>Weed Sci.</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Aspects of the population ecology of charlock</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Ecol.</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>172</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nalewaja</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Economic control of weeds in wheat, <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic></article-title>. <source>Weed Technol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>261</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gressel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Molecular Biology of Weed Control</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gressel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segel</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>The paucity of plants evolving genetic resistance to herbicides: possible reasons and implications</article-title>. <source>J. Theor. Biol.</source>
<volume>75</volume>, <fpage>349</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>371</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 745447?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">745447</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gressel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segel</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Modeling the effectiveness of herbicide rotations and mixtures as strategies to delay or preclude resistance</article-title>. <source>Weed Tecnol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>186</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>198</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guttieri</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eberlein</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallory-Smith</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thill</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>DNA sequence variation in Domain A of the acetolactate synthase genes of herbicide-resistant and -susceptible weed biotypes</article-title>. <source>Weed Sci.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>670</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>676</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guttieri</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eberlein</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thill</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Diverse mutations in the acetolactate synthase gene confer chlorsulfuron resistance in Kochia (<italic>Kochia scoparia</italic>) biotypes</article-title>. <source>Weed Sci.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>178</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heap</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <source>The International Survey of Herbicide Resistant Weeds</source>. Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.weedscience.com">http://www.weedscience.com</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holdsworth</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Finch-Savage</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grappin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominique</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Post-genomics dissection of seed dormancy and germination</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2007.11.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18160329?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18160329</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jugulam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mclean</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Inheritance of picloram and 2,4-D resistance in wild mustard (<italic>Brassica kaber</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Weed Sci.</source>
<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>417</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>423</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1614/WS-04-149R</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karssen</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>La&#xE7;ka</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>A revision of hormone balance theory of seed dormancy: studies on gibberellin and/or abscisic acid-deficient mutants of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>, in <source>Plant Growth Substances</source>, ed <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bopp</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>), <fpage>315</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>323</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kocsy</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Die or survive? &#x2013; redox changes as seed viability markers</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ.</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>1008</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1010</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pce.12515</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25652043?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25652043</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koger</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poston</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Factors affecting seed germination, seedling emergence, and survival of texasweed (<italic>Caperonia palustris</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Weed Sci.</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>989</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>995</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1614/WS-03-139R2</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leubner-Metzger</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>&#x3B2;-1,3-glucanase gene expression in low hydrated seeds as a mechanism for dormancy release during tobacco after-ripening</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>133</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>145</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02284.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15610356?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15610356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallory&#x2013;Smith</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thill</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alcocer-Ruthling</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Growth comparisons of sulfonylurea resistant and susceptible biotypes</article-title>, in <source>Proceedings of the First International Weed Control Congress</source>, Vol. 2 (<publisher-loc>Melbourne, VIC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Weed Science Society of Victoria</publisher-name>), <fpage>301</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>303</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallory-Smith</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thill</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dial</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Identification of sulfonylurea herbicide resistant prickly lettuce (<italic>Lactuca seriola</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Weed Technol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>163</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>168</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Ghersa</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghersa</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benech-Arnold</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mac Donough</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanches</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Adaptive traits regulating dormancy and germination of invasive plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Species Biol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>127</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>137</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1442-1984.2000.00033.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roush</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Radosevich</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Predicting the evaluation and dynamics of herbicide resistance in weed populations</article-title>. <source>Weed Technol.</source>
<fpage>2</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>13</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 19566704?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19566704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neve</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diggle</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>F. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Powles</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Simulating evolution of glyphosate resistance in <italic>Lolium rigidum</italic> I: population biology of a rare resistance trait</article-title>. <source>Weed Res.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>404</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>417</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.0043-1737.2003.00358.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>K. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallory-Smith</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller-Warrant</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Ecological fitness of acetolactate synthase inhibitor-resistant and susceptible downy brome (<italic>Bromus tectorum</italic>) biotypes</article-title>. <source>Weed Sci.</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>768</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>773</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1614/WS-04-081R</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prado</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osuna</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prado</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Molecular basis of resistance to sulfonylureas in <italic>Papaver rhoeas</italic></article-title>. <source>Pesticide Biochem. Physiol.</source>
<volume>79</volume>, <fpage>10</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pestbp.2004.01.003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Primiani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotterman</surname><given-names>M. J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saari</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Resistance of kochia (<italic>Kochia scoparia</italic>) to sulfonylurea and imidazolinone herbicides</article-title>. <source>Weed Technol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>169</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>172</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16667465?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16667465</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Donovan</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurice</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Sulfonylurea herbicide resistance in <italic>Sonchus asper</italic> biotypes in Alberta, Canada</article-title>. <source>Weed Res.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>214</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>220</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3180.2003.00336.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>T. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Site of action of chlorsulfuron</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>75</volume>, <fpage>827</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>831</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16663712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16663712</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>SAS</collab></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Statistical Analysis Systems, SAS/STAT User's guide, Version 8</source>. <publisher-loc>Cary, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Statistical Analysis Systems Institute</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sathasivan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haughn</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murai</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Nucleotide sequence of a mutant acetolactate synthase gene from an imidazolinone-res&#x131;stant <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> var. Columbia</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>2188</fpage>. <?supplied-pmid 2336405?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2336405</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seefeldt</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuerst</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Log-logistic analysis of herbicide dose-response relationships</article-title>. <source>Weed Technol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>218</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>227</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Medd</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Characterisation of the acetolactate synthase (ALS) gene of <italic>Raphanus raphanistrum</italic> L. and the molecular assay of mutations associated with herbicide resistance</article-title>. <source>Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>163</volume>, <fpage>195</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>205</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9452(02)00082-1</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thill</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shafii</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Germination characteristics of sulfonylurea resistant and susceptible <italic>Kochia scoparia</italic></article-title>. <source>Weed Sci.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>172</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>179</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Topuz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemli</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Preliminary Studies on the Density of some Important Weed Seed Species in the Soil and Determination of the Relationship Between Soil Seed Bank and Weed Flora in Cereal Areas of Manyas (Bal&#x131;kesir) Province</source>. M.Sc. Thesis (2000), Ege University, Izmir.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tranel</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Resistance of weeds to ALS-inhibiting herbicides: what have we learned?</article-title>
<source>Weed Sci.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>700</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>712</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1614/0043-1745(2002)050[0700:rrowta]2.0.co;2</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umbarger</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Amino acid biosynthesis and its regulation</article-title>. <source>Ann. Rev. Biochem.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>533</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>606</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 354503?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">354503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vila-Aiub</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neve</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steadman</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Powles</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Ecological fitness of a multiple herbicide-resistant <italic>Lolium rigidum</italic> population; dynamics of seed germination and seedling emergence of resistance and susceptible phenotypes</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Ecol.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>288</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>298</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2664.2005.01017.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B45">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warwick</surname><given-names>S. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauder</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckie</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Resistance in Canadian biotypes of wild mustard (<italic>Sinapis arvensis</italic>) to acetolactate synthase inhibiting herbicides</article-title>. <source>Weed Sci.</source>
<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>631</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>639</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1614/WS-05-003R1.1</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B46">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warwick</surname><given-names>S. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauder</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckie</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Acetolactate synthase target-site mutations and single nucleotide polymorphism genotyping in ALS-resistant kochia (<italic>Kochia scoparia</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Weed Sci.</source>
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>797</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>806</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1614/WS-08-045.1</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B47">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weitbrecht</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leubner-Metzger</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>First off the mark: early seed germination</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>3289</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3309</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err030</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21430292?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21430292</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B48">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakabayashi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentsink</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soppe</surname><given-names>W. J. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Reduced Dormancy5 encodes a protein phosphatase 2C that is required for seed dormancy in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>4362</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4375</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.114.132811</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25415980?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25415980</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B49">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yajima</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kav</surname><given-names>N. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Proteome level differences between auxinic herbicide susceptible and resistant wild mustard (<italic>Sinapis arvensis</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>J. Agri. Food Chem.</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>5063</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5070</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf0495284</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15291476?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15291476</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
