<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Nature Pub. Group</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4510693</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pii">ncomms8618</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms8618</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26173063</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Gut microbiota mediate caffeine detoxification in the primary insect pest of coffee</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ceja-Navarro</surname>
            <given-names>Javier A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Vega</surname>
            <given-names>Fernando E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">b</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Karaoz</surname>
            <given-names>Ulas</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>Zhao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jenkins</surname>
            <given-names>Stefan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lim</surname>
            <given-names>Hsiao Chien</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kosina</surname>
            <given-names>Petr</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8805-0306</contrib-id>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Infante</surname>
            <given-names>Francisco</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Northen</surname>
            <given-names>Trent R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Brodie</surname>
            <given-names>Eoin L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c3">c</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Ecology Department, Earth Sciences Division, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory</institution>, Berkeley, California 94720, <country>USA</country></aff>
        <aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Sustainable Perennial Crops Laboratory, United States Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Service</institution>, Building 001, BARC-W, Beltsville, Maryland 20705, <country>USA</country></aff>
        <aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Genome Dynamics Department, Life Sciences Division, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory</institution>, Berkeley, California 94720, <country>USA</country></aff>
        <aff id="a4"><label>4</label><institution>International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT)</institution>, Carretera Mexico-Veracruz Km. 45, El Bat&#xE1;n, Texcoco 56130, <country>Mexico</country></aff>
        <aff id="a5"><label>5</label><institution>El Colegio de la Frontera Sur (ECOSUR)</institution>, Carretera Antiguo Aeropuerto Km. 2.5, Tapachula, Chiapas 30700, <country>Mexico</country></aff>
        <aff id="a6"><label>6</label><institution>Department of Environmental Science, Policy and Management, University of California</institution>, Berkeley, California 94720, <country>USA</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1">
          <label>a</label>
          <email>jcnavarro@lbl.gov</email>
        </corresp>
        <corresp id="c2">
          <label>b</label>
          <email>Fernando.Vega@ars.usda.gov</email>
        </corresp>
        <corresp id="c3">
          <label>c</label>
          <email>elbrodie@lbl.gov</email>
        </corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>07</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <elocation-id>7618</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>05</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2015, Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-holder>
        <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <!--author-paid-->
          <license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The coffee berry borer (<italic>Hypothenemus hampei</italic>) is the most devastating insect pest of coffee worldwide with its infestations decreasing crop yield by up to 80%. Caffeine is an alkaloid that can be toxic to insects and is hypothesized to act as a defence mechanism to inhibit herbivory. Here we show that caffeine is degraded in the gut of <italic>H. hampei</italic>, and that experimental inactivation of the gut microbiota eliminates this activity. We demonstrate that gut microbiota in <italic>H. hampei</italic> specimens from seven major coffee-producing countries and laboratory-reared colonies share a core of microorganisms. Globally ubiquitous members of the gut microbiota, including prominent <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> species, subsist on caffeine as a sole source of carbon and nitrogen. <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> caffeine demethylase genes are expressed <italic>in vivo</italic> in the gut of <italic>H. hampei</italic>, and re-inoculation of antibiotic-treated insects with an isolated <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> strain reinstates caffeine-degradation ability confirming their key role.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract abstract-type="web-summary">
        <p><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="i1" xlink:href="ncomms8618-i1.jpg"/>The coffee berry borer, the main insect pest of coffee, feeds and lives on the caffeine-rich beans despite caffeine's toxic effects. Here Ceja-Navarro <italic>et al.</italic> show that certain microbes, including <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> species, mediate caffeine detoxification in the insect's gut.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Of 124 species in the genus <italic>Coffea</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>, only two are commercially traded: <italic>Coffea arabica</italic> and <italic>C. canephora</italic>. <italic>C. arabica</italic> is a high-altitude species endemic to southwestern Ethiopia, southeast Sudan and northern Kenya, while <italic>C. canephora</italic> (commonly referred to as robusta coffee) is a lowland plant endemic to tropical Africa, west of the Rift Valley<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>. These species differ in the content of the purine alkaloid caffeine (1,3,7-trimethylxanthine), representing <italic>ca.</italic> 1% of seed dry weight in <italic>C. arabica</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref> and up to 1.7&#x2013;2.4% in <italic>C. canephora</italic>. Although at low concentrations, it may have other roles<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>; caffeine in plants has been hypothesized to serve as protection against herbivory<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>. Caffeine imparts a bitter taste that inhibits insect feeding<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>; it also paralyses and intoxicates insects by inhibiting phosphodiesterase activity and increasing the intracellular levels of cyclic AMP<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>. Caffeine toxicity is also related to its negative effects on DNA repair and recombination pathways, and the delay of cell cycle progression as shown in systems such as yeast and zebrafish<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>. Because of its demonstrated negative effects on insects, arachnids, slugs and snails, caffeine is considered a natural pest repellent<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref> and, while over 850 insect species can feed on other parts of the coffee plant<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>, and a few of them occasionally on the coffee seed, only <italic>Hypothenemus hampei</italic> (Ferrari) (Coleoptera; Curculionidae: Scolytinae) has developed the ability to feed and complete its life cycle solely on the economically important caffeine-rich coffee bean.</p>
    <p>Endemic to Africa, the coffee berry borer entered Indonesia in 1908 (ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>) and Brazil in 1913 (ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>) and is now present in most coffee-producing nations<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>. Female coffee berry borers are minute bark beetles (<italic>ca.</italic> 2&#x2009;mm long) that bore a hole in the coffee berry and build galleries within the coffee seed, where they deposit their eggs. Larvae feed on the seed, causing significant losses both in quality and yields. Yearly losses in Brazil alone have been estimated at $285&#x2013;315 million (ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>), making the insect the most devastating pest of coffee worldwide. This cryptic life cycle inside the berry makes insect control problematic. The devastating socioeconomic consequences of <italic>H. hampei's</italic> worldwide invasion have stimulated ample research on possible pest management methods; however, detailed information on some basic aspects of the insect's biology, such as metabolism, is scarce. Acu&#xF1;a <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref> demonstrated that the natural acquisition and integration of a mannanase gene of bacterial origin into the <italic>H. hampei</italic> genome has enabled the insect to exploit the primary carbohydrate reserve found in coffee beans. Moreover, previous work<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref> reported no correlation between caffeine concentrations (range: 2&#x2013;17&#x2009;mg&#x2009;g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) in the beans of 12 <italic>Coffea</italic> species and resistance to <italic>H. hampei</italic>, suggesting that the insect possesses mechanisms to degrade or efficiently excrete caffeine, which permits it to withstand its toxic effects, and significantly reduce crop yield.</p>
    <p>In insects as in other animals caffeine degradation can be catalysed by cytochrome P450 enzymes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>. However, no other metazoans have been reported to endure the concentrations of caffeine to which <italic>H. hampei</italic> is exposed while simultaneously subsisting and completing its full life cycle exclusively on green coffee beans. We hypothesized that caffeine degradation in <italic>H. hampei</italic> is primarily mediated by the activity of its gut microbiota. Here we present the first study of the microbiome of <italic>H. hampei</italic> and its role in the detoxification of caffeine in the insect. Our discovery of a microbiota component to the transformation of caffeine and subsistence of <italic>H. hampei</italic> on coffee beans has important implications for understanding the metabolism and ecology of this major pest.</p>
    <sec disp-level="1" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Caffeine degradation in <italic>H. hampei</italic></title>
        <p>To test the hypothesis that caffeine degradation is a microbially mediated process in <italic>H. hampei</italic>, we obtained specimens from seven geographically dispersed coffee-producing regions: Kenya (Kiambu), Indonesia (East Java), India (Karnataka), Puerto Rico (Adjuntas), Hawaii (Kona), Guatemala (Coatepeque) and Mexico (Chiapas). Specimens from India also included insects sampled from both dominant <italic>Coffea</italic> species (<italic>C. arabica</italic> and <italic>C. canephora</italic>). In addition, we used a laboratory-reared colony originally derived from a Colombian <italic>H. hampei</italic> population and three other bark beetle species incapable of subsisting on coffee beans (<italic>H. crudiae</italic>, <italic>H. eruditus</italic> and <italic>Scolytodes maurus</italic>).</p>
        <p>First, we tested for caffeine degradation following passage through the insect gut and determined whether the gut microbiota were responsible for this process. This hypothesis was tested with the use of a <italic>H. hampei</italic> laboratory-reared colony in a controlled experiment using an artificial diet (here referred to as minimal diet), containing green <italic>C. arabica</italic> coffee beans with a final caffeine concentration of &#x223C;1.8&#x2013;2.2&#x2009;mg&#x2009;g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. <italic>Hypothenemus hampei</italic> specimens were introduced to vials containing this defined diet and displayed typical boring activity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Movie 1</xref>) and production of frass. The quantity of diet consumed and the residence time of diet in the <italic>H. hampei</italic> digestive tract were determined by incorporating fluorescent sphere tracers in the diet. Residence time was typically 3&#x2009;h (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>) and corresponded to a mass of &#x223C;14&#x2009;&#x3BC;g of diet or 25&#x2009;ng of caffeine. To quantify caffeine concentrations in the low masses of produced frass, we used Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR) calibrated with pure caffeine standards<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>). Measurements of caffeine concentration by FTIR were further validated using gas chromatography&#x2013;mass spectrometry (GC&#x2013;MS; Methods and <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). After passage of diet through the <italic>H. hampei</italic> digestive tract, caffeine was no longer detectable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1a</xref>). To determine involvement of the microbiota in caffeine detoxification, we eliminated microorganisms using the defined diet supplemented with three broad-spectrum antibiotics (tetracycline, rifampicin and streptomycin). Laboratory insects were reared on this antibiotic-supplemented diet for 4 weeks, which eliminated culturable microorganisms, before being transferred to fresh antibiotic-free diet and were allowed to feed for 4&#x2009;h. Antibiotic-treated insects exhibited no decrease in caffeine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1b</xref>), with concentrations in their frass being similar to that of the diet. This was strongly suggestive of a role of the gut microbiota in caffeine removal. Elimination of the gut microbiota also had a significant impact on <italic>H. hampei</italic> fitness with approximately a 95% decline in eggs and larvae relative to control insects, and no progression to pupa or adult stage over the 44-day experiment (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Biogeography analysis of <italic>H. hampei</italic>'s microbiome</title>
        <p>To identify members of the <italic>H. hampei</italic> gut microbiota that may contribute to caffeine degradation, we analysed the bacterial composition of <italic>H. hampei</italic> microbial communities using 16S rRNA gene sequencing from specimens of major coffee-producing regions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Data 1</xref>). Phylogenetic &#x3B2;-diversity and hierarchical clustering showed the separation of microbiomes by geographic origin (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>). Nonparametric permutational multivariate analysis of variance was used to partition variance in microbiome composition among the key factors. Geographic location explained much of the variance (45%) in bacterial composition (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>). In locations where the coffee species varied (India; <italic>C. arabica</italic> and <italic>C. canephora</italic>), coffee species accounted for 78% of the variance in microbial composition. Although the dominant microbial taxa also varied geographically, network analysis showed a core of organisms detected across all locations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2a</xref>). These organisms were affiliated with the orders Pseudomonadales, Enterobacteriales, Turicibacteriales, Rhizobiales, Alteromonadales, Actinomycetales among others; with the Pseudomonadales being highly abundant in all collected specimens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2b</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Caffeine-degrading bacteria in the gut of <italic>H. hampei</italic></title>
        <p>To determine whether the identified microorganisms in the biogeography analysis were involved in caffeine detoxification in <italic>H. hampei</italic>, we isolated bacteria that were capable of subsisting on caffeine as a sole carbon and nitrogen source using the digestive tracts of insects collected in Mexico and Hawaii as inocula. More than 100 isolates comprising 12 bacterial species were obtained from the orders of the Pseudomonadales, Enterobacteriales, Rhizobiales, Actinomycetales, Sphingomonadales and Xanthomonadales (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>). Considering the high relative abundance and frequency of the Pseudomonadales in the biogeography and isolation studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figs 2b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">3a</xref>), all isolates were screened for the <italic>ndmA</italic> gene (coding for the alpha subunit of a caffeine demethylase)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>; only <italic>P. fulva</italic> possessed this gene. Sequence analysis of this gene from this species demonstrated a 96% amino-acid similarity to the caffeine demethylase of <italic>P. putida</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref>). We confirmed expression of this gene using reverse transcriptase quantitative PCR (qPCR) from RNA extracts of field-collected insects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 5</xref>), suggesting a contribution of <italic>P. fulva</italic> to the process of caffeine degradation in natural populations of <italic>H. hampei</italic>. This gene could not be detected in specimens from other bark beetles (<italic>H. crudiae</italic>, <italic>H. eruditus</italic> and <italic>S. maurus</italic>) that lack the capacity to consume the coffee bean (data not shown).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Oxygen profiles in the gut of <italic>H. hampei</italic></title>
        <p>Oxygen gradients were measured in the gut of <italic>H. hampei</italic> with the use of microelectrodes. All measurements were performed in the anterior midgut of the beetle (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>). During these procedures, the tip of the electrode was driven to the surface of the gut wall and maintained in position until measured concentrations of O<sub>2</sub> stabilized. In all cases, once the tip penetrated the gut wall, oxygen concentrations declined with steep gradients going from microaerophilic conditions to a reduced anaerobic core (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Reinstating caffeine degradation in <italic>H. hampei</italic></title>
        <p>Antibiotic-treated laboratory specimens of <italic>H. hampei</italic> were initially fed on the minimal diet containing <italic>P. fulva</italic> for 1 week. Insects were subsequently transferred to a freshly prepared sterile minimal diet and were allowed to feed for 4&#x2009;h before frass was collected and caffeine concentrations quantified. Both GC&#x2013;MS and FTIR analyses showed an almost complete depletion of caffeine content in the frass of the reinfected insects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3c</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). The reproductive fitness of the antibiotic-treated and <italic>P. fulva</italic>-reinfected insects was also tested. Insects did not recover their ability to reproduce after <italic>P. fulva</italic> inoculation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="1" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Although other insects have been occasionally reported to feed on the coffee seed<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>, <italic>H. hampei</italic>, is the only insect that has specialized on feeding and completing its entire life cycle exclusively within the coffee beans inside the berry<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>. While surviving in this environment, <italic>H. hampei</italic> experiences chronic exposure to caffeine which is known to be a toxic alkaloid<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>, making this insect an attractive model system in which to evaluate the role of microbes in the adaptation of animals to unusual environments. In this study, we tested whether caffeine degradation in <italic>H. hampei</italic> is mediated by the insect's gut microbiota.</p>
      <p>To test for the contribution of <italic>H. hampei</italic>'s gut-associated microbes to caffeine degradation, first feeding rates and transit time of the fed-diet through the insect's gut were determined. Once the parameters for the transit time of the diet were obtained, a set of insects was fed on minimal diet supplemented with antibiotics to deplete its microbiota. Frass samples were collected from <italic>H. hampei</italic> specimens feeding on minimal diet and diet supplemented with antibiotics and their caffeine content compared using FTIR and GC&#x2013;MS. These results demonstrated that insects with an intact microbiome had a nearly complete degradation of the caffeine during its transit through the beetle gut. However, contrary to the control insects, antibiotic treated <italic>H. hampei</italic> specimens lost the ability to degrade caffeine, demonstrating the importance of the insect's microbiome to this critical function. Depletion of the microbiome also had a pronounced impact on the insect's reproductive fitness. Across all developmental stages observed, antibiotic treatment resulted in significant and substantial declines in numbers of viable insects relative to controls. While the mechanism underlying this observation is likely complex and not addressed here, it has been observed previously that members of other insect microbiomes can be responsible for the regulation of behaviour, feeding habits, mating preferences, reproductive capacity and the acquisition or the production of nutrients required by the host<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>.</p>
      <p>Members of the gut microbiota of <italic>H. hampei</italic> were identified from insects collected from seven coffee-producing countries and a laboratory colony. The calculated &#x3B2;-diversity and variance partitioning analyses demonstrated that the composition of the <italic>H. hampei</italic> microbiome was significantly associated with geographic origin of the coffee and also with the species of coffee where that varied (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Data 1</xref>). The formation of morphocryptic units was previously demonstrated in <italic>H. hampei</italic> samples collected from different coffee-producing countries by the analysis of microsatellite markers and COI gene sequences<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>. These reported &#x2018;species complexes', together with our findings of a geographic variation of microbial communities in <italic>H. hampei</italic>, may be indicative of the co-evolution of insects and their microbiota. Caffeine content varies significantly between the coffee species assessed<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref> and, although not tested here, caffeine concentration may be another important factor having an impact on <italic>H. hampei</italic> gut microbiome composition.</p>
      <p>Despite the observed variation in microbiome composition demonstrated by the biogeography analysis, all insect specimens shared a common core of microorganisms as demonstrated by network analysis. The shared microbial groups included the Pseudomonadales, Enterobacteriales, Turicibacteriales, Rhizobiales, Alteromonadales and Actinomycetales. Fourteen caffeine-subsisting bacteria from the orders of the Pseudomonadales, Rhizobiales, Enterobacteriales and Actinomycetales were isolated from the guts of field specimens of <italic>H. hampei</italic> on media containing caffeine as the sole source of carbon and nitrogen. It is significant that many of the <italic>H. hampei</italic> microbiome common core were also confirmed to subsist <italic>in vitro</italic> on caffeine. To evaluate the possible mechanisms of caffeine degradation, all isolates were screened for the gene <italic>ndmA</italic> that codes for a monooxygenase that participates in the initial demethylation of caffeine in bacteria<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>. Only <italic>P. fulva</italic> isolates yielded positive amplification. Given that the Pseudomonadales were also the dominant group detected in the <italic>H. hampei</italic> gut microbiome across all sampled locations, we determined whether this pathway was active in field specimens of <italic>H. hampei</italic> actively infecting coffee beans. Total RNA from these field specimens was analysed using quantitative PCR with reverse transcription for transcripts of the <italic>ndmA</italic> gene and positive amplification demonstrated its expression <italic>in situ</italic>, providing further evidence of the possible contribution of <italic>P. fulva</italic> to caffeine degradation in the insect. Because the monooxygenase encoded by the <italic>ndmA</italic> gene is an enzyme that requires oxygen to function, oxygen availability in the gut of <italic>H. hampei</italic> was also characterized with the use of microelectrodes. As in the case of other insects<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref>, the gut of <italic>H. hampei</italic> contains a radial oxygen gradient that changes slowly from microaerophilic to anaerobic conditions. The existence of this gradient suggests that the gut of this insect can provide the environment for the occurrence of aerobic processes such as the transformation of caffeine by the NdmA demethylase, and also anaerobic processes that are likely important such as the fermentation of the sugars from the coffee bean.</p>
      <p>To confirm the role of <italic>P. fulva</italic> in the degradation of caffeine <italic>in vivo</italic>, antibiotic-treated laboratory specimens were reinfected with <italic>P. fulva</italic>. Insects were subsequently fed with sterile minimal diet and their frass collected for caffeine quantification. This demonstrated that re-inoculation with <italic>P. fulva</italic> reinstated the ability of <italic>H. hampei</italic> to degrade caffeine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3c</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>), confirming the importance of this member of the gut microbiota in the caffeine-detoxification process. To test whether <italic>P. fulva</italic> alone could aid <italic>H. hampei</italic> in the recovery of its reproductive fitness, a third set of insects treated with antibiotic was inoculated with <italic>P. fulva</italic> and used for the fitness assessment. However, insects did not recover their ability to reproduce after inoculation. A process as complex as reproduction may require a proper nutritional state of the insect that relies in part on the metabolic activity of its associated microbes or may require the presence of other bacterial endosymbionts known to influence reproductive health<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>. Determining the minimal set of microorganisms to reinstate reproductive fitness as well as comparison of the effect of coffee species with varying caffeine concentrations on the microbial communities associated with <italic>H. hampei</italic> are important topics for further research.</p>
      <p>Here we demonstrate that <italic>H. hampei</italic>, the most devastating coffee pest in coffee-producing countries, possesses a common core of gut microbiota that is shared among individuals from different geographic locations, and that many of these organisms can subsist on caffeine as their sole source of carbon and nitrogen. We also demonstrate that the <italic>H. hampei</italic> microbiota are responsible for caffeine degradation in the insect's digestive tract. Microbial communities play important roles in all ecosystems, from participating in the cycling of nutrients in soil to shaping the immune system in humans<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref>. Our demonstration of the role of the gut microbiota in the detoxification of caffeine in <italic>H. hampei</italic> has important implications for understanding the metabolism and ecology of this important coffee pest. It also provides novel avenues to develop biocontrol strategies, where the microbiome represents a novel target because of the role of associated microorganisms in the enhanced ability of the host to survive and dominate a hostile environment.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="1" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Insect specimens</title>
        <p><italic>H. hampei</italic> specimens (<italic>n</italic>=68; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Data 1</xref>) were obtained from Kenya (Kiambu), Indonesia (East Java), India (Karnataka), Puerto Rico (Adjuntas), Hawaii (Kona), Guatemala (Coatepeque) and Mexico (Chiapas; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Data 1</xref>). Insects from India were collected from <italic>C. arabica</italic> and from a robusta hybrid (<italic>C. congensis</italic> &#xD7; <italic>C. canephora</italic>). <italic>H. obscurus, H. crudiae</italic> and <italic>S. maurus</italic> were obtained from <italic>Cecropia</italic> leaf stems in Chiapas, Mexico. For the biogeography study and comparison purposes, coffee berry borers reared on artificial diet<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref> (laboratory insects) were also included. At all collection sites, individual insects were placed alive in tubes containing RNAlater (Ambion, Grand Island, NY, USA) and shipped to our laboratory for analyses.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>DNA extraction, PCR amplification and high-throughput sequencing</title>
        <p>For DNA extraction, individual specimens were removed from RNAlater, and were surface-sterilized by passing the beetles through four sequential washing steps in microcentrifuge tubes containing 500&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of diethylpyrocarbonate (DEPC)-treated water, commercial bleach, absolute ethanol or DEPC&#x2013;water, respectively. At each step, the sample was vigorously shaken for <italic>ca.</italic> 30&#x2009;s. A Biomasher (Investigen, Hercules, CA) column was placed in a microcentrifuge tube, and 180&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of ATL buffer from the QIAmp DNA micro kit (Qiagen, Grand Island, NY, USA) added to the column. Individual insects were placed on the column and ground with the biomasher pestle. The biomasher column was kept in place, and 5&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of proteinase K (Ambion) was added to the column, mixed by tapping and incubated at 56&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 30&#x2009;min. The sample was centrifuged at 16,000<italic>g</italic> for 1&#x2009;min; the column and biomasher were discarded afterwards. The flow-through was incubated at 56&#x2009;&#xB0;C for an additional 30&#x2009;min. Lysozyme buffer (180&#x2009;&#x3BC;l; 20&#x2009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 2&#x2009;mM EDTA, 1.2% Triton X) containing 10&#x2009;mg&#x2009;ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> of lysozyme was then added to the flow-through and the mixture incubated at 37&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 30&#x2009;min. The DNA was then precipitated and purified following the QIAmp DNA micro protocol for tissues (Qiagen). The DNA concentration was determined with the use of a Qubit fluorometer (Qiagen). The DNA yields ranged from 0.5 to 5&#x2009;ng&#x2009;&#x3BC;l<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. The bacterial/archaeal hypervariable domains V3&#x2013;V4 of the 16S rRNA gene were amplified from each DNA extract in triplicate reactions using the primers 515F and 806R modified with adaptors and unique barcodes for Illumina sequencing<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>. All samples were then pooled and purified with the use of SPRI beads (Agencourt AMPure XP, Beckman Coulter, Brea, CA, USA). Sequencing of amplicons was carried out on a GAIIX Illumina Sequencer (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>16S rRNA gene analysis</title>
        <p>Reads between 80 and 100&#x2009;bp were used for downstream analysis in the Quantitative Insights Into Microbial Ecology pipeline<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref>. The total number of reads amounted to 15,000,000 with an average number of 169,000 sequences per sample (range: 19,000&#x2013;200,000). All reads were deposited at the European Bioinformatics Institute with the accession code PRJEB8706. Sequences were clustered at 97% pairwise identity using the UCLUST<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref> reference-based Operational Taxonomic Unit (OTU) picking method, where the reference data set was the GreenGenes 99% (GG99_12_10; ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">42</xref>). A representative sequence from each OTU was aligned to the GG99 data set using PyNAST (ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">43</xref>). The concatenated alignment of OTUs was filtered to remove gaps and hypervariable regions using the GreenGenes Lane mask<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">44</xref>. A phylogenetic tree was constructed from the filtered alignment using FastTree<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">45</xref>. Taxonomic assignments were carried out with the naive Bayesian algorithm<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref> developed for the Ribosomal Database Project (RDP) classifier<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">47</xref> using the GG99 taxonomy data set as training<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">42</xref>. OTU-generated matrices were used to create network profiles that were visualized with the Cytoscape software<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">48</xref>. For network visualization, only the most abundant bacterial groups were retained. Node sizes were adjusted according to the degree of each node, and the edge intensity adjusted to its corresponding weight (number of sequences associated with a node). Phylogenetic &#x3B2;-diversity was quantified with a weighted Unifrac distance matrix (Weighted Unifrac), which was constructed at a depth of coverage of 20,000 sequences (normalized coverage to the minimum number of sequences in the data set). The resulting distance matrix was used to cluster samples using the UPGMA hierarchical clustering algorithm. Support values for the UPGMA dendrograms were calculated using 100 jackknife permutations, and nodes having at least 50% support were deemed to have high support. The samples were categorized according to their geographical origins, insect species and plant species from where the samples were collected. The effect of the categories on the data variations was tested with Adonis (nonparametric permutation multivariate analysis of variance) performing 1,000 permutations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Isolation of caffeine-degrading bacteria and their identification</title>
        <p>To isolate bacteria with the ability to degrade caffeine, <italic>H. hampei</italic> specimens collected in Hawaii and Mexico were used. Ten <italic>H. hampei</italic> specimens per location were dissected and macerated in 100&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of 1 &#xD7; phosphate buffer and further diluted at a proportion of 1:10 in 1 &#xD7; phosphate buffer. Fifty microlitres of the diluted gut solution were plated on agar plates containing the following: (1) mineral media (9.5&#x2009;mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 4.8&#x2009;mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.1&#x2009;mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.8&#x2009;mM Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> and 20&#x2009;g&#x2009;l<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> bacto agar), with a gradient of caffeine ranging from 5 to 12.8&#x2009;mM (1 to 2.5&#x2009;g&#x2009;l<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>); (2) mineral media, 5 to 12.5&#x2009;mM gradient of caffeine and 2&#x2009;mM of glucose; or (3) mineral media, 5 to 12.5&#x2009;mM caffeine gradient and 9&#x2009;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl. The inoculated plates were incubated at 30&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 1 week. The growth of bacteria was monitored every day to follow the formation of morphologically distinct colonies that were picked and transferred to fresh minimal media agar plates containing 7.7&#x2009;mM (1.5&#x2009;g&#x2009;l<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) caffeine. Isolated colonies were transferred to assay tubes containing 5&#x2009;ml of tryptic soy broth and incubated at 30&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 72&#x2009;h to produce biomass for DNA extraction, and to prepare glycerol stocks that were placed at &#x2212;80&#x2009;&#xB0;C for storage. The bacterial DNA was extracted with the DNeasy Blood and Tissue Kit (Qiagen) following the protocol for Gram-positive bacteria, and used for the amplification of the complete 16S rRNA genes using the primers 27F (5&#x2032;-GTTTGATCCTGGCTCAG-3&#x2032;) and 1492R (5&#x2032;-GGTTACCTTGTTACGACTT-3&#x2032;). The PCR reactions were prepared as follows: 10&#x2009;ng of DNA as template, 5&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of 10 &#xD7; <italic>ExTaq</italic> Buffer, 200&#x2009;&#x3BC;M of dNTPs, 2.5&#x2009;U ExTaq DNA polymerase (Takara Mirus Bio Inc., WI, USA), 300&#x2009;ng&#x2009;&#x3BC;l<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> of BSA, 10&#x2009;&#x3BC;M of each primer and DEPC-treated water to a final volume of 25&#x2009;&#x3BC;l. The PCR conditions were 98&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 3&#x2009;min, then 30 cycles of 98&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 10&#x2009;s, followed by 57&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 30&#x2009;s, 72&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 30&#x2009;s and a final extension step of 72&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 2&#x2009;min. The PCR products were then purified with the MinElute PCR purification kit (Qiagen) and bi-directionally sequenced with the same primers. The isolates were identified by phylogenetic analysis as follows. Sequences were visualized using 4Peaks and edited with the Seaview software<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49">49</xref>. The obtained 16S rRNA sequences were aligned using Clustal X (ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">50</xref>) with corresponding reference sequences from NCBI, and phylogenetic analysis was carried out with maximum parsimony criteria in PAUP<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51">51</xref>. Heuristic tree searches were performed using a tree bisection reconnection model and a branch-swapping algorithm with 100 random stepwise swaps. One hundred trees were calculated for each pseudoreplicate. A rescaled consistency index, derived from trees and obtained by unweighted analysis, was used to generate an <italic>a posteriori</italic> weighted data set. The same heuristic search conditions as used for the unweighted data were used to analyse the weighted data set. Branch support was obtained with 100 bootstrap replicates. <italic>Desulfurobacterium thermolitotrophum</italic> (NR_025270) was used as outgroup in each phylogenetic reconstruction.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Screening of the <italic>ndmA</italic> gene in isolates and <italic>H. hampei</italic></title>
        <p>For the screening of the <italic>ndmA</italic> gene, the DNA from each isolate was used as template for PCR amplification with the primers A-degF1 and cdm-Rev1<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>. The PCR reactions were prepared as follows: 50&#x2009;ng of DNA as template, 5&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of 10 &#xD7; <italic>ExTaq</italic> Buffer, 200&#x2009;&#x3BC;M of dNTPs, 2.5&#x2009;U ExTaq DNA polymerase (Takara Mirus Bio Inc., WI, USA), 300&#x2009;ng&#x2009;&#x3BC;l<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> of BSA, 10&#x2009;&#x3BC;M of each primer and DEPC-treated water to a final volume of 25&#x2009;&#x3BC;l. The temperature profiles were as reported in ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref> for the same set of primers. Positive reactions were defined by the presence of a 1,000-bp band. Obtained PCR bands were purified and sequenced with the same set of primers. Obtained DNA sequences were aligned, and a second set of primers designed for qPCR (CBBcdmF, 5&#x2032;-TGGCATCCCGTWTGTACYGT-3&#x2032;; CBBcdmR, 5&#x2032;-CTTGKATAACRATTCGCAACC-3&#x2032;) generating an &#x223C;400-bp product. RNA was extracted from a pool of five insects collected in Mexico using the ISOLATE II RNA micro kit (Bioline, MA, USA) and complementary DNA prepared using 100&#x2009;ng of total RNA. Total RNA, 300&#x2009;ng of random hexamer primers and 20&#x2009;nmol of each dNTP were combined to a total volume of 11&#x2009;&#x3BC;l and the mixture incubated at 65&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 5&#x2009;min. Then, 5&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of 5 &#xD7; first strand buffer was added to the mixture, together with 20&#x2009;U of SUPERase-ln (Invitrogen), and incubated at 25&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 2&#x2009;min. After incubating, 200&#x2009;U of SuperScript III reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen) was added to the mixture and incubated at 50&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 50&#x2009;min. The reaction was inactivated at 70&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 10&#x2009;min. cDNA was then used as a template for qPCR with the primers CBBcdmF and CBBcdmR. Amplification reactions were carried out in a total volume of 25&#x2009;&#x3BC;l, which consisted of 1&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of a diluted (1:10) cDNA template, 12.5&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of 2 &#xD7; iQ SYBR green super mix (Bio-Rad), 0.4&#x2009;&#x3BC;M of each primer and 9.5&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of water. The PCR conditions were 95&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 3&#x2009;min, then 45 cycles of 95&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 10&#x2009;s, followed by 57&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 30&#x2009;s with the iQ system (Bio-Rad). qPCR products from each gut region were pooled and purified using the QIAquick PCR purification kit (Qiagen) and cloned into competent <italic>E. coli</italic> JM109 cells (Promega) using the pGEM-T Easy Vector Kit (Promega) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Transformants were incubated in modified LB media (0.4% glycerol and 1.7&#x2009;mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> and 7.2&#x2009;mM K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>) at 37&#x2009;&#xB0;C and 300&#x2009;r.p.m. for 19&#x2009;h. Plasmids were extracted using the SeqPrep 96 HP Plasmid Prep Kit and sequenced with an ABI377 sequencer (Applied Biosystems, Grand Island, NY, USA) using M13 universal forward and reverse sequencing primers. Sequences were visualized using 4Peaks and edited with the Seaview software<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49">49</xref>. DNA sequences from both isolates and <italic>H. hampei</italic> were aligned, trimmed and translated in all frames using the CLC sequence Viewer 6 (CLC Bio, Cambridge, MA, USA). Translated NdmA sequences were aligned using Clustal X (ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">50</xref>) with related protein reference sequences from NCBI and phylogenetic analysis was carried out with maximum parsimony criteria in PAUP as described before. The ammonia monooxygenase protein sequence of <italic>Mycobacterium rhodesiae</italic> (AEV73531) was used as an outgroup for the phylogenetic reconstruction.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>O<sub>2</sub> measurements using microelectrodes</title>
        <p>Oxygen gradients in the gut of <italic>H. hampei</italic> were measured as described before<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>. Briefly, insects were dissected keeping the head of the insects attached to the gut to avoid releasing the gut content and O<sub>2</sub> profiles measured at the anterior midgut. Clark-type oxygen microelectrodes (OX-25, Unisense) were used for the measurement of O<sub>2</sub> concentration. Before use, the electrodes were polarized overnight and calibrated in water saturated with air, as well as in an anoxic solution consisting of 0.1&#x2009;M sodium hydroxide and 0.1&#x2009;M sodium ascorbate. Calibration was carried out before each experiment. The current was measured with a Unisense microsensor multimeter and recorded using the SensorTracePRO software (Unisense). Before microelectrode measurements 10&#x2009;ml of low-melting-point agarose consisting of 2% agarose in insect Ringer's solution was cast into a microchamber. A freshly dissected gut was placed on this layer of agarose, fully extended and immediately covered with a second layer of molten 1% agarose at 30&#x2009;&#xB0;C. Microelectrodes were positioned using a motorized micromanipulator (MXU2, Pyro Science). Measurements were performed radially starting at the surface of the gut wall (0&#x2009;&#x3BC;m) through the beetle gut until the tip completely penetrated the whole tissue. The progress of the tip was followed with a digital microscope (44032 Celestron) connected to a computer. All measurements were carried out at room temperature.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Diet-transit time in <italic>H. hampei</italic></title>
        <p>A modified diet, here referred to as minimal diet, was formulated based on the artificial diet used for rearing <italic>H. hampei</italic> (laboratory insects)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref>, but containing only 50-g twice-ground green coffee beans, 1&#x2009;g Wesson salts, 0.5&#x2009;g nipagin, 0.4&#x2009;g benzoic acid, 1&#x2009;ml 37% formaldehyde, 1.5&#x2009;g of gellan gum as a solidifying agent and 375&#x2009;ml water. The diet was modified to reduce protein interaction with antibiotics. A population of laboratory insects maintained in the regular artificial diet was transferred to the minimal diet and allowed to feed for 3 weeks. A subsample of the minimal diet-fed laboratory insects was used for all of the experimental procedures. Four 10-ml vials containing 2&#x2009;g of minimal diet and fluorescent spheres (Fluospheres, Invitrogen) at a concentration of 1,800 particles per mg of diet were inoculated with 20 laboratory insects. Each vial was sampled at 1, 2, 3, 4 and 24&#x2009;h, and a total of four <italic>H. hampei</italic> specimens selected per sampling time for gut extraction<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52">52</xref>. After dissection, each gut was placed on a cover slide and covered with 2&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of 1 &#xD7; phosphate buffer. The dissected guts were then screened using a microscope at &#xD7; 40 magnification under ultraviolet light for the detection and counting of the fluorescent spheres. Considering a homogeneous distribution of particles in the diet, the number of counted fluorescent spheres per sampling point was transformed into mg of ingested diet over the time. The counts were fitted to a model in the R software environment<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53">53</xref> using a nonlinear least squares regression to calculate the feeding rates of <italic>H. hampei</italic>. The time at which the fluorescent spheres were localized near the anal opening was considered to be the total transit time of the diet; after this period, dropping activity (defecation) and release of the fluospheres was expected and confirmed by placing 4-h-fed <italic>H. hampei</italic> into a clean PCR tube for 2&#x2009;h. The insects were then removed and frass-homogenized with water and screened with ultraviolet-microscopy for the detection of the fluospheres.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Antibiotic treatment and reinfection</title>
        <p>Twenty laboratory specimens of <italic>H. hampei</italic> were transferred into five sets of 10-ml triplicated vials containing 2&#x2009;ml of minimal diet supplemented with a mixture of 50&#x2009;&#x3BC;g&#x2009;ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> tetracycline, 200&#x2009;&#x3BC;g&#x2009;ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> rifampicin and 100&#x2009;&#x3BC;g&#x2009;ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> streptomycin; one set was prepared for direct detection of caffeine and the second for the reinfection experiments. The same number of insects was transferred to control vials containing 2&#x2009;ml of minimal diet (no antibiotics). The insects were transferred to freshly prepared sterile diet every week during a 4-week period. After the fourth week, 10 insects from each vial were aseptically transferred to new 10-ml vials containing sterile minimal diet with fluorescent spheres (1,800 particles&#x2009;mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>). Insects were allowed to feed for 4&#x2009;h (time required to reach gut content equilibrium) and then transferred to a clean flat-bottom 96-well plate for frass collection. After 4&#x2009;h the insects were removed from the wells and the frass collected by washing the wells with 50&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of water. The samples were then stored at &#x2212;20&#x2009;&#xB0;C until further analysis. For the reinfection experiments, isolate iMX49 (identified as <italic>P. fulva</italic>) was propagated in tryptic soy broth at 30&#x2009;&#xB0;C and 100&#x2009;r.p.m. for 24&#x2009;h. The resulting biomass was centrifuged and the pellet washed and stored in 5&#x2009;ml of 1 &#xD7; phosphate buffer. The number of CFUs corresponding to this bacterial solution were determined by plating a 1:100 dilution of the suspension on tryptic soy agar plates and incubated for 24&#x2009;h at 30&#x2009;&#xB0;C. New minimal diet was prepared and supplemented with the iMX49 bacterial solution at rate of 10,000&#x2009;CFU&#x2009;ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, and left to dry for 48&#x2009;h at room temperature. Antibiotic-treated insects (after their fourth week) were transferred to the bacteria-inoculated diet and were allowed to feed. After 1 week, the frass from the reinfected insects was collected in the same way as for the control samples. Since the amount of frass was too small to be weighed accurately, three 10-&#x3BC;l aliquots (per treatment) of the frass solution were visualized under the microscope under ultraviolet illumination to count the fluospheres. The number of fluospheres was then used to transform quantities to milligram of diet for normalization purposes. The obtained samples from each treatment were then analysed using FTIR and GC&#x2013;MS to determine their corresponding levels of caffeine as described below.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Detection of caffeine in frass samples</title>
        <p>To determine the concentration of caffeine in the frass samples of the antibiotic-treated-, antibiotic-infected- and control beetles, two strategies were followed: measurement of caffeine in raw frass with FTIR and measurement of extracted caffeine from frass samples with GC&#x2013;MS.</p>
        <p><italic>Measurement of caffeine in raw frass using FTIR:</italic> Obtained frass solutions were first deposited and air-dried for 5&#x2009;min on a 1-mm-thick zinc-selenide crystal and then infrared absorption spectra of the samples collected with a transmission FTIR<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref> microscope (Nic-Plan IR Microscope with Nicolet Magna 760 bench, Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc.) with a 100-&#x3BC;m aperture. A globar thermal source, a MCT detector and a KBr beamsplitter were used in all the experiments. Each spectrum was averaged by 128 scans at the 4-cm<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> spectral resolution. The whole area of each sample was raster-scanned and the spectra were averaged for each sample. Known amounts of pure caffeine (0.03, 0.12, 0.2 and 0.3&#x2009;&#x3BC;g of caffeine; Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA) were also deposited on the same crystal and their corresponding signals used as the standards for the relative quantification of caffeine in the frass samples (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>). The major infrared absorption peaks at &#x223C;1,655 and &#x223C;1,705&#x2009;cm<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, related to the stretching vibrations of carbon&#x2013;nitrogen double bond and the carbonyl groups, respectively, are used to identify the presence of caffeine and evaluate the caffeine concentration in different frass samples. The two Lorentzian peaks were deconvolved from each obtained absorption spectrum, and the peak area data were used to compare with the areas obtained from the standards. The caffeine content of the frass samples was normalized by the amount of frass deposited in the zinc-selenide crystal per sample.</p>
        <p><italic>Caffeine extraction from frass and GC&#x2013;MS:</italic> Water-solubilized frass samples were nitrogen-dried and then derivatized<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54">54</xref>. Briefly, 10&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of a solution containing 40&#x2009;mg&#x2009;ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> of 98% methoxyamine hydrochloride in pyridine was added to each dry sample followed by 90&#x2009;min of shaking at 30&#x2009;&#xB0;C. A mixture of internal retention index markers was prepared using fatty acid methyl esters (FAMEs) of C8, C9, C10, C12, C14, C16, C18, C20, C22, C24, C26, C28 and C30 linear chain length, dissolved in chloroform at a concentration of 0.8&#x2009;mg&#x2009;ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> (C8&#x2013;C16) and 0.4&#x2009;mg&#x2009;ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> (C18&#x2013;C30). The FAME mixture (20&#x2009;&#x3BC;l) was added to 1&#x2009;ml of N-Methyl-N-(trimethylsilyl)-trifluoroacetamide containing 1% of Trimethylclorosilane. Ninety microlitres of N-Methyl-N-(trimethylsilyl)-trifluoroacetamide spiked with the FAME mixture was then added to each extract followed by mixing for 30&#x2009;min at 37&#x2009;&#xB0;C. Pure caffeine (Sigma-Aldrich) was used to generate a calibration curve with levels at 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2.5, 5, 10 and 20&#x2009;&#x3BC;g&#x2009;ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> in 50% methanol. One hundred microlitres of each level was dried and derivatized using the same procedure described for the samples. Derivatized samples were manipulated using a Gerstel automatic liner exchange MPS system (Gerstel, Muehlheim, Germany) controlled with the Maestro software v.1.4.25.8 to inject 2&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of sample into a Gerstel CIS cooled injection system. The injector was operated in the splitless mode, and the split vent was opened after 25&#x2009;s. Samples were injected into the inlet initially at 60&#x2009;&#xB0;C, which was then ramped to 270&#x2009;&#xB0;C in 12&#x2009;&#xB0;C&#x2009;s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> increments and held for 3&#x2009;min. Sample separation was carried out on a 30-m-long, 0.25-mm ID Rtx-5Sil MS column (Restek, Bellefonte, PA), 0.25&#x2009;mm 5% diphenyl film with a 10-m integrated guard column using an Agilent 7890 gas chromatograph (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA), controlled with the Agilent GC&#x2013;MS MassHunter Acquisition software v.B07.00 SP1 with a constant flow rate of 1&#x2009;ml&#x2009;min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. Initial oven temperature was 60&#x2009;&#xB0;C with the following gradient applied: held at 60&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 1&#x2009;min; ramp at 10&#x2009;&#xB0;C&#x2009;min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> to 310&#x2009;&#xB0;C, held for 10&#x2009;min. Mass spectrometry was performed with an Agilent 5977 single quadrupole MS with 250&#x2009;&#xB0;C transfer line temperature, electron ionization at 70&#x2009;eV, an ion source temperature of 230&#x2009;&#xB0;C and a quadrupole temperature of 150&#x2009;&#xB0;C. Mass spectra were acquired in a selected ion-monitoring mode at a scan rate of 4.4 spectra&#x2009;s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. Selected ions for caffeine were 55, 82, 109 and 194. A quality-control mix was run in triplicate before and after the sample set to confirm GC and MS signal reproducibility. Caffeine levels were quantitated in acquired data using Agilent MassHunter Quantitative Analysis v.B.07.00.</p>
        <p>For FTIR and GC&#x2013;MS analyses, significant differences between treatments (control, antibiotic-treated and antibiotic-treated/re-inoculated) were determined using one-way analysis of variance and least significant differences using the R software environment<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53">53</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Antibiotic treatment effect on <italic>H. hampei</italic> reproduction</title>
        <p>One hundred females recently emerged as adults were placed together with 20 males in vials containing regular diet and were incubated for 14 days to maximize mating. After the initial mating incubation, individual females were transferred to a vial containing either regular diet (control) or diet supplemented with antibiotics (as described above) and incubated for 44 days. A third set of mated females was treated with antibiotics for 3 weeks, transferred to diet with <italic>P. fulva</italic> and also incubated for 44 days. Fifteen vials from each treatment were destructively sampled on each sampling time (days 14, 24, 34 and 44) and screened for eggs, larvae, pupae and adults. A logistic regression was performed on the sum of all stages in each vial. Then, a model was fit with just the main effects (DIET&#x2014;control, antibiotics, infection; and SAMPLE&#x2014;sampling time), where overdispersion was included. Both main effects were significant, that is, there is a significant effect of DIET when compared with control, and there is a significant effect of sample (later samples had higher counts).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="1">
      <title>Additional information</title>
      <p><bold>Accession codes:</bold> 16S rRNA sequences from the biogeography analysis have been deposited in the European Bioinformatics Institute (EBI) database with the accession code PRJEB8706. The 16S rRNA sequences from the isolated caffeine-subsisting bacteria and the <italic>ndmA</italic> sequences have been deposited in the GenBank database with accession codes <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KF913733">KF913733</ext-link> to <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KF913844">KF913844</ext-link>, and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KJ159083">KJ159083</ext-link> to <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KJ159093">KJ159093</ext-link>, respectively.</p>
      <p><bold>How to cite this article</bold>: Ceja-Navarro, J. A. <italic>et al.</italic> Gut microbiota mediate caffeine detoxification in the primary insect pest of coffee. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic> 6:7618 doi: 10.1038/ncomms8618 (2015).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e18" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Information</title>
          <p>Supplementary Figures 1-5</p>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms8618-s1.pdf"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e24" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Movie 1</title>
          <p>Video showing specimens of Hypothenemus hampei foraging and boring into defined media.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms8618-s2.mov"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e30" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Data 1</title>
          <p>Metadata of insects collected in seven major coffee producing countries. Data includes Country, Location, Insects Species, Host plant (or diet), GPS coordinates.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms8618-s3.xls"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This work was funded by the United States Department of Agriculture Agricultural Research Service, and part of this work was funded by the Laboratory Directed Research and Development programme at the Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory under United States Department of Energy contract number DE-AC02-05CH11231. J.A.C.-N. was supported in part by a grant from &#x2018;<italic>Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnolog&#xED;a</italic>' (CONACyT, Mexico) and the Laboratory Directed Research and Development Program of Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory under US Department of Energy Contract DE-AC02-05CH1121231. We are very grateful to S. Wiryadiputra (Indonesia), P.K. Vinod Kumar (India), A. Ramirez (Puerto Rico), PePe Miranda (Hawaii) and J. Jaramillo (Kenya) for providing specimens used in this study. We thank Susan Lynch for comments on this manuscript, Hoi-Ying Holman for advice on FTIR analyses, and Clark Santee for laboratory assistance.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="b1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Govaerts</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bridson</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Stoffelen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>An annotated taxonomic conspectus of the genus <italic>Coffea</italic> (Rubiaceae)</article-title>. <source>Bot. J. Linn. Soc.</source>
<volume>152</volume>, <fpage>465</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>512</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tosh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruch</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Growing coffee: <italic>Psilanthus</italic> (Rubiaceae) subsumed on the basis of molecular and morphological data; implications for the size, morphology, distribution and evolutionary history of <italic>Coffea</italic></article-title>. <source>Bot. J. Linn. Soc.</source>
<volume>167</volume>, <fpage>357</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>377</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ashihara</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Crozier</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Caffeine: a well known but little mentioned compound in plant science</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>407</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>413</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11544129</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Caffeine in floral nectar enhances a pollinator's memory of reward</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>339</volume>, <fpage>1202</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1204</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23471406</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nathanson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><article-title>Caffeine and related methylxanthines: possible naturally occurring pesticides</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>226</volume>, <fpage>184</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>187</lpage> (<year>1984</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6207592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Uefuji</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Caffeine production in tobacco plants by simultaneous expression of three coffee N-methyltrasferases and its potential as a pest repellant</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><volume>59</volume>, <fpage>221</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>227</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16247553</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.-S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Uefuji</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ogita</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Transgenic tobacco plants producing caffeine: a potential new strategy for insect pest control</article-title>. <source>Transgenic Res.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>667</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>672</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17091387</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Detzel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Wink</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Attraction, deterrence or intoxication of bees (<italic>Apis mellifera</italic>) by plant allelochemicals</article-title>. <source>Chemoecology</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>18</lpage> (<year>1993</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>I. A.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Genome-wide screen of genes required for caffeine tolerance in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>4</volume>, <fpage>e6619</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19672306</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abdelkader</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Exposure time to caffeine affects heartbeat and cell damage-related gene expression of zebrafish <italic>Danio rerio</italic> embryos at early developmental stages</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Toxicol.</source><volume>33</volume>, <fpage>1277</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1283</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22886764</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hollingsworth</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Caffeine as a repellent for slugs and snails</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>417</volume>, <fpage>915</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>916</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12087394</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ashihara</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Crozier</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> in <source>Methylxanthines (Fredholm, B. B.)</source>
<volume>200</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>31</lpage>Springer (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Le Pelley</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name><article-title>Coffee insects</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Entomol.</source><volume>18</volume>, <fpage>121</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>142</lpage> (<year>1973</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hagedorn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><article-title>Wieder ein neuer kaffeesch&#xE4;dlinge</article-title>. <source>Entomol. Bl&#xE4;tter</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>14</lpage> (<year>1910</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Neiva</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> Os trabalhos da Commiss&#xE3;o de Estudo e Debella&#xE7;&#xE3;o da Praga Cafeeira desde seu inicio. <italic>Commiss&#xE3;o de Estudo e Debella&#xE7;&#xE3;o da Praga Cafeeira</italic>, Publica&#xE7;&#xE3;o No. 21, 27 (<year>1928</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Jaramillo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>From forest to plantation? Obscure articles reveal alternative host plants for the coffee berry borer, <italic>Hypothenemus hampei</italic> (Coleoptera: Curculionidae)</article-title>. <source>Biol. J. Linn. Soc.</source>
<volume>107</volume>, <fpage>86</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>94</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Auad</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Frizzas</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Economic impact of exotic insect pests in Brazilian agriculture</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Entomol.</source>
<volume>137</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>15</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Acu&#xF1;a</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Adaptive horizontal transfer of a bacterial gene to an invasive insect pest of coffee</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume>109</volume>, <fpage>4197</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4202</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22371593</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guerreiro Filho</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Mazzafera</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Caffeine and resistance of coffee to the berry borer <italic>Hypothenemus hampei</italic> (Coleoptera: Scolytidae)</article-title>. <source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>6987</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6991</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14611159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gokulakrishnan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chandraraj</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Gummadi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Microbial and enzymatic methods for the removal of caffeine</article-title>. <source>Enzyme Microb. Technol.</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>225</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>232</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Metabolism of caffeine-3H in the rat*1, *2</article-title>. <source>Toxicol. Appl. Pharmacol.</source><volume>112</volume>, <fpage>720</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>730</lpage> (<year>1972</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4644703</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paradkar</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Irudayaraj</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A rapid FTIR spectroscopic method for estimation of caffeine in soft drinks and total methylxanthines in tea and coffee</article-title>. <source>J. Food Sci.</source>
<volume>67</volume>, <fpage>2507</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2511</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Novel, highly specific N-demethylases enable bacteria to live on caffeine and related purine alkaloids</article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source><volume>194</volume>, <fpage>2041</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2049</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22328667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Barrera</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><italic>Encyclopedia of Entomology</italic> (ed. Capinera, J. L.) 961&#x2013;998 (Springer Dordrecht, The Netherlands (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Infante</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> in <italic>Encyclopedia of Pest Management</italic> (ed. Pimentel, D.) 1&#x2013;4 (Dekker, (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ezenwa</surname><given-names>V. O.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gerardo</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inouye</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Microbiology. Animal behavior and the microbiome</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>338</volume>, <fpage>198</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>199</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23066064</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sharon</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Commensal bacteria play a role in mating preference of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume>107</volume>, <fpage>20051</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>20056</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21041648</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lilburn</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Nitrogen fixation by symbiotic and free-living spirochetes</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>292</volume>, <fpage>2495</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2498</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11431569</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoffmeister</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Interspecific evolution: microbial symbiosis, endosymbiosis and gene transfer</article-title>. <source>Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>641</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>649</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12871231</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><article-title>Multiple cryptic genetic units in <italic>Hypothenemus hampei</italic> (Coleoptera: Scolytinae): evidence from microsatellite and mitochondrial DNA sequence data</article-title>. <source>Biol. J. Linn. Soc.</source><volume>101</volume>, <fpage>113</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>129</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Waldhauser</surname><given-names>S. S. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Baumann</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Compartmentation of caffeine and related purine alkaloids depends exclusively on the physical chemistry of their vacuolar complex formation with chlorogenic acids</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>985</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>996</lpage> (<year>1996</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ceja-Navarro</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Compartmentalized microbial composition, oxygen gradients and nitrogen fixation in the gut of <italic>Odontotaenius disjunctus</italic></article-title>. <source>ISME J.</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>6</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>18</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23985746</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brune</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Breznak</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The termite gut microflora as an oxygen sink: microelectrode determination of oxygen and pH gradients in guts of lower and higher termites</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>2681</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2687</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16535076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benavides</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title><italic>Wolbachia</italic> infection in the coffee berry borer (Coleoptera: Scolytidae)</article-title>. <source>Ann. Entomol. Soc. Am.</source>
<volume>95</volume>, <fpage>374</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>378</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ingham</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trofymow</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ingham</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Interactions of bacteria, fungi, and their nematode grazers: effects on nutrient cycling and plant growth</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Monogr.</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>119</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>140</lpage> (<year>1985</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garbeva</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Raaijmakers</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The rhizosphere microbiome: significance of plant beneficial, plant pathogenic, and human pathogenic microorganisms</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Rev.</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>634</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>663</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23790204</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. K.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Mazmanian</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Has the microbiota played a critical role in the evolution of the adaptive immune system?</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>330</volume>, <fpage>1768</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1773</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21205662</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Villacorta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Barrera</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Nova dieta mer&#xED;dica para cria&#xE7;&#xE3;o de <italic>Hypothenemus hampei</italic> (Ferrari, 1867)</article-title>. <source>An. Soc. Entomol. Bras.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>405</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>409</lpage> (<year>1867</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Ultra-high-throughput microbial community analysis on the Illumina HiSeq and MiSeq platforms</article-title>. <source>ISME J.</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1621</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1624</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22402401</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>QIIME allows analysis of high-throughput community sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>335</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>336</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383131</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b41">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><article-title>Search and clustering orders of magnitude faster than BLAST</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics.</source><volume>26</volume>, <fpage>2460</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2461</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20709691</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b42">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Impact of training sets on classification of high-throughput bacterial 16s rRNA gene surveys</article-title>. <source>ISME J.</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>94</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>103</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21716311</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b43">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>PyNAST: a flexible tool for aligning sequences to a template alignment</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>26</volume>, <fpage>266</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>267</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19914921</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b44">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>DeSantis</surname><given-names>T. Z.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Greengenes, a chimera-checked 16S rRNA gene database and workbench compatible with ARB</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>72</volume>, <fpage>5069</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5072</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16820507</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b45">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dehal</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Arkin</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>FastTree 2&#x2013;approximately maximum-likelihood trees for large alignments</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>e9490</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20224823</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b46">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garrity</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tiedje</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Naive Bayesian classifier for rapid assignment of rRNA sequences into the new bacterial taxonomy</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>5261</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5267</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586664</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b47">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>The Ribosomal Database Project: improved alignments and new tools for rRNA analysis</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>37</volume>, <fpage>D141</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>D145</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19004872</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b48">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Cytoscape: a software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks</article-title>. <source>Genome Res.</source><volume>13</volume>, <fpage>2498</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2504</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14597658</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b49">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gouy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<article-title>SeaView version 4: a multiplatform graphical user interface for sequence alignment and phylogenetic tree building</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>221</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>224</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19854763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b50">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><article-title>The CLUSTAL_X windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis tools</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>25</volume>, <fpage>4876</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4882</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9396791</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b51">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Swofford</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name> PAUP*: phylogenetic analysis using parsimony, ver 4.0b10. (Sinauer Associates, Sunderland, Massachusetts, USA, (<year>1998</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b52">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ceja-Navarro</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brodie</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A technique to dissect the alimentary canal of the coffee berry borer (<italic>Hypothenemus hampei</italic>), with isolation of internal microorganisms</article-title>. <source>J. Entomol. Acarol. Res.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>e21</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b53">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">The R Development Core Team. <source>R: a language and environment for statistical computing</source> R Found. Stat. Comput. (<year>2010</year>) At http://www.r-project.org/ .</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b54">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kind</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>FiehnLib: mass spectral and retention index libraries for metabolomics based on quadrupole and time-of-flight gas chromatography/mass spectrometry</article-title>. <source>Anal. Chem.</source><volume>81</volume>, <fpage>10038</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10048</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19928838</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p><bold>Author contributions</bold> E.L.B., J.A.C.-N. and F.E.V. designed experiments, analysed data and wrote the manuscript. H.C.L. contributed to molecular analysis of microbiome composition. P.K. and F.I. contributed to manuscript writing. J.A.C.-N., P.K. and F.I. collected insect specimens. Z.H. performed FTIR analysis, U.K. performed biogeography analysis, S.J. and T.N. performed mass spectrometry analysis.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f1">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <title>The role of bacteria in the transformation of caffeine in <italic>H. hampei</italic>.</title>
        <p>(<bold>a</bold>) Experimental design and analysis of caffeine concentrations in the frass of control and antibiotic-treated <italic>H. hampei</italic> specimens. Antibiotic-mediated depletion of the <italic>H. hampei</italic> microbiome eliminates the transformation of caffeine and increases caffeine excretion. (<bold>b</bold>) FTIR profiles for pure caffeine (black), frass of control (non-antibiotic-treated insects&#x2014;red) and frass of antibiotic-treated insects (green). Depicted profiles represent the average of all measurements (<italic>n</italic>=6).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms8618-f1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f2">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <title>The core gut microbiome of <italic>H. hampei</italic> specimens collected from multiple coffee-producing countries.</title>
        <p>(<bold>a</bold>) Phylogenetic network analysis showing the dominant bacterial groups associated with <italic>H. hampei</italic> specimens from seven major coffee-producing countries. Specimens from Mexico also included non-<italic>H. hampei</italic> insects. &#x25CA;, <italic>H. hampei</italic>, <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="i2" xlink:href="ncomms8618-i2.jpg"/>&#x2014;<italic>S. maurus</italic>; &#x394;, <italic>H. crudiae</italic>; &#x25A1;, <italic>H. eruditus</italic>. (<bold>b</bold>) Proportions of <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp. sequences in the microbiome of the collected specimens.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms8618-f2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f3">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Isolated caffeine-subsisting bacteria and their activity in <italic>H. hampei</italic>.</title>
        <p>(<bold>a</bold>) Caffeine gradient plate depicting bacterial colonies isolated from <italic>H. hampei</italic> digestive tract and their identity as determined by phylogenetic analyses. <italic>P. fulva</italic> was the main group of isolates obtained. (<bold>b</bold>) Phylogenetic tree for the caffeine demethylase alpha-subunit (NdmA) sequences obtained from isolated bacteria (yellow) and also from RNA extracted from <italic>H. hampei</italic> field specimens (green). (<bold>c</bold>) Four-week antibiotic-pre-treated <italic>H. hampei</italic> specimens were inoculated with <italic>P. fulva</italic>, reinstating their ability to degrade caffeine as demonstrated using FTIR and GC&#x2013;MS measurements of caffeine in their frass (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms8618-f3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f4">
      <label>Figure 4</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Oxygen profiles in the anterior midgut of <italic>H. hampei</italic>.</title>
        <p>The figure shows the oxygen profiles of three beetle guts. Note the transition from a microaerophilic region to an anaerobic core in the lumen of the anterior midgut (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ncomms8618-f4"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="t1">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Quantification using GC&#x2013;MS and FTIR of the role of bacteria in the transformation of caffeine in <italic>H. hampei</italic>.</title>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
        <colgroup>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="char" char="&#xB1;"/>
          <col align="center"/>
        </colgroup>
        <thead valign="bottom">
          <tr>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Experiment</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Treatment</bold>
              <xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn2">*</xref>
            </th>
            <th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" char="&#xB1;" charoff="50">
              <bold>Caffeine in frass</bold>
              <xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn3">&#x2020;</xref>
              <bold>, mean&#xB1;s.e</bold>
              <hr/>
            </th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</th>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" char="&#xB1;" charoff="50">
              <bold>GC&#x2013;MS</bold>
              <xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn4">&#x2021;</xref>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>FTIR</bold>
              <xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn4">&#x2021;</xref>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Control</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>H. hampei</italic>&#x2014;normal microbiome</td>
            <td align="char" valign="top" char="&#xB1;" charoff="50">0.348&#xB1;0.038 (b)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">BDT<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn5">&#xA7;</xref> (b)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Antibiotic</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>H. hampei</italic>&#x2014;antibiotic-treated</td>
            <td align="char" valign="top" char="&#xB1;" charoff="50">2.154&#xB1;0.127 (a)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="top" char="&#xB1;" charoff="50">1.757&#xB1;0.410 (a)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Antibiotic-reinfection</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>H. hampei</italic>&#x2014;antibiotic-treated, reinfected with <italic>P. fulva</italic></td>
            <td align="char" valign="top" char="&#xB1;" charoff="50">0.639&#xB1;0.022 (b)</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">BDT<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn5">&#xA7;</xref> (b)</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn id="t1-fn1">
          <p>ANOVA, analysis of variance; BDT, below detection limits; FTIR, Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy; GC&#x2013;MS, gas chromatography&#x2013;mass spectrometry; LSD, least significant differences.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t1-fn2">
          <p><sup>*</sup>After treatment, insects were transferred to antibiotic-free fluorosphere-labelled diet (minimal diet) and left to feed for 4&#x2009;h before frass collection. <italic>N</italic>=6 (measured samples) for FTIR and <italic>N</italic>=4 for GC&#x2013;MS. Caffeine values per treatment were statistically compared with one-way ANOVA and least significant difference test.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t1-fn3">
          <p><sup>&#x2020;</sup>In milligram of caffeine per gram of diet.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t1-fn4">
          <p><sup>&#x2021;</sup>Values with same letter are not statistically different from each other, LSD test (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="t1-fn5">
          <p><sup>&#xA7;</sup>For ANOVA analysis, these values were defined as zero.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
