<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2935872</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erq211</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Papers</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Duplicate polyphenol oxidase genes on barley chromosome 2H and their functional differentiation in the phenol reaction of spikes and grains</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Taketa</surname>
            <given-names>Shin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Matsuki</surname>
            <given-names>Kanako</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Amano</surname>
            <given-names>Satoko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Saisho</surname>
            <given-names>Daisuke</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Himi</surname>
            <given-names>Eiko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shitsukawa</surname>
            <given-names>Naoki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yuo</surname>
            <given-names>Takahisa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Noda</surname>
            <given-names>Kazuhiko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Takeda</surname>
            <given-names>Kazuyoshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Institute of Plant Science and Resources, 2-20-1 Chuo, Okayama University, Kurashiki 710-0046, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Faculty of Agriculture, Kagawa University, 2393 Ikenobe, Miki, Kagawa 761-0795, Japan</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed: E-mail: <email>staketa@rib.okayama-u.ac.jp</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>8</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>8</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>61</volume>
      <issue>14</issue>
      <fpage>3983</fpage>
      <lpage>3993</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2010 The Author(s).</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
          <license-p>This paper is available online free of all access charges (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html">http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html</ext-link> for further details)</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Polyphenol oxidases (PPOs) are copper-containing metalloenzymes encoded in the nucleus and transported into the plastids. Reportedly, PPOs cause time-dependent discoloration (browning) of end-products of wheat and barley, which impairs their appearance quality. For this study, two barley <italic>PPO</italic> homologues were amplified using PCR with a primer pair designed in the copper binding domains of the wheat <italic>PPO</italic> genes. The full-lengths of the respective <italic>PPO</italic> genes were cloned using a BAC library, inverse-PCR, and 3&#x2032;-RACE. Linkage analysis showed that the polymorphisms in <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> co-segregated with the phenol reaction phenotype of awns. Subsequent RT-PCR experiments showed that <italic>PPO1</italic> was expressed in hulls and awns, and that <italic>PPO2</italic> was expressed in the caryopses. Allelic variation of <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> was analysed in 51 barley accessions with the negative phenol reaction of awns. In <italic>PPO1</italic>, amino acid substitutions of five types affecting functionally important motif(s) or C-terminal region(s) were identified in 40 of the 51 accessions tested. In <italic>PPO2</italic>, only one mutant allele with a precocious stop codon resulting from an 8 bp insertion in the first exon was found in three of the 51 accessions tested. These observations demonstrate that <italic>PPO1</italic> is the major determinant controlling the phenol reaction of awns. Comparisons of <italic>PPO1</italic> single mutants and the <italic>PPO1PPO2</italic> double mutant indicate that <italic>PPO2</italic> controls the phenol reaction in the crease on the ventral side of caryopses. An insertion of a hAT-family transposon in the promoter region of <italic>PPO2</italic> may be responsible for different expression patterns of the duplicate <italic>PPO</italic> genes in barley.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Gene duplication</kwd>
        <kwd>grasses</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>mutant</kwd>
        <kwd>phenol reaction</kwd>
        <kwd>PPO</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Polyphenol oxidases (PPOs) or tyrosinases catalyse oxidation of various phenolic substrates to quinones and initiate enzymatic browning in plant tissues. Although their role in metabolism remains largely unknown, PPOs are implicated in defence against insects and plant pathogens. In fact, PPOs are encoded by nuclear genes, but the enzyme is localized in the thylakoids of plastids without being an integral membrane protein. The enzyme is separated spatially from its phenolic substrates, which are located in the vacuole. The browning reaction therefore occurs only in the event that tissue damage degrades subcellular compartmentation. Plant <italic>PPO</italic> genes encode bi-copper metalloenzymes that possess two conserved copper-binding domains, CuA and CuB; at each site, a Cu ion is bound by conserved histidine residues. This pair of Cu ions is the site of interaction of PPOs with both oxygen molecule and phenolic substrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Vaughn <italic>et al.</italic>, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">van Gelder <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Yoruk and Marshall, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Marusek <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Mayer, 2006</xref>).</p>
      <p>To date, full-length sequences of <italic>PPO</italic> genes have been isolated in several dicotyledonous plant species including broad bean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Cary <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>), potato (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hunt <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>), grape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Dry and Robinson, 1994</xref>), apple (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Boss <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>), tomato (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Shahar <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Thipyapong <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">1997</xref>), poplar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Constabel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>), and red clover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Sullivan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Moreover, PPOs have been studied in monocotyledonous species. In wheat, PPOs have been studied intensively because of their association with the quality of flour products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Demeke and Morris, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Raman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Anderson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">He <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Massa <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). In addition, PPOs play an important role in the browning and discoloration of pasta (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Simeone <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>), steamed bread (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Dexter <italic>et al.</italic>, 1984</xref>), and Asian noodles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Fuerst <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). In rice, a <italic>PPO</italic> gene was recently proved to be responsible for the phenol reaction phenotype of grains and hulls, which is a diagnostic characteristic differentiating two subspecies; the phenol reaction is negative in all <italic>japonica</italic> subspecies lines, but it is positive in nearly all <italic>indica</italic> and wild progenitor lines. Three independent origins of negative phenol-reaction mutations were clarified in <italic>japonica</italic> rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Yu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). In barley, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Takeda and Chang (1996)</xref> reported similar varietal differences in the phenol reaction of spikes and grains. Then they selected 51 (0.6%) phenol reaction-negative accessions from a screening of 8849 world collections. Phenol reaction-negative type is rare in barley, but is distributed in wide areas along the Silk Road, an ancient trade route, ranging from Spain through the Middle East to Korea. Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Takeda and Chang (1996)</xref> mapped the phenol reaction (<italic>Phr</italic>) gene to the long arm of barley chromosome 2H, molecular identity of the gene controlling the phenol reaction in awns remains unclarified.</p>
      <p>The objective of this study was to isolate barley <italic>PPO</italic> genes using wheat <italic>PPO</italic> sequence information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Himi and Noda, 2004</xref>) because of their connection with grain quality (Quinde-Axtell and Baik, 2006) and putative involvement in the phenol reaction phenotype. Molecular cloning of two linked <italic>PPO</italic> genes from barley is described. The second objective was to clarify the role of the duplicate <italic>PPO</italic> genes of barley in the phenol reaction in spikes and grains. For this purpose, comparative phylogenetic analyses among grass species and analysis of phenol-reaction-negative mutations were carried out.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Plant materials</title>
        <p>For initial PCR amplification of partial sequences of the barley <italic>PPO</italic> genes, three barley cultivars were used as a template DNA source: Haruna Nijo (abbreviated hereafter as HA2, phenol reaction positive), Kodoku Shirazu (code J239, phenol reaction positive), Shogor 3 (I677, phenol reaction negative). Fifty-one barley accessions of negative phenol reaction in awns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Takeda and Chang, 1996</xref>) were obtained from Research Institute for Bioresources, Okayama University, Japan and used for allelic diversity studies of <italic>PPO</italic> genes. For gene expression analyses, an isogenic line of the Bowman barley cultivar carrying the naked caryopsis gene (hereafter designated as <italic>nud</italic>-Bowman) was used. This line is phenol reaction positive. Representative phenol reaction-negative accessions were backcrossed with <italic>nud</italic>-Bowman, and near-isogenic lines (NILs) with regard to <italic>PPO1</italic> variant alleles were developed following one or two backcrosses (BC<sub>1</sub> or BC<sub>2</sub>). During backcrosses, plants that were homozygous for the recessive naked (<italic>nud</italic>) gene were selected using marker-assisted selection according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Taketa <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref>. The NILs with the <italic>nud</italic> gene allowed evaluation of PPO enzyme activity assay using whole naked caryopses because grains are easily separated from the hulls.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Cloning of barley <italic>PPO</italic> genes</title>
        <p>For the amplification of <italic>PPO</italic> homologues from barley, a pair of wheat <italic>PPO</italic> primers (deg1LP and degRP) were used; the primers were designed in the conserved copper binding domains based on the registered sequences of three seed-specific <italic>PPO</italic> genes from the respective wheat genomes (A1, AB254803.1; B1, AB254804.1; and D1, AB254805.1; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Himi and Noda, 2004</xref>). PCR-amplified bands were recovered individually from gels using a gel extraction kit (QIA quick; Qiagen Inc.) and cloned using a cloning <sc>K</sc>it (TOPO TA; Invitrogen Corporation). The bacterial artificial chromosome (BAC) library of HA2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Saisho <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) was screened for clones containing <italic>PPO</italic> genes using a high-density replica membrane and an ECL kit (GE Healthcare, Buckinghamshire, UK). The BAC DNA extraction and pulsed field gel electrophoresis (PFGE) was done according to standard protocols. Inverse PCR was performed to isolate entire genomic DNA sequences of the <italic>PPO</italic> genes according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Ochman <italic>et al.</italic> (1988)</xref>. PCR primer sequences are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq211/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online. The <italic>PPO</italic> sequences reported in this paper have been deposited in the EMBL/GenBank/DDBJ databases [accession no. AB549330 (<italic>PPO1</italic>) and AB549331 (<italic>PPO2</italic>)]. For genomic Southern hybridization, total DNA (10 &#x3BC;g) from HA2 was digested with <italic>Bgl</italic>II, <italic>Hin</italic>dIII, or <italic>Xho</italic>I, electrophoresed in 0.7% agarose gels, transferred to a positively charged nylon membrane, and hybridized with a digoxigenin (Roche)-labelled probe synthesized from a full-length cDNA clone of barley <italic>PPO1</italic>. Washing and immunological detection was performed following the manufacturer's instructions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Mapping</title>
        <p>DNA was isolated according to the standard SDS-phenol method. Wheat (cv. Chinese Spring)&#x2013;barley (cv. Betzes) disomic and ditelosomic chromosome addition lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Islam <italic>et al.</italic>, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Islam, 1983</xref>) were used for chromosome arm assignment of the <italic>PPO</italic> genes. For molecular mapping of the <italic>PPO</italic> genes, 111 F<sub>2</sub> plants derived from a cross between HA2 and Shogor 3 were used. An additional 171 F<sub>2</sub> plants from the same cross combination were examined only for <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> markers and the phenol reaction. Molecular markers for barley chromosome 2H reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> (1996)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Komatsuda <italic>et al.</italic> (1998)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Ramsay <italic>et al.</italic> (2000)</xref> were used.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Phenotyping for the phenol reaction</title>
        <p>For mapping, the phenol reaction was phenotyped in awns by staining with a 1% phenol solution because the reaction was sharpest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Takeda and Chang, 1996</xref>). In the NILs and their parental accessions, the phenol reaction of various tissues, such as awns, hulls, grains, and rachises, was tested at maturity. The phenol reaction of grains was evaluated by placing samples in a Petri dish on the filter paper moisted with a 1% phenol solution for 24 h.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>cDNA cloning and expression analysis</title>
        <p>Tissues for RNA extraction were collected from <italic>nud</italic>-Bowman plants grown in a growth cabinet with a constant temperature of 15 &#xB0;C and natural sunlight. Individual spikes were tagged daily to mark the flowering date, and total RNA was extracted from hulls (including palea and glume), caryopses, flag leaf, and awns, at 7 d intervals for 3 weeks starting from the date of flowering. For caryopses, endosperm parts were removed by pinching with fingers. Total RNA was isolated with the Isogen kit (Nippon Gene Co. Ltd). The DNase treatment of extracted RNA was made using RQ1 RNase-Free DNase (Promega Corporation). A first-strand cDNA was synthesized with SuperScript II RNase H<sup>&#x2013;</sup> Reverse Transcriptase (Invitrogen Corporation) using oligo-dT primer and 5 &#x3BC;g total RNA. For cDNA cloning, the first-strand cDNA was used as a template, and cDNA was amplified using PCR with gene-specific primer pairs and DNA polymerases [KOD-Plus (Toyobo Co. Ltd.) for <italic>PPO1</italic> and ExTaq (Takara Bio Inc.) for <italic>PPO2</italic>], according to the manufacturer's recommended protocol. The PCR products were recovered and cloned using the Zero Blunt TOPO PCR cloning Kit (Invitrogen Corp.) or TOPO TA Cloning Kit (Invitrogen Corporation). For gene expression analysis by RT-PCR, Ampli Taq Gold (ABI) was used for PCR amplification; the number of cycles was 30; barley actin was used as a control, as reported before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Taketa <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). The 3&#x2032; region of <italic>PPO</italic> cDNA was determined using the 3&#x2032;-RACE methods. PCR primers are summarized in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq211/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Phylogenetic analysis</title>
        <p>The deduced amino acid sequences for PPO1 and PPO2 in barley are compared with PPO proteins of wheat as well as those of four grass species having known genome sequences (rice, maize, sorghum, and <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>). For analysis, partial peptide sequences corresponding to motifs 1, 4, 10, 3, 7, and 2 were extracted and aligned using SALAD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Mihara <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Motifs used for tree construction were extracted from the following 19 sequences: barley (AB549330, AB549331), wheat (AB254803.1, AB254804.1, AB254805.1, EF070147.1, EF070148.1, EF070149.1, and EF070150.1), rice (LOC_Os04g53300 and LOC_Os01g58100), maize (EU956830.1 and EU963699.1), sorghum (Sb06g025570, Sb06g025580, Sb03g035850, Sb03g036870, and Sb10g024220), and <italic>B. distachyon</italic> (Bradi2g52260). The evolutionary history was inferred using the Neighbor&#x2013;Joining method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Saitou and Nei, 1987</xref>). The bootstrap consensus tree inferred from 500 replicates is taken to represent the evolutionary history of the taxa analysed, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Felsenstein (1985)</xref>. Branches corresponding to partitions reproduced in less than 50% bootstrap replicates are collapsed. The percentages of replicate trees in which the associated taxa clustered together in the bootstrap test (500 replicates) are shown next to the branches. The tree is drawn to scale, with branch length in the same units as those of the evolutionary distances used to infer the phylogenetic tree. The evolutionary distances were computed using the Poisson correction method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Zuckerkandl and Pauling, 1965</xref>) and are in the units of the number of amino acid substitutions per site. All positions containing gaps and missing data were eliminated from the dataset (Complete deletion option). In all, the final dataset included 194 positions. Phylogenetic analyses were conducted in MEGA4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Tamura <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Allelic diversity of <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> genes</title>
        <p>For sequencing of the <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> genes, 10 accessions (7 phenol reaction negative and 3 phenol reaction positive) were selected based on their geographical distribution and morphological characteristics. The sequenced accessions were I677, I750, K095, I341, U004, C2-60, C1-76, HA2, FI1 (Bowman), and J239, of which the last three are phenol reaction positive and the others are phenol reaction negative. For these 10 accessions, genomic sequences from the start codon to stop codon were determined for both <italic>PPO</italic> genes. The DNA sequence was determined using the ABI310 sequencer, and both strands were sequenced. Phylogenetic trees based on nucleotide sequences of <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> from start to stop codon were constructed using the Neighbor&#x2013;Joining method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Saitou and Nei, 1987</xref>). Based on DNA sequences of <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> alleles, polymorphic markers were developed. These markers allow genotyping of each allele specifically as CAPS or dCAPS markers. The primers and restriction enzymes used are summarized in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq211/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> at JXB online.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>PPO enzyme activity assay</title>
        <p>The PPO enzyme activity of whole grains in <italic>nud</italic>-Bowman and its NILs for five mutant <italic>PPO1</italic> alleles was measured according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Anderson and Morris (2001)</xref>. 3,4,-Dihydroxy-L-phenylalanine (L-DOPA) was used as a substrate; absorbance at 475 nm was recorded. Experiments were conducted in six replications and each replication contained five grains. Data were analysed statistically using <italic>t</italic> tests.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Molecular cloning and mapping of barley <italic>PPO</italic> homologues</title>
        <p>Using a wheat <italic>PPO</italic> primer pair, PCR amplified two bands in all three barley accessions that were tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). A stronger band of about 700 bp was designated as <italic>PPO1</italic>; a weaker band of about 800 bp was named <italic>PPO2</italic>. After cloning and sequencing, primer pairs that specifically amplify either <italic>PPO1</italic> or <italic>PPO2</italic> and detect polymorphisms by restriction enzyme digestion were designed. Mapping using wheat&#x2013;barley chromosome addition lines and molecular markers showed that both <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> were located on the long arm of chromosome 2H (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq211/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online) and that no recombination among <italic>PPO1</italic>, <italic>PPO2</italic>, and the phenol reaction phenotype were found in 111 F<sub>2</sub> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>). An additional 171 F<sub>2</sub> plants were tested, but no recombination was found among them. Consequently, in 282 F<sub>2</sub> plants, <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> co-segregated with <italic>Phr</italic>. It is therefore suggested that the phenol reaction of awns is likely to be controlled by either <italic>PPO1</italic> or <italic>PPO2</italic>.</p>
        <fig id="fig1" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Isolation of barley <italic>PPO</italic> homologues and their molecular mapping. (A) PCR amplicons of barley were amplified using a primer pair that was designed on the copper binding domains of wheat <italic>PPO</italic> genes. 100 bp ladder (M), template DNA of I677 (1), Haruna Nijo (HA2) (2), and J239 (3). Arrowheads and arrows, respectively, indicate 1000 bp and 500 bp. (B) A molecular map of <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> in 111 F<sub>2</sub> plants of the cross between HA2 and I677.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq211f01_ht"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Gene structure of <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> in barley</title>
        <p>To recover entire <italic>PPO</italic> sequences from barley, BAC clones containing the PCR-amplified <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> fragments were screened from the HA2 BAC library. No BAC clone carrying both <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> fragments was identified. One BAC clone each containing either <italic>PPO1</italic> (clone name HNB164B24) or <italic>PPO2</italic> (HNB630O21) was selected and analysed in detail. The BAC clones differed considerably in PFGE patterns after digestion with three eight-base cutters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). The insert sizes of <italic>PPO1</italic>-containing and <italic>PPO2</italic>-containing BAC clones were estimated, respectively, as about 110 kb and 120 kb. Using primer pairs designed based on BAC-end sequences of the respective clones, PCR showed that the <italic>PPO1</italic>-containing and <italic>PPO2</italic>-containing BAC clones did not mutually overlap (data not shown). These observations indicate that <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> genes are physically separated on the 2HL.</p>
        <fig id="fig2" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Analysis of barley BAC clones containing either the <italic>PPO1</italic> or the <italic>PPO2</italic> gene. (A) After digestion with eight-base cutters, BAC DNA was separated by pulsed-field gel electrophoresis. (B) BAC DNA containing the <italic>PPO1</italic> gene was digested with various six-base cutters and separated using electrophoresis on a 1% agarose gel (left). Southern blot was probed with the <italic>PPO1</italic> fragment (right). M1: DNA molecular weight marker III (Roche). M2: &#x3BB; <italic>Hin</italic>dIII digest.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq211f02_ht"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To select restriction enzymes suitable for cloning of the full-length <italic>PPO</italic> genes by inverse PCR, BAC DNA was digested using various six-base cutters and analysed using Southern hybridization. Actually, <italic>Kpn</italic>I was selected for <italic>PPO1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>), and <italic>Xho</italic>I was selected for <italic>PPO2</italic> (data not shown) because these enzymes showed a single band in BAC DNA Southern hybridization using respective <italic>PPO</italic> gene fragments as a probe. In the case of <italic>PPO1</italic>, clones with the expected 6 kb insert size were selected using colony PCR. Unfortunately, sequencing to the direction of 3&#x2032;-UTR region revealed a precocious <italic>Kpn</italic>I site. Thus, the 3&#x2032;-UTR region of the <italic>PPO1</italic> gene is not fully recovered in the clones obtained using inverse PCR. To recover the entire <italic>PPO1</italic> coding sequence, 3&#x2032;-RACE was performed. The 3&#x2032;-UTR of the <italic>PPO1</italic> was 162 bp long; a typical polyadenylation signal (AATAAA) was found. In <italic>PPO2</italic>, the expected 4.5 kb insert size was recovered. The 4.5 kb clones covered the entire <italic>PPO2</italic> gene; 3&#x2032;-RACE showed that the length of the 3&#x2032;-UTR was 177 bp without a canonical polyadenylation signal. About 3.6 kb of the sequence upstream from the <italic>PPO2</italic> translation start codon was also obtained by &#x2018;walking&#x2019; along the BAC clone. Genomic Southern hybridization using a full-length cDNA clone of <italic>PPO1</italic> as a probe detected two bands for <italic>Bgl</italic>II or <italic>Hin</italic>dIII digest and three bands for <italic>Xho</italic>I digest (data not shown), confirming the presence of at least two <italic>PPO</italic> genes in the barley genome.</p>
        <p>To know the intron&#x2013;exon structure, genomic sequences and cDNA sequences were compared. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref> shows the gene structure of <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic>. Both <italic>PPO</italic> genes harbour two introns, one within the CuA domain and the other between CuA and CuB. The <italic>PPO1</italic> gene is 1946 bp long and has two introns of 96 bp and 122 bp. The <italic>PPO2</italic> gene is 2026 bp long and has two introns of 205 bp and 90 bp. The thylakoid translocation domain and two copper binding domains are highly conserved in both genes (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq211/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). Predicted amino acid lengths are 575 aa for PPO1 and 576 aa for PPO2. Apparently, PPO1 and PPO2 encode 64.1 kDa and 62.8 kDa precursor proteins, respectively, and those are processed into mature PPO of 55.8 kDa and 54.0 kDa after removal of the amino-terminal signal polypeptide. The sequence identity between <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> was 82% at the nucleotide level and 73% at the amino acid level. Similar gene structure and high sequence identity suggest that <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> are duplicate genes.</p>
        <fig id="fig3" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Structure of the <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> genes in barley. Boxes show exons; the black bar between the boxes shows introns. Blue arrows indicate critical mutation sites that were detected in phenol reaction-negative accessions (types I&#x2013;V). The asterisk denotes a stop codon and F.S. signifies a frame shift. In the proximity of the promoter region of the <italic>PPO2</italic> gene, an insertion of a hAT-family transposon was found.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq211f03_3c"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Phylogenetic analysis of PPO in grasses</title>
        <p>Phylogenetic analysis was performed based on predicted amino acid sequences of the <italic>PPO</italic> genes from six grass species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Two barley PPO protein sequences from cultivar HA2 (HvPPO1 and HvPPO2) were compared with the deduced PPO amino acid sequences of five other species (wheat, rice, maize, sorghum, and <italic>B. distachyon</italic>) that were selected through a database search. Based on motif analysis using the SALAD database, only PPO peptide sequences with a common central domain of tyrosinase (Pfam00264) were selected and used for analyses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Accession numbers or unigene names of each abbreviation are described in the legends of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>. Of the four rice <italic>PPO</italic> genes reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Yu <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref>, only two genes that were mapped onto rice chromosome 1 and 4 [Os01PPO (LOC_Os01g58100) and Os04PPO (LOC_Os04g53300)] were included in the analysis: two other PPOs on rice chromosome 4 are truncated C-terminally because of a premature stop codon. They are considered non-functional. Two barley PPO proteins (HvPPO1 and HvPPO2, both on barley 2HL) were closely related to wheat PPOs on 2AL, 2BL, and 2DL, forming a clade supported with intermediate bootstrap values. Barley PPOs were clustered in the same major clade (labelled with group A), which includes the rice chromosome 4 PPO (Os04PPO). Another rice chromosome 1 PPO (Os01PPO) formed a different major clade (group B) including no barley or wheat clone. These phylogenetic data validate that the two barley <italic>PPO</italic> homologues isolated in this study represent true <italic>PPO</italic> genes with a conserved domain of tyrosinase. The two linked HvPPO1 and HvPPO2 in barley are likely to have been derived by duplication. Two sorghum PPOs (Sb06PPO1 and Sb06PPO2) that are linked on chromosome 6 are sister to the barley and wheat clade. It remains unknown whether <italic>PPO</italic> gene duplication in barley (chromosome 2H) and sorghum (chromosome 6) on syntenic chromosomes have a common origin or not.</p>
        <fig id="fig4" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Phylogenetic analysis of PPO proteins in six grass species. SALAD analysis selected the following 19 sequences for tree construction. Sequences are represented by the following abbreviations (accession numbers/unigene names and chromosome location are in parentheses): barley HvPPO1 (AB549330, chr. 2HL), HvPPO2 (AB549331, chr. 2HL); wheat TaSSPPO-A1 (AB254803.1, chr. 2AL), TaSSPPO-B1 (AB254804.1, chr. 2BL), TaSSPPO-D1 (AB254805.1, chr. 2DL), TaPpo-A1a (EF070147.1, chr. 2AL), TaPpo-A1b (EF070148.1, chr. 2AL), TaPpo-D1a (EF070149.1, chr. 2DL), TaPpo-D1b (EF070150.1, chr. 2DL); rice Os04PPO (LOC_Os04g53300, chr. 4), Os01PPO (LOC_Os01g58100, chr. 1); maize ZmPPO1 (EU956830.1, chr. 9), ZmPPO2 (EU963699.1, chr. 10); sorghum Sb06PPO1 (Sb06g025570, chr. 6), Sb06PPO2 (Sb06g025580, chr. 6), Sb03PPO1 (Sb03g035850, chr. 3), Sb03PPO2 (Sb03g036870, chr. 3), Sb10PPO (Sb10g024220, chr. 10), and <italic>B. distachyon</italic> Bd2PPO (Bradi2g52260, chr. 2). (A) Phylogenetic tree. Amino acids of the central tyrosinase domain (Pfam00264) were compared and the tree was constructed using the Neighbor&#x2013;Joining method. Numbers indicate bootstrap values. PPO proteins were classified into two major groups labelled with group A and group B. (B) Motif analysis by SALAD database.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq211f04_3c"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Allelic diversity of <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> genes</title>
        <p>To know which of <italic>PPO1</italic> or <italic>PPO2</italic> is responsible for the phenol reaction phenotype in awns, seven phenol reaction-negative (I677, I750, K095, I341, U004, C2-60, and C1-76) and three phenol reaction-positive (HA2, FI1, and J239) accessions of diverse geographic origin were sequenced for both <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> genes. Seven alleles in <italic>PPO1</italic> and four alleles in <italic>PPO2</italic> were found (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq211/DC1">Supplementary Tables S2</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq211/DC1">S3</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). In <italic>PPO1</italic>, HA2 and FI1 (both phenol reaction positive) had an identical sequence, and another phenol reaction-positive accession, J239, had a sequence identical to those of two phenol reaction-negative accessions (C2-60 or C1-76). However, the remaining five phenol reaction-negative accessions had nucleotide changes that are predicted to cause an amino acid substitution(s) or premature stop codon affecting functionally important motifs compared with that of the standard accession HA2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). In fact, I341 (type I) had a single amino acid substitution within the thylakoid translocation domain. Also, U004 (type II), I677 (type III), and K095 (type V) had a premature stop codon at amino acid positions 161, 248, and 528, respectively; I750 (type IV) had a single amino acid substitution within a copper binding domain (CuB). Types I&#x2013;IV are estimated to affect either or both of the copper binding domains of the <italic>PPO1</italic> gene, whereas type V had a truncated carboxyl terminus. Some PPO studies of grape have shown that the C-terminal extension must be removed for activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Dry and Robinson, 1994</xref>); thereby, type V barley is likely to be affected in PPO activity. On the other hand, in <italic>PPO2</italic>, predicted amino acid sequences of three types were found, but only one type was specifically found in the phenol reaction-negative accessions tested. Compared with the standard accession HA2, I677 had an 8 bp insertion in the first exon, causing a frame shift and a premature stop codon at amino acid position 147. The 8 bp insertion in <italic>PPO2</italic> was found in three out of 51 phenol reaction-negative accessions. A single amino acid deletion of the 125th alanine (A) as a result of an in-frame 3 bp deletion in the first exon was found both in phenol reaction-negative accessions (I750, K095, C2-60, and C1-76) and in a phenol reaction-positive accession (J239), suggesting that the missing amino acid residue 125A is dispensable for PPO2 function. Available results indicate that <italic>PPO1</italic>, rather than <italic>PPO2</italic>, controls the phenol reaction in awns.</p>
        <p>Neighbor&#x2013;Joining trees were constructed based on <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> nucleotide sequences including both exons and introns in 10 accessions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). In <italic>PPO1</italic>, five phenol reaction-negative accessions (types I&#x2013;V) occupied unique positions separated from the three phenol reaction-positive accessions. In the <italic>PPO2</italic> gene, ambiguous separation of phenol reaction-positive and reaction-negative accessions was observed, which also supports the conclusion that <italic>PPO1</italic> is the major determinant of the phenol reaction in awns. Although I677 (a type III Pakistani accession) and U004 (a type II Spanish accession) share the short-haired rachilla trait in common, they are distantly related.</p>
        <fig id="fig5" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 5.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Phylogenetic relations of <italic>PPO</italic> genes in 10 barley accessions differing in phenol reaction. Unrooted genetic distance trees are generated using the Neighbor&#x2013;Joining method based on <italic>PPO</italic> genomic sequences: (A) <italic>PPO1</italic> gene, (B) <italic>PPO2</italic> gene. Underlined accessions are phenol reaction positive and others are phenol reaction negative.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq211f05_lw"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The PCR primers that specifically distinguish mutant alleles in the <italic>PPO1</italic> locus were designed; all 51 phenol reaction-negative accessions were genotyped. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref> portrays the geographical distribution of mutant <italic>PPO1</italic> genes that were found in domesticated barley accessions with a negative phenol-reaction of awns. Of 51, 40 accessions were classified into one of the five non-functional types found by sequencing. However, the remaining 11 accessions were indistinguishable from phenol reaction-positive accessions by marker analyses and are classified as others. These unclassified accessions, which were collected in India, China, and Nepal, require further sequencing in the promoter region. Type IV was most prevalent and was distributed in wide areas ranging from Turkey, Iran, and Afghanistan, to Xinjiang. This distribution pattern indicates that type IV was disseminated by human activities along the Silk Road. Types I and III were locally distributed in Pakistan; type I accessions are all naked caryopsis (<italic>nud</italic>), and type III accessions all have short rachilla hair (<italic>srh</italic>). Type II was only found in Spain and this type carried short rachilla hair (<italic>srh</italic>). Type V was found only in Korea. These results show that loss-of-function mutations of the <italic>PPO1</italic> gene occurred independently as barley spread from the two centres of origin, namely the Near East and southern areas of Central Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Morrell and Clegg, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Saisho and Purugganan, 2007</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig6" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 6.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Geographical distribution of five non-functional <italic>PPO1</italic> mutant alleles that were found in 51 phenol reaction-negative barley accessions. Roman numerals (I&#x2013;IV) indicate PPO1 amino acid variants. Number inside or beside the circle shows the number of accessions. The group of 11 phenol reaction-negative accessions that could not be differentiated from the phenol reaction-positive accessions is shown as others in the lower right.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq211f06_3c"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Expression analysis</title>
        <p>Results show that <italic>PPO1</italic> is most strongly expressed in awns followed by in hulls, but <italic>PPO2</italic> is weakly expressed in caryopses; expression of <italic>PPO1</italic> in awns and hulls peaked at 2&#x2013;3 weeks after flowering, but the peak of <italic>PPO2</italic> expression in caryopses occurred at 2 weeks after flowering (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>). This expression pattern coincides with the present conclusion&#x2013;&#x2013;based on allele diversity analysis&#x2013;&#x2013;that <italic>PPO1</italic> is responsible for the phenol reaction of awns. In the proximity of the <italic>PPO2</italic> promoter region, an insertion of a hAT-family transposon was found (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). Such a transposon insertion might be responsible for the differential expression patterns of <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> genes.</p>
        <fig id="fig7" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 7.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>RT-PCR analysis of <italic>PPO</italic> gene expression. Numbers represent weeks after flowering: g, genomic DNA control. Markers (M) are 100 bp ladder, and arrowheads and arrows, respectively, indicate 1000 bp and 500 bp.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq211f07_ht"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The phenol reaction of the representative phenol reaction-negative barley accessions and NILs were tested. The results showed that <italic>PPO1</italic> mutants are not stained in awns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8A</xref>), grains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8B</xref>), hulls or rachises, although these tissues are strongly stained in the phenol reaction-positive control. It is particularly interesting that a closer examination of grains revealed that the <italic>PPO1PPO2</italic> double mutant (type III) showed no staining in the crease on the ventral side of grains, although other <italic>PPO1</italic> single mutants and the control show strong coloration in the crease (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8B</xref>). This phenol reaction pattern suggests that <italic>PPO2</italic> expression is localized to the crease of grains, whereas <italic>PPO1</italic> appears to govern the phenol reaction of overall spike tissues including awns, hulls (lemma and palea), rachises, and caryopsis surface except for the crease on the ventral side.</p>
        <fig id="fig8" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 8.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Phenol staining of awns (A) and grains (B) after 24 h in 1% phenol solution. In (A), c is Haruna Nijo and I&#x2013;V are phenol reaction-negative accessions: I, I341; II, U004; III, I677; IV, I750; V, K095. In (B), c is <italic>nud</italic>-Bowman, and naked caryopses from near-isogenic lines in the genetic background of <italic>nud</italic>-Bowman were tested. The <italic>PPO1</italic> allele types of respective lines are shown above. Bar is 0.5 cm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq211f08_3c"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The PPO activity assay in whole grains showed that NILs of the five <italic>PPO</italic> mutant alleles had a reduced level of PPO activity compared with the control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>). The NIL of the <italic>PPO1PPO2</italic> double mutant (III) had a PPO activity similar to the NILs of the <italic>PPO1</italic> single mutant lines (I, II, IV, and V).</p>
        <fig id="fig9" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 9.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>PPO activities of grains of near-isogenic lines assayed using the whole grain method: C, <italic>nud</italic>-Bowman; I&#x2013;V, near-isogenic lines for <italic>PPO1</italic> mutant alleles&#x2013;&#x2013;III is a double mutant for <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic>. Asterisks (**) indicate that activity was significantly different (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01) from the control (C) according to the <italic>t</italic> test. Bars represent standard deviations (<italic>n</italic>=6).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq211f09_ht"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Allele diversity of <italic>PPO</italic> genes, and phenol reaction phenotypes in barley</title>
        <p>In this study, duplicate barley <italic>PPO</italic> genes that are closely linked on the long arm of chromosome 2H were isolated. Both <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> co-segregated with <italic>Phr</italic> controlling the phenol reaction of the awns. Allele variation in <italic>PPO1</italic> was closely associated with the phenol reaction of the awns: in 40 (78.4%) out of 51 barley accessions having negative phenol reaction of awns, five amino acid variants affecting functionally relevant motif(s) or C-terminal region(s) were found. Such a strong association was not found for <italic>PPO2</italic>. Thus, the available results indicated that <italic>PPO1</italic>, rather than <italic>PPO2</italic>, is the major determinant controlling the phenol reaction of awns. <italic>PPO1</italic> also appears to control the phenol reaction of hulls, caryopses, and rachises because these parts were stained in normal barley but were not stained in <italic>PPO1</italic> single mutants. In the <italic>PPO1PPO2</italic> double mutant, staining of the crease on the ventral side of caryopses was absent. This indicates that <italic>PPO2</italic> controls the phenol reaction of the crease of caryopses. Subsequent RT-PCR experiments revealed that <italic>PPO1</italic> is expressed in awns and hulls, and that <italic>PPO2</italic> was weakly expressed only in caryopses among the tissues tested. Consequently, the observed pattern of phenol staining of caryopses is slightly contradictory to the gene expression pattern. This contradiction might be explained by assuming that <italic>PPO1</italic> is also weakly expressed in caryopses under the detection limit by RT-PCR and that <italic>PPO2</italic> is expressed specifically in the crease of the ventral side of caryopses.</p>
        <p>The present study revealed that two genes (<italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic>) are responsible for the phenol reaction phenotypes in barley. This is in sharp contrast to the case in rice, where <italic>Phr1</italic> on syntenic rice chromosome 4 is the sole <italic>PPO</italic> gene controlling the phenol reaction in hulls and grains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Yu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>PPO</italic> in grasses</title>
        <p>The phylogenetic tree shows that, in the grass family, two groups of <italic>PPO</italic> genes exist (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). The two barley <italic>PPO</italic> genes on 2HL isolated here were included in the first group (group A in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>) together with wheat <italic>PPO</italic> genes on homoeologous group 2 chromosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Himi and Noda, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">He <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) and rice chromosome 4 <italic>PPO</italic> gene (<italic>Phr1</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Yu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Triticeae group 2 chromosomes and rice chromosome 4 are known to be syntenic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Devos and Gale, 2000</xref>), and therefore an orthologous relationship is suggested. Another active <italic>PPO</italic> gene on rice chromosome 1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Yu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) was included in the second group (group B). Presumably the rice chromosome 1 <italic>PPO</italic> gene is functionally differentiated from the rice chromosome 4 <italic>PPO</italic> gene because the former is predominantly expressed in vegetative organs such as the leaf blade and leaf sheath; the latter is strongly expressed in panicles (Y Nagamura <italic>et al.</italic>, personal communication). Based on phylogenetic analysis of partial <italic>PPO</italic> sequences of wheat, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Jukanti <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> classified wheat <italic>PPO</italic> genes into two groups: one group is expressed in seeds; the other group is expressed in vegetative organs. However, this classification is not fully confirmed because of the absence of full-length cDNA sequences and unknown chromosome assignment of the latter group. Using maize <italic>PPO</italic> gene as a probe, Southern hybridization detected <italic>PPO</italic> genes on a minimum of five chromosomes in wheat&#x2013;&#x2013;5B, 7D, 6A, 6B, and 6D (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). Quantitative trait loci for PPO activity were detected on wheat chromosomes 2A, 2B, 3B, 3D, and 6B (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Demeke <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). A syntenic relationship of wheat homoeologous group 3 chromosomes and rice chromosome 1 was reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Devos and Gale, 2000</xref>). To obtain the whole picture of <italic>PPO</italic> genes in barley and wheat, identification of full-length <italic>PPO</italic> genes that are preferentially expressed in vegetative tissues is necessary.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Gene duplication and functional differentiation in barley PPOs</title>
        <p>In many plant species, PPOs are encoded by a multigene family. In tomato, a seven-member gene family is clustered within a 165 kb locus on chromosome 8. They are differentially expressed in different stages and tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Newman <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Thipyapong <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). In red clover, six PPOs are clustered over an approximately 510 kb region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Winters <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). In rice, two pseudogenes are clustered in the vicinity of an active <italic>PPO</italic> gene (<italic>Phr1</italic>) on chromosome 4, and another <italic>PPO</italic>-like gene is present on chromosome 1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Yu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). The <italic>PPO</italic> genes that control the phenol reaction phenotypes in barley are similarly clustered as described above. The <italic>PPO</italic> gene family appears to have been generated through the duplication of an ancestral single-copy gene by unequal crossing over or other mechanisms. Results of the present expression analysis suggest functional differentiation between <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> in barley. Functional diversification of duplicate <italic>PPO</italic> genes in barley might be mediated by an insertion of a hAT-family transposon in the proximity of the <italic>PPO2</italic> promoter because the transposon insertion in the promoter region was reported to modulate gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Hayashi and Yoshida, 2009</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Origin of <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> mutant alleles in barley</title>
        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Takeda and Chang (1996)</xref> proposed a monophyletic origin for the phenol reaction-negative accessions in barley based on a very low frequency of occurrence (0.6%) and restricted distribution along the Silk Road. However, the present molecular characterization of the <italic>PPO1</italic> gene demonstrated multiple independent origins of phenol reaction-negative mutations in barley. In barley, five types of non-functional <italic>PPO1</italic> alleles were detected. They were distributed in different regions of the world with clear localization. The fact that the most prevalent <italic>PPO1</italic> type-IV allele distributed along the Silk Road indicates that domesticated barley was transported eastward through this trade route by human activities. The low frequency of mutant accessions probably reflects their recent origin. Multiple independent origins of phenol reaction-negative accessions were also observed in rice, but their frequency was much higher because all <italic>japonica</italic> subspecies carries one of the three types of loss-of-function alleles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Yu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Fixation of dysfunctional <italic>PPO</italic> genes in <italic>japonica</italic> rice was probably caused by positive selection for reduced browning of grains during storage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Yu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Plant PPOs are reportedly associated with disease resistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Thipyapong <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Li and Steffens, 2002</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Yu <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> argued that the retention of phenol reaction activity in <italic>indica</italic> rice, in contrast to its ubiquitous loss in <italic>japonica</italic>, is as follows: <italic>Phr1</italic> activities are necessary for <italic>indica</italic> rice to maintain disease resistance in warmer climates. The independent occurrence of five non-functional <italic>PPO1</italic> alleles in different regions of barley cultivation might indicate that such mutants do not pose serious problems in maintaining disease resistance in the case of barley, which grows in temperate climates.</p>
        <p>The <italic>PPO2</italic> gene is also of particular evolutionary interest, although the magnitude of its genetic diversity is lower than that of the <italic>PPO1</italic> gene and a weaker contribution to the phenol-reaction phenotype in the ventral side of the crease was observed. However, a unique hAT family transposon insertion in the proximity of the promoter sequence makes this gene an attractive model for duplicate gene evolution.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title><italic>PPO</italic> mutants in barley research</title>
        <p>In rice, PPO activity of phenol reaction-negative accessions was almost completely lost (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Yu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), but barley <italic>PPO</italic> mutants&#x2013;&#x2013;either single <italic>PPO1</italic> mutants or a <italic>PPO1PPO2</italic> double mutant&#x2013;&#x2013;retained about half the PPO activity of the normal control. This difference in the level of residual PPO activity in <italic>PPO</italic> mutants between rice and barley might be explained as follows. Polyphenol content in barley grains is about twice that in rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Hodzic <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Therefore, auto-oxidation of phenolic compounds might occur rapidly in barley and preclude accurate PPO activity measurements. Alternatively, oxidation might be mediated by non-PPO oxidase enzymes such as dioxygenases or mono-oxygenases (cytochrome P450). Another possibility is that an unidentified <italic>PPO</italic> gene(s) might still be present in the barley genome because genomic Southern analysis suggests the possible occurrence of a third PPO in barley. Such a PPO might have diverged sequences and could have escaped the PCR-oriented cloning approach. It is not certain whether manipulation of the <italic>PPO</italic> genes might be effective in reducing the discoloration of barley products. However, allele variants of <italic>PPO1</italic> and <italic>PPO2</italic> identified in this study should be useful to test the relation of <italic>PPO</italic>s to disease resistance in barley.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Supplementary data</title>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq211/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link> are available at <italic>JXB</italic> online.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq211/DC1"><bold>Figure S1.</bold></ext-link> Chromosome assignment of the <italic>PPO1</italic> gene using wheat&#x2013;barley disomic and ditelosomic chromosome addition lines. PCR primers of Hvdeg1LP1 and degRP21 were used for amplification. Barley chromosomes added to wheat are indicated above the lane. M: 100-bp ladder, W: wheat cv. Chinese Spring, B: barley cv. Betzes. An arrow indicates 500 bp.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq211/DC1"><bold>Figure S2.</bold></ext-link> Alignment of two barley PPO protein sequences of Haruna Nijo. Copper binding domains and a putative thylakoid translocation signal sequence are highlighted respectively in red and green. An arrow indicates the predicted cleavage site of N-terminal signal peptide, and triangles show the intron positions.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq211/DC1"><bold>Table S1.</bold></ext-link> PCR primers used in this experiment.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq211/DC1"><bold>Table S2.</bold></ext-link> Natural allelic variation in the <italic>PPO1</italic> gene using Haruna Nijo (HA2) as a standard.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq211/DC1"><bold>Table S3.</bold></ext-link> Natural allelic variation in the <italic>PPO2</italic> gene using Haruna Nijo (HA2) as a standard.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Data</title>
        </caption>
        <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_61_14_3983__index.html"/>
        <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_erq211_00047365-file001.pdf"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors are grateful to Dr N Kohyama for useful advice related to PPO chemistry, Dr Y Nagamura for providing rice <italic>PPO</italic> expression data, and to Ms Y Yamashita and Ms T Kojima for technical assistance. Dr M Ichii gave much-appreciated encouragement. The resources were provided by the National Bioresource Project&#x2014;Barley, Japan. This work was supported in part by grants from NIAS genebank project and the Ohara Foundation for Agricultural Research.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>JV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morris</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An improved whole-seed assay for screening of wheat germplasm for polyphenol oxidase activity</article-title>
          <source>Crop Science</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>1697</fpage>
          <lpage>1705</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fuerst</surname>
              <given-names>EP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hurkman</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vensel</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morris</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Biochemical and genetic characterization of wheat (<italic>Triticum</italic> spp.) kernel polyphenol oxidases</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Cereal Science</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>353</fpage>
          <lpage>367</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boss</surname>
              <given-names>PK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gardner</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Janssen</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ross</surname>
              <given-names>GS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An apple polyphenol oxidase cDNA is up-regulated in wounded tissues</article-title>
          <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>429</fpage>
          <lpage>433</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7888632</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cary</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lax</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Flurkey</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cloning and characterization of cDNAs coding for <italic>Vicia faba</italic> polyphenol oxidase</article-title>
          <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>245</fpage>
          <lpage>253</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1391768</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Constabel</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yip</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patton</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Christopher</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Polyphenol oxidase from hybrid poplar. Cloning and expression in response to wounding and herbivory</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>124</volume>
          <fpage>285</fpage>
          <lpage>295</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10982443</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Demeke</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morris</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular characterization of wheat polyphenol oxidase (PPO)</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>104</volume>
          <fpage>813</fpage>
          <lpage>818</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12582641</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Demeke</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morris</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campbell</surname>
              <given-names>KG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>GE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>H-G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wheat polyphenol oxidase: distribution and genetic mapping in three inbred line populations</article-title>
          <source>Crop Science</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>1750</fpage>
          <lpage>1757</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Devos</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gale</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genome relationships: the grass model in current research</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>637</fpage>
          <lpage>646</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10810140</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dexter</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Preston</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsuo</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tipples</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of a high extraction flour for the GRL Pilot Mill to evaluate Canadian wheat potential for the Chinese market</article-title>
          <source>Canadian Institute of Food Science and Technology Journal</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>253</fpage>
          <lpage>259</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dry</surname>
              <given-names>IB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular cloning and characterization of grape berry polyphenol oxidase</article-title>
          <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>495</fpage>
          <lpage>502</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7948897</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Felsenstein</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Confidence limits on phylogenies: an approach using the bootstrap</article-title>
          <source>Evolution</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>783</fpage>
          <lpage>791</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fuerst</surname>
              <given-names>EP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>JV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morris</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Delineating the role of polyphenol oxidase in the darkening of alkaline wheat noodles</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>2378</fpage>
          <lpage>2384</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16536622</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hayashi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoshida</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Refunctionalization of the ancient rice blast disease resistance gene <italic>Pit</italic> by the recruitment of a retrotransposon as a promoter</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Journal</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>413</fpage>
          <lpage>425</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18808453</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>ZH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>LP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morris</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fuerst</surname>
              <given-names>EP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>XC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Allelic variation of polyphenol oxidase (PPO) located on chromosome 2A and 2D and development of functional markers for the PPO genes in common wheat</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>115</volume>
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          <lpage>58</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17426955</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Himi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Noda</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Structural variation of <italic>SSPPO</italic> genes related to flour color in A-, B-, and D-genome of wheat</article-title>
          <source>Breeding Research</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>Supplement 2</issue>
          <fpage>119</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hodzic</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pasalic</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Memisevic</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sraboric</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saletovic</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poljakovic</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The influence of total phenols content on antioxidant capacity in the whole grain extracts</article-title>
          <source>European Journal of Scientific Research</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>471</fpage>
          <lpage>477</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hunt</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eannetta</surname>
              <given-names>NT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Newman</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steffens</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>cDNA cloning and expression of potato polyphenol oxidase</article-title>
          <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>59</fpage>
          <lpage>68</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7678763</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Islam</surname>
              <given-names>AKMR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Sakamoto</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ditelosomic additions of barley chromosomes to wheat</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 6th International Wheat Genetics Symposium</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <publisher-loc>Kyoto</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Maruzen</publisher-name>
          <fpage>233</fpage>
          <lpage>238</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Islam</surname>
              <given-names>AKMR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shepherd</surname>
              <given-names>KW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sparrow</surname>
              <given-names>DHB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isolation and characterization of euplasmic wheat-barley chromosome addition lines</article-title>
          <source>Heredity</source>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>161</fpage>
          <lpage>174</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jukanti</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bruckner</surname>
              <given-names>PL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fischer</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of wheat polyphenol oxidase genes</article-title>
          <source>Cereal Chemistry</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <fpage>481</fpage>
          <lpage>485</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Komatsuda</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakamura</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takaiwa</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oka</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of STS markers closely linked to the vrs1 locus in barley, <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic></article-title>
          <source>Genome</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>680</fpage>
          <lpage>685</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Constanzo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jia</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Olsen</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caicedo</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evolutionary dynamics of the genomic region around the blast resistance gene <italic>Pi-ta</italic> in AA genome <italic>Oryza</italic> species</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>183</volume>
          <fpage>1315</fpage>
          <lpage>1325</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19822730</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steffens</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Overexpression of polyphenol oxidase in transgenic tomato plants results in enhanced bacterial disease resistance</article-title>
          <source>Planta</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>215</volume>
          <fpage>239</fpage>
          <lpage>247</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12029473</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>WL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Faris</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chittoor</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leach</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hulbert</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genomic mapping of defence response genes in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <fpage>226</fpage>
          <lpage>233</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Z-W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Biyashev</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saghai Maroof</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of simple sequence repeat DNA markers and their integration into a barley linkage map</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>869</fpage>
          <lpage>876</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marusek</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trobaugh</surname>
              <given-names>NM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Flurkey</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inlow</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparative analysis of polyphenol oxidase from plant and fungal species</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Inorganic Biochemistry</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <fpage>108</fpage>
          <lpage>123</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16332393</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Massa</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beecher</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morris</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Polyphenol oxidase (PPO) in wheat and wild relatives: molecular evidence for a multigene family</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <fpage>1239</fpage>
          <lpage>1247</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17468807</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mayer</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Polyphenol oxidases in plant and fungi: Going places? A review</article-title>
          <source>Phytochemistry</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>2318</fpage>
          <lpage>2331</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16973188</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib29">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mihara</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Itoh</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Izawa</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>SALAD database: a motif-based database of protein annotations for plant comparative genomics</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <comment>Database issue D835&#x2013;D842</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib30">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Morrell</surname>
              <given-names>PL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clegg</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic evidence for a second domestication of barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>) east of the Fertile Crescent</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>104</volume>
          <fpage>3289</fpage>
          <lpage>3294</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib31">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Newman</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eannetta</surname>
              <given-names>NT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prince</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Vicente</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanksley</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steffens</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Organization of the tomato polyphenol oxidase gene family</article-title>
          <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>1035</fpage>
          <lpage>1051</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8098228</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib32">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ochman</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gerber</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hartl</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic applications of an inverse polymerase chain reaction</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <fpage>621</fpage>
          <lpage>625</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2852134</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib33">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Quinde-Axtell</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baik</surname>
              <given-names>B-K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phenolic compounds of barley grain and their implication in food product deicoloration</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>9978</fpage>
          <lpage>9984</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17177530</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib34">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Raman</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raman</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnstone</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lisle</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic and <italic>in silico</italic> comparative mapping of the polyphenol oxidase gene in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>
          <source>Functional and Integrative Genomics</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>185</fpage>
          <lpage>200</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15918034</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib35">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ramsay</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Macaulay</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>degli Ivanissevich</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A simple sequence repeat-based linkage map of barley</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>156</volume>
          <fpage>1997</fpage>
          <lpage>2005</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11102390</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib36">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saisho</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Purugganan</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular phylogeography of domesticated barley traces expansion of agriculture in the Old World</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>177</volume>
          <fpage>1765</fpage>
          <lpage>1776</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17947416</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib37">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saisho</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Myoraku</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kawasaki</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sato</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takeda</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Construction and characterization of a bacterial artificial chromosome (BAC) library from the Japanese malting barley &#x2018;Haruna Nijo&#x2019;</article-title>
          <source>Breeding Science</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>29</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib38">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saitou</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nei</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Neighbor&#x2013;Joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>406</fpage>
          <lpage>425</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3447015</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib39">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shahar</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henning</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gutfinger</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hareven</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lifschitz</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The tomato 66.3-kDa polyphenol oxidase gene: molecular identification and developmental expression</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Cell</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>147</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1633491</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib40">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Simeone</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pasqualone</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clodoveo</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blanco</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic mapping of polyphenol oxidase in tetraploid wheat</article-title>
          <source>Cellular and Molecular Biology Letters</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>763</fpage>
          <lpage>769</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12378236</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib41">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sullivan</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hatfield</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thoma</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Samac</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cloning and characterization of red clover polyphenol oxidase cDNAs and expression of active protein in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and transgenic alfalfa</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>136</volume>
          <fpage>3234</fpage>
          <lpage>3244</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466227</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib42">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Takeda</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Inheritance and geographical distribution of phenol reaction-less varieties of barley</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <fpage>217</fpage>
          <lpage>221</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib43">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Taketa</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amano</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsujino</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Barley grain with adhering hulls is controlled by an ERF family transcription factor gene regulating a lipid biosynthesis pathway</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>105</volume>
          <fpage>4062</fpage>
          <lpage>4067</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib44">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tamura</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dudley</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nei</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software ver. 4.0</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>1596</fpage>
          <lpage>1599</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488738</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib45">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thipyapong</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hunt</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steffens</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Systemic wound induction of potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic>) polyphenol oxidiase</article-title>
          <source>Phytochemistry</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>673</fpage>
          <lpage>676</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib46">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thipyapong</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Joel</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steffens</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differential expression and turnover of the tomato polyphenol oxidase gene family during vegetative and reproductive development</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <fpage>707</fpage>
          <lpage>718</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12223637</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib47">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>van Gelder</surname>
              <given-names>CWG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Flurkey</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wichers</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sequence and structural features of plant and fungal tyrosinases</article-title>
          <source>Phytochemistry</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>1309</fpage>
          <lpage>1323</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9237394</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib48">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vaughn</surname>
              <given-names>KC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lax</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duke</surname>
              <given-names>SO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Polyphenol oxidase: the chloroplast oxidase with no established function</article-title>
          <source>Physiologia Plantarum</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <fpage>659</fpage>
          <lpage>665</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib49">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yoruk</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marshall</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Physicochemical properties and function of plant polyphenol oxidase: a review</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Food Biochemistry</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>361</fpage>
          <lpage>422</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib50">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qian</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zeng</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>C-I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Independent loss of function in a polyphenol oxidase in rice: differentiation in grain discoloration between subspecies and the role of positive selection under domestication</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>2946</fpage>
          <lpage>2959</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19033526</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib51">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Winters</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heywood</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farrar</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Donnison</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Webb</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification of an extensive gene cluster among a family of PPOs in <italic>Trifolium pratense</italic> L. (red clover) using a large insert BAC library</article-title>
          <source>BMC Plant Biology</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>94</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19619287</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib52">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zuckerkandl</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pauling</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Bryson</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vogel</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evolutionary divergence and convergence in proteins</article-title>
          <source>Evolving genes and proteins</source>
          <year>1965</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>97</fpage>
          <lpage>166</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
