<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Evol Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Evolutionary Biology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2148</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2955719</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2148-10-296</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20920202</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-10-296</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Unusual conservation among genes encoding small secreted salivary gland proteins from a gall midge</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Ming-Shun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>ming-shun.chen@ars.usda.gov</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Xuming</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>xmliu@ksu.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Ziheng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>z.yang@ucl.ac.uk</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Huixian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref>
          <email>hxzhao212@yahoo.com.cn</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5">
          <name>
            <surname>Shukle</surname>
            <given-names>Richard H</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref>
          <email>shukle@purdue.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6">
          <name>
            <surname>Stuart</surname>
            <given-names>Jeffrey J</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref>
          <email>stuartjj@purdue.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7">
          <name>
            <surname>Hulbert</surname>
            <given-names>Scot</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref>
          <email>scot_hulbert@wsu.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>USDA-ARS, Hard Winter Wheat Genetics Research Unit, 4008 Throckmorton Hall, Kansas State University, Manhattan, KS 66506, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Entomology, Kansas State University, Manhattan, KS 66506, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Biology, University College London, London NW12HE, UK</aff>
      <aff id="I4"><label>4</label>College of Life Sciences, Northwest A&amp;F University, Yangling, Shaanxi, China</aff>
      <aff id="I5"><label>5</label>USDA-ARS and Department of Entomology, Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN 47907, USA</aff>
      <aff id="I6"><label>6</label>Department of Plant Pathology, Washington State University, Pullman, WA 99164, USA</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <fpage>296</fpage>
      <lpage>296</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9;2010 Chen et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Chen et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/10/296"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>In most protein-coding genes, greater sequence variation is observed in noncoding regions (introns and untranslated regions) than in coding regions due to selective constraints. During characterization of genes and transcripts encoding small secreted salivary gland proteins (SSSGPs) from the Hessian fly, we found exactly the opposite pattern of conservation in several families of genes: the non-coding regions were highly conserved, but the coding regions were highly variable.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Seven genes from the <italic>SSSGP-1 </italic>family are clustered as one inverted and six tandem repeats within a 15 kb region of the genome. Except for <italic>SSSGP-1A2</italic>, a gene that encodes a protein identical to that encoded by <italic>SSSGP-1A1</italic>, the other six genes consist of a highly diversified, mature protein-coding region as well as highly conserved regions including the promoter, 5'- and 3'-UTRs, a signal peptide coding region, and an intron. This unusual pattern of highly diversified coding regions coupled with highly conserved regions in the rest of the gene was also observed in several other groups of SSSGP-encoding genes or cDNAs. The unusual conservation pattern was also found in some of the SSSGP cDNAs from the Asian rice gall midge, but not from the orange wheat blossom midge. Strong positive selection was one of the forces driving for diversification whereas concerted homogenization was likely a mechanism for sequence conservation.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Rapid diversification in mature SSSGPs suggests that the genes are under selection pressure for functional adaptation. The conservation in the noncoding regions of these genes including introns also suggested potential mechanisms for sequence homogenization that are not yet fully understood. This report should be useful for future studies on genetic mechanisms involved in evolution and functional adaptation of parasite genes.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Insect salivary glands are the main organs for producing proteins that are injected into hosts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Plant-feeding insects, especially those with sucking mouthparts, inject proteins and other substances into host plants to facilitate mouthpart penetration, partially digest food before ingestion, and suppress plant defense [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Substances, including proteins with regulatory roles that can alter host physiology, are referred to as effectors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Pathogens, including bacteria, fungi, oomycetes, and nematodes, deliver various effector proteins into host tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Substantial evidence suggests that some of the salivary proteins injected into host plants by insects also act as effectors to suppress defense and/or reprogram physiological pathways of host plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Gall midges (Cecidomyiidae), a large family of plant-feeding insects, apparently secrete effectors into host tissues, inducing various forms of plant outgrowth (galls) and altering other aspects of host physiology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Plant galls contain a zone of "metabolic habitat modification" in which the parasite experiences a selective advantage because of enhanced nutrition and reduced plant defense [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Several organic compounds and enzymes injected into host plants by galling insects have been identified, including amino acids, auxin, proteases, oxidases, and pectinases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], but the general composition of the proteins delivered into host plants by gall midges has not yet been fully characterized.</p>
      <p>The Hessian fly, <italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic>, is the most destructive insect pest of wheat worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Because of its importance in agriculture, intriguing behavior, ease of maintenance in culture, and relatively well-characterized genetics, Hessian fly is becoming a model species for studying insect-plant interactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Hessian fly does not induce the formation of an outgrowth gall, but nutritive cells with similarity to those inside macroscopic galls are formed at the larval feeding site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Larvae do not cause extensive tissue damage to host plants, with their specialized mandibles making only a pair of small holes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Nevertheless, wheat plants become permanently and irreversibly stunted after 4-5 days of feeding by a single larva [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Even if larvae are removed, growth of wheat seedlings cannot be restored [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], suggesting that larvae inject substances into host plants that dramatically alter biochemical and physiological pathways of the attacked plant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>].</p>
      <p>As the first step to identify some of those proteins that are injected into host plants, we have previously generated numerous ESTs from cDNAs derived from dissected salivary glands of Hessian fly first instar larvae [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. The majority of the salivary gland transcripts encode small proteins (50 to 200 amino acids) with typical secretion signal peptides at the N-termini. We refer to these proteins as "small secreted salivary gland proteins" (SSSGPs). Here we report unusual conservation patterns of SSSGP-encoding genes and we discuss potential mechanisms for gene evolution and functional adaptation.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Results and Discussion</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Unconventional conservation of SSSGP-encoding genes</title>
        <p>The <italic>SSSGP-1 </italic>gene family includes seven members and is clustered as one inverted and six tandemly repeated genes within a 15 kb region of the genome (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). The predicted structures of the genes were verified by comparing the genomic sequences with cDNA clones corresponding to genes <italic>SSSGP-1A</italic>, <italic>SSSGP-1B1</italic>, <italic>SSSGP-1C1 </italic>and <italic>SSSGP-1D1 </italic>(a cDNA for <italic>SSSGP-1E1 </italic>has yet to be identified). All seven genes have a common structure, including a conserved putative promoter region, a 5'-untranslated region (5'-UTR), a signal peptide-coding region (SPCR), an intron, a mature protein-coding region (MPCR), and a 3'-untranslated region (3'-UTR; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). Intergenic regions are small, ranging from 0.2 to 1 kB (Genbank accession: GU196316). Among the seven genes, <italic>SSSGP-1A2</italic>, present in the inverted repeat, was apparently recently duplicated and encodes an identical protein with <italic>SSSGP-1A1</italic>. The other six genes consist of highly diversified MPCRs as well as highly conserved regions, including the promoter region, 5'- and 3'-UTRs, SPCR, and the intron (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>, Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure S1A). The predicted proteins are almost identical in their putative signal peptides, but share little similarity among the mature proteins (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). This extreme pattern of diversification in MPCR, which we refer to here as super-diversification, coupled with strong conservation in other regions was also observed in several other groups of SSSGP-encoding genes (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure S1) or cDNAs from Hessian fly (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>, Figure S2).</p>
        <fig id="F1" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Genomic organization and structural comparison of the Hessian fly <italic>SSSGP-1 </italic>family members</bold>. <bold>A: </bold><italic>SSSGP-1 </italic>family members derived by sequencing a BAC clone made from biotype GP. <bold>B: </bold>Nucleotide sequence comparison of the seven <italic>SSSGP-1 </italic>genes. Comparisons were divided into the promoter region (Promoter), 5'-untranslated region (5'-UTR), signal peptide coding region (SPCR), an intron, mature protein coding region (MPCR), and 3'-untranslated region (3'-UTR). The numbers in boxes are average scores and score range (in parentheses) derived from pair-wise comparisons of all possible combinations of the genes (see Materials and Methods). Red color indicates conserved regions. Blue color indicates diversified regions. The lowest score for any pairwise comparison in the MPCR was 13. Unrelated random sequences can produce scores as high as 15. The actual alignments of these genes are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure S1A. <bold>C: </bold>Sequence alignments of putative proteins. Dashes represent gaps in the sequence alignments. The first 18 amino acids constitute a putative signal peptide.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-10-296-1"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Similarity of different regions among cDNAs from different gene groups</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">Gene group</th>
                <th align="center">No. of Seq.</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="3">5'-Untranslated region (5'-UTR)</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="3">Signal peptide coding region (SPCR)</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="3">Mature protein coding region (MPCR)</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="3">3'-untranslated region (3'-UTR)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Length</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Score AVE</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Score</bold>
                  <break/>
                  <bold>range</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Length</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Score AVE</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Score</bold>
                  <break/>
                  <bold>range</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Length</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Score AVE</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Score</bold>
                  <break/>
                  <bold>range</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Length</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Score AVE</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Score</bold>
                  <break/>
                  <bold>range</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="14">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-1</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center">6</td>
                <td align="left">58 - 59</td>
                <td align="left">92</td>
                <td align="left">87 - 98</td>
                <td align="left">57</td>
                <td align="left">94</td>
                <td align="left">92 - 98</td>
                <td align="left">252 - 484</td>
                <td align="left">49</td>
                <td align="left">13 - 100</td>
                <td align="left">186 - 258</td>
                <td align="left">88</td>
                <td align="left">79 - 94</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="14">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-2</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center">15</td>
                <td align="left">6 - 198</td>
                <td align="left">84</td>
                <td align="left">52 - 100</td>
                <td align="left">60</td>
                <td align="left">87</td>
                <td align="left">78 - 95</td>
                <td align="left">258 - 462</td>
                <td align="left">10</td>
                <td align="left">3 - 57</td>
                <td align="left">77 - 269</td>
                <td align="left">81</td>
                <td align="left">57 - 92</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="14">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-3</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center">4</td>
                <td align="left">31 - 36</td>
                <td align="left">87</td>
                <td align="left">80 - 100</td>
                <td align="left">54</td>
                <td align="left">80</td>
                <td align="left">70 - 96</td>
                <td align="left">189 - 312</td>
                <td align="left">22</td>
                <td align="left">6 - 71</td>
                <td align="left">64 - 210</td>
                <td align="left">73</td>
                <td align="left">49 - 98</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="14">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-4</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center">7</td>
                <td align="left">37 - 47</td>
                <td align="left">94</td>
                <td align="left">83 - 100</td>
                <td align="left">75</td>
                <td align="left">80</td>
                <td align="left">58 - 93</td>
                <td align="left">360 - 636</td>
                <td align="left">10</td>
                <td align="left">4 - 27</td>
                <td align="left">121 - 222</td>
                <td align="left">52</td>
                <td align="left">14 - 82</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="14">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-5</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center">3</td>
                <td align="left">81 - 87</td>
                <td align="left">94</td>
                <td align="left">93 - 95</td>
                <td align="left">69</td>
                <td align="left">96</td>
                <td align="left">95 - 97</td>
                <td align="left">4 - 279</td>
                <td align="left">15</td>
                <td align="left">11 - 19</td>
                <td align="left">71 - 124</td>
                <td align="left">65</td>
                <td align="left">48 - 85</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="14">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-6</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center">2</td>
                <td align="left">24 - 25</td>
                <td align="left">87</td>
                <td align="left">87</td>
                <td align="left">63</td>
                <td align="left">95</td>
                <td align="left">95</td>
                <td align="left">249 - 255</td>
                <td align="left">79</td>
                <td align="left">79</td>
                <td align="left">57 - 60</td>
                <td align="left">91</td>
                <td align="left">91</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="14">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-31</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center">4</td>
                <td align="left">52 - 65</td>
                <td align="left">93</td>
                <td align="left">88 - 97</td>
                <td align="left">39</td>
                <td align="left">97</td>
                <td align="left">94 - 100</td>
                <td align="left">213 - 330</td>
                <td align="left">16</td>
                <td align="left">8 - 28</td>
                <td align="left">90 - 122</td>
                <td align="left">92</td>
                <td align="left">85 - 96</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <p>Score average (AVE) and score range were derived by pair-wise comparison (Materials and Methods). Except for the two members from group <italic>SSSGP-6</italic>, the score average for MPCR is at least 40% less than those for other regions. The two members from group <italic>SSSGP-6 </italic>are likely relatively recent duplicates since they share an overall 83% sequence identity. The score average for these two members is 13% less than those for other regions.</p>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Except for the common features of diversification/conservation, there are no noticeable sequence or structural similarities between the different groups of <italic>SSSGP </italic>genes, and no apparent sequence similarities could be detected among different groups with currently available alignment methods such as BLAST. Most groups of <italic>SSSGP </italic>genes contain one intron (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figures S1A, S1C, S1D). However, one group lacks introns (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure S1B) and several other groups contain multiple introns (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure S1E). For those genes containing introns, the first (or the sole) intron is located either at the boundary between the SPCR and MPCR, or within the SPCR (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure S1). The positions of intron/exon boundaries are generally conserved among members within a group. However, deletions or shifts in intron/exon boundaries occur in gene groups with multiple introns (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure S1E). For all gene groups, multiple members in each group are clustered within short chromosome regions in the Hessian fly genome (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>, Figure S3).</p>
        <p>To determine if such a genetic phenomenon exists in other gall midges, a similar analysis of salivary gland cDNAs was conducted on two other related insects, the orange wheat blossom midge (<italic>Sitodiplosis mosellana</italic>) and the Asian rice gall midge (<italic>Orseolia oryzae</italic>). Approximately 8,500 cDNAs from the wheat blossom midge and 3,500 from the Asian rice gall midge were sequenced. In each case, a similar proportion (45-50%) of cDNA clones was found encoding different SSSGPs. Forty-eight different groups of putative SSSGPs were identified from the wheat blossom midge while 25 different groups of putative SSSGPs were identified from the Asian rice gall midge. Comparative analysis revealed that cDNAs and their encoded proteins from the Asian rice midge, wheat blossom midge, and Hessian fly were typically found to be species-specific; cDNAs from one species shared no detectable sequence similarity with those from the other two species, consistent with the rapidly evolving nature of SSSGP-encoding genes. The species-specific nature of SSSGP-encoding genes was further confirmed by PCR and by Southern blot analysis. No PCR amplification could be achieved using primer pairs designed according to cDNAs from another species. Similarly, no cross hybridization could be observed on Southern blots using cDNA probes from a different species (data not shown). The typical unconventional conservation pattern of SSSGP-encoding genes observed in Hessian fly was also found in some of the SSSGP-encoding transcripts of the Asian rice midge (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>, Figure S2G), but not in any transcripts of the wheat blossom midge. This observation indicates that the unconventional conservation of SSSGP-encoding genes might be linked to adaption to environmental changes such as a change in host plants. Even though they live on different plant species, the Asian rice midge and Hessian fly larvae share a similar feeding mechanism. Larvae of both species feed on the meristem of a leaf-sheath within a plant, and their survival strictly depends on their ability to induce the formation of nutritive cells of plant tissue at the feeding site, to inhibit plant growth, and to suppress host defense [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Wheat blossom midges, on the other hand, feed on developing wheat seeds and either do not require extensive manipulation of host plants such as growth inhibition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], or manipulate host plants in different ways.</p>
        <p>Several genes from different mosquito species have been found encoding diverse secreted salivary proteins and some of these genes are also organized as tandem repeats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Diverse toxic small peptides have been found in the venoms of predatory cone snails [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. However, the extreme cases described here with a very short (100 to 500 bp), highly diversified segment followed by a very short (~500 bp), highly conserved segment arranged as multiple tandem repeats has not been found in any other organisms.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Strong positive selection on <italic>SSSGP </italic>loci and alleles</title>
        <p>Strong positive (diversifying) selection appears to be one of the forces driving diversifications in MPCRs. Highly diversified members with less than 80% sequence identity within MPCRs did not produce meaningful alignments for analyzing nonsynonymous to synonymous substitution ratio (<italic>dN/dS</italic>), but the fact that the coding regions are hard to align is itself evidence for fast evolution by positive selection or other mechanisms such as Y-family polymerases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Analysis of moderately diversified group members with 80 to 95% sequence identity in their MPCRs all yielded <italic>dN/dS </italic>above one (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>, Figure S4). One pair of group members produced a <italic>dN/dS </italic>ratio above 18, indicating very strong positive selection. Due to the small size, similar sequences with greater than 95% sequence identity within MPCRs did not possess sufficient nucleotide substitutions to confidently discern evolutionary patterns through analyzing <italic>dN/dS</italic>. However, a different analysis of similar sequences derived from different alleles also produced strong evidence for positive selection (below).</p>
        <table-wrap id="T2" position="float">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Evidence for positive selection on <italic>SSSGP </italic>group members</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">Group</th>
                <th align="left">cDNA pair</th>
                <th align="left">Codon</th>
                <th align="left">dN/dS</th>
                <th align="left">dN &#xB1; SE</th>
                <th align="left">dS &#xB1; SE</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-1</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">1C1/1C2</td>
                <td align="left">85</td>
                <td align="left">1.32</td>
                <td align="left">0.11 &#xB1; 0.03</td>
                <td align="left">0.08 &#xB1; 0.04</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-2</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">G19B4/S21C6</td>
                <td align="left">122</td>
                <td align="left">9.43</td>
                <td align="left">0.12 &#xB1; 0.02</td>
                <td align="left">0.01 &#xB1; 0.01</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-2</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">G10H7/G14E6</td>
                <td align="left">129</td>
                <td align="left">3.59</td>
                <td align="left">0.08 &#xB1; 0.02</td>
                <td align="left">0.02 &#xB1; 0.01</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-2</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">L4C4/G28G12</td>
                <td align="left">78</td>
                <td align="left">1.12</td>
                <td align="left">0.22 &#xB1; 0.04</td>
                <td align="left">0.20 &#xB1; 0.07</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-4</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">G13E6/G22C4</td>
                <td align="left">127</td>
                <td align="left">1.21</td>
                <td align="left">0.10 &#xB1; 0.02</td>
                <td align="left">0.08 &#xB1; 0.04</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-4</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">G2C8/L4H12</td>
                <td align="left">173</td>
                <td align="left">1.46</td>
                <td align="left">0.14 &#xB1; 0.02</td>
                <td align="left">0.10 &#xB1; 0.03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-4</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">G16C10/G29D6</td>
                <td align="left">156</td>
                <td align="left">2.49</td>
                <td align="left">0.26 &#xB1; 0.03</td>
                <td align="left">0.11 &#xB1; 0.03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-4</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">G9B3/L1C12</td>
                <td align="left">179</td>
                <td align="left">1.52</td>
                <td align="left">0.13 &#xB1; 0.02</td>
                <td align="left">0.09 &#xB1; 0.03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-6</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">G7H5/G8C4</td>
                <td align="left">81</td>
                <td align="left">2.92</td>
                <td align="left">0.31 &#xB1; 0.05</td>
                <td align="left">0.11 &#xB1; 0.05</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-7</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">G10C11/G15G6</td>
                <td align="left">119</td>
                <td align="left">1.48</td>
                <td align="left">0.11 &#xB1; 0.02</td>
                <td align="left">0.07 &#xB1; 0.03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-10</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">G8C1/G14G1</td>
                <td align="left">75</td>
                <td align="left">2.51</td>
                <td align="left">0.18 &#xB1; 0.04</td>
                <td align="left">0.07 &#xB1; 0.03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-26</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">G4C3/S22E4</td>
                <td align="left">162</td>
                <td align="left">5.67</td>
                <td align="left">0.04 &#xB1; 0.01</td>
                <td align="left">0.00 &#xB1; 0.00</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-31</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">G7D10/S4A9</td>
                <td align="left">100</td>
                <td align="left">1.82</td>
                <td align="left">0.06 &#xB1; 0.02</td>
                <td align="left">0.03 &#xB1; 0.03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-37</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">S5E9/G9G9</td>
                <td align="left">41</td>
                <td align="left">2.51</td>
                <td align="left">0.11 &#xB1; 0.04</td>
                <td align="left">0.04 &#xB1; 0.04</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-79</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">S14G9/S22D12</td>
                <td align="left">63</td>
                <td align="left">18.8</td>
                <td align="left">0.19 &#xB1; 0.04</td>
                <td align="left">0.01 &#xB1; 0.01</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>SSSGP-80</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">L7H8/S8C9</td>
                <td align="left">123</td>
                <td align="left">1.84</td>
                <td align="left">0.04 &#xB1; 0.01</td>
                <td align="left">0.03 &#xB1; 0.02</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <p>dN/dS ratio were obtained by comparing MPCRs using PAML42 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>].</p>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Multiple transcripts corresponding to genes <italic>SSSGP-1A1, SSSGP-1B1</italic>, and <italic>SSSGP-1C1 </italic>were isolated from three different Hessian fly populations. These different transcripts were likely derived from different alleles since evidence from <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization, Southern blots with genomic and BAC DNA samples, and primer specific PCR suggests a single locus for this gene family (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>, Figure S5). The ratio between nonsynonymous and synonymous substitutions was 1.5 or more within the MPCR, but less than 0.9 in the SPCR (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, Additional files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>), again indicating positive selection in MPCRs for different alleles.</p>
        <table-wrap id="T3" position="float">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Evidence for positive selection on different alleles (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>, Figure S6)</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">Gene</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="4">Total cDNAs sequenced</th>
                <th align="left">Unique</th>
                <th align="left">Unique</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="2">Nonsyn/Syn</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>GP</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>L</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>S</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Total</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>cDNAs</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>proteins</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>SPCR</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>MPCR</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="9">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>
                    <bold>SSSGP-1A1</bold>
                  </italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">60</td>
                <td align="left">43</td>
                <td align="left">45</td>
                <td align="left">148</td>
                <td align="left">71</td>
                <td align="left">27</td>
                <td align="left">0.83 (5/6)</td>
                <td align="left">1.56 (28/18)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="9">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>
                    <bold>SSSGP-1B1</bold>
                  </italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">106</td>
                <td align="left">24</td>
                <td align="left">36</td>
                <td align="left">166</td>
                <td align="left">66</td>
                <td align="left">35</td>
                <td align="left">0.80 (4/5)</td>
                <td align="left">1.50 (21/14)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="9">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>
                    <bold>SSSGP-1C1</bold>
                  </italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">27</td>
                <td align="left">5</td>
                <td align="left">12</td>
                <td align="left">44</td>
                <td align="left">20</td>
                <td align="left">14</td>
                <td align="left">0.60 (3/5)</td>
                <td align="left">2.33 (21/9)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="9">
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>RPs</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">157</td>
                <td align="left">34</td>
                <td align="left">23</td>
                <td align="left">214</td>
                <td align="left">96</td>
                <td align="left">47</td>
                <td align="left">N/A</td>
                <td align="left">0.26 (50/195)</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <p>cDNAs were derived from three Hessian fly populations: biotype GP, biotype L, and a Syrian population (S). As a control, cDNAs coding for 26 different ribosomal proteins (RPs) that were isolated along with <italic>SSSGP </italic>cDNAs were included in this analysis. Sequence alignments for different <italic>SSSGP </italic>cDNAs are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>, Figure S6 whereas alignments for RP cDNAs are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>, Figure S7. "Nonsyn/Syn" represents the ratios of non-synonymous against synonymous substitutions in SPCR and MPCR, respectively.</p>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Evidence for positive selection is not common but has been demonstrated at several different types of genes controlling interactions between organisms that are mediated by molecular recognition. Typical examples are defense-related genes including the major histocompatibility complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], immunoglobulins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>], defensins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>], plant resistance genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>], plant chitinase genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], and pathogen effector genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. The strong positive selection observed in SSSGP-encoding genes indicated that SSSGPs are also likely involved in interactions between Hessian fly and other organisms. Considering that Hessian fly larvae live within host plants, some of these SSSGPs may be secreted into host plants as effector proteins with a role in the insect's virulence. In plant-herbivore interactions, successful pathogens and parasitic arthropods not only require a large number of genes coding for effector proteins to suppress innate defense of host plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>], but also require the ability to change this arsenal in response to shifts in the host population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. Evolution of plant populations in parasite recognition and surveillance systems thus provides strong selection for counter changes in effector proteins from parasites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. The Hessian fly has been very successful in adaptation to changes in host plant populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. The super-diversification in SSSGP genes may have provided the genetic basis for the development of counter-resistance in Hessian fly in response to changes in host plants.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Concerted homogenization of noncoding regions</title>
        <p>Very strong selection for divergence could account for rapid divergence of MPCR but the high homology of the other regions of the genes is difficult to explain. Recombination between gene-family members, particularly those arranged in tandem arrays, acts to homogenize their sequences so they evolve in a concerted fashion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. Typically, however, this homogenization occurs throughout the whole gene and even the intergenic regions, not just specific domains in the genes. While crossover events would tend to homogenize the whole array, smaller gene conversion events might homogenize smaller regions. Little is known about recombination in gall midges, but conversion tracts at the <italic>Rosey </italic>locus of <italic>Drosophila </italic>have been found to be in the order of a few hundred base pairs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. Differences in sequence affinity among the various sub-regions of the <italic>SSSGP-1 </italic>family members corroborate frequent recombination in short DNA regions during Hessian fly evolution (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The homogenization could be confined to termini of the genes if the conversion events were initiated near the ends of the genes or in intergenic regions. The nature of recombination hotspots varies between species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>], but they are commonly initiated intergenically [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>], possibly at specific sequence motifs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>] or regulatory regions. Sequence heterogeneity in the MPCR due to strong positive selection could, in turn, affect the length of conversion tracks or how the recombination intermediates are resolved; conversion or crossover events [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. If the sequence homogeneity of the SSSGP-encoding families was caused by concerted evolution from short conversion tracks initiated in the flanking regions, one would expect introns in the middle of the larger genes to be less homogenized. This is in fact what was observed in the <italic>SSSGP-2 </italic>family; noticeably, several introns (introns 22, 23, 26, 27, 35, 36, 37) were rearranged or deleted (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure S1E). The coding regions of the two <italic>SSSGP-2 </italic>family members correspond to approximately 950 nucleotides with 35 introns.</p>
        <fig id="F2" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Phylogenetic tree for different regions of <italic>SSSGP-1 </italic>family members inferred using the Neighbor-joining method implemented in MEGA</bold>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-10-296-2"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To explore whether functional adaptation might explain conservation of certain regions of gene families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>], we analyzed the patterns of transcript levels corresponding to specific genes under different conditions (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). In general, SSSGPs with higher sequence similarity in the promoter regions had more similar patterns of gene expression (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). <italic>SSSGP-1A1</italic>, <italic>SSSGP-1A2</italic>, <italic>SSSGP-1B1</italic>, and <italic>SSSGP-1C1</italic>, whose promoters were very similar (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>), also exhibited similar expression patterns among tissues (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>) and developmental stages (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>), and among insects interacting with different plant genotypes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). The promoters of <italic>SSSGP-1C2</italic>, and <italic>SSSGP-1E1 </italic>were also similar to each other (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>), and these two genes also exhibited similar transcription patterns. However, the genes in the first group (<italic>SSSGP-1A1</italic>, <italic>SSSGP-1A2</italic>, <italic>SSSGP-1B1</italic>, and <italic>SSSGP-1C1</italic>) and the second group (<italic>SSSGP-1C2 </italic>and <italic>SSSGP-1E1</italic>) had strikingly different expression patterns (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Small differences in the transcription patterns among members in the same promoter group were also observed. For example, <italic>SSSGP-1C2 </italic>was expressed abundantly in 0.5-day old larvae (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>, <italic>1C2</italic>), whereas little <italic>SSSGP-1E1 </italic>expression was observed in the same larvae (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>, <italic>1E1</italic>). These differences could indicate that small differences in the promoter (or other regulatory elements in other regions) of the genes can fine-tune the level of transcripts to satisfy specific requirements. These observations suggest that the conservation/diversification of the promoter regions has been strictly driven by functional adaptation.</p>
        <fig id="F3" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Distribution and abundance of transcripts corresponding to specific <italic>SSSGP-1 </italic>family members</bold>. <bold>A</bold>: Transcript distribution among tissues was determined using 3-day old biotype GP larvae. The remains after removing salivary glands, gut, and Malphigian tubules were designated as carcass. <bold>B</bold>: Transcript abundance in 0.5 to 12-day old larvae on susceptible wheat plants (cultivar 'Newton'). <bold>C</bold>: Transcript abundance in 0.5 to 4-day old (dying) larvae on resistant wheat (cultivar 'Molly' containing <italic>H13 </italic>R-gene). Primer pairs and methods are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S8">8</xref>, Table S1.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-10-296-3"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The homogenization of 5'- and possibly even 3'-UTRs may also have a functional basis. Because UTRs play critical roles in post-transcriptional regulation of gene expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>], we speculate that the SSSGP UTRs are critical for proper post-transcriptional regulation. For example, part of the conserved UTRs could serve as elements for binding with regulatory proteins or as pairing sites for interacting with micro-RNAs that may affect RNA stability or translation efficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. Multiple layers of gene regulation may be needed to ensure spatial and tissue-specific expression and prompt response of SSSGP-encoding genes to changes of host and other environmental conditions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Functional division of SSSGPs: initiators and maintainers</title>
        <p>SSSGPs appear to have a division of labor, with "initiators" expressed only immediately after the start of feeding and "maintainers" expressed at later stages in the time course of feeding and plant response. Initiators, such as <italic>SSSGP-1C2 </italic>and <italic>SSSGP-1E </italic>in the <italic>SSSGP-1 </italic>family, were predominantly expressed in salivary glands (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>) at early stage of larval development (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>), and their expression was elevated at later time points in larvae feeding on resistant plants (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). These observations are consistent with the postulation that initiators are secreted into plant tissue as effectors to manipulate plant cells. Hessian fly suppresses plant defense and induces the formation of nutritive cells within the first couple of days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Once the insect has successfully manipulated host plants, one would expect that the expression of initiators is no longer needed. Indeed the manipulation of wheat seedlings is irreversibly achieved within the first few days following the Hessian fly initial attack [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. The elevated expression of initiators in larvae feeding on resistant plants at later stages may reflect the fact that Hessian fly larvae continue to secret effectors to counter increased plant defense in these plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>].</p>
        <p>Maintainers, such as <italic>SSSGP-1A</italic>, <italic>SSSGP-1C1</italic>, and <italic>SSGP-1C1</italic>, were also expressed in other tissues besides the salivary glands (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). The proteins produced in Malphigian tubules and carcass are unlikely to play a role in interaction with host plants, but could play a role in regulating Hessian fly symbiotic or associated microbes in insect tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. In addition, some SSSGPs could also play a role in regulating secondary microbial infection of the host tissues damaged at the feeding site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]. The maintainers may possess antimicrobial activity, and are under selection pressure from changes in microbial populations. Further research on the network of these initiators and maintainers encoded by rapidly evolving genes will shed light on the biology and feeding behavior of gall midges.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In this study, we observed an unconventional conservation pattern in genes encoding SSSGPs in the Hessian fly. In the SSSGP-encoding genes, noncoding regions are highly conserved whereas regions coding for mature proteins are highly diversified. Rapid diversification in mature SSSGPs suggests that the genes are under selection pressure for functional adaptation. Considering the fact that most SSSGP-encoding genes are exclusively expressed in salivary glands, it is likely that rapid diversification in SSSGP-encoding genes is for the insect to counter changes in host plants for virulence. The conservation in the noncoding regions of these genes including introns also suggested potential mechanisms for sequence homogenization that are not yet fully understood. This report should be useful for future studies on genetic mechanisms involved in evolution and functional adaptation of parasite genes.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>DNA libraries and sequencing</title>
        <p>cDNA libraries and sequencing were as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. A BAC library with 5&#xD7; coverage was made from biotype GP Hessian fly larvae through a commercial contract with Amplicon Express (Pullman, WA). The BAC library contains inserts with average size of ~150 kB ligated into <italic>Hind </italic>III of pECBA1. A positive BAC clone, 10A23, was identified by screening the BAC library with a cDNA probe corresponding to the <italic>SSSGP-1C1 </italic>gene. A shotgun library with average sizes of 1.5 kB was made with 10 times coverage of the BAC clone 10A23, again through a commercial contract with Amplicon Express. The shotgun library was sequenced using ABI 3730 DNA analyzer at Kansas State University DNA sequencing facility. The shotgun sequences were assembled using Cap3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>] and confirmed by PCR amplification and resequencing. The sequence of the whole BAC clone is 130 kB and was deposited into Genbank with accession number GU196316. The 15 kB cluster was located in the middle region toward 5'-end of the BAC.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) analysis</title>
        <p>RNA extraction, reverse-transcription and real-time PCR were carried out as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Two hundred larvae or tissues from 200 larvae were collected and pooled for RNA isolation for each replicate. Three biological replicates were included for each analysis. The ratio between abundances on resistant plants and the corresponding ones on susceptible plants were calculated. Primers used for PCR reactions are listed in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S8">8</xref>, Table S1.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Sequence analysis and comparison</title>
        <p>Sequence alignments and comparison were conducted using ClustalW [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]. For pairwise comparison, each sequence was compared with every other sequence. Scores for individual alignments are calculated based on the method of Wilbur and Lipman [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. The higher the score is for a pairwise alignment, the higher the degree of conservation is between the two aligned sequences. Average scores were derived by dividing the sum of all pair-wise scores with the number of alignments. Score range was the lowest score to the highest score among all pair-wise alignments. For analysis of nucleotide substitutions, pair-wise alignments were obtained using ClusterW. Nonsynomonous (<italic>dN</italic>) and synomonous (<italic>dS</italic>) substitution ratios (<italic>dN/dS</italic>) were obtained using PAML42 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>].</p>
        <p>Phylogenetic trees were produced based on neighbor joining and maximum likelihood using MEGA4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Southern blot analysis</title>
        <p>Hessian fly genomic DNA was isolated following a salting out protocol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. For Southern blot, 10 &#x3BC;g of purified genomic DNA was digested with individual restriction enzymes. The digested DNA fragments were separated on a 0.8% agarose gel and blotted onto GeneScreen membrane (Perkin Elmer, Beltsville, MD). The membranes were then hybridized separately to individual probes of cDNAs from either the Hessian fly, or Asian rice midge, or wheat blossom midge. cDNA probes were produced with <sup>32</sup>P dCTP using a random labeling kit from Stratagene (La Jolla, CA). Hybridization was carried out overnight at 42&#xB0;C in a plastic bag containing a 15-mL hybridization solution, which consisted of 10% dextran sulfate, 1% SDS, 1 M NaCl, pH 8.0. After hybridization, the membranes were washed twice with 2 &#xD7; SSC at room temperature for 30 min, twice with 2 &#xD7; SSC (0.3 M sodium chloride and 30 mM tri-Sodium citrate dihydrate, pH 7.0) plus 1% SDS at 65&#xB0;C for 30 min, and twice with 0.1 &#xD7; SSC plus 1% SDS at room temperature for 30 min. Images were visualized by exposing the membranes to Kodak SR-5 X-ray film overnight.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors' contributions</title>
      <p>MSC participated in sequence analysis and manuscript preparation. XL participated in library construction and sequence analysis. ZY involved in phylogenetic analysis and bioinformatics. HZ did real-time PCR analysis. RHS characterized cDNAs from rice midge and wheat midge. JJS and SH participated in data analysis and manuscript preparation. All authors have read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 1</title>
          <p>Figure S1: Sequence alignments of different groups of SSSGP-encoding genes.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2148-10-296-S1.DOC" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 2</title>
          <p>Figure S2: Sequence alignments of different groups of SSSGP-encoding cDNAs.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2148-10-296-S2.DOC" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 3</title>
          <p>Figure S3: Evidence for clustered organization of SSSGP-encoding genes.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2148-10-296-S3.DOC" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 4</title>
          <p>Figure S4: Alignments of moderately diversified <italic>SSSGP </italic>group members (cDNAs).</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2148-10-296-S4.DOC" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S5">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 5</title>
          <p>Figure S5: Evidence for single location of genes in the <italic>SSSGP-1 </italic>family.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2148-10-296-S5.DOC" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S6">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 6</title>
          <p>Figure S6: Sequence alignment of similar SSSGP-encoding cDNAs (presumably derived from different alleles).</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2148-10-296-S6.DOC" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S7">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 7</title>
          <p>Figure S7: Sequence alignment of cDNAs encoding ribosomal proteins.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2148-10-296-S7.DOC" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S8">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 8</title>
          <p>Table S1: Primers used for PCR reactions.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2148-10-296-S8.DOC" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>Mention of commercial or proprietary product does not constitute endorsement by the USDA. The authors thank Drs Frank White and Richard Beeman for reviewing an earlier version of the manuscript. Hessian fly voucher specimens (No. 150) are located in the KSU Museum of Entomological and Prairie Arthropod Research, Kansas State University, Manhattan, Kansas. This research was supported by USDA-ARS and a grant from USDA-NRI (2004-03099).</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Chapman</surname>
            <given-names>RF</given-names>
          </name>
          <source>The insects: structure and function (Chapman eds.)</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <edition>4</edition>
          <publisher-name>Cambridge Univeristy press, Cambridge, UK</publisher-name>
          <fpage>12</fpage>
          <lpage>36</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Miles</surname>
            <given-names>PW</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Aphid saliva</article-title>
          <source>Biol Rev</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>41</fpage>
          <lpage>85</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0006323198005271</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Tjallingii</surname>
            <given-names>WF</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Salivary secretions by aphids interacting with proteins of phloem wound responses</article-title>
          <source>J Exp Bot</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>739</fpage>
          <lpage>745</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erj088</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16467410</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Mutti</surname>
            <given-names>NS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pappan</surname>
            <given-names>LK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Begum</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pappan</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>M-S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reese</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reeck</surname>
            <given-names>GR</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A protein from the salivary glands of the pea aphid, <italic>Acyrthosiphon pisum</italic>, is essential in feeding on a host plant</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>105</volume>
          <fpage>9965</fpage>
          <lpage>9969</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0708958105</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18621720</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Grant</surname>
            <given-names>SR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fisher</surname>
            <given-names>EJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chang</surname>
            <given-names>JH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mole</surname>
            <given-names>BM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dangl</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Subterfuge and manipulation: Type III effector proteins of phytopathogenic bacteria</article-title>
          <source>Ann Rev Microbiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>425</fpage>
          <lpage>449</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.micro.60.080805.142251</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>De Wit</surname>
            <given-names>PJGM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mehrab</surname>
            <given-names>IR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Van den Burg</surname>
            <given-names>HA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stergiopoulo</surname>
            <given-names>SI</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Fungal effector proteins: past, present and future</article-title>
          <source>Mol Plant Pathol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>735</fpage>
          <lpage>747</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1364-3703.2009.00591.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19849781</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Kamoun</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A catalogue of the effector secretome of plant pathogenic oomycetes</article-title>
          <source>Ann Rev Phytopathol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>41</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.phyto.44.070505.143436</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Pate</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hamamouch</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hewezi</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hussey</surname>
            <given-names>RS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Baum</surname>
            <given-names>TJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mitcchum</surname>
            <given-names>MG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Davis</surname>
            <given-names>EL</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A nematode effector protein similar to annexins in host plants</article-title>
          <source>J Exp Bot</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>235</fpage>
          <lpage>248</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erp293</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19887499</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Byers</surname>
            <given-names>RA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gallun</surname>
            <given-names>RL</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Ability of Hessian fly to stunt winter wheat. 1. Effect of larval feeding on elongation of leaves</article-title>
          <source>J Econ Entomol</source>
          <year>1972</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>955</fpage>
          <lpage>958</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Bede</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Musser</surname>
            <given-names>RO</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Felton</surname>
            <given-names>GW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Korth</surname>
            <given-names>KL</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Caterpillar herbivory and salivary enzymes decrease transcript levels of <italic>Medicago truncatula </italic>genes encoding enzymes in terpeniod biosynthesis</article-title>
          <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>519</fpage>
          <lpage>531</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-005-4923-y</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16525889</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Musser</surname>
            <given-names>RO</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hum-Musser</surname>
            <given-names>SM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Eichenseer</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Peiffer</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ervin</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Murphy</surname>
            <given-names>JB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Felton</surname>
            <given-names>GW</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Herbivory: Caterpillar saliva beats plant defences</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>416</volume>
          <fpage>599</fpage>
          <lpage>600</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/416599a</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11948341</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Weech</surname>
            <given-names>M-H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chapleau</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pan</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ide</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bede</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Caterpillar saliva interferes with induced <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana </italic>defence responses via the systemic acquired resistance pathway</article-title>
          <source>J Exp Bot</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>2437</fpage>
          <lpage>2448</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ern108</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18487634</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Hori</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">Shorthouse JD, Rohfritsch D</person-group>
          <article-title>Insect secretions and their effect on plant growth</article-title>
          <source>Biology of Insect-Induced Galls</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <publisher-name>Oxford University Press, New York</publisher-name>
          <fpage>118</fpage>
          <lpage>140</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Dieleman</surname>
            <given-names>FL</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Effect of gall midge infestation on plant growth and growth regulating substances</article-title>
          <source>Ento Exp Appl</source>
          <year>1969</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>745</fpage>
          <lpage>749</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00297101</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Goethals</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vereecke</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jaziri</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Van Montagu</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Holsters</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Leafy gall formation by <italic>Rhodococcus fascians</italic></article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>27</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.phyto.39.1.27</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11701858</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hatchett</surname>
            <given-names>JH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Starks</surname>
            <given-names>KJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Webster</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Insect and mite pests of wheat</article-title>
          <source>Wheat and Wheat improvement. Agronomy Monograph No</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>625</fpage>
          <lpage>675</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Harris</surname>
            <given-names>MO</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stuart</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mohan</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nair</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lamb</surname>
            <given-names>RJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rohfritsch</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Grasses and gall midges: plant defense and insect adaptation</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>549</fpage>
          <lpage>577</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ento.48.091801.112559</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12460937</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Stuart</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harris</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">Hunter, Kole</person-group>
          <article-title>Hessian fly</article-title>
          <source>Genome Mapping and Genomics in Animals, Volume 1: Genome Mapping and Genomics in Arthropods</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <publisher-name>Springer, Berlin, Heidelberg, New York</publisher-name>
          <fpage>93</fpage>
          <lpage>100</lpage>
          <comment>full_text</comment>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Harris</surname>
            <given-names>MO</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Freeman</surname>
            <given-names>TP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rohfritsch</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>KG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Payne</surname>
            <given-names>SA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Moore</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Virulent Hessian fly (Diptera: Cecidomyiidae) larvae induce a nutritive tissue during compatible interactions with wheat</article-title>
          <source>Ann Entomol Soc Am</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>305</fpage>
          <lpage>316</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0013-8746(2006)099[0305:VHFDCL]2.0.CO;2</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Stuart</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hatchett</surname>
            <given-names>JH</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Morphogenesis and cytology of the salivary gland of the Hessian fly, <italic>Mayetiola destructor </italic>(Diptera: Cecidomyiidae)</article-title>
          <source>Ann Entomol Soc Am</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>475</fpage>
          <lpage>482</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>XL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bai</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Weng</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reese</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harris</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stuart</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Gene expression of different wheat genotypes during attack by virulent and avirulent Hessian fly (<italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic>) larvae</article-title>
          <source>J Chem Ecol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>2171</fpage>
          <lpage>2194</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-007-9382-2</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18058177</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>XM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jeannotte</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reese</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harris</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stuart</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Hessian fly (<italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic>) attack causes dramatic shift in carbon and nitrogen metabolism in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>70</fpage>
          <lpage>78</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI-21-1-0070</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18052884</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fellers</surname>
            <given-names>JP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stuart</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reese</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>XM</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A group of related cDNAs encoding secreted proteins from Hessian fly [<italic>Mayetiola destructor </italic>(Say)] salivary glands</article-title>
          <source>Insect Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>101</fpage>
          <lpage>108</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2583.2004.00465.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14728671</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>HX</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>YC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Scheffler</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>XM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hulbert</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stuart</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Analysis of transcripts and proteins expressed in the salivary glands of Hessian fly (<italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic>) larvae</article-title>
          <source>J Insect Physiol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>16</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinsphys.2007.07.007</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17854824</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Bennett</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bentur</surname>
            <given-names>JS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pasalu</surname>
            <given-names>IC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Krishnaiah</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>New approaches to gall midge resistance</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the International Workshop</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <publisher-name>Hyderabad, India</publisher-name>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>23</lpage>
          <comment>22-24 November 1998</comment>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Calvo</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mans</surname>
            <given-names>BJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Andersen</surname>
            <given-names>JF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ribeiro</surname>
            <given-names>MC</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Function and evolution of a mosquito salivary protein family</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>281</volume>
          <fpage>1935</fpage>
          <lpage>1942</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M510359200</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16301315</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Olivera</surname>
            <given-names>BM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rivier</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Clark</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ramilo</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Corpuz</surname>
            <given-names>GP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Abogadie</surname>
            <given-names>FC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mena</surname>
            <given-names>EE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Woodward</surname>
            <given-names>SR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hillyard</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cruz</surname>
            <given-names>LJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Diversity of conus neuropeptides</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>249</volume>
          <fpage>257</fpage>
          <lpage>263</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.2165278</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2165278</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Lehmann</surname>
            <given-names>AR</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>New functions for Y family polymerases</article-title>
          <source>Mol Cell</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>493</fpage>
          <lpage>495</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2006.10.021</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17188030</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hughes</surname>
            <given-names>AL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nei</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Pattern of nucleotide substitution at major histocompatibility complex class I loci reveals overdominant selection</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>335</volume>
          <fpage>167</fpage>
          <lpage>170</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/335167a0</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Tanaka</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nei</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Positive Darwinian selection observed at the variable-region genes of immunoglobulins</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>447</fpage>
          <lpage>459</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2796726</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hughes</surname>
            <given-names>AL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yeager</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Coordinated amino acid changes in the evolution of mammalian defensins</article-title>
          <source>J Mol Evol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>675</fpage>
          <lpage>682</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/PL00006191</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9169560</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Michelmore</surname>
            <given-names>RW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Meyers</surname>
            <given-names>BC</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Clusters of resistance genes in plants evolve by divergent selection and a birth-and-death process</article-title>
          <source>Genome Res</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>1113</fpage>
          <lpage>1130</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9847076</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Bishop</surname>
            <given-names>JG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dean</surname>
            <given-names>AM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mitchell-Olds</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Rapid evolution in plant chitinases: Molecular targets of selection in plant-pathogen coevolution</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>5322</fpage>
          <lpage>5327</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.10.5322</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10805791</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Morgan</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kamoun</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>RXLR effectors of plant pathogenic oomycetes</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>332</fpage>
          <lpage>338</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2007.04.005</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17707688</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Boller</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>SY</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Innate immunity in plants: An arms race between pattern recognition receptors in plants and effectors in microbial pathogens</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>324</volume>
          <fpage>742</fpage>
          <lpage>744</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1171647</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19423812</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Burdon</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thrall</surname>
            <given-names>PH</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Coevolution of plants and their pathogens in natural habitats</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>324</volume>
          <fpage>755</fpage>
          <lpage>756</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1171663</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19423818</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Bent</surname>
            <given-names>AF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Machey</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Elicitors, effectors and R genes: The new paradigm and a lifetime supply of questions</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>399</fpage>
          <lpage>436</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.phyto.45.062806.094427</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17506648</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Dover</surname>
            <given-names>GA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Molecular drive: a cohesive mode of species evolution</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>199</volume>
          <fpage>111</fpage>
          <lpage>117</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/299111a0</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Liao</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">Cooper DN</person-group>
          <article-title>Concerted evolution</article-title>
          <source>Nature Encyclopedia of the Human Genome</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group, London</publisher-name>
          <fpage>938</fpage>
          <lpage>942</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hilliker</surname>
            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harauz</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reaume</surname>
            <given-names>AG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gray</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Clark</surname>
            <given-names>SH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chovnick</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Meiotic gene conversion tract length distribution within the rosy locus of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>137</volume>
          <fpage>1019</fpage>
          <lpage>1026</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7982556</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Cromie</surname>
            <given-names>GA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hyppa</surname>
            <given-names>RW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cam</surname>
            <given-names>HP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Farah</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Grewal</surname>
            <given-names>SI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>GR</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A discrete class of intergenic DNA dictates meiotic DNA break hotspots in fission yeast</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Genet</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>e141</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030141</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17722984</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>M&#xE9;zard</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Meiotic recombination hotspots in plants</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Soc Trans</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>531</fpage>
          <lpage>534</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BST0340531</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16856852</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Steiner</surname>
            <given-names>WW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Steiner</surname>
            <given-names>EM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Girvin</surname>
            <given-names>AR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Plewik</surname>
            <given-names>LE</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Novel nucleotide sequence motifs that produce hotspots of meiotic recombination in <italic>Schizosaccharomeces prombe</italic></article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>182</volume>
          <fpage>459</fpage>
          <lpage>469</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.109.101253</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19363124</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Jeffreys</surname>
            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>May</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Intense and highly localized gene conversion activity in human meiotic crossover hot spots</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>151</fpage>
          <lpage>156</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1287</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14704667</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B45">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hurst</surname>
            <given-names>LD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>GC</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The evolution of concerted evolution</article-title>
          <source>Proc R Soc Lond B</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>265</volume>
          <fpage>121</fpage>
          <lpage>127</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.1998.0272</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B46">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Black</surname>
            <given-names>BL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Olson</surname>
            <given-names>EN</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The MEF2A 3' untranslated region functions as a <italic>cis</italic>-acting translational repressor</article-title>
          <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>2756</fpage>
          <lpage>2763</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9111346</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B47">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Di Liegro</surname>
            <given-names>CM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bellafiore</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Izquierdo</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rantanen</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cuezva</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>3'-untranslated regions of oxidative phosphorylation mRNAs function in vivo as enhancers of translation</article-title>
          <source>Biochem J</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>109</fpage>
          <lpage>115</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/0264-6021:3520109</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B48">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hannon</surname>
            <given-names>GJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>MicroRNAs: small RNAs with a big role in gene regulation</article-title>
          <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>522</fpage>
          <lpage>531</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg1379</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15211354</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B49">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Bourtzis</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miller</surname>
            <given-names>TA</given-names>
          </name>
          <source>Insect Symbiosis</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <publisher-name>CRC Press/Taylor &amp;Francis, New York</publisher-name>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>276</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B50">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Boosalis</surname>
            <given-names>GM</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Hessian fly in relation to the development of crown and basal stem rot of wheat</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathol</source>
          <year>1954</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>224</fpage>
          <lpage>229</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B51">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Madan</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>CAP3: A DNA sequence assembly program</article-title>
          <source>Genome Res</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>45</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B52">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Chenna</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sugawara</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Koike</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lopez</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gibson</surname>
            <given-names>TJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Higgins</surname>
            <given-names>DG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thompson</surname>
            <given-names>JD</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Multiple sequence alignment with the Clustal series of programs</article-title>
          <source>Nucl Acid Res</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>3497</fpage>
          <lpage>3500</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg500</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B53">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Wilbur</surname>
            <given-names>WJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lipman</surname>
            <given-names>DJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Rapid similarity searches of nucleic acid and protein data banks</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>726</fpage>
          <lpage>730</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.80.3.726</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6572363</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B54">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>PAML 4: Phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>1586</fpage>
          <lpage>1591</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msm088</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483113</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B55">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Tamura</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dudley</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nei</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kumar</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>MEGA4: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>1596</fpage>
          <lpage>1599</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msm092</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488738</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B56">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>YC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reese</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wilde</surname>
            <given-names>GE</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Genes encoding a group of related small secreted proteins from the gut of Hessian fly larvae [<italic>Mayetiola destructor </italic>(Say)]</article-title>
          <source>Insect Sci</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>339</fpage>
          <lpage>348</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7917.2006.00102.x</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
