<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4792873</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.00307</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Plant Science</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Original Research</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The 160 bp Insertion in the Promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> Plays a Vital Role in Increasing Wheat Height</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lou</surname>
            <given-names>Xueyuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002">
            <sup>&#x2020;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Xin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002">
            <sup>&#x2020;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Aixia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pu</surname>
            <given-names>Mingyu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shoaib</surname>
            <given-names>Muhammad</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Dongcheng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Jiazhu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Aimin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Wenlong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
          <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/274272/overview"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <sup>1</sup>
        <institution>The State Key Laboratory of Plant Cell and Chromosome Engineering, Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology, Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>
        <country>Beijing, China</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <sup>2</sup>
        <institution>Graduate University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>
        <country>Beijing, China</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <sup>3</sup>
        <institution>The Collaborative Innovation Center for Grain Crops in Henan, Henan Agricultural University</institution>
        <country>Zhengzhou, China</country>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Edited by: <italic>Keqiang Wu, National Taiwan University, Taiwan</italic></p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Reviewed by: <italic>Yuri Shavrukov, University of Adelaide, Australia; Aizhong Cao, Nanjing Agricultural University, China</italic></p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: <italic>Aimin Zhang, <email xlink:type="simple">amzhang@genetics.ac.cn</email>; Wenlong Yang, <email xlink:type="simple">wlyang@genetics.ac.cn</email></italic></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn002">
          <p>
            <sup>&#x2020;</sup>
            <italic>These authors have contributed equally to this work.</italic>
          </p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn003">
          <p>This article was submitted to Plant Genetics and Genomics, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <elocation-id>307</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2016 Lou, Li, Li, Pu, Shoaib, Liu, Sun, Zhang and Yang.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Lou, Li, Li, Pu, Shoaib, Liu, Sun, Zhang and Yang</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The extensive use of two alleles (<italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic>) at the <italic>Rht-1</italic> locus in wheat allowed dramatic increases in yields, triggering the so-called &#x201C;Green Revolution.&#x201D; Here, we found that a new natural allelic variation (<italic>Rht-B1i</italic>) containing a single missense SNP (A614G) in the coding region significantly increased plant height against the genetic background of both <italic>Rht-D1a</italic> (11.68%) and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> (7.89%). To elucidate the molecular mechanism of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic>, we investigated the promoter region. Sequence analysis showed that the <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> promoter could be divided into two classes depending on the presence or absence of a specific 160 bp insertion: <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> (with the 160 bp insertion) and <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> (without the 160 bp insertion). The promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> contained 32 more possible <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements than <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>, including a unique auxin response element AUXREPSIAA4. Quantitative RT-PCR analysis indicated that the 160 bp insertion is likely to promote the transcription of the <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> gene. The coleoptile lengths of wheat varieties treated with IAA, GA<sub>3</sub>, and IAA/GA<sub>3</sub>, combined with the histochemical staining of transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> containing the <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> promoter, showed that the height-increasing effect of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> may be due to the synergistic action of IAA and GA<sub>3</sub>. These results augment our understanding of the regulatory mechanisms of <italic>Rht-1</italic> in wheat and provide new genetic resources for wheat improvement.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd><italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Rht-B1i</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>height-increasing effect</kwd>
        <kwd>promoter</kwd>
        <kwd>160 bp insertion</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source id="cn001">National Basic Research Program of China</funding-source>
          <award-id rid="cn001">2014CB138101</award-id>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source id="cn002">CAS Strategic Priority Program</funding-source>
          <award-id rid="cn002">XDA08010104</award-id>
        </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="6"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <equation-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="41"/>
        <page-count count="13"/>
        <word-count count="0"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The decrease in the stem stature of common wheat has resulted in improved lodging resistance and increased harvest index (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Gale and Youssefian, 1985</xref>; <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Youssefian et al., 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Miralles and Slafer, 1995</xref>). As a result, plant height has made a significant contribution to high and stable yields in common wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.).</p>
      <p>Several wheat loci are or were once associated with decreased plant height and these are termed as <italic>Reduced height</italic> (<italic>Rht</italic>). These loci include the three homoeologs of <italic>Rht-1</italic> (<italic>Rht-A1</italic>; <italic>Rht-B1</italic>; <italic>Rht-D1</italic>) and 19 other loci (<italic>Rht4</italic>&#x2013;<italic>9</italic>; <italic>Rht11</italic>&#x2013;<italic>23</italic>; <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">McIntosh et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2015</xref>). These <italic>Rht</italic> genes are divided into two subgroups, GA-sensitive genes and GA-insensitive genes, depending on their response to exogenous gibberellic acid (GA; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">B&#xF6;rner et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Pestsova et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2015</xref>).</p>
      <p>Among GA-insensitive semi-dwarfing genes, two genes in Norin 10, originally named <italic>Rht1</italic> and <italic>Rht2</italic>, were re-designated as <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic>, respectively, as they were found to be mutant alleles of the <italic>Rht-1</italic> loci on the short arms of chromosomes 4B and 4D (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Gale et al., 1975</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Gale and Marshall, 1976</xref>; <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">McVittie et al., 1978</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">B&#xF6;rner et al., 1996</xref>). Under near-isogenic genetic backgrounds, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> both have the ability to reduce plant height by 15&#x2013;20% (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Gale and Youssefian, 1985</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Flintham et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Miedaner and Voss, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Blake et al., 2009</xref>). In combination, they can reduce plant height by 40% (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Flintham et al., 1997</xref>). This effect is caused by a nucleotide substitution that creates a premature stop codon, resulting in truncated DELLA proteins in the region responsible for the GA response (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 1999</xref>). In the 1960s, the introduction of the <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> alleles in wheat resulted in a great increase in yield during the &#x2018;Green Revolution&#x2019; (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Hedden, 2003</xref>), which abated a major worldwide food shortage.</p>
      <p>At the <italic>Rht-B1</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1</italic> loci, five <italic>Rht-B1</italic> alleles (<italic>Rht-B1a&#x2013;e</italic>) and four <italic>Rht-D1</italic> alleles (<italic>Rht-D1a&#x2013;d</italic>) have been isolated and characterized in hexaploid wheat (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Pearce et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Li A.X. et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Li Y.Y. et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Wen et al., 2013</xref>). Compared with the wild-type alleles <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1a</italic>, the dwarfism conferred by <italic>Rht-B1b, Rht-B1d, Rht-B1e, Rht-D1b</italic>, and <italic>Rht-D1d</italic> is due to a single nucleotide change that introduces a premature stop codon in the DELLA region of encoded proteins (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Pearce et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Li A.X. et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2013</xref>). <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> derived from &#x201C;Tom Thumb&#x201D; differs from <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> by one 2 kb <italic>Veju</italic> retrotransposon insertion, three SNPs in the coding region and one 197-bp insertion and four SNPs in the 1-kb upstream sequence (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Wen et al., 2013</xref>). The intragenic insertion, which results in an in-frame 90-bp insertion in the transcript and a predicted 30-amino acid insertion within the DELLA domain, is primarily responsible for severe dwarfism (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Pearce et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Wen et al., 2013</xref>). In contrast, as the strongest height-reducing allele in wheat, <italic>Rht-D1c</italic> derived from &#x201C;Aibian 1&#x201D; generates a tandem segmental duplication (TSD) of a 1-Mb region, resulting in two copies of <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Pearce et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Li Y.Y. et al., 2012</xref>).</p>
      <p>To facilitate the understanding of the diversity of <italic>Rht-1</italic> and the utilization of new resources in breeding programs, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2013)</xref> previously identified six new <italic>Rht-A1</italic> allelic variations (<italic>Rht-A1b</italic>&#x2013;<italic>g</italic>), eight new <italic>Rht-B1</italic> allelic variations (<italic>Rht-B1h</italic>&#x2013;<italic>o</italic>), and six new <italic>Rht-D1</italic> allelic variations (<italic>Rht-D1e</italic>&#x2013;<italic>j</italic>) in Chinese wheat germplasm by a modified EcoTILLING method. <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2013)</xref> found that <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> (E205G) have frequencies of 4.2% in Chinese wheat MCC and 2.28% in 1,537 important Chinese wheat cultivars and germplasms, respectively. These frequencies are relatively high among the 10 <italic>Rht-B1</italic> allelic variations (<italic>Rht-B1a, b, h</italic>&#x2013;<italic>o</italic>). Recently, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Wilhelm et al. (2013b)</xref> discovered new haplotypes of <italic>Rht-1</italic> in western wheat cultivars and tetraploid and diploid wheat, and found that three haplotypes (<italic>Rht-B1a_2, 3, 4</italic>) also contained an E205G substitution in the poly S/T/V region. Moreover, there are five <italic>Rht-B1a_2</italic>, one <italic>Rht-B1a_3</italic>, and two <italic>Rht-B1a_4</italic> in the 66 bread wheat accessions (nine accessions for bread wheat set 1, 12 accessions for a subset of BW1 accessions widely grown in the UK, and 45 accessions from the INRA worldwide bread wheat core collection of 372 accessions), the frequency of E205G substitution is 12.12%. Sequence alignment revealed that the open reading frame (ORF) sequences of the three haplotypes (<italic>Rht-B1a_2, 3, 4</italic>) in <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Wilhelm et al. (2013b)</xref> is identical to <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> in <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2013)</xref>, indicating that <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> widely exist in the Chinese and western wheat cultivars.</p>
      <p>Interestingly, the new natural allelic variation <italic>Rht-B1i</italic>, which contains a single missense SNP (A614G) in the coding region resulting in E205G, may increase plant height (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2013</xref>). However, the underlying mechanism for this effect is unclear. Current studies mainly focus on alleles with dwarfing effects. Moderate dwarfing can increase grain yield in wheat breeding, but excessive dwarfing reduces production owing to decreased biomass. Reports of alleles with height-increasing effects are extremely rare, and elucidating this effect of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> may enable the allele to contribute to ameliorating excessive dwarfism in wheat. In this study, we isolated and characterized the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic>. According to the presence or absence of 160 bp insertion, <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> could be divided into <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> (with 160 bp insertion in promoter) and <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> (without 160 bp insertion in promoter) using molecular markers and sequencing analysis. Quantitative RT-PCR analysis revealed that the 160 bp insertion may promote the transcription of the <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> gene. The coleoptile lengths of wheat varieties treated with IAA, GA<sub>3</sub>, and IAA/GA<sub>3</sub>, combined with the histochemical staining of transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> containing the <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> promoter, indicated that the height-increasing effect of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> may be due to the synergistic action of IAA and GA<sub>3</sub>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Plant Height Determinations</title>
        <p>The Chinese wheat micro-core collections (MCC) consist of Chinese Spring (CS), 155 landraces, 89 Chinese wheat-bred cultivars, and 17 introduced foreign accessions. The MCC is representative of 1% of the national wheat collection but over 70% of the genetic diversity (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2013</xref>). We planted accessions containing five genotypes (<italic>Rht-B1a, b, h</italic>&#x2013;<italic>j</italic>) against the genetic background of <italic>Rht-D1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> in the field site of the Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology, Chinese Academy of Sciences (Beijing, China) in 2012 and 2013. There are one accession &#x2018;Chinese Spring&#x2019; of <italic>B1a</italic>/<italic>D1a</italic>, eleven accessions of <italic>B1b</italic>/<italic>D1a</italic>, eight accessions of <italic>B1h</italic>/<italic>D1a</italic>, 10 accessions of <italic>B1i</italic>/<italic>D1a</italic> (8 <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> and 2 <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic>), 11 accessions of <italic>B1j</italic>/<italic>D1a</italic>, five accessions of <italic>B1a</italic>/<italic>D1b</italic>, five accessions of <italic>B1b</italic>/<italic>D1b</italic>, three accessions of <italic>B1h</italic>/<italic>D1b</italic>, four accessions of <italic>B1i</italic>/<italic>D1b</italic>, and two accessions of <italic>B1j</italic>/<italic>D1b</italic>. Each accession was planted in 2-m two-row plot with 25 cm between rows and 40 seeds per row, and repeated for three times. Plants were managed using standard wheat production management. We measured plant height at 20 days after flowering using 10 randomly selected plants from each plot, and calculated the means and standard deviations of plant height using Microsoft Office Excel (2013). Differences among groups were analyzed with analysis of variance (ANOVA) procedure using SAS software (version 9.1).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Coleoptile Length Determinations</title>
        <p>We chose CS and four varieties containing <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> (three varieties of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> genotype H8, H83, and H215 containing a promoter with the 160 bp insertion as well as one variety of <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> genotype H251 containing a promoter without the 160 bp insertion) to assess the effects of IAA and GA<sub>3</sub> on coleoptile elongation. Seeds were treated with 1% (w/v) H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in 4&#xB0;C for 24 h and rinsed three times with sterile deionized water, then cultured individually with ddH<sub>2</sub>O (control), IAA (10 &#x3BC;M), GA<sub>3</sub> (10 &#x3BC;M), or IAA/GA<sub>3</sub> (1:1) in a greenhouse under controlled conditions (23&#xB0;C, dark) for 7 days. We measured coleoptile length for each treatment. Each experiment used 20 plants, and all experiments were carried out in triplicate. We calculated the means and standard deviations of coleoptile length using Microsoft Office Excel (2013). Differences among groups were analyzed with analysis of variance (ANOVA) procedure using SAS software (version 9.1).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Wheat DNA and RNA Isolation</title>
        <p>We grew 70 wheat lines containing different allelic variations at the <italic>Rht-1</italic> locus (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>), including CS, Mercia-carrying <italic>Rht-B1e</italic>, 68 Chinese wheat MCC varieties (including 23 Chinese wheat landraces, 37 Chinese wheat bread cultivars, and eight introduced foreign accessions), and 35 Chinese wheat-leading cultivars and important germplasm (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S2</xref>). All plants were grown in a greenhouse under controlled conditions (23&#xB0;C, 16:8 photoperiod) for 2 weeks. We collected young leaves for genomic DNA extraction using the hexadecyl trimethyl ammonium bromide (CTAB) method (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Aldrich, 1993</xref>).</p>
        <p>We randomly selected 30 wheat lines from 46 <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> varieties (11 Chinese wheat MCC lines and 35 Chinese wheat-leading cultivars and important germplasm lines). All plants were grown in a greenhouse under controlled conditions (23&#xB0;C, 16:8 photoperiod) for 2 weeks, and we collected samples of their young leaves to isolate total RNA using the RNeasy Plant Mini Kit (QIAGEN, Germany). Flag leaves and the fourth internodes from four varieties of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> genotype H8, H83, H213, H215, and one variety of <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> genotype H251 at the heading stage were also sampled for RNA extraction. CS was used as control variety. The first strand of cDNA was synthesized using FastQuant RT Kit (with gDNase; TIANGEN, Beijing) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Cloning of Promoters from <italic>Rht-1</italic> Allelic Variations</title>
        <p>To clone the promoters of the <italic>Rht-1</italic> allelic variations, we designed two primers, PB-CF and PB-CR (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S3</xref>), according to the sequence of <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> (FR719732, <italic>Triticum aestivum Rht-B1a</italic> gene for DELLA protein). We performed PCR in 20-&#x3BC;L reaction volumes containing 200 ng DNA template, 0.4 &#x3BC;M forward and reverse primers, 1 U TaKaRa LA Taq (Takara, Biotechnology Co., Ltd, Dalian, China), 1 &#xD7; GC Buffer I, and 0.4 mM of each dNTP under the following conditions: 94&#xB0;C for 5 min, followed by 35 cycles of 94&#xB0;C for 30 s, 58&#xB0;C for 30 s, and 72&#xB0;C for 2 min; a final extension was performed at 72&#xB0;C for 10 min. PCR products were cloned into pGEM-T easy vectors (Promega, Madison, WI, USA), introduced into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, and 10 positive independent clones were commercially sequenced. The promoter sequences and their GC characteristics were analyzed using DNAMAN software, and their <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements were predicted using PLACE and PlantCARE.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Allele-Specific Markers for <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic></title>
        <p>To facilitate the use of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> in wheat-breeding programs, we developed two allele-specific PCR markers, B1i-MF1/MR1 and B1i-MF2/MR2 (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S3</xref>), based on the 160 bp insertion of the promoter. PCR was performed on an ABI 9700 thermal cycler (Applied Biosystems) as described above. The PCR products were separated on a 2% agarose gel and visualized using a UV spectrometer after ethidium bromide staining.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Quantitative Real-Time PCR Analysis</title>
        <p>We carried out quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) to determine the transcript level of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> using the LightCycler 480 system (Roche, Indianapolis, IN, USA) with SYBR Green I Master (Roche, Indianapolis, IN, USA). The gene-specific primers Rht-B1.EF and Rht-B1.ER (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S3</xref>) were used for gene expression analysis with the <italic>Ta4045</italic> gene (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Paolacci et al., 2009</xref>) as a reference. All qRT-PCR experiments were performed independently with three biological and three technical replicates, respectively. We calculated the relative expression of each gene according to the comparative CT method (&#x394;&#x394;CT; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Livak and Schmittgen, 2001</xref>) and calculated the means and standard deviations using Microsoft Office Excel (2013). Differences among groups were analyzed with analysis of variance (ANOVA) procedure using SAS software (version 9.1).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Expression of the GUS Gene Driven by the Promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic></title>
        <p>To construct the plasmid for promoter analysis, we cloned promoters of <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> with the primers PB-<italic>Pst</italic>I-F/PB-<italic>Nco</italic>I-R to introduce <italic>Pst</italic>I and <italic>Nco</italic>I sites (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S3</xref>). The amplified fragment was inserted into the pGEM-T vector and recombined with pCAMBIA 3301 (<italic>35S::GUS</italic>) by replacing the <italic>35S</italic> promoter before the <italic>GUS</italic> reporter gene to generate <italic>pB1a::GUS</italic> and <italic>pB1i-1::GUS</italic>. The plant binary vectors were introduced into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain GV3101 using the freezing and thawing method and then transformed into <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> using the flower-dipping method (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Clough and Bent, 1998</xref>, modified from <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bechtold et al., 1993</xref>). Transgenic lines were selected on MS (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Murashige and Skoog, 1962</xref>) plates with PPT (phosphinothricin, 5 mg/L), and more than 20 transgenic lines were obtained. Histochemical detection of GUS activity (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Jefferson et al., 1987</xref>) was carried out on the T<sub>3</sub> transgenic plants. T<sub>3</sub> plants were grown in MS medium with PPT (5 mg/L) for 7 days, then moved to MS medium with GA<sub>3</sub> (10 &#x3BC;M), IAA (10 &#x3BC;M), or IAA/GA<sub>3</sub> (1:1) and grown for 5 days. Seedlings were fixed in 90% (v/v) acetone on ice for 10 min, then infiltrated in GUS staining solution [50 mM sodium phosphate buffer, pH 7.0, 10 mM EDTA, 0.01% Triton X-100, 1 mM potassium ferricyanide, 1 mM potassium ferrocyanide, 500 &#x3BC;g/mL 5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indoyl-&#x3B2;-<sc>D</sc>-glucuronic acid (X-gluc)], and incubated overnight at 37&#xB0;C. Later, the GUS solution was replaced with 100% (v/v) ethanol at room temperature for 6 h and kept in 70% (v/v) ethanol at 4&#xB0;C. The stained seedlings were observed and photographed using light microscopy (Olympus SZX16, Olympus Co., Japan).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title><italic>Rht-B1i</italic> Significantly Increases the Plant Height of Wheat</title>
        <p>We analyzed the effects of five genotypes (<italic>Rht-B1a, b, h</italic>&#x2013;<italic>j</italic>) on wheat plant height against the backgrounds of <italic>Rht-D1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> using 2 years (2012, 2013) of agronomic trait data (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></bold>). Against the background of <italic>Rht-D1a, Rht-B1b</italic> significantly reduced plant height by 24.27% as compared with <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>. The plant heights for <italic>Rht-B1h</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1j</italic> were roughly the same as those for <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>, whereas the height of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> was significantly increased, by 11.68%, compared with that of <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>. The plant heights for all genotypes were smaller against the background of <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> than against the background of <italic>Rht-D1a</italic>. <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> reduced plant height by 10.91% compared with <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>, whereas <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> increased plant height by 7.89% compared with <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>. These results indicate that <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> significantly increased wheat plant height against both the <italic>Rht-D1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> backgrounds.</p>
        <fig id="F1" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Plant height in different <italic>Rht-B1</italic> genotypes of wheat.</bold> The blue column represents <italic>Rht-B1</italic> allelic variations against the <italic>Rht-D1a</italic> background, and the green column represents <italic>Rht-B1</italic> allelic variations against the <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> background; the left box compares plant height for different genotypes using <italic>B1a</italic>/<italic>D1a</italic> as a control, and the right box compares plant height for different genotypes using <italic>B1a</italic>/<italic>D1b</italic> as a control. <sup>&#x2217;, &#x2217;&#x2217;</sup>Denotes significant differences at 5 and 1% probability levels, respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-00307-g001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>The Promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> Contains a 160 bp Insertion</title>
        <p>To further investigate the height-increasing effects of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic>, we analyzed the entire coding region of <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1i</italic>. Sequence alignment showed that the missense SNP occurring in <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> was A614G, giving rise to an E205G amino acid change in the Poly S/T/V region of the encoded DELLA protein (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2013</xref>). The SIFT (Sorting Intolerant from Tolerant, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Sim et al., 2012</xref>) score of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> was 0.41, indicating that the variation had no obvious effect on the protein: non-synonymous SNPs are predicted to be damaging to the encoded protein if the SIFT score is &lt;0.05. Therefore, the height-increasing effect of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> is unlikely to result directly from the missense mutation in the coding region. Next, we cloned the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> using PB-CF/CR primers (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S3</xref>). Sequence alignment revealed a 160 bp insertion at 365 bp upstream of the start codon in the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic>, whereas this insertion was not found in the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>.</p>
        <p>To identify whether the 160 bp insertion was specific to <italic>Rht-B1i</italic>, we cloned the promoters of <italic>Rht-B1</italic> allelic variations from <italic>Rht-B1e</italic> (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Li A.X. et al., 2012</xref>) and 10 other <italic>Rht-B1</italic> allelic variations (<italic>Rht-B1a, b, h</italic>&#x2013;<italic>o</italic>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2013</xref>). The promoters of <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> (P0, 2040 bp) and seven other <italic>Rht-B1</italic> allelic variations (<italic>Rht-B1b, e, j, k, m&#x2013;o</italic>; P1, 2040 bp, GenBank accession no. LN907868) were identical; the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1h</italic> (P2, 2237 bp, the GenBank accession no. LN907869) contained seven SNPs and a 197 bp insertion at 596 bp upstream of the start codon; the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> (P3, 2200 bp, GenBank accession no. LN907870) carried a 160 bp insertion at 365 bp upstream of the start codon; and the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1l</italic> (P4, 2020 bp, GenBank accession no. LN907871) had a 20-bp deletion at 3 bp upstream of the start codon (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>, Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>). The 160 bp insertion can only be found in <italic>Rht-B1i</italic>, nevertheless, two of 11 MCC accessions containing <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> have no 160 bp insertion (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="F2" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Sequence alignment for promoters of <italic>Rht-B1</italic> allelic variations in wheat.</bold> Four promoters cloned from seventy wheat lines containing different allelic variations at the <italic>Rht-B1</italic> loci. Compared with the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> (P0), P1 was coincide exactly with it, P2 had a 197 bp insertion (sequences on blue lines), P3 had a 160 bp insertion (sequences on red lines), and P4 had a 20 bp deletion (sequences on green line).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-00307-g002"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To facilitate the use of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> in wheat-breeding programs, and ascertain whether all the accessions containing <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> have 160 bp insertion in the promoter, we developed two allele-specific PCR markers (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S3</xref>), B1i-MF1/MR1 (dominant) and B1i-MF2/MR2 (codominant), based on the 160 bp insertion of <italic>Rht-B1i.</italic> The amplification products were 330 bp and 586 bp, respectively, in most <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> varieties (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref></bold>). The PCR products of B1i-MF1/MR1 (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref></bold>) showed no amplification among the <italic>Rht-B1</italic> allelic variations <italic>Rht-B1a, Rht-B1b, Rht-B1e</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1h</italic>, whereas nine of the 12 varieties carrying <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> produced a positive 330-bp band. The PCR products of B1i-MF2/MR2 (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref></bold>) displayed 426-bp bands from <italic>Rht-B1a, Rht-B1b, Rht-B1e</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1h</italic>, whereas 586 bp bands were observed in nine of 12 varieties containing <italic>Rht-B1i</italic>. Hence, the primers B1i-MF1/MR1 and B1i-MF2/MR2 are allele-specific for most <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> accessions. However, there were three accessions (Wumangchunmai, Kashi 1, and Jimai 37) that contained <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> but could not be identified by these two markers. We therefore amplified and sequenced their promoters and found that they lacked a 160 bp insertion. Using B1i-MF1/MR1 and B1i-MF2/MR2 to screen 262 Chinese wheat MCC and 1,537 Chinese wheat-leading cultivars and important germplasms, we found 3.4 and 2.02% frequencies of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic>, respectively. This is lower than the 4.2 and 2.28%, respectively, reported by <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2013)</xref>, indicating that the <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> genotype might have other haplotypes.</p>
        <fig id="F3" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold><italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> significantly increases the plant height of wheat. (A)</bold> PCR with B1i-MF1/MR1, <bold>(B)</bold> PCR with B1i-MF2/MR2, <bold>(C)</bold> Plant height in <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> genotypes of wheat. Lanes: <italic>M</italic>, molecular weight markers (DNA marker III, Tiangen Biotech Co. Ltd, China), the bands are 4,500, 3,000, 2,000, 1,200, 800, 500, and 200 bp, respectively; <italic>1</italic>, CS (<italic>Rht-B1a</italic>), <italic>2</italic>, Jinchun 3 (<italic>Rht-B1b</italic>), <italic>3</italic>, Mercia (<italic>Rht-B1e</italic>), <italic>4</italic>, Zhongyou 9507 (<italic>Rht-B1h</italic>), <italic>5</italic>, Guangtou (<italic>Rht-B1i</italic>), <italic>6</italic>, KaBka3 (<italic>Rht-B1i</italic>), <italic>7</italic>, Triumph (<italic>Rht-B1i</italic>), <italic>8</italic>, Dalibanmang (<italic>Rht-B1i</italic>), <italic>9</italic>, Huzhuhong (<italic>Rht-B1i</italic>), <italic>10</italic>, Dingxi 24 (<italic>Rht-B1i</italic>), <italic>11</italic>, Wumangchunmai (<italic>Rht-B1i</italic>), <italic>12</italic>, Kashi 1 (<italic>Rht-B1i</italic>), <italic>13</italic>, Xinshuguang 6 (<italic>Rht-B1i</italic>), <italic>14</italic>, Jinmai 56 (<italic>Rht-B1i</italic>), <italic>15</italic>, Jinan24 (<italic>Rht-B1i</italic>), <italic>16</italic>, Jimai 37 (<italic>Rht-B1i</italic>). The blue column represents <italic>Rht-B1</italic> allelic variations against the <italic>Rht-D1a</italic> background, and the green column represents <italic>Rht-B1</italic> allelic variations against the <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> background; the left box compares plant height for different genotypes using <italic>B1a</italic>/<italic>D1a</italic> as a control, and the right box compares plant height for different genotypes using <italic>B1a</italic>/<italic>D1b</italic> as a control. <sup>&#x2217;, &#x2217;&#x2217;</sup>Denotes significant differences at 5 and 1% probability levels, respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-00307-g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Therefore, we cloned and sequenced the promoters from 46 lines, which were validated as carrying <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> from 262 Chinese wheat MCC (11 lines) and 1,537 Chinese wheat-leading cultivars and important germplasms (35 lines). Of 11 Chinese wheat MCC, nine accessions had the 160 bp insertion; among 35 Chinese wheat-leading cultivars and important germplasms, 25 lines had the 160 bp insertion (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S2</xref>). Consequently, we subclassified the <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> genotype into <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> (75.8% had a 160 bp insertion in the promoter) and <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> (24.2% were missing a 160 bp insertion in the promoter). To identify the effect of the 160 bp insertion, we analyzed the plant height of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref></bold>). Whether under the background of <italic>Rht-D1a</italic> or <italic>Rht-D1b, Rht-B1i-1</italic> significantly increased plant height by 10.18 and 9.89% as compared with <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>, meanwhile, the height of <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> was increased, by 3.64 and 3.54%, with no significance, indicating that <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> significantly increased wheat plant height under both <italic>Rht-D1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> backgrounds.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>The 160 bp Insertion Affect <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> Expression</title>
        <p>Structural analysis of promoters has wide implications in molecular biology, because it allows the prediction of gene expression profiles. We analyzed the GC content in the 1,500-bp section upstream from the translation initiation codon of the <italic>Rht-B1</italic> allelic variations and found that the AT-content of the four <italic>Rht-B1</italic> promoters (P1, 51.47%; P2, 52.53%; P3, 51.60%; P4, 51.80%) was greater than the corresponding GC content (48.53, 47.47, 48.40, and 48.20%, respectively), which is consistent with a role as an AT-rich plant gene-promoter element. To study the contribution of the 160 bp insertion to gene transcription, we performed quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) using the seedlings of CS and 30 other varieties containing <italic>Rht-B1i</italic>, flag leaves and the fourth internodes from four varieties of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> genotype H8, H83, H213, H215, and one variety of <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> genotype H251 at the heading stage, and using <italic>Ta4045</italic> as the reference gene. For seedlings (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref></bold>), all eight varieties containing <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> (without the 160 bp insertion) expressed lower levels than wild-type <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>, but these differences were not statistically significant. Among the 22 varieties carrying <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> (with the 160 bp insertion), 13 expressed higher levels than <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> (statistically significant in 2/13), whereas nine varieties expressed lower levels than <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>. This indicates that the 160 bp insertion can have differential effects on gene expression. For flag leaves (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref></bold>), the variety containing <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> also expressed lower level than <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>, whereas three of the four varieties containing <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> expressed significantly higher levels than <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>. For the fourth internodes (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref></bold>), the expression level of the variety containing <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> was significantly lower than <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>, however, the expression levels of three varieties containing <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> were significantly higher than <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>. Overall, the 160 bp insertion can affect the expression of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic>.</p>
        <fig id="F4" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Expression analysis of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1i-2.</italic> (A)</bold> Expression analysis in seedlings, <bold>(B)</bold> Expression analysis in flag leaves and the fourth internodes. The red line shown the relative expression levels of <italic>Rht-B1</italic> in CS which containing <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> (control). <sup>&#x2217;, &#x2217;&#x2217;</sup>Denotes significant differences at 5 and 1% probability levels, respectively. +, &#x2013; Denote <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> containing the 160 bp insertion and <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> missing the 160 bp insertion, respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-00307-g004"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>The Height-Increasing Effect of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> May Be Related to Auxin</title>
        <p>We carried out predictive analysis of the <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements in the promoters of <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> using PLACE<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">1</xref></sup> and PlantCARE<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn02">2</xref></sup>. The analysis revealed various possible <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements in the two promoters: in addition to basic <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements, such as TATA-box, CAAT-box, and so on, there were many possible <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements that were related to phyto-hormone response, tissue-specific expression, and stress induction. This suggests that <italic>Rht-B1</italic> may participate in the regulation of multiple phyto-hormones and environmental signaling pathways. There were 453 and 485 possible <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements in the promoters of <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic>, respectively, with the 32 additional possible <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements located in the 160 bp insertion in the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref></bold>). Among these 32 additional elements, the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> contained four unique <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements, including an auxin response element (AUXREPSIAA4). This indicates that the regulatory network of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> is highly complex and that the height-increasing effect of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> may be related to auxin.</p>
        <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p><italic>Cis</italic>-acting elements analysis of the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1i.</italic></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</th>
                <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARR1AT</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARR1-binding element</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUXREPSIAA4</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auxin responsive element</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INRNTPSADB</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Light-responsive element</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB1AT</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB recognition site</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB2CONSENSUSAT</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB recognition site</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EECCRCAH1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB binding site</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB2AT</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB binding site</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYBATRD22</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB binding site</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYBCORE</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB binding site</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACTFTPPCA1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required for mesophyll expression</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DOFCOREZM</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Core site required for binding of Dof proteins</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NODCON2GM</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative nodulin consensus sequences</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ROOTMOTIFTAPOX1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Motif found both in promoters of rolD</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RHERPATEXPA7</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root Hair-specific <italic>cis</italic>-elements</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RYREPEATBNNAPA</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required for seed specific expression</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RYREPEATGMGY2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required for seed specific expression</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RYREPEATLEGUMINBOX</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required for seed specific expression</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANAERO2CONSENSUS</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Involved in the fermentative pathway</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAATBOX1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAAT promoter consensus sequence</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CURECORECR</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Copper-response element</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GATABOX</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required for high level, light regulated, and tissue specific expression</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSE2ROOTNODULE</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organ-specific elements activated in infected cells of root nodules</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TATABOXOSPAL</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding site for OsTBP2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>To study the effects of the 160 bp insertion on the function of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic>, we treated CS, three varieties containing <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> (H8, H83, and H215 which had significantly higher expression levels), and one variety containing <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> (H251) with IAA, GA<sub>3</sub>, and IAA/GA<sub>3</sub> (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref></bold>). The coleoptile length of CS carrying <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> was significantly reduced after IAA treatment, but it clearly increased after GA<sub>3</sub> and IAA/GA<sub>3</sub> treatment, indicating that <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> has a strong response to IAA, GA<sub>3</sub>, and IAA/GA<sub>3</sub>. However, we observed no significant difference in the coleoptile length of variety containing <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> after IAA, GA<sub>3</sub>, or IAA/GA<sub>3</sub> treatment, indicating that <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> was insensitive to IAA, GA<sub>3</sub>, and IAA/GA<sub>3</sub>. The coleoptile length of varieties containing <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> showed no significant difference after GA<sub>3</sub> treatment, but it significantly increased after IAA and, particularly, IAA/GA<sub>3</sub> treatment. This suggests that <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> is also insensitive to GA<sub>3</sub> and that the height-increasing effect of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> might be caused by the synergistic action of IAA and GA<sub>3</sub>.</p>
        <fig id="F5" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>The coleoptile length of wheat varieties with <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic>.</bold> The phyto-hormone treatments of three genotypes, <italic>Rht-B1a, Rht-B1i-1</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic>, with ddH<sub>2</sub>O as a control. <sup>&#x2217;&#x2217;</sup>Denote significant differences at the 1% probability level. +, &#x2013; Denote <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> containing the 160 bp insertion and <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> missing the 160 bp insertion, respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-00307-g005"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>The Promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> Plays a Role in the Response to GA<sub>3</sub> and IAA</title>
        <p>To study the response of the promoters to exogenous IAA and GA<sub>3</sub>, we fused the promoters of <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> (<italic>pB1a</italic>, 2,040 bp) and <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> (<italic>pB1i-1</italic>, 2,200 bp) with the <italic>GUS</italic> (&#x3B2;-glucuronidase) reporter gene using the binary vector pCAMBIA 3301-GUS. Vectors were then transformed into <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ecotype Col-0. The transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings treated with GA<sub>3</sub> had slender roots (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A&#x2013;C</xref></bold>), those treated with IAA had more lateral roots (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D&#x2013;F</xref></bold>), and those treated with IAA/GA<sub>3</sub> had slender lateral roots (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6G&#x2013;I</xref></bold>). The <italic>35S::GUS</italic> transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings expressed strong GUS activity in the entire plant after GA<sub>3</sub> (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref></bold>), IAA (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D</xref></bold>), and IAA/GA<sub>3</sub> (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6G</xref></bold>) treatment. After GA<sub>3</sub> treatment, the <italic>pB1a::GUS</italic> (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref></bold>) and <italic>pB1i-1::GUS</italic> (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref></bold>) transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings both expressed strong GUS activity in leaves and stems and weak GUS activity in roots, although the difference was non-significant. After treated with IAA and IAA/GA<sub>3</sub>, the <italic>pB1a::GUS</italic> transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6E,H</xref></bold>) primarily expressed GUS activity in leaves and stems. However, the <italic>pB1i-1::GUS</italic> transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6F,I</xref></bold>) strongly expressed GUS activity not only in leaves and stems but also in roots, illustrating that the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> played a role in the response to IAA and IAA/GA<sub>3</sub>. The above results are in accordance with the predictive analysis of <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements in promoters and with the coleoptile lengths of wheat varieties treated with IAA, GA<sub>3</sub>, and IAA/GA<sub>3</sub>, demonstrating that the height-increasing effect of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> may be caused by the synergistic effects of IAA and GA<sub>3</sub>.</p>
        <fig id="F6" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 6</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>The histochemical staining of phyto-hormone-treated transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings.</bold><italic>pB1a</italic> represents promoter of <italic>Rht-B1a, pB1i-1</italic> represents promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic>. <bold>(A&#x2013;C)</bold>
<italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings treated with GA<sub>3</sub>: <bold>(A)</bold>
<italic>35S::GUS</italic> transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedling, <bold>(B)</bold>
<italic>pB1a::GUS</italic> transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedling, <bold>(C)</bold>
<italic>pB1i-1::GUS</italic> transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedling. <bold>(D&#x2013;F)</bold>
<italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings treated with IAA: <bold>(D)</bold>
<italic>35S::GUS</italic> transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedling, <bold>(E)</bold>
<italic>pB1a::GUS</italic> transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedling, <bold>(F)</bold>
<italic>pB1i-1::GUS</italic> transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedling. <bold>(G&#x2013;I)</bold>
<italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings treated with IAA/GA<sub>3</sub>: <bold>(G)</bold>
<italic>35S::GUS</italic> transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedling, <bold>(H)</bold>
<italic>pB1a::GUS</italic> transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedling, <bold>(I)</bold>
<italic>pB1i-1::GUS</italic> transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedling.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-00307-g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The primary function of the <italic>Rht-1</italic> gene is to reduce the plant height of wheat. <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">B&#xF6;rner et al. (1996)</xref> found that the relative strength of this effect among alleles at <italic>Rht-1</italic> loci is <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> &lt; <italic>Rht-B1d</italic> &lt; <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> &lt; <italic>Rht-B1e</italic> &lt; <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>, and <italic>Rht-D1a</italic> &lt; <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> &lt; <italic>Rht-D1d</italic> &lt; <italic>Rht-D1c</italic>. Among these <italic>Rht</italic> alleles, the two &#x2018;green revolution&#x2019; genes, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic>, are the most economically important and, by far, the most commonly used. Therefore we analyzed the effects of <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> on the plant height of wheat against the genetic backgrounds of <italic>Rht-D1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> using 2 years (2012, 2013) of agronomic traits data. We quantified the effect in terms of the percentage reduction in plant height after the introduction of the <italic>Rht-1</italic> gene. Compared with the wild-type gene <italic>Rht-B1a, Rht-B1b</italic> significantly reduced plant height by 24.27 and 11.68% against the backgrounds of <italic>Rht-D1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic>, respectively. <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>+<italic>Rht-D1b</italic> reduced plant height by a statistically significant 38%. <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Flintham et al. (1997)</xref> also reported that <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> has the ability to reduce plant height by 14% but that <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> + <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> can reduce plant height by 42%, as can two copies of either <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> or <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> against near-isogenic backgrounds. Current studies are focusing on alleles with dwarfing effects; <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> are also associated with increased harvestable yield under favorable conditions (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Gale and Youssefian, 1985</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Flintham et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Chapman et al., 2007</xref>). However, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> also contribute to reduced coleoptile length and seedling vigor (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Rebetzke et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Addisu et al., 2009</xref>) and may reduce crop water-use efficiency in unfavorable environments (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Butler et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Chapman et al., 2007</xref>).</p>
      <p>The discovery of new beneficial <italic>Rht-1</italic> alleles is very important for wheat-breeding programs. Our previous study (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2013</xref>) identified six new <italic>Rht-A1</italic> allelic variations (<italic>Rht-A1b</italic>&#x2013;<italic>g</italic>), eight new <italic>Rht-B1</italic> allelic variations (<italic>Rht-B1h</italic>&#x2013;<italic>o</italic>), and six new <italic>Rht-D1</italic> allelic variations (<italic>Rht-D1e</italic>&#x2013;<italic>j</italic>) by a modified EcoTILLING method. Among these, <italic>Rht-B1h, Rht-B1i</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1j</italic> have relatively high frequencies in Chinese wheat MCC and Chinese wheat-leading cultivars and important germplasms. Interestingly, <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> containing a single missense SNP (A614G) in the coding region significantly increased wheat plant height against the background of both <italic>Rht-D1a</italic> (11.68%) and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> (7.89%), suggesting that <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> could counteract the effects of <italic>Rht-D1b</italic>. Elucidating the height-increasing effect of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> will contribute to our understanding of the regulatory mechanism of <italic>Rht-1</italic> and aid in the use of <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> for ameliorating excessive dwarfism in wheat.</p>
      <p>The missense SNP occurring in <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> results in an E205G amino acid change in the Poly S/T/V region of the encoded DELLA protein. However, the SIFT score (0.41) indicates that the mutation has no obvious effect on the protein (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2013</xref>), suggesting that the height-increasing effect does not result directly from the missense mutation in the coding region. The expression of a protein depends on the transcription induction of the corresponding gene; therefore, the analysis of promoter regions is highly relevant. <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2011)</xref> found that base mutants in the pyrimidine box upstream of the <italic>BnGID1</italic> sequence probably explain the low expression level of the GID1 protein. Similarly, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Park et al. (2013)</xref> showed that the DELLA and BOI proteins inhibit GA responses by binding to the promoters of GA-responsive genes. Recognizing the importance of these regions, we isolated the promoters of <italic>Rht-B1</italic> alleles, found a 160 bp insertion, and classified <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> into <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> (with the 160 bp insertion in the promoter) and <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> (without the 160 bp insertion in the promoter) genotypes. <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Wilhelm et al. (2013b)</xref> directly sequenced the ORF and 5&#x2032; and 3&#x2032; flanking regions in western bread cultivars and tetraploid and diploid wheat and also identified three haplotypes (<italic>Rht-B1a_2, 3, 4</italic>) that have a 160 bp insertion in the 5&#x2032; flanking regions. Sequence alignment revealed several variants of <italic>Rht-B1i: Rht-B1a_2, Rht-B1a_3</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1a_4</italic>. <italic>Rht-B1a_2</italic> is identical to <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic>; <italic>Rht-B1a_3</italic> has two SNPs in the 5&#x2032; flanking region; and <italic>Rht-B1a_4</italic> has a CTA insertion in the 3&#x2032; flanking region. The <italic>Rht-B1</italic> 160 bp insertion is also present in a high frequency in western wheat accessions, and has a wide geographic distribution, suggesting that they are prevalent in modern bread wheat varieties. But the 160 insertion was not identified in any tetraploid and diploid wheat accessions, indicating that it is a recent event. In addition, the 160 bp insertion occurs in the middle of a highly conserved non-coding sequences among three wheat <italic>Rht-1</italic> homoeologs and in <italic>Rht-1 Poaceae</italic> orthologs, could be important <italic>Rht-1</italic> regulatory regions (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Wilhelm et al., 2013a</xref>,<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>).</p>
      <p><italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> with the 160 bp insertion in the promoter significantly increases the plant height of wheat against both the <italic>Rht-D1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> backgrounds. To study the contribution of the 160 bp insertion to gene transcription, we analyzed the expression profiles of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> with <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> as a control. qRT-PCR analysis of CS and varieties containing <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> at the seedling and heading stage indicated that the 160 bp insertion might affect gene expression. At the seedling stage, nine of 22 varieties containing <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> and all eight varieties containing <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> expressed lower levels than wild-type <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>, whereas other 13 of 22 varieties carrying <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> expressed higher levels than <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> (statistically significant in 2/13). Furthermore, at the heading stage, the variety H251 containing <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> expressed significant lower level than <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> in the fourth internodes, whereas, the expression levels of three varieties H8, H83, and H215 containing <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> were significantly higher than <italic>Rht-B1a</italic> in flag leaves and the fourth internodes. Although the <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> gene was expressed at different levels in different varieties at seedling and heading stage, the general trend is relatively consistent, indicating the 160 bp insertion is likely to promote the transcription of the <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> gene. Compared with the three spring wheat varieties H8, H83, and H215, the expression levels of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> in H213 (which is a weak winter wheat variety from Qinghai province, China) were lower than that of CS at seedling and heading stage. Their difference in the expression levels of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> may be caused by the genetic backgrounds, this needs further investigation. <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Wilhelm et al. (2013b)</xref> reported that the insertions may have a minor effect on <italic>Rht-B1</italic> transcript abundance in seedling tissue, although the normalized <italic>Rht-B1</italic> transcript levels were slightly (non-significantly) reduced. The discrepancy among these varieties may be explained by their different genetic backgrounds, and <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Wilhelm et al. (2013b)</xref> used only two lines with the 160 bp insertion (&#x2018;Mercia&#x2019; and &#x2018;Paragon&#x2019;) for qRT-PCR. Moreover, the <italic>Rht-1</italic> gene was expressed at different levels in different tissues and developmental stages (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Pearce et al., 2011</xref>), our previous study showed that <italic>Rht-1</italic> preferentially expressed in the fourth internodes than flag leaves at the heading stage (unpublished data). The effect of the 160 bp insertion on transcript needs more analysis in more tissues and developmental stages.</p>
      <p><xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Wilhelm et al. (2013a)</xref> found that <italic>Rht-B1a-160</italic> was associated with a small reduction in GA sensitivity relative to <italic>Rht-B1a-0</italic> accessions, but the difference was not statistically significant. In the present study, the coleoptile lengths of varieties containing <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> showed no significant effect of GA<sub>3</sub> treatment, indicating that <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> was insensitive to GA<sub>3</sub>. <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> contain a single nucleotide change introducing a premature stop codon in the DELLA domain of encoded proteins which conferred dwarfism and GA insensitivity, as well as <italic>Rht-B1d, Rht-B1e</italic>, and <italic>Rht-D1d</italic> (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Hedden, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Pearce et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Li A.X. et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2013</xref>). It is very surprise that <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> who could increases the plant height of wheat was insensitive to GA<sub>3</sub>, the mechanism needs further investigation. Since the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> is the same as <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>, while their response to GA<sub>3</sub> are different, suggesting the missense SNP occurring in <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> resulted in an E205G amino acid change in the Poly S/T/V region has an effect on the activity of Rht-B1i protein. <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Itoh et al. (2002)</xref> revealed that the polyS/T/V region had a strong suppression function for the activity of SLR protein. The function of this missense SNP in <italic>Rht-B1i</italic> needs further investigation.</p>
      <p><italic>Rht-B1</italic> may participate in the regulation of multiple phyto-hormones and environmental signaling pathways because of the various <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements in its promoters. The 160 bp insertion in the promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> contained 32 possible <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements not found in <italic>Rht-B1a</italic>. Among these 32 elements, four, including the auxin response element AUXREPSIAA4, are unique to <italic>Rht-B1i-1.</italic> This indicates that the height-increasing effect of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> may be related to auxin. GA can promote the transport of auxin, whereas auxin can promote the biosynthesis of GA (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Frigerio et al., 2006</xref>). In root growth and differentiation, GA and DELLA proteins control the transport of auxin and coordinate cell division and differentiation (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Moubayidin et al., 2010</xref>). In the present study, the coleoptile lengths of wheat varieties with the <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> genotype responded to IAA, and IAA/GA<sub>3</sub>, while that of <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> genotype did not respond to IAA, and IAA/GA<sub>3</sub>, and the transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings with promoter of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> also responded to IAA, and IAA/GA<sub>3</sub>, that of <italic>Rht-B1i-2</italic> did not, illustrating the height-increasing effect of <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic> may be caused by the synergistic effects of IAA and GA<sub>3</sub>. Further comprehensive study should be launch to elucidate the mechanism of the height-increasing effect for <italic>Rht-B1i-1</italic>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>XYL, XL, AL, MP, and WY participated in experiments, drafting the manuscript and proposal writing. DL and JS participated in material preparation, AZ and WY participated in experimental design and corrected the manuscript. MS corrected the manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title>
      <p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This work was supported financially by the National Basic Research Program of China (2014CB138101) and CAS Strategic Priority Program (XDA08010104). We thank all the colleagues in our laboratory for constructive discussion and technical assistance.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn01">
        <label>1</label>
        <p>
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dna.affrc.go.jp/PLACE/signalscan.html">http://www.dna.affrc.go.jp/PLACE/signalscan.html</ext-link>
        </p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn02">
        <label>2</label>
        <p>
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.psb.ugent.be/webtools/plantcare/html/">http://bioinformatics.psb.ugent.be/webtools/plantcare/html/</ext-link>
        </p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary material">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fpls.2016.00307">http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fpls.2016.00307</ext-link></p>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1">
        <media xlink:href="Table_1.DOCX">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addisu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snape</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gooding</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Reduced height (Rht) and photoperiod insensitivity (Ppd) allele associations with establishment and early growth of wheat in contrasting production systems.</article-title>
<source><italic>Euphytica</italic></source>
<volume>166</volume>
<fpage>249</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>267</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-008-9838-7</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>CTAB DNA extraction from plant tissues.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>128</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>141</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02670471</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bechtold</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>In planta Agrobacterium mediated gene transfer by infiltration of adult <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>C. R. Acad. Sci. Paris Life Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>316</volume>
<fpage>1194</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1199</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanning</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naruoka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Effect of variation for major growth habit genes on maturity and yield in five spring wheat populations.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>1211</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1220</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2008.08.0505</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#xF6;rner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plaschke</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Korzun</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Worland</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The relationship between the dwarfing genes of wheat and rye.</article-title>
<source><italic>Euphytica</italic></source>
<volume>89</volume>
<fpage>69</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/plb.12237</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haley</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Agronomic performance of Rht alleles in a spring wheat population across a range of moisture levels.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>939</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>947</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2004.0323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trethowan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Relationsips between height and yield in near-isogenic spring wheats that contrast for major reduced height genes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Euphytica</italic></source>
<volume>157</volume>
<fpage>391</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>397</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-006-9304-3</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bian</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Characterization of a novel reduced height gene (Rht23) regulating panicle morphology and plant architecture in bread wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Euphytica</italic></source>
<volume>203</volume>
<fpage>583</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>594</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-014-1275-1</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Floral dip: a simplified method for Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>735</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>743</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.1998.00343.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10069079</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flintham</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#xF6;rner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Worland</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Optimizing wheat grain yield: effects of Rht (gibberellin-insensitive) dwarfing genes.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>128</volume>
<fpage>11</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00223795</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frigerio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alabad&#xED;</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#xE9;rez-G&#xF3;mez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#xED;a-C&#xE1;rcel</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedden</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Transcriptional regulation of gibberellin metabolism genes by auxin signaling in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>142</volume>
<fpage>553</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>563</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.106.084871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16905669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Worland</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <article-title>The chromosomal location of a major dwarfing gene from Norin 10 in new British semi-dwarf wheats.</article-title>
<source><italic>Heredity</italic></source>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>417</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>421</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hdy.1975.112</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <article-title>The chromosomal location of Gai1 and Rht1 genes for Gibberellin insensitivity and semi-dwarfism, in a derivative of Norin 10 wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Heredity</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>283</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>289</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hdy.1976.88</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Youssefian</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>&#x201C;Dwarfing genes in wheat,&#x201D; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Progress in Plant Breeding</italic></source>
<role>ed.</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Butterworths</publisher-name>) <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedden</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The genes of the green revolution.</article-title>
<source><italic>Trends Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>5</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9525(02)00009-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12493241</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueguchi-Tanaka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The gibberellin signaling pathway is regulated by the appearance and disappearance of SLENDER RICE1 in nuclei.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>57</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.010319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11826299</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavanagh</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bevan</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>GUS fusions: &#x3B2;-glucuronidase as a sensitive and versatile gene fusion marker in higher plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>EMBO J.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>3901</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3907</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3327686</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Isolation of a gibberellin-insensitive dwarfing gene, Rht-B1e, and development of an allele-specific PCR marker.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Breed.</italic></source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>1443</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1451</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-012-9730-y</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Novel natural allelic variations at the Rht-1 loci in wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Integr. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>1026</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1037</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jipb.12103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23992198</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A GA-insensitive dwarf mutant of <italic>Brassica napus</italic> L. correlated with mutation in pyrimidine box in the promoter of GID1.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Biol. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>191</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>197</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11033-010-0094-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20358292</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>X. G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>A tandem segmental duplication (TSD) in green revolution gene Rht-D1b region underlies plant height variation.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>196</volume>
<fpage>282</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>291</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2012.04243.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22849513</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2 (-Delta Delta C(T)) method.</article-title>
<source><italic>Methods</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>402</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>408</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubcovsky</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Appels</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>&#x201C;Catalogue of gene symbols for wheat,&#x201D; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Proceeding of the 12th International wheat genetics Symposium</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Yokohama</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McVittie</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westcott</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>The intrachromosomal mapping of the Norin 10 and Tom Thumb dwarfing genes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Heredity</italic></source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>67</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hdy.1978.8</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miedaner</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Voss</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Effect of dwarfing Rht genes on Fusarium head blight resistance in two sets of near-isogenic lines of wheat and check cultivars.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>2115</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2122</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2008.02.0107</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miralles</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slafer</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Yield, biomass and yield components in dwarf, semi-dwarf and tall isogenic lines of spring wheat under recommended and late sowing dates.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Breed.</italic></source>
<volume>114</volume>
<fpage>392</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>396</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0523.1995.tb00818.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moubayidin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perilli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dello Ioio</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Mambro</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costantino</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The rate of cell differentiation controls the Arabidopsis root meristem growth phase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Curr. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>1138</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1143</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2010.05.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20605455</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murashige</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skoog</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962</year>). <article-title>A revised medium for rapid growth and bio-assays with tobacco tissue cultures.</article-title>
<source><italic>Physiol. Plant.</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>473</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>497</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.1962.tb08052.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paolacci</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanzarella</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Porceddu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciaffi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Identification and validation of reference genes for quantitative RT-PCR normalization in wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>:<issue>11</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2199-10-11</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>K. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>J.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>DELLA proteins and their interacting RING finger proteins repress gibberellin responses by binding to the promoters of a subset of gibberellin-responsive genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>927</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>943</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.108951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23482857</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saville</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spark</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Molecular characterization of Rht-1 dwarfing genes in hexaploid wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>157</volume>
<fpage>1820</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1831</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.183657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22013218</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Devos</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flintham</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>&#x201C;Green revolution&#x201D; genes encode mutant gibberellin response modulators.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nature</italic></source>
<volume>400</volume>
<fpage>256</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>261</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/22307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10421366</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pestsova</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Korzun</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#xF6;rner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Validation and utilisation of Rht dwarfing gene specific markers.</article-title>
<source><italic>Cereal Res. Commun.</italic></source>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>235</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>246</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1556/CRC.36.2008.2.4</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rebetzke</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnett</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Molecular mapping of genes for coleoptile growth in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>114</volume>
<fpage>1173</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1183</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-007-0509-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17294164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henikoff</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>SIFT web server: predicting effects of amino acid substitutions on proteins.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nucleic Acids Res.</italic></source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>W452</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>W457</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22689647</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>Y. P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Analysis of Pina and Pinb alleles in the micro-core collections of Chinese wheat germplasm by Ecotilling and identification of a novel Pinb allele.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Cereal Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>836</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>842</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcs.2008.06.005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Q. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>L. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Sequence variations of the partially dominant DELLA gene Rht-B1c in wheat and their functional impacts.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>64</volume>
<fpage>3299</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3312</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ert183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23918966</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulton</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Kaff</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balfourier</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bordes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013a</year>). <article-title>Rht-1 and Ppd-D1 associations with height, GA sensitivity, and days to heading in a worldwide bread wheat collection.</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>126</volume>
<fpage>2233</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2243</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-013-2130-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23722594</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>I. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saville</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Korolev</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balfourier</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013b</year>). <article-title>Haplotype dictionary for the Rht-1 loci in wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>126</volume>
<fpage>1733</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1747</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-013-2088-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23553443</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X. P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Dominant and pleiotropic effects of a GAI gene in wheat results from lack of interaction between DELLA and GID1.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>157</volume>
<fpage>2120</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2130</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.185272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22010107</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Youssefian</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>E. J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Pleitropic effects of the GA-insensitive <italic>Rht</italic> dwarfing genes in wheat: 2. Effects on leaf, stem, ear and floret growth.</article-title>
<source><italic>Field Crop Res.</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>191</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>210</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-4290(92)90039-C</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
