<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.0 20040830//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3236209</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-15202</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028810</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Agriculture</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Crops</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cereals</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Wheat</subject>
                <subject>Wheats</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Crop Diseases</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genomics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genome Analysis Tools</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Transcriptomes</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Plant Science</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plant Pathology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Plant Pathogens</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plants</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Seedlings</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plant Biochemistry</subject>
              <subject>Plant Genetics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Transcriptome Analysis of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-Treated Wheat Seedlings Reveals a H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-Responsive Fatty Acid Desaturase Gene Participating in Powdery Mildew Resistance</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Transcriptome Analysis of Wheat under H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> Stress</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Aili</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Rongzhi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Pan</surname>
            <given-names>Lei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>Lichuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Guangyao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>Mingzhu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chu</surname>
            <given-names>Jinfang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaohong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>Bo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Xiangqi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jia</surname>
            <given-names>Jizeng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mao</surname>
            <given-names>Long</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>National Key Facility for Crop Gene Resources and Genetic Improvement, Institute of Crop Science, MOA Key Lab for Germplasm and Biotechnology, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences (CAAS), Beijing, People's Republic of China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Plant Genomics, National Centre for Plant Gene Research, Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, People's Republic of China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>The State Key Laboratory of Plant Cell and Chromosome Engineering, Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, People's Republic of China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Donlin</surname>
            <given-names>Maureen J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">Saint Louis University, United States of America</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>maolong@caas.net.cn</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AL LM. Performed the experiments: AL LP LT GZ JC XS BW. Analyzed the data: AL RZ MZ XZ JJ LM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AL RZ LP LM. Wrote the paper: AL RZ LP LM.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>12</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <elocation-id>e28810</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Li et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) plays important roles in plant biotic and abiotic stress responses. However, the effect of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> stress on the bread wheat transcriptome is still lacking. To investigate the cellular and metabolic responses triggered by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, we performed an mRNA tag analysis of wheat seedlings under 10 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment for 6 hour in one powdery mildew (PM) resistant (PmA) and two susceptible (Cha and Han) lines. In total, 6,156, 6,875 and 3,276 transcripts were found to be differentially expressed in PmA, Han and Cha respectively. Among them, 260 genes exhibited consistent expression patterns in all three wheat lines and may represent a subset of basal H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> responsive genes that were associated with cell defense, signal transduction, photosynthesis, carbohydrate metabolism, lipid metabolism, redox homeostasis, and transport. Among genes specific to PmA, &#x2018;transport&#x2019; activity was significantly enriched in Gene Ontology analysis. MapMan classification showed that, while both up- and down- regulations were observed for auxin, abscisic acid, and brassinolides signaling genes, the jasmonic acid and ethylene signaling pathway genes were all up-regulated, suggesting H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-enhanced JA/Et functions in PmA. To further study whether any of these genes were involved in wheat PM response, 19 H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-responsive putative defense related genes were assayed in wheat seedlings infected with <italic>Blumeria graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic> (<italic>Bgt</italic>). Eight of these genes were found to be co-regulated by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>Bgt</italic>, among which a fatty acid desaturase gene <italic>TaFAD</italic> was then confirmed by virus induced gene silencing (VIGS) to be required for the PM resistance. Together, our data presents the first global picture of the wheat transcriptome under H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> stress and uncovers potential links between H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>Bgt</italic> responses, hence providing important candidate genes for the PM resistance in wheat.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="16"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) is a well known toxic molecule and is also a specific component of several biotic and abiotic signaling pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Costa1">[1]</xref>. In plants, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production causes oxidative stress during external stimuli such as chilling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Prasad1">[2]</xref>, drought <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Loggini1">[3]</xref>, salinity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Valderrama1">[4]</xref>, UV irradiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Mackerness1">[5]</xref>, ozone exposure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Pellinen1">[6]</xref>, heavy metal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Schutzendubel1">[7]</xref>, and wounding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Liu1">[8]</xref>. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is also produced upon phytohormone treatments such as abscisic acid (ABA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Pei1">[9]</xref> and jasmonic acid (JA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Liu1">[8]</xref>, as well as during elicitor and pathogen challenges <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Levine1">[10]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Li1">[11]</xref>. In almost all cases, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> seems to be positively employed by plants to activate certain stress-responsive genes that help them cope with adverse environmental changes.</p>
      <p>Global gene expression profiling experiments on H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-treated plants have revealed a large number of genes in Arabidopsis and tobacco that are mostly involved in response to oxidative stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Desikan1">[12]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Vanderauwera1">[14]</xref>. Such treatments, however, not only affect genes involved in reactive oxygen species (ROS) detoxification, but also drive the expression of genes involved in signal transduction, transcriptional regulation and protein, carbohydrate or lipid metabolism, illustrating the complexity of the transcriptional responses to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Recently, a proteomics investigation of proteins that are differentially accumulated responding to exogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> was performed in rice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Wan1">[15]</xref>. The study identified proteins that are involved in various cellular responses and metabolic processes, redox homeostasis, signal transduction, protein synthesis and degradation, photosynthesis and photorespiration, and carbohydrate/energy metabolism.</p>
      <p>Production of ROS has been observed during pathogen infection and is also a hallmark of successful recognition of infection and activation of plant defense systems. Oxidative burst is one of the fastest defense responses activated in plants to resist pathogen and parasite attacks. It consists of the production of ROS, mainly H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, at the first site of pathogen invasion: the plant cell wall, and incurs a number of events before the transcription-dependent defense mechanisms are activated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Lenucci1">[16]</xref>. Subsequently, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> works as a selective signal for the induction of a subset of defense genes including phosphorylation cascades <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Kovtun1">[17]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Mou1">[18]</xref>, cyclic oxylipins of the jasmonate type <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Montillet1">[19]</xref>, phytoalexins and secondary metabolites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Thoma1">[20]</xref>, as well as genes associated with programmed cell death <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Mur1">[21]</xref> and plant hormone signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Torres1">[22]</xref>. Phyto-oxylipins are metabolites produced in plants by the oxidative transformation of unsaturated fatty acids via a series of diverse metabolic pathways and are believed to play a pivotal role in plant defenses as signal molecules and/or protective compounds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Blee1">[23]</xref>. Along with salicylic acid (SA), JA, and ethylene (Et) are hormones usually associated with the induction of defenses where they antagonistically interact with SA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Kunkel1">[24]</xref>. ROS are proposed to be the central component of a self-amplifying loop that regulates the interaction between SA, JA and Et to mediate the response to ozone and possibly some defense and cell death processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Overmyer1">[25]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Bouchez1">[26]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) is one of the most important crops to feed the world's population. Each year, wheat powdery mildew (PM) causes serious yield loss worldwide. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> has been shown to accumulate in the mesophyll cells during the early stage of the wheat-PM incompatible interaction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Li1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Vanacker1">[27]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Torres2">[28]</xref>, suggesting that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signaling plays a role in PM defense. In Arabidopsis, the co-regulation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signaling and defense responses was reported. For example, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> regulates the coordinated action of the Arabidopsis <italic>TGA1</italic> (<italic>TGACG motif-binding factor 1</italic>) and <italic>NPR1</italic> (<italic>non expressor of pathogenesis-related genes 1</italic>) genes that are required for defense gene expression and systemic acquired disease resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Mou1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Despres1">[29]</xref>. Similarly, a serine/threonine kinase gene, <italic>Stpk-V</italic> introgressed from <italic>Haynaldia villosa</italic>, a wild relative of wheat, is recently reported to be induced by both <italic>Blumeria graminis</italic> s.sp. <italic>tritici</italic> (<italic>Bgt</italic>) and exogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, and confers the resistance to the powdery mildew (PM) in wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Cao1">[30]</xref>. These studies demonstrate the coordination of the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced signaling pathways and that of pathogens. The recent advance in next-generation sequencing technology provides a powerful tool for sequence-based transcriptome analysis in species with large genomes such as wheat. However, a global analysis of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes in wheat is still lacking, especially H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-triggered defense related genes and molecular pathways.</p>
      <p>In the present work, we performed a transcriptome analysis of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-treated wheat seedlings in the PM resistant (PmA) and susceptible (Cha and Han) lines. Using the mRNA tag sequencing approach, we identified differentially expressed genes with consistent expression patterns in all three wheat lines as well as those with specific expression patterns in PmA. We found that the basal H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes in wheat were involved in various cellular responses and metabolic processes, with functions toward cell defense, signal transduction, photosynthesis, carbohydrate metabolism, lipid metabolism, redox homeostasis, and transport. In PmA, Gene Ontology analysis revealed the enrichment of &#x2018;transport&#x2019; activities, while MapMan classification unraveled activated genes in PmA for JA and Et signaling pathway. Further, eight genes were found to be co-regulated by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment and <italic>Bgt</italic> inoculation, among which a fatty acid desaturase gene (<italic>TaFAD</italic>) was shown to be involved in the PM resistance. Our work is the first transcriptome-wide analysis of wheat genes responding to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment and provides candidate genes that may deserve further investigation for PM resistance in wheat.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>The morphological and physiological changes of wheat seedlings under H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment</title>
        <p>H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> can act as signaling molecules at low concentrations by diffusing into cells and be rapidly and specifically perceived by a series of target proteins before being scavenged by antioxidative defense mechanisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Wan1">[15]</xref>. These H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signals are transmitted to downstream signaling molecules and together modulate various metabolic and defense pathways in plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Pei1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Mittler1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Anthony1">[31]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Stone1">[32]</xref>. To study the effects of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> on wheat seedlings and discover genes that are potentially involved in biotic responses, we set out to investigate the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-triggered transcriptome profile changes in one PM-resistant (PmA) and two PM-susceptible lines (Cha and Han; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g001">Figure 1B</xref>, the growth of 9-day-old wheat seedlings in 10 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 6 hours (h) did not cause evident changes in morphology, which was in contrast to the severely curled leaves of rice seedlings under similar conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Wan1">[15]</xref>. To confirm that the application of exogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> indeed elevated the cytosolic H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> level, we determined the endogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration in the treated leaves. The results showed that the internal H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> level indeed increased by more than 200% over the control in all of the three wheat lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). In contrast, the net photosynthetic rate (Pn) in all of the three wheat lines were decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g001">Figure 1D</xref>). These measurements demonstrate that the current treatment condition was sufficient to cause physiological changes in the wheat cells. We then carried out an mRNA tag profiling analysis using RNA samples extracted from the seedling leaves. The two libraries derived from the 0 h and 6 h time points were named as follows: for PmA, PK and P6, respectively; for Han, HK and H6, respectively; and for Cha, CK and C6, respectively.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0028810-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028810.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment on wheat seedlings.</title>
            <p>(A) PM response of the resistance line PmAm6/Beijing837 BC5F3 (PmA) and the susceptible lines Beijing837 (Bj), Hanxuan10 (Han), and Chadianhong (Cha) at 10 day after <italic>Bgt</italic> inoculation. (B) Phenotypes of 9-day-old wheat seedlings after 6 h 10 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment. (C) Accumulation of endogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in wheat seedling leaves. (D) Suppression of photosynthesis efficiency (Pn) in wheat seedling leaves by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. For (C) and (D), the data are based on three biological replicates, each with ten plants.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0028810.g001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>The mRNA tag raw data processing, gene association, and differential expression analysis</title>
        <p>An average total of 11,841,476 high quality tags (clean tags) were obtained from each of the six libraries. After removing un-mappable reads, 9,201,359 tags were shown to have at least one match (with less than 1 bp mismatch considering the existence of homoeo-alleles) in the reference tag database generated from 274,754 PlantGDB sequences (Release 163b). The unmatched tags may arise from the absence of ESTs in the current datasbase or from sequencing errors, and were not pursued further. More than 30,000 genes that were tagged by 291,026 unambiguous tags for each library were further analyzed for differential expression analysis (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and methods</xref> for the data processing details, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s002">Table S1</xref>), with an average number of tags per gene as 137.9. A total of 6,157, 6,876, and 3,268 transcripts were found to be differentially expressed between 0 h and 6 h H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment in PmA, Han, and Cha respectively (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001 and FDR&lt;0.001). In PmA, the number of up-regulated transcripts (4,008) was nearly 2-fold that of the down-regulated transcripts (2,148), whereas the numbers of up- and down-regulated transcripts in Han (3,780 vs 3,095) and Cha (1,780 vs 1,487) were similar (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s003">Table S2</xref>). A BlastN search between tagged ESTs and sequences presented on Affymetrix wheat GeneChips showed that only a third of these differentially expressed transcripts were represented by the latter methodology, demonstrating that the high-throughput sequencing technology-based gene expression methodology provides more comprehensive information than the traditional array-based approach.</p>
        <p>A correlation analysis showed that the correlation coefficients (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) between libraries of the same wheat line were higher (&gt;0.95) than those between different wheat lines, regardless whether the plants were treated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> or not. This result indicates significant variations in basal gene expression levels between the wheat lines of different genetic backgrounds (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s004">Table S3</xref>). This observation also cautions us to take all three of the lines into consideration when identifying genes that specifically respond to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. A total of 28 differentially expressed genes between PK and P6, as measured in tag numbers, were then verified using qRT-PCR. The result showed &gt;86% (24 out of 28 genes) consistency between the two methods (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s005">Table S4</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Functional classification of differential expression genes with consistent expression patterns in all three wheat lines</title>
        <p>To reduce the potential variation derived from different genetic backgrounds, we firstly looked at the genes with consistent differential expression patterns in all three of the lines. A total of 260 genes fell in this category, with 135 genes up-regulated and 125 down-regulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g002">Figure 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s006">Table S5</xref>). We then manually classified these genes using functional categories as reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Wan1">[15]</xref>. The numbers of up- and down-regulated genes were significantly different (Fisher's exact test <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05) in the functional categories related to cell rescue/defense, photosynthesis, and carbohydrate metabolism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g002">Figure 2B, 2C</xref>). For example, nearly a third (30 ESTs, or 29%) of the up-regulated genes were annotated as to be involved in cell rescue/defense, significantly more than the ones down regulated (9 ESTs, or 11%). In this category, a number of genes induced by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> are clear components of defense responses, such as chitinase (Ta-1686165446), cytochrome P450 enzymes (Ta-98605, 137154, 127510), hypersensitive-induced response protein (Ta-1646165446, 265165443), late embryogenesis abundant group 1 protein (Ta-108515, 44767, 04365), wound-induced precursor (Ta-1412165445, 012207), and glycosyl hydrolases family protein (Ta-0877, 33326, 81876), whereas those down regulated are cellulase (Ta-64131), expansins (Ta-1865165444, 89717), and WAX2 (Ta-93863) genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028810-t001">Table 1</xref>). In contrast, the expressions of genes for other two categories, i.e. photosynthesis and carbohydrate metabolism, were all repressed. Twelve genes (14%) were associated with photosynthesis including those for the light harvest center such as chlorophyll A-B binding proteins (Ta-0112922, 036375, 053588, 129259, 146211, 19895, 2098165442, 3264165442, 98245) and photosynthesis I and II reaction center proteins (Ta-2040165448, 132758). The consequent repression of carbohydrate metabolism genes included key sucrose synthesis genes such as beta-amylase (Ta-155349), trehalose-6-phosphate synthase (Ta-2355165445), and ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase small chain precursor (Ta-3117165446; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s006">Table S5</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0028810-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028810.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Classification of differentially expressed genes in wheat seedlings under H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment.</title>
            <p>(A) Venn diagram analysis of the differentially expressed genes (fold change &#x2265;2; tag number &#x2265;12; <italic>P</italic> value&lt;0.001) in PmA (PK/P6), Han (HK/H6), and Cha (CK/C6). Functional classification of 135 (104 annotated) up-regulated (B) and 125 (84 annotated) down-regulated genes (C) that are differentially expressed across all three lines. Wheat ESTs were annotated by their similarity to rice proteins. The significance between up and down regulated gene numbers was tested using Fisher's exact test. *<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0028810.g002"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0028810-t001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028810.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-responsive ESTs annotated with cell rescue/defense functions.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0028810-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0028810.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PlantGDB EST No.</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative function</td>
                  <td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Fold change (log2)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PmA</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Han</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cha</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Up-regulated</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-1686165446</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHIT8 - Chitinase family precursor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-28626</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSLF8 - cellulose synthase-like family F; beta1,3;1,4 glucan synthase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-98605</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome P450 72A1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.02</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-137154</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome P450</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.49</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.87</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.50</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-127510</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome P450</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.73</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-760165445</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dehydrin</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.75</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.17</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-1646165446</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hypersensitive-induced response protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-265165443</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hypersensitive-induced response protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-108515</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">late embryogenesis abundant group 1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.56</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.64</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.29</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-44767</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">late embryogenesis abundant group 1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.99</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.44</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-04365</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">late embryogenesis abundant group 1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-85498</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OsRCI2-5 - Putative low temperature and salt responsive protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-65960</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pectinesterase inhibitor domain containing protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.52</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-1137165445</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pectinesterase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-1864165443</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pleiotropic drug resistance protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.95</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-33080</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">thaumatin</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.49</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.73</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-1412165445</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WIP3 - Wound-induced precursor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.77</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-012207</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WIP3 - Wound-induced precursor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.19</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-0109885</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glyoxalase family protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-36034</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wound/stress protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-95374</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">jacalin-like lectin domain containing protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.08</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-0877</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glycosyl hydrolases family 16</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.15</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-33326</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glycosyl hydrolases family 16</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-81876</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glycosyl hydrolases family 16</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.98</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-58864</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glycosyl hydrolases</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-839165443</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">alpha-1,4-glucan-synthase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.08</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-111845</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">vignain precursor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-1262165444</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">vignain precursor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.44</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.29</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-152385</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lysM domain containing protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.17</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-92174</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BBTI6 - Bowman-Birk type bran trypsin inhibitor precursor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.57</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.97</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Down-regulated</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-64131</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cellulase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;1.58</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;2.20</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;1.39</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-117342</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome P450</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;1.47</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;2.49</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;4.38</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-1865165444</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">expansin precursor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;9.44</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;1.86</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;2.11</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-89717</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">expansin precursor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;8.16</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;6.44</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;8.11</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-0115846</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glycosyl hydrolases</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;1.62</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;2.85</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;2.40</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-111456</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">late embryogenesis abundant D-34</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;1.97</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;3.20</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;1.89</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-1523165444</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os1bglu5 - beta-glucosidase homologue, similar to G. max isohydroxyurate hydrolase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;1.87</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;3.02</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;1.70</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-101667</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">verticillium wilt disease resistance protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;2.15</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;1.61</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;8.05</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-93863</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WAX2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;1.73</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;1.33</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;1.99</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>6 h TPM&#x2236;0 h TPM;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <p>Ta, PUT-163b-Triticum_aestivum; PmA, PmAm6/Beijing837 BC5F3; Han, Hanxuan10; Cha, Chadianhong.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>In addition, four categories contain similar numbers of induced and repressed genes. These categories were signal transduction, lipid metabolism, redox homeostasis, and transport. Genes for signal transduction, for example, were comprised of 27 (26%) induced genes and 16 (19%) repressed ones (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s006">Table S5</xref>). These genes are of various signaling functions and encode putative calcium/calmodulin-dependent protein kinase (Ta-18711), calmodulin-related calcium sensor protein (CML) (Ta-095679), mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) (Ta-60654), phosphatase 2C proteins (Ta-2846165449, 18275, 57939, 133196, 804165440, 3652165444), and AP2 transcription factors (Ta-51510, 29471), MYBs (Ta-089056, 056632, 24630), WRKY (Ta-064372), zinc-finger (Ta-9295), and bHLH (Ta-58552). Eleven genes were involved in lipid metabolism (9 up- and 2 down-regulated), including putative lipid transfer protein like (LTPs) family proteins (Ta-104587, 035988, 459165442, 66239), lipoxygenases (Ta-01383, 1776165447), fatty acid hyroxylase (Ta-45483), and acyl carrier protein (Ta-15083). There were nine genes (4 up- and 5 down-regulated) that were involved in redox homeostasis. The genes in this category encode dehydrogenases (Ta-21469, 31030), tropinone reductase 2 proteins (Ta-36863, Ta-060010), glutathione S-transferase (GST, Ta-66576), glutathione peroxidase (Ta-19785), peroxisomal membrane protein (Ta-121223), peroxidase precursor (Ta-010988), and thioredoxin (Ta-2210165449). There were seven genes that were involved in transport activity (2 up- and 5 down-regulated). The genes in this category encode MDR-like ABC transporter (Ta-2659165443), transmembrane amino acid transporter protein (Ta-151041), amino acid transporter (Ta-118377), mitochondrial carrier protein (Ta-01816), peptide transporter (Ta-149275), and trafficking particle complex subunit (Ta-95913). The genes in other category were mainly were involved in protein biosynthesis and degradation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s006">Table S5</xref>). In addition, a group of 38 genes (15 up- and 23 down-regulated) were annotated to encode putative, hypothetical, or expressed proteins of unknown functions. Finally, we compared these H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-regulated genes with those differential genes from several other wheat microarray works. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028810-t002">Table 2</xref>, a number of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> regulated genes also participated in other biotic and abiotic stresses, such as heat, drought, and pathogen infections (leaf rust, yellow rust, and <italic>Fusarium pseudograminearum</italic>), confirming the diverse functions of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in wheat stress responses. There seem to be more common genes differentially expressed under our condition and under drought and heat conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Qin1">[33]</xref>. This may be attributed to the similar time points for sample collection in the two experiments.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0028810-t002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028810.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Co-regulation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-responsive wheat genes under other stress conditions as detected by the microarray analyses.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0028810-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0028810.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ArrayExpress or GEO accession</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condition</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time course</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold change cut-off<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Common genes</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-MEXP-1523</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heat and drought</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 h, 3 h, 24 h</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qin et al. 2008 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Qin1">[33]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA23</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drought</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 DPA</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">April et al. 2009 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Aprile1">[34]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSE6227 (TA29)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Puccinia triticina</italic> race MFBL (<italic>Lr34</italic>)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 h</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hulbert et al. 2007 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Hulbert1">[35]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. striiformis f. sp. tritici</italic> (<italic>Yr39</italic>)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 h</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coram et al. 2008 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Coram1">[36]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA24</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnaporthe isolate BR32 (adapted)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 h</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boyd 2009 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Boyd1">[37]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSE13346 (TA31)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Fusarium pseudograminearum</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 day</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Desmond et al. 2008 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Desmond1">[38]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSE13660</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>Blumeria graminis f. sp. Tritici</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 weeks</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chain et al. 2009 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Chain1">[39]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TA2 (E-GEOD-12508)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seedling root vs seedling leaf</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schreiber et al. 2009 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Schreiber1">[40]</xref></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>As used by the authors or selected to make a dataset of a reasonable size.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Gene Ontology analysis suggests H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-enhanced transport activities in PmA</title>
        <p>In barley and wheat, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> can accumulate in the mesophyll cells during the early stage of the host-PM incompatible interaction, where it acts as an important signaling molecule to activate defense systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Li1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Vanacker1">[27]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Torres2">[28]</xref>. Since PmA is resistant to <italic>Bgt</italic> isolate E09 while Han and Cha are susceptible, we studied in PmA H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> responding genes that were &#x201C;subtracted&#x201D; with their expression patterns in Han and Cha. We defined three classes of PmA-specific (PmA-H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) genes: class I comprises genes whose expression was induced in PmA (U) but suppressed (D) or remained unchanged (N) in both Han and Cha (UDD/UNN); class II includes genes that were suppressed in PmA (D) but induced or unchanged in Han and Cha (DUU/DNN); class III contains genes whose expression was not affected in PmA but changed in Han and Cha (NUU/NDD) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s007">Table S6</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s008">S7</xref>). A total of 2,982 genes fell in these categories. Among them, nearly 60% of the genes (1,763) belong to class I genes (fold change &#x2265;2, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001, and FDR&lt;0.001), while classes II and III genes comprise 28% (846) and 12% (373) respectively.</p>
        <p>Gene Ontology (GO) analysis showed that class I genes were mostly enriched in functions associated with the biological process (BP) terms &#x201C;localization&#x201D;, &#x201C;response to stimulus&#x201D;, and &#x201C;metabolic process&#x201D;, the molecular function (MF) terms &#x201C;transporter activity&#x201D;, &#x201C;catalytic activity&#x201D; and &#x201C;binding&#x201D;, and the cellular component (CC) terms &#x201C;plasma membrane&#x201D;, &#x201C;vacuole&#x201D; and &#x201C;membrane-bounded organelle&#x201D; (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028810-t003">Table 3</xref>). A total of 112 genes were associated with &#x201C;localization&#x201D; including 43 transporters, 18 protein targeting proteins, and 11 cell vesicle transporters (data not shown), among which a total of 21 genes were annotated as related to the vesicle-mediated transport (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s009">Table S8</xref>). Genes with &#x201C;transporter activity&#x201D; were 17.5 fold more over-represented than in the Arabidopsis ATH1 Genome Array ATH1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028810-t003">Table 3</xref>) that contains more than 22,500 probe sets representing approximately 24,000 genes. Transporter genes are known to be associated with defense responses by participating in the formation of multi-vesicular bodies and cell wall-associated paramural bodies that have been shown to be involved in secretion of building blocks for cell wall appositions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-An1">[41]</xref>. These vesicle bodies not only arrest fungal penetration but also can cause hypersensitive cell death through blocking plasmodesmata. However, whether H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> enhanced membrane transport, as observed here in wheat, plays a role in pathogen defense or not may need further experimental investigation.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0028810-t003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028810.t003</object-id>
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Enriched GO terms among H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes in the PM resistant line PmA.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0028810-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0028810.t003"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO terms</td>
                  <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Percent of total transcripts</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> over representation</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FDR</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Study</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATH1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>UNN/UDD (Class I)</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Biological Process</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">localization</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.90E-15</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40E-12</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">response to stimulus</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.40E-10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10E-07</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">metabolic process</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70E-10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50E-08</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Molecular Function</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transporter activity</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80E-06</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70E-04</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">catalytic activity</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10E-13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90E-10</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">binding</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60E-06</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70E-04</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Cell Component</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">plasma membrane</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80E-40</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10E-37</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">vacuole</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30E-19</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.80E-18</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">membrane-bounded organelle</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.20E-27</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10E-24</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>DNN/DUU (Class II)</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Biological Process</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">localization</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20E-04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.90E-03</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cellular process</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30E-06</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.30E-04</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">metabolic process</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60E-07</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.30E-05</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Molecular Function</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">electron carrier activity</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.80E-04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10E-02</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">catalytic activity</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50E-09</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.90E-07</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">binding</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40E-03</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50E-02</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Cell Component</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chloroplast stroma</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80E-14</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10E-12</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chloroplast thylakoid membrane</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.20E-12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50E-11</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">plasma membrane</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90E-09</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30E-08</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>NUU/NDD (Class III)</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Biological Process</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cellular component biogenesis</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70E-02</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">response to stimulus</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80E-05</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80E-03</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">metabolic process</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50E-05</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60E-03</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Molecular Function</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">catalytic activity</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30E-07</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20E-04</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Cell Component</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chloroplast stroma</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40E-07</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80E-06</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">organelle membrane</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.10E-03</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.70E-02</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">plasma membrane</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.10E-06</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.80E-05</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>GO analysis showed that class II genes were also enriched with &#x201C;localization&#x201D; and &#x201C;metabolic process&#x201D; (BP), &#x201C;catalytic activity&#x201D; and &#x201C;binding&#x201D; (MF), and &#x201C;plasma membrane&#x201D; (CC). The difference between the class II and the class I genes was the enrichment of the GO terms &#x201C;chloroplast stroma&#x201D; (CC, 10 fold enrichment) and &#x201C;thylakoid membrane&#x201D; (CC, 8.3 fold enrichment) in class II genes, suggesting significant effects on chloroplast functions by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. The composition of the class III genes (up- or down-regulated only in both Han and Cha) was enriched with the BP term &#x201C;cellular component biogenesis&#x201D; and the CC term &#x201C;chloroplast stroma&#x201D; (10 fold enrichment). In contrast, the BP &#x201C;localization&#x201D; was not enriched among the genes of this category, demonstrating a difference in membrane transport activities between the PM susceptible and resistant lines. Therefore, these data point to possible roles of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in pathogen defense, with enhanced vesicle transportation as one of the possible approaches.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>MapMan analysis showed H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-enhanced JA/Et signaling pathway in PmA</title>
        <p>To study the possible roles of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> responding genes in biotic response, we overlaid classes I, II, and III genes to the Arabidopsis GeneChip template in the MapMan program <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Thimm1">[42]</xref> and analyzed them in the biotic stress overview (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s001">Figure S1</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g003">Figure 3A</xref> summarizes 10 major categories of genes that were associated with biotic response according to the MapMan classification. Among these, the most abundant genes (102 ESTs) were involved in protein degradation of various functions such as subtilases, cysteine protease, aspartate protease, serine protease, metalloprotease, AAA type, ubiquitin E1, ubiquitin E2 and ubiquitin E3 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s010">Table S9</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s011">S10</xref>). Ubiquitination-associated proteins have been shown to play important roles in plant-microbe interactions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Zeng1">[43]</xref>. The second group of genes (75 ESTs) was associated with signaling including more than 30 receptor kinases, calcium/calmodulin dependent kinases, and ras-related proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g003">Figure 3A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s011">Table S10</xref>). Protein kinases are well known to play a central role in the pathogen recognition and subsequent activation of plant defense <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Romeis1">[44]</xref>. The biotic stress overview also displays genes involved in redox homeostasis (31 ESTs), secondary metabolism (31 ESTs), cell wall (23 ESTs), heat shock proteins (13 ESTs), pathogenesis-related proteins (PRs; 4 ESTs), and 31 ESTs that may be overlapping with additional abiotic responses.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0028810-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028810.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Functional categories of MapMan biotic stress overview of differentially expressed genes specific to the PM resistant line PmA.</title>
            <p>(A) An overview of genes involved in biotic stress. Genes of classes I, II, and III are as defined in the text. Numbers of down regulated genes are represented by negative numbers. Genes in each functional category were listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s011">Table S10</xref>. (B) List of genes involved in hormone signaling and their relative expression levels between 0 h and 6 h H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment. The expression levels are represented as the log<sub>2</sub> value of the mRNA tag number ratios between the two libraries.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0028810.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>A total of 30 genes were involved in hormone signaling according to their annotation. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g003">Figure 3B</xref>, except for salicylic acid (SA), putative signaling genes for auxin, abscisic acid (ABA), JA, Ethylene (Et), and brassinolides (BR) were all affected by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> among PmA-H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> genes. For ABA, Auxin, and BR, some genes were up regulated whereas others were down regulated. In contrast, all JA and Et signaling genes were up regulated, indicating that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is able to enhance JA/Et signaling in PmA (the two hormones often work together) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-McConn1">[45]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Thomma1">[47]</xref>. The 12 putative JA/Et signaling genes encode lipoxygenases (LOXs, Ta-07168, 15852, 2498165446), lipozygenase (Ta-108080), allene oxide synthase 2 (AOS2, Ta-134687), jasmonic acid carboxyl methyltransferase (JMT, Ta-89552), ethylene receptors (ETRs, Ta-2002165441, 124905), esterase (Ta-0103737), ethylene response factor (ERF, Ta-147978), and endothelial differentiation-related factors (Ta-3023, 56281; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). Six of the above 12 JA/Et genes (Ta-2498165446, 108080, 134687, 89552, 2002165441, 147978) were selected for qRT-PCR confirmation and, as expected, were all induced by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s012">Table S11</xref>). Besides, two additional JA biogenesis-related genes Ta-80972 and Ta-04807 were also confirmed by qRT-PCR to be up regulated by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s012">Table S11</xref>). Ta-80972 encodes a cytochrome P450 that is highly similar to a rice allene oxide synthase (AOS), a key enzyme in the oxylipin pathway leading to AOS-derived jasmonates, while Ta-048072 encodes the enzyme 12-oxophytodienoate (OPDA) reductase that is involved in JA biosynthesis by catalyzing the reduction of 10, 11-double bonds of OPDA to yield 3-oxo-2-(2&#x2032;-pentenyl)-cyclopentane-1-octanoic acid (OPC-8:0). These results suggest that it is not only the signaling, but also the biogenesis of JA that may have been enhanced in the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-treated wheat.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Co-regulation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> responsive genes by <italic>Bgt</italic> inoculation in PmA</title>
        <p>Several studies demonstrate that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced genes can also be regulated by pathogen infections, including powdery mildew <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Mou1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Despres1">[29]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Cao1">[30]</xref>. To identify H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> regulated genes that may also respond to wheat <italic>Bgt</italic> infection, 19 PmA-H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> ESTs that were annotated as related to defense response were selected for expression study using qRT-PCR assay between PmA and its susceptible isogenic line Beijing837 (Bj; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028810-t004">Table 4</xref>). Eight of these genes were found to have similar expression patterns between H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment and <italic>Bgt</italic> inoculation. Among them, five were class I genes including Ta-048072, 147978, 019566, 92123, and 02061 that encode 12-oxophytodienoate reductase (JA pathway), ethylene-responsive transcription factor (Et pathway), calcium/calmodulin dependent kinases (signaling), heavy metal-associated domain containing protein (cell rescue/defense), and stripe rust resistance Yr10-associated (cell rescue/defense) respectively. In the mean time, two class II genes Ta-138137 and Ta-2126165445 that respectively encode a helix-loop-helix DNA-binding domain containing protein (signaling) and an ABC transporter family protein (transport) were co-suppressed by both treatments. These H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>Bgt</italic> co-regulated genes may be involved in the PM responses. The last EST Ta-0109540 represents a gene encoding a fatty acid desaturase (named <italic>TaFAD</italic>) and is a class III gene that was significantly repressed by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in the two PM susceptible lines Han and Cha (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028810-t004">Table 4</xref>). In PmA, the fold change of the TaFAD expression under 0 and 6 h H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatments was calculated as close to 0.5, but was not significant under our statistic threshold (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001;). qRT-PCR assay showed that under <italic>Bgt</italic> inoculation, <italic>TaFAD</italic> was significantly (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) repressed by <italic>Bgt</italic> infection in the PM susceptible isogenic line Bj (6 h&#x2236;0 h ratio 0.25&#xB1;0.08) when the change in PmA was marginal (6 h&#x2236;0 h ratio 0.53&#xB1;0.09). A more detailed analysis over a 48 h <italic>Bgt</italic> inoculation course showed that <italic>TaFAD</italic> was indeed significantly repressed by <italic>Bgt</italic> infection in Bj (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05), whereas in PmA the modest down regulation was statistically insignificant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g004">Figure 4</xref>). These data demonstrate that the capability to maintain a constant expression level of <italic>TaFAD</italic> might be essential for PM resistant wheat lines.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0028810-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028810.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Response of <italic>TaFAD</italic> to the <italic>Bgt</italic> treatment.</title>
            <p>Expression patterns of <italic>TaFAD</italic> in the PM resistant (PmA) and the susceptible (Bj) near isogenic lines under <italic>Bgt</italic> inoculation as detected by qRT-PCR. ** <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001; * <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0028810.g004"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0028810-t004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028810.t004</object-id>
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Expression patterns of selected H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes under <italic>Bgt</italic> inoculation in the near isogenic lines PmA and Bj.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0028810-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0028810.t004"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PlantGDB EST</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annotation</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Class</td>
                  <td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment</td>
                  <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"><italic>Bgt</italic> inoculation</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PmA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Han<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cha<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PmA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">b</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PmA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">b</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bj<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">b</xref></td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-048072<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-oxophytodienoate reductase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>3.72</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>3.15&#xB1;1.07</bold>
                    <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>2.95&#xB1;0.44</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#xB1;2.21</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-18253</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGS domain containing</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2&#xB1;0.13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08&#xB1;0.02</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13&#xB1;0.01</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-147978</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethylene-responsive transcription factor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>2.19</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>2.11&#xB1;0.07</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>2.5&#xB1;0.21</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35&#xB1;0.49</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-3577165441</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acyl-CoA thioesterase 2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3&#xB1;0.18</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34&#xB1;0.06</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56&#xB1;0.21</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-1259165445</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serine/threonine- kinase PRP4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83&#xB1;0.15</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57&#xB1;0.59</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23&#xB1;1.01</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-129760</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethylene-responsive element-binding</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.33&#xB1;1.92</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08&#xB1;0.71</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92&#xB1;0.27</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-019566</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAMK_KIN1/SNF1/Nim1_like.38 - CAMK</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>3.6</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>2.37&#xB1;0.31</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>15.8&#xB1;4.21</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.9&#xB1;3.72</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-1676165442</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solute carrier family 35 member B1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.31</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.23&#xB1;1.15</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57&#xB1;0.23</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67&#xB1;0.32</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-92123</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heavy metal-associated domain containing</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>2.73</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>2.78&#xB1;0.21</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>2.53&#xB1;0.12</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36&#xB1;1.09</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-99839</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peptide transporter PTR2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.71</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01&#xB1;0.27</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59&#xB1;0.22</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45&#xB1;0.12</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-02061</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stripe rust resistance Yr10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>5.54</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>3.55&#xB1;0.43</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>4.47&#xB1;1.03</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.92&#xB1;1.23</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-121165441</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-box/LRR-repeat protein 14</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17&#xB1;0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13&#xB1;1.11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85&#xB1;0.24</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-4496</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hcr2-5D</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.41</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.88</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23&#xB1;0.06</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62&#xB1;0.52</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#xB1;0.15</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-099263</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thioesterase family protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.89</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32&#xB1;0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96&#xB1;1.12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71&#xB1;0.11</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-1039165449</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OsIAA12 - Auxin-responsive Aux/IAA gene family member</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.44</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12&#xB1;0.09</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26&#xB1;0.44</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9&#xB1;0.33</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-138137</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Helix-loop-helix DNA-binding domain containing protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>0.37</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.29</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">324.0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>0.29&#xB1;0.05</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>0.02&#xB1;0.02</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06&#xB1;0.04</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-2126165445</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC transporter family protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>0.37</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.79</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>0.24&#xB1;0.13</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>0.4&#xB1;0.21</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28&#xB1;0.22</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-0109540</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatty acid desaturase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">e</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>0.23</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>0.07</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25&#xB1;0.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">e</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53&#xB1;0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">e</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>0.25&#xB1;0.08</bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta-3709</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homeobox and START domains containing</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52&#xB1;0.33</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05&#xB1;0.05</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94&#xB1;5.63</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>Fold change detected by mRNA tag profiling (6 h TPM&#x2236;0 h TPM);</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt105">
              <label>b</label>
              <p>Fold change determined by real time PCR (6 h&#x2236;0 h);</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt106">
              <label>c</label>
              <p>Ta, PUT-163b-Triticum_aestivum;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt107">
              <label>d</label>
              <p>Standard error shown here indicates three biological repeats; Bolded numbers represent co-activation or co-suppression;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt108">
              <label>e</label>
              <p>indicates that the change is statistically insignificant.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>In Arabidopsis and rice, FADs have been shown to be involved in disease resistance by modulating JA and SA signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Kachroo1">[48]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Jiang1">[49]</xref>. To study whether <italic>TaFAD</italic> may play a role in wheat PM resistance, we silenced <italic>TaFAD</italic> in PmA using virus-induced gene silencing (VIGS) technique. A 231-bp fragment comprising the 3&#x2032; end of the ORF and part of the 3&#x2032; UTR sequence was used to increase the specificity, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Scofield1">[50]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Wang1">[51]</xref>. The results showed that down-regulation of <italic>TaFAD</italic> caused the compatibility between <italic>Bgt</italic> and PmA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g005">Figure 5</xref>). The reduction of <italic>TaFAD</italic> expression resulted in the growth of <italic>Bgt</italic> spores on the leaves of the BSMV&#x2236;TaFAD plants and enhanced PM penetration efficiency (PE, 28% vs. 0%; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s013">Table S12</xref>). To ensure that no additional genes were affected by &#x201C;off target&#x201D; silencing, we also tested the expression level of <italic>TaFAD6</italic>, the next closest gene of <italic>TaFAD</italic> in wheat, and indeed no co-suppression was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). These data thus suggest that the constant expression of <italic>TaFAD</italic> is indeed required for the PM resistance in PmA. Since FADs have been shown to be involved in disease resistance by modulating JA and SA signaling, we then investigated wheat genes homologous to functionally characterized rice marker genes in JA and SA signaling pathways in these VIGS plants. The SA-signaling gene used was the acidic pathogenesis-related protein gene <italic>PR1a</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s014">Table S13</xref>), whereas the JA-signaling genes encode a lipoxygenase (<italic>LOX</italic>, Ta-2498165446), an allene oxide synthase 2 (<italic>AOS2</italic>, Ta-134687), and a pathogenesis-related protein PR1b which acts in both the JA- and SA-dependent pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Qiu1">[52]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Tao1">[53]</xref>. As shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s014">Table S13</xref>, the JA pathway related genes, Ta-134687 (<italic>AOS2</italic>), Ta249865446 (<italic>LOX</italic>), and Ta-141027 (<italic>PR1b</italic>) were significantly down-regulated in <italic>BSMV&#x2236;TaFAD</italic> plants, whereas the expression level of <italic>PR1a</italic> remained unchanged. Therefore, we deduce that the loss of PM resistance in <italic>BSMV&#x2236;TaFAD</italic> plants was likely caused by the failure to maintain proper JA signaling. <italic>BSMV&#x2236;HSP90</italic> was used as a positive control for successful silencing of the disease resistance system because <italic>HSP90</italic> is essential for the plant hypersensitive reaction (HR) to diverse pathogens as shown by previous studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Scofield1">[50]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Wang1">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Lu1">[54]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Zhou1">[56]</xref>. In <italic>BSMV&#x2236;TaHSP90</italic> VIGS plants, <italic>AOS2</italic> and <italic>LOX</italic> were significantly up-regulated, whereas <italic>PR1a</italic> were down-regulated (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028810.s014">Table S13</xref>), suggesting different regulatory modes of <italic>TaFAD</italic> and <italic>TaHSP90</italic>. Overall, these observations suggest the potential modulation of <italic>TaFAD</italic> on JA signaling during wheat powdery mildew infection, which deserves further investigation.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0028810-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028810.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Virus Induced Gene Silencing (VIGS) assay of <italic>TaFAD</italic>.</title>
            <p>(A) Significant down regulation of <italic>TaFAD</italic> (left) in PmA plants by BSMV&#x2236;TaFAD inoculation. The expression level of another fatty acid desaturase gene <italic>TaFAD6</italic> (right) was not affected. (B) Susceptibility of PmA leaves to <italic>Bgt</italic> inoculation when <italic>TaFAD</italic> was &#x201C;silenced&#x201D; by VIGS. Bejing837 (Bj) was used as a control for successful <italic>Bgt</italic> infection; Mock, GKP buffer; <italic>BSMV&#x2236;GFP</italic>, empty vector-like control; <italic>BSMV&#x2236;HSP90</italic>, positive control for VIGS; At least fifteen VIGS plants were tested for each vector. (C) Microscopic observation of leaves from VIGS plants after 5 days of <italic>Bgt</italic> inoculation showing elongated secondary hyphae in VIGS plants. Short bars represent 10 &#xB5;m. Student's <italic>t</italic> test <italic>p</italic> value *&lt;0.05.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0028810.g005"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In plant cells, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> plays a dual role as a toxic by-product of normal cell metabolism and as a regulatory molecule in stress perception and signal transduction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Wan1">[15]</xref>. A complex interplay between H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and other signaling molecules is known to exist in plant cells, which explains the versatility of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> functions in different scenarios. However, the knowledge about the transcriptome changes by exogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment in wheat is limited, especially the knowledge about the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-trggered defense related genes and signaling pathways. In this work, we performed a mRNA tag analysis of the wheat seedling transcriptome after 6 h 10 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment using the next-generation sequencing technology. We found that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> caused differential expression of genes associated with important biological processes such as cell rescue/defense responses, photosynthesis, and carbohydrate metabolism. Further analysis in the PM resistant wheat line provided additional clues about the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-triggered molecular pathways and the possible links of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signaling and <italic>Bgt</italic> defense.</p>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>The effects of exogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> on gene expression profiles in wheat</title>
        <p>In rice, the exposure of seedlings to exogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> caused leaves to curl severely <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Wan1">[15]</xref>. By contrast, the wheat seedlings did not exhibit evident morphological changes after growth in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> solution for 6 hours. Consistent with this, we found only three percent (9 out of 260) differentially expressed genes related to redox detoxification in the transcripts with identical expression patterns in all three wheat lines, suggesting that dramatic oxidative stress had not taken place under the current experimental condition. Despite this, exposure of wheat seedling roots to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> stress did result in increased endogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation with impaired photosynthesis in wheat leaves. A total of 12 genes were associated with the photosynthetic process and were all down-regulated, together with 6 carbohydrate metabolism genes, indicating that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> can effectively repress photosynthesis and related carbohydrate metabolism in wheat.</p>
        <p>Several studies show that exogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> can initiate signal transduction processes in treated plants that render them to acquire tolerance to various abiotic and biotic stresses. In Arabidopsis, for example, genes responding to exogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> are also involved in wilting, UV irradiation, and elicitor challenge response, indicating that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> can mediate cross-tolerance toward other stresses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Desikan1">[12]</xref>. Extra H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> caused by high light in a catalase-deficient Arabidopsis mutant can regulate the transcription of two clusters of genes that encode heat shock proteins (HSPs) known to be involved in stress responses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Vanderauwera1">[14]</xref>. Similarly, treatment of winter wheat with low concentrations of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and catalase inhibitor may enhance its tolerance to low temperature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Matsuda1">[57]</xref>. We found significant activation of putative cell rescue/defense genes than repression in the same functional category, indicating that, as in a number of other studies, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> can stimulate defense responsive genes in wheat. Further comparative analysis showed that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes also participated in the response to other biotic and abiotic stresses, such as heat, drought and pathogen infections, indicating that at least some of these genes were indeed involved in defense responses.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>The characteristics of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> responses in the powdery mildew resistant wheat</title>
        <p>The accumulation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in the mesophyll cells has been observed in barley and wheat during the early stage of the host-PM incompatible interaction, indicating that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> works as an important signaling molecule in defense system activation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Li1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Vanacker1">[27]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Torres2">[28]</xref>. Two events were observed during this process: the accumulation of vesicles and vesicle-like materials at the cells in contact with microorganisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-An1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Collins1">[58]</xref> and the subsequent hypersensitive response (HR) in the epidermis cells directly nearby the penetration sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Li1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Vanacker1">[27]</xref>. We studied the differential gene responses in the PM resistant line PmA by GO enrichment analysis and found the &#x201C;localization&#x201D; was the most enriched BP term, together with the most enrichment GO MF term &#x201C;transporter activity&#x201D; and GO CC term &#x201C;Plasma membrane&#x201D; and &#x201C;vacuole&#x201D;. The enrichment of these GO terms suggest that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> enhanced the membrane trafficking, supporting the hypothesis that trafficking of membrane-bound solutes, such as H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2,</sub> is essential not only for signaling but also for accommodating the cellular volume changes associated defense response <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Leshem1">[59]</xref>.</p>
        <p>It is nowadays impossible to discuss ROS and redox signaling in plants without considering plant hormones and related signal molecules because these compounds act together with redox-modulated signaling pathways to process and transmit environmental cues into appropriate responses. Compounds strongly interacting with redox processes include classical hormones such as auxin, ethylene, and ABA, as well as defense-related signals such as SA and JA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Fryer1">[60]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Muhlenbock1">[65]</xref>. JA is synthesized from &#x3B1;-linolenic acid in chloroplast membranes. The three chloroplast-located enzymes 13-lipoxygenase (13-LOX), 13-allene oxide synthase (13-AOS), and the AOC catalyze the first half of JA biosynthesis up to the intermediate product cis-(+)-12-oxophytodienoic acid (OPDA). The Arabidopsis AOS promoter is activated by a variety of signals including jasmonic acid, wounding, OPDA, and SA, indicating that regulation of the AOS gene might exert a major control on JA signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Laudert1">[66]</xref>. As for OPDA, it alone is sufficient to induce defense responses. The methylation of jasmonic acid to MeJA is catalyzed by an S-adenosyl-L-methionine&#x2236;jasmonic acid carboxyl methyltransferase (JMT) in Arabidopsis. The expression of JMT itself is sufficient to induce some JA-dependent responses. In our study, we simultaneously detected the up-regulation of JA signaling and biogenesis genes including Ta-80972 (AOS), Ta-048072 (OPDA), Ta-07168, 15852, 2498165446 (LOX), and Ta-89552 (JMT). We also detected the activation of an ethylene receptor (ETR, Ta-2002165441) and an ethylene-responsive transcription factor (ERF, Ta-147978) by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment in PmA. It has been shown that JA, alone or often in combination with Et, mainly works in defense to insect wounding and necrotrophic pathogen attack <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-McConn1">[45]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Thomma1">[47]</xref>. Our results suggest that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> may play a role in biotic stress by enhancing JA and/or Et signaling pathways. Whether these responsive genes also play any function in response to the infection of the biotrophic pathogens such as wheat PM is worth further investigation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>The potential links between H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signaling and <italic>Bgt</italic> defense</title>
        <p>The recent identification of a serine/threonine kinase gene, <italic>Stpk-V</italic> as a PM resistant gene in wheat, provides further evidence that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>Bgt</italic> co-regulated genes can be involved in disease resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Cao1">[30]</xref>. This gene however was not detected in our work, probably because it was an introgressed gene from <italic>Haynaldia villosa</italic> and did not exist in the wheat line used here. In our study, eight genes exhibited similar expression patterns under H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment and <italic>Bgt</italic> inoculation. These representative genes belong to various functional categories such as cell rescue/defense, signaling, JA/Et signaling pathways, transport, and lipid metabolism, and may participate in the PM defense. We show that the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> responsive fatty acid desaturase gene <italic>TaFAD</italic> is indeed involved in the PM resistance, indicating that, as in other plants, fatty acids play important roles in wheat pathogen defense. In Arabidopsis, oleic acid (18&#x2236;1) has been implicated to participate in SA and JA-mediated defense pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Kachroo1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Kachroo2">[67]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Kachroo5">[70]</xref>. It has been shown that suppressing the gene for stearoyl acyl carrier protein fatty acid desaturase (SACPD) enhances the resistance of Arabidopsis (<italic>SSI2</italic>), soybean, and rice to multiple pathogens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Kachroo1">[48]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Jiang1">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Kachroo5">[70]</xref>. In addition, another fatty acid desaturase gene <italic>FAD7</italic> is required for the accumulation of the systemic acquired resistance-inducing activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Chaturvedi1">[71]</xref>, suggesting that different FAD family members may play distinct roles in plant defense. Therefore, the role of <italic>TaFAD</italic> in wheat PM resistance is not accidental since this gene is significantly repressed by both H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>Bgt</italic> in the PM susceptible lines Han, Cha and Bj while maintained a relative stable expression level in the PM resistant line PmA. The observation that silencing of <italic>TaFAD</italic> causes the loss of PM resistance in PmA and the significant down-regulation of the JA signaling pathway supports the idea that the maintenance of <italic>TaFAD</italic> function is crucial for the defense response, probably due to its potential regulatory role in modulating JA signaling. Whether or how H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> regulates the <italic>TaFAD</italic> expression in PmA during <italic>Bgt</italic> infection needs further investigation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>An overview of the transcriptome changes caused by exogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in wheat</title>
        <p>Several issues that are intrinsic to the hexaploid nature of the bread wheat need to be taken into consideration. For example, the mRNA tag numbers should represent the collective levels of the three homoeologous alleles if they were all expressed. Although consensus primers can be applied during qRT-PCR when sequences for all three alleles are available, allele-specific studies will result in more precise conclusions. Despite this, our analysis for the first time provides a global insight about the transcriptomic response to exogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment in wheat seedlings. Combining our observations and the previous studies, we present in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028810-g006">Figure 6</xref> several major cellular and metabolic processes in response to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment in wheat. First, the application of exogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> may increase the cytosolic H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> level causing the disruption of the redox homeostasis that can be relayed by MAPKs and type-2C protein phosphatase (PP2C) or perceived by the chloroplasts where both photosynthesis and carbohydrate metabolism are consequently suppressed. Second, the MAPK cascade and/or the retrograde signals from the chloroplast are then transmitted into the nucleus where the activation of transcription factors may initiate defense related genes. Third, the enhanced JA and Et signaling, accompanied with largely up regulated lipid metabolism (which may provide needed JA precursors), may positively regulate genes for defense response where H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-enhanced trafficking of membrane-bound solutes may also play an important role. Finally, we propose that possible links of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signaling and <italic>Bgt</italic> defense may exist in the processes of signaling, transport, JA/Et pathway, and lipid metabolism (indicated by stars). Genes involved in these aspects of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> response may deserve further study for their roles in the PM resistance in wheat.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0028810-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028810.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>An overview of the molecular pathways and cellular processes in response to the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment in the bread wheat.</title>
            <p>Displayed are common molecular pathways among all three wheat lines studied that may represent basal cellular response under exogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment, except for the JA/Et pathway which is specific for PmA. Pathways labeled by stars are postulated to be also involved in biotic responses according to their enrichment in PmA. MAPK, mitogen-activated protein kinase; ROS, reactive oxygen species; AOS, allene oxide synthase; LOX, lipoxygenase; 12-OPDA, 12-oxophytodienoate; ETR ethylene receptor; ERF, ethylene-responsive transcription factor; JA, jasmonic acid; ET, ethylene; CAB proteins, chlorophyll A&#x2013;B binding proteins; Lea proteins, late embryogenesis abundant group 1 proteins; LTPLs, lipid transfer protein like family proteins; ER, endoplasmic reticulum.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0028810.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Plant Growth and Treatments</title>
        <p>Am6 is a synthetic amphiploid derived from a cross between <italic>Triticum durum</italic> (AABB) accession DR147 and <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> (DD) accession Ae39 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Zhou2">[72]</xref>. The line used for this study (PmA) is a BC5F3 progeny between Am6 and the cultivar Beijing837 with a novel powdery mildew resistant gene. PmA is resistant to the popular <italic>Blumeria graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic> (<italic>Bgt</italic>) race No. 15 in the Beijing area, whose virulence type is E09, while Beijing837 is susceptible. Hanxuan10 is a drought tolerant cultivar and Chadianhong is known to be salt tolerant, both of which are susceptible to the Bgt race No. 15. Wheat seedlings were grown in a chamber at 22&#xB0;C and a photoperiod of 16 h (60 &#xB5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> photon flux density). For H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment, 9-day-old seedlings were transferred to a Hoagland's solution containing 10 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. For PM inoculation, the <italic>Bgt</italic> isolate E09 conidia on heavily diseased leaves were shaken off over a settling tower onto the wheat primary leaves, harvested at 0 and 6 h after treatment, and stored at &#x2212;80&#xB0;C until use. Inoculated plants were checked later to ensure proper development of powdery mildew on the leaves of the susceptible control.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Measurements of Photosynthesis Efficiency and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> Levels</title>
        <p>Net photosynthetic rates of the first and second leaves of wheat seedlings were measured using a LI-COR 6400 portable gas analysis system with a light-emitting diode light source (LI-COR Inc., Lincoln, NE), with seven duplicates. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation in wheat leaves was measured according to a previously described method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Tiwari1">[73]</xref>. Briefly, leaves were grounded to a fine powder and extracted with 5 mM titanium sulfate. The oxidation of titanium sulfate was recorded by reading the absorbance at 410 nm. The readings were converted to corresponding concentrations using a standard calibration plot.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Tag Library Construction and the Initial Bioinformatic Processing</title>
        <p>Wheat seedling leaves at 0 h and 6 h after H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment were used for mRNA tag library construction, as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Hoen1">[74]</xref>. Sequencing was performed by Beijing Genomics Institute, Shenzhen, China (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sequencing.genomics.com.cn/">http://sequencing.genomics.com.cn/</ext-link>). For the tag number counting, a reference tag database was generated using 274,754 PlantGDB sequences (Release 163b). For convenience, the prefix &#x201C;PUT-163b-Triticum_aestivum&#x201D; was replaced by a shorter one, &#x201C;Ta&#x201D;. A total of 217,691 sequences were found to have GATC sites, which generated a total of 425,312 reference tags, with340,097 unambiguous tags (79.96%). The tags derived from wheat mRNA libraries were counted for redundancy and, therefore, copy numbers, using in-house Perl scripts. Numbers of all the tags on one EST or assembly were used to represent its expression levels.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>mRNA Tag Data Analysis</title>
        <p>Tag numbers for each gene were normalized with the total number of tags in the corresponding library. The statistical difference between corresponding genes in differently libraries was measured using a previously described method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Audic1">[75]</xref>. Expression level changes were calculated using the log2 ratios of transcripts per million mapped reads (TPM) between conditions (P6/PK, H6/HK, C6/CK). The sets of genes were selected for further analysis after the following filters: (1) TPM log2 ratios were either &#x2265;1 for up regulation or &#x2264;1 for down regulation; (2) the copy numbers for each condition should be &#x2265;12; (3) the FDR for differential expression was set to be &lt;0.001. For convenience, transcripts with zero detected tags in one condition were arbitrarily designated as 0.01 TPM and marked, whereas others were normalized using the total tag numbers in one library (minimum 12 copies for tags to be included for analysis). For MapMan analysis, wheat EST sequences were compared using Blastx against Arabidopsis sequences represented on Affymetrix GeneChips. Fold change numbers were then transferred to the best Arabidopsis matches which were mapped to the Arabidopsis template in the MapMan program for display <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Thimm1">[42]</xref>. The manual functional classification of genes followed Wan and Liu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Wan1">[15]</xref>. Gene Ontology enrichment analysis was performed using <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> proteins as templates at AGRIGO website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.cau.edu.cn/agriGO/">http://bioinfo.cau.edu.cn/agriGO/</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Virus Induced Gene Silencing Assays</title>
        <p>The plasmids utilized in these experiments were based on the constructs described by Holzberg <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Holzberg1">[76]</xref>. The virus-induced gene silencing of <italic>TaFAD</italic> (PlantGDB EST Ta-0109540) and <italic>TaHSP90</italic> (<italic>TaHSP90.3-D1</italic>, GQ240789.1; <italic>TaHSP90.3-A1</italic>, GQ240787.1) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Wang1">[51]</xref> was performed using a &#x3B4; RNA vector, pSS031-1. <italic>TaHSP90</italic> was used as a positive control for powdery mildew resistance. A 231-bp fragment of <italic>TaFAD</italic> was amplified from the plasmid pTaFAD with the forward primer, <named-content content-type="gene">CTA<underline>GCTAGC</underline>GGGGTCTTCTGGTACAGC</named-content>, and the reverse primer, <named-content content-type="gene">CTA<underline>GCTAGC</underline>GACACGCTACTCTTTCCTTT</named-content>. A 355-bp fragment of <italic>TaHSP90</italic> was amplified from the plasmid pTaHSP90 with the forward primer, <named-content content-type="gene">CTA<underline>GCTAGC</underline>GAGACCTTCGCCTTCCAG</named-content>, and the reverse primer, <named-content content-type="gene">CTA<underline>GCTAGC</underline>CACCGAACTGCCCAATCA</named-content>. The underlined bases are the NheI restriction sites. Plants were infected with BSMV using a modified protocol <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Scofield1">[50]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Holzberg1">[76]</xref>. Briefly, capped transcripts were prepared from three linearized plasmids that contain the tripartite barley stripe mosaic virus (BSMV) genome using the mMessage mMachine T7 in vitro transcription kit (Ambion, Austin, TX), following the manufacturer's protocol. These in vitro transcription reactions typically resulted in a final concentration of 1 to 1.5 mg/ml of RNA.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4f">
        <title><italic>Bgt</italic>-wheat Interaction Assays</title>
        <p>The method to estimate <italic>Bgt</italic> infection efficiency is largely in accord to Li <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Li1">[11]</xref>. Wheat leaves of three centimeters were aligned on the surface of 0.5% agarose with 50 mg/L 2-[(4-chlorophenenyl)methyl]-1H-benzimidazol and sprayed with <italic>Bgt</italic> spores (isolate E09) using an air compressor and nozzle. After 5 days, the leaves were bleached with trichloroacetic acid (1.5 g L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) in ethanol&#x2236;chloroform (4&#x2236;1 v/v), stained with aniline blue (1 g L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>), and observed under a light microscope for the formation of elongated secondary hyphae. A segment of the same leaf was kept at &#x2212;80&#xB0;C for mRNA extraction and subsequent quantitative real time PCR (qRT-PCR). For VIGS plants, newly emerging leaves of 14 d after the viral inoculation (usually the fourth leaves) were used. At least 8 VIGS plants were tested for each VIGS vector with three independent biological replicates.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4g">
        <title>Measurements of Gene Expression Levels by qRT-PCR</title>
        <p>For mRNA tag data and gene silencing confirmation, RNA was extracted using Trizol reagent (TIANGEN, China) and qRT-PCR experiments were performed on an ABI Prism&#xAE; 7300 (Applied Biosystems, USA). The number of transcripts was normalized with the constitutively expressed glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) mRNA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Hong1">[77]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0028810-Paolacci1">[78]</xref>, which was tested as the most stable reference gene for the wheat seedling powdery mildew infection assay (data not shown).. The qRT-PCR assays were repeated three times, each with three biological replicates. To test the silencing efficiency, qRT-PCR primers were designed as: <italic>TaFAD</italic> forward, <named-content content-type="gene">TACGTCGAGCCCGAGGACCG</named-content>; <italic>TaFAD</italic> reverse, <named-content content-type="gene">TGCCCCAAAATGCCCTCTTGCT</named-content>; <italic>TaFAD6</italic> (Ta-1294165443) forward, <named-content content-type="gene">GGGAGAAGTCACCACCAA</named-content>; and <italic>TaFAD6</italic> reverse, <named-content content-type="gene">GACCGAAAGCATACGAAG</named-content>. RNA from the BSMV&#x2236;GFP-treated plants was used as controls.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s001">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>MapMan biotic overview of PmA-specific H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> responding genes.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s001.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s002">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The statistics of the mRNA tags from the six wheat libraries in this study.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s002.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s003">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The statistics of the differentially expressed transcripts in response to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment in the wheat lines PmA, Han, and Cha.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s003.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s004">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The correlation coefficients (<italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic>) of the mRNA tag numbers for genes shared among different libraries.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s004.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s005">
        <label>Table S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>q</bold>RT-PCR validation of 28 differentially expressed genes as detected by the miRNA tag analysis.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s005.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s006">
        <label>Table S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The full list of genes with the same differential expression patterns in all three wheat lines under H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> stress.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s006.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s007">
        <label>Table S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Classification of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> responsive genes with specific expression patterns in PmA.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s007.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s008">
        <label>Table S7</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The full list of 2,982 PmA-specific differentially expressed ESTs under H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s008.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s009">
        <label>Table S8</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Representative H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> regulated genes associated with the enriched GO term vesicle-mediated transport from the class I PmA specific genes.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s009.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s010">
        <label>Table S9</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Functional categories of PmA-specific H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> responding genes from the MapMan biotic stress overview.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s010.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s011">
        <label>Table S10</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Functional classification of 328 PmA-specific ESTs from the biotic overview in MapMan.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s011.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s012">
        <label>Table S11</label>
        <caption>
          <p>qRT-PCR confirmation of JA/Et signal pathway genes under H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s012.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s013">
        <label>Table S12</label>
        <caption>
          <p><italic>Blumeria graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic> penetration efficiency (PE) in the VIGS plants.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s013.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0028810.s014">
        <label>Table S13</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Expression patterns of putative JA and SA signaling pathway related genes in the <italic>BSMV&#x2236;FAD</italic> and <italic>BSMV&#x2236;HSP90</italic> plants.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0028810.s014.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We would like to thank Dr. Daowen Wang, IGDB, CAS and Dr. Ruilian Jing, ICS, CAAS for kindly providing the VIGS vector and the seeds of Hanxuan10 respectively.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p><bold>Funding: </bold>This work is supported in part by the National &#x201C;863&#x201D; program of Ministry of Science and Technology (#2009AA02Z307), and the National Transgenic Key Project (#2009ZX08009-009B and #2011ZX08009-001). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Costa1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drago</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Behera</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zottini</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pizzo</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <article-title>H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in plant peroxisomes: an <italic>in vivo</italic> analysis uncovers a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent scavenging system.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Journal</source>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <fpage>760</fpage>
          <lpage>772</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20230493</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Prasad1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Prasad</surname>
              <given-names>TK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stewart</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1994</year>
          <article-title>Evidence for chilling-induced oxidative stress in maize seedlings and a regulatory role for hydrogen peroxide.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>65</fpage>
          <lpage>74</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12244221</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Loggini1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Loggini</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scartazza</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brugnoli</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Navari-Izzo</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1999</year>
          <article-title>Antioxidative defense system, pigment composition, and photosynthetic efficiency in two wheat cultivars subjected to drought.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>119</volume>
          <fpage>1091</fpage>
          <lpage>1099</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10069848</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Valderrama1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Valderrama</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corpas</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carreras</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gomez-Rodriguez</surname>
              <given-names>MV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chaki</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>The dehydrogenase-mediated recycling of NADPH is a key antioxidant system against salt-induced oxidative stress in olive plants.</article-title>
          <source>Plant, Cell &amp; Environment</source>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>1449</fpage>
          <lpage>1459</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Mackerness1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mackerness</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surplus</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blake</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>John</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buchanan-Wollaston</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>1999</year>
          <article-title>Ultraviolet-B induced stress and changes in gene expression in Arabidopsis thaliana: role of signaling pathways controlled by jasmonic acid, ethylene and reactive oxygen species.</article-title>
          <source>Plant, Cell &amp; Environment</source>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>1413</fpage>
          <lpage>1423</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Pellinen1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pellinen</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Palva</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kangasja</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1999</year>
          <article-title>Subcellular localization of ozone-induced hydrogen peroxide production in birch (<italic>Betula pendula</italic>) leaf cells.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Journal</source>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>349</fpage>
          <lpage>356</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10571895</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Schutzendubel1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schutzendubel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Polle</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Plant responses to abiotic stresses: heavy metal-induced oxidative stress and protection by mycorrhization.</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>1351</fpage>
          <lpage>1365</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11997381</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Liu1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhan</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pan</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Systemic induction of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in pea seedlings pretreated by wounding and exogenous jasmonic acid.</article-title>
          <source>Science in China Series C: Life Sciences</source>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>202</fpage>
          <lpage>212</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Pei1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pei</surname>
              <given-names>ZM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murata</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benning</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomine</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klusener</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>Calcium channels activated by hydrogen peroxide mediate abscisic acid signalling in guard cells.</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <volume>406</volume>
          <fpage>731</fpage>
          <lpage>734</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10963598</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Levine1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Levine</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tenhaken</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dixon</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lamb</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1994</year>
          <article-title>H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> from the oxidative burst orchestrates the plant hypersensitive disease resistance response.</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>583</fpage>
          <lpage>593</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7954825</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Li1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kong</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huo</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Comparative analysis of early H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation in compatible and incompatible wheat-powdery mildew interactions.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Pathology</source>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>308</fpage>
          <lpage>316</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Desikan1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Desikan</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mackerness</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hancock</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neill</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>Regulation of the Arabidopsis transcriptome by oxidative stress.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>127</volume>
          <fpage>159</fpage>
          <lpage>172</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11553744</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Mittler1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mittler</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vanderauwera</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gollery</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Breusegem</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Reactive oxygen gene network of plants.</article-title>
          <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>490</fpage>
          <lpage>498</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15465684</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Vanderauwera1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vanderauwera</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zimmermann</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rombauts</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vandenabeele</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Langebartels</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Genome-wide analysis of hydrogen peroxide-regulated gene expression in Arabidopsis reveals a high light-induced transcriptional cluster involved in anthocyanin biosynthesis.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>139</volume>
          <fpage>806</fpage>
          <lpage>821</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16183842</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Wan1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wan</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Comparative proteomics analysis reveals an intimate protein network provoked by hydrogen peroxide stress in rice seedling leaves.</article-title>
          <source>Molecular &amp; Cell Proteomics</source>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>1469</fpage>
          <lpage>1488</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Lenucci1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lenucci</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Piro</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dalessandro</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>In muro feruloylation and oxidative coupling in monocots A possible role in plant defense against pathogen attacks.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Signaling &amp; Behaviour</source>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>228</fpage>
          <lpage>230</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Kovtun1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kovtun</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiu</surname>
              <given-names>WL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tena</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sheen</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>Functional analysis of oxidative stress-activated mitogen-activated protein kinase cascade in plants.</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>2940</fpage>
          <lpage>2945</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Mou1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mou</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Inducers of plant systemic acquired resistance regulate NPR1 function through redox changes.</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>935</fpage>
          <lpage>944</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12837250</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Montillet1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Montillet</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chamnongpol</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rusterucci</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dat</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van de Cotte</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Fatty acid hydroperoxides and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in the execution of hypersensitive cell death in tobacco leaves.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>138</volume>
          <fpage>1516</fpage>
          <lpage>1526</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980200</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Thoma1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thoma</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loeffler</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sinha</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krischke</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Cyclopentenone isoprostanes induced by reactive oxygen species trigger defense gene activation and phytoalexin accumulation in plants.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Journal</source>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>363</fpage>
          <lpage>375</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12713542</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Mur1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mur</surname>
              <given-names>LAJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kenton</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lloyd</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ougham</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prats</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>The hypersensitive response; the centenary is upon us but how much do we know?</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>501</fpage>
          <lpage>520</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18079135</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Torres1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Torres</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>JDG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dangl</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Reactive oxygen species signaling in response to pathogens.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>141</volume>
          <fpage>373</fpage>
          <lpage>378</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16760490</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Blee1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Blee</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Impact of phyto-oxylipins in plant defense.</article-title>
          <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>315</fpage>
          <lpage>322</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12119169</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Kunkel1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kunkel</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brooks</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Cross talk between signaling pathways in pathogen defense.</article-title>
          <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>325</fpage>
          <lpage>331</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12179966</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Overmyer1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Overmyer</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brosche</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kangasjarvi</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Reactive oxygen species and hormonal control of cell death.</article-title>
          <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>335</fpage>
          <lpage>342</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12878018</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Bouchez1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bouchez</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huard</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lorrain</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roby</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balague</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Ethylene is one of the key elements for cell death and defense response control in the Arabidopsis lesion mimic mutant vad1.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>145</volume>
          <fpage>465</fpage>
          <lpage>477</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17720753</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Vanacker1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vanacker</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carver</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Foyer</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>Early H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation in mesophyll cells leads to induction of glutathione during the hyper-sensitive response in the barley-powdery mildew interaction.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>123</volume>
          <fpage>1289</fpage>
          <lpage>1300</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10938348</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Torres2">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Torres</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <article-title>ROS in biotic interactions.</article-title>
          <source>Physiologia Plantarum</source>
          <volume>138</volume>
          <fpage>414</fpage>
          <lpage>429</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20002601</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Despres1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Despres</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chubak</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rochon</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clark</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bethune</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>The Arabidopsis NPR1 disease resistance protein is a novel cofactor that confers redox regulation of DNA binding activity to the basic domain/leucine zipper transcription factor TGA1.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>2181</fpage>
          <lpage>2191</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12953119</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Cao1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cao</surname>
              <given-names>AZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xing</surname>
              <given-names>LP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>XM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Serine/threonine kinase gene Stpk-V, a key member of powdery mildew resistance gene Pm21, confers powdery mildew resistance in wheat.</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <volume>108</volume>
          <fpage>7727</fpage>
          <lpage>7732</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Anthony1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Anthony</surname>
              <given-names>RG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henriques</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Helfer</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meszaros</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rios</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>A protein kinase target of a PDK1 signalling pathway is involved in root hair growth in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
          <source>EMBO Journal</source>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>572</fpage>
          <lpage>581</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14749726</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Stone1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stone</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>An assessment of proposed mechanisms for sensing hydrogen peroxide in mammalian systems.</article-title>
          <source>Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics</source>
          <volume>422</volume>
          <fpage>119</fpage>
          <lpage>124</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14759598</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Qin1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Qin</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peng</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yao</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ni</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Heat stress-responsive transcriptome analysis in heat susceptible and tolerant wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) by using Wheat Genome Array.</article-title>
          <source>BMC Genomics</source>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>432</fpage>
          <lpage>451</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18808683</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Aprile1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aprile</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mastrangelo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Leonardis</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galiba</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roncaglia</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Transcriptional profiling in response to terminal drought stress reveals differential responses along the wheat genome.</article-title>
          <source>BMC Genomics</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>279</fpage>
          <lpage>297</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19552804</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Hulbert1">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hulbert</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bai</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fellers</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pacheco</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bowden</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Gene expression patterns in near isogenic lines for wheat rust resistance gene Lr34/Yr18.</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>1083</fpage>
          <lpage>1093</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944173</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Coram1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Coram</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Settles</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Transcriptome analysis of high-temperature adult-plant resistance conditioned by Yr39 during the wheat-Puccinia striiformis f. sp. tritici interaction.</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant Pathology</source>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>479</fpage>
          <lpage>493</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18705862</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Boyd1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boyd</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Wheat blast: histopathology and transcriptome reprogramming in response to adapted and nonadapted Magnaporthe isolates.</article-title>
          <source>New Phytologist</source>
          <volume>184</volume>
          <fpage>473</fpage>
          <lpage>484</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19645735</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Desmond1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Desmond</surname>
              <given-names>OJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manners</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schenk</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maclean</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kazan</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Gene expression in the wheat response to infection by <italic>Fusarium pseudograminearum</italic>.</article-title>
          <source>Physiological and Molecular Plant Pathology</source>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>40</fpage>
          <lpage>47</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Chain1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chain</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cote-Beaulieu</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Belzile</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Menzies</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Belanger</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>A Comprehensive Transcriptomic Analysis of the Effect of Silicon on Wheat Plants Under Control and Pathogen Stress Conditions.</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant-Microbe Interaction</source>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>1323</fpage>
          <lpage>1330</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Schreiber1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schreiber</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sutton</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caldo</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalashyan</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lovell</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Comparative transcriptomics in the Triticeae.</article-title>
          <source>BMC Genomics</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>285</fpage>
          <lpage>302</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19558723</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-An1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>An</surname>
              <given-names>QL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ehlers</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kogel</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Bel</surname>
              <given-names>AJE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>H&#xFC;ckelhoven</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Multivesicular compartments proliferate in susceptible and resistant MLA12-barley leaves in response to infection by the biotrophic powdery mildew fungus.</article-title>
          <source>New Phytologist</source>
          <volume>172</volume>
          <fpage>563</fpage>
          <lpage>576</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17083686</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Thimm1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thimm</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blsing</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gibon</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meyer</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>MAPMAN: A user-driven tool to display genomics data sets onto diagrams of metabolic pathways and other biological processes.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Journal</source>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>914</fpage>
          <lpage>939</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14996223</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Zeng1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zeng</surname>
              <given-names>LR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vega-S&#xE1;nchez</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Ubiquitination-mediated protein degradation and modification: an emerging theme in plant-microbe interactions.</article-title>
          <source>Cell Research</source>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>413</fpage>
          <lpage>426</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16699537</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Romeis1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Romeis</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>Protein kinase in the plant defence response.</article-title>
          <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>407</fpage>
          <lpage>414</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11597498</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-McConn1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McConn</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Creelman</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bell</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mullet</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1997</year>
          <article-title>Jasmonate is essential for insect defense in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>5473</fpage>
          <lpage>5477</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Vijayan1">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vijayan</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shockey</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levesque</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cook</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1998</year>
          <article-title>A role for jasmonate in pathogen defense of Arabidopsis.</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <fpage>7209</fpage>
          <lpage>7214</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Thomma1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thomma</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eggermont</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Broekaert</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cammue</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>Disease development of several fungi on Arabidopsis can be reduced by treatment with methyl jasmonate.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</source>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>421</fpage>
          <lpage>427</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Kachroo1">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kachroo</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shanklin</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Whittle</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klessig</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>A fatty acid desaturase modulates the activation of defense signaling pathways in plants.</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <fpage>9448</fpage>
          <lpage>9453</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Jiang1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimono</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maeda</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inoue</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mori</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Suppression of the rice fatty-acid desaturase gene OsSSI2 enhances resistance to blast and leaf blight diseases in rice.</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant-Microbe Interaction</source>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>820</fpage>
          <lpage>829</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Scofield1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scofield</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brandt</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Development of a virus-induced gene-silencing system for hexaploid wheat and its use in functional analysis of the Lr21-mediated leaf rust resistance pathway.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>138</volume>
          <fpage>2165</fpage>
          <lpage>2173</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16024691</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Wang1">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>GF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wei</surname>
              <given-names>XN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>HB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>XP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Molecular analysis of common wheat genes encoding three types of cytosolic heat shock protein 90 (Hsp90): functional involvement of cytosolic Hsp90s in the control of wheat seedling growth and disease resistance.</article-title>
          <source>New Phytologist</source>
          <volume>191</volume>
          <fpage>418</fpage>
          <lpage>431</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21488877</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Qiu1">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Qiu</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xiao</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ding</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xiong</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cai</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>OsWRKY13 mediates rice disease resistance by regulating defense-related genes in salicylate- and jasmonate-dependent signaling.</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant-Microbe Interaction</source>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>492</fpage>
          <lpage>499</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Tao1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tao</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qiu</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>A pair of allelic WRKY genes play opposite role in rice-bacteria interactions.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>151</volume>
          <fpage>936</fpage>
          <lpage>948</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19700558</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Lu1">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malcuit</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moffett</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruiz</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peart</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>High throughput virus-induced gene silencing implicates heat shock protein 90 in plant disease resistance.</article-title>
          <source>EMBO Journal</source>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>5690</fpage>
          <lpage>5699</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14592968</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Hein1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hein</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barciszewska-Pacak</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hrubikova</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williamson</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dinesen</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Virus-induced gene silencingbased functional characterization of genes associated with powdery mildew resistance in barley.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>138</volume>
          <fpage>2155</fpage>
          <lpage>2164</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16040663</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Zhou1">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>HB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>SF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deng</surname>
              <given-names>ZY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>XP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Molecular analysis of three new receptor-like kinase genes from hexaploid wheat and evidence for their participation in the wheat hypersensitive response to stripe rust fungus infection.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Journal</source>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>420</fpage>
          <lpage>434</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17764502</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Matsuda1">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Matsuda</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okuda</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sagisaka</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1994</year>
          <article-title>Regulation of Protein Synthesis by Hydrogen Peroxide in Crowns of Winter Wheat.</article-title>
          <source>Bioscience,Biotechnology, and Biochemistry</source>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>906</fpage>
          <lpage>909</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Collins1">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Collins</surname>
              <given-names>NC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thordal-Christensen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lipka</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bau</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kombrink</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>SNARE-protein-mediated disease resistance at the plant cell wall.</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <volume>425</volume>
          <fpage>973</fpage>
          <lpage>977</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14586469</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Leshem1">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Leshem</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Melamed&#x2013;Book</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cagnac</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ronen</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nishri</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Suppression of Arabidopsis vesicle-SNARE expression inhibited fusion of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-containing vesicles with tonoplast and increased salt tolerance.</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>18008</fpage>
          <lpage>18013</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Fryer1">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fryer</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ball</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oxborough</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karpinski</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mullineaux</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Control of ascorbate peroxidase 2 expression by hydrogen peroxide and leaf water status during excess light stress reveals a functional organisation of Arabidopsis leaves.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Journal</source>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>691</fpage>
          <lpage>705</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12609042</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Chang1">
        <label>61</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>CCC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ball</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fryer</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baker</surname>
              <given-names>NR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karpinski</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Induction of ascorbate peroxidase 2 expression in wounded Arabidopsis leaves does not involve known wound-signalling pathways but is associated with changes in photosynthesis.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Journal</source>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>499</fpage>
          <lpage>511</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15086807</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Mateo1">
        <label>62</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mateo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muhlenbock</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rusterucci</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>CCC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miszalski</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Lesion simulating disease 1 is required for acclimation to conditions that promote excess excitation energy.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>136</volume>
          <fpage>2818</fpage>
          <lpage>2830</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15347794</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Overmyer2">
        <label>63</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Overmyer</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brosche</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pellinen</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuittenen</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tuominen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Ozone-induced programmed cell death in the Arabidopsis radical-induced cell death 1 mutant.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>137</volume>
          <fpage>1092</fpage>
          <lpage>1104</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728341</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Mateo2">
        <label>64</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mateo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Funck</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muhlenbock</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kular</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mullineaux</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Controlled levels of salicylic acid are required for optimal photosynthesis and redox homeostasis.</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>1795</fpage>
          <lpage>1807</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16698814</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Muhlenbock1">
        <label>65</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Muhlenbock</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plaszczyca</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plaszczyca</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mellerowicz</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karpinski</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Lysigenous aerenchyma formation in Arabidopsis is controlled by lesion simulating disease1.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>3819</fpage>
          <lpage>3830</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18055613</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Laudert1">
        <label>66</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Laudert</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weiler</surname>
              <given-names>EW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1998</year>
          <article-title>Allene oxide synthase: A major control point in Arabidopsis thaliana octadecanoid signalling.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Journal</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>675</fpage>
          <lpage>684</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9778849</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Kachroo2">
        <label>67</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kachroo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lapchyk</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fukushigae</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hildebrand</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klessig</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003a</year>
          <article-title>Plastidal fatty acid signaling modulates SA- and JA-mediated signaling in the Arabidopsis ssi2 mutant.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>2952</fpage>
          <lpage>2965</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14615603</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Kachroo3">
        <label>68</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kachroo</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kachroo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lapchyk</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hildebrand</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klessig</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003b</year>
          <article-title>Restoration of defective cross talk in <italic>ssi2</italic> mutant: Role of salicylic acid, jasmonic acid, and fatty acids in <italic>SSI2</italic>-mediated signaling.</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant-Microbe Interaction</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>1022</fpage>
          <lpage>1029</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Kachroo4">
        <label>69</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kachroo</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srivathsa</surname>
              <given-names>CV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Navarre</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lapchyk</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kachroo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Role of salicylic acid and fatty acid desaturation pathways in <italic>ssi2</italic>-mediated signaling.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>139</volume>
          <fpage>1717</fpage>
          <lpage>1735</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16306139</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Kachroo5">
        <label>70</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kachroo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daqi</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Havens</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Navarre</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kachroo</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Virus-induced gene silencing of stearoyl-acyl carrier protein-desaturase in soybean results in constitutive defense and enhanced resistance to pathogens.</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant-Microbe Interaction</source>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>564</fpage>
          <lpage>575</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Chaturvedi1">
        <label>71</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chaturvedi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krothapalli</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Makandar</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nandi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sparks</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Plastid &#x3C9;3-fatty acid desaturase-dependent accumulation of a systemic acquired resistance inducing activity in petiole exudates of Arabidopsis thaliana is independent of jasmonic acid.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Journal</source>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>106</fpage>
          <lpage>117</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18088304</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Zhou2">
        <label>72</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>ZD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kong</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huo</surname>
              <given-names>NX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tian</surname>
              <given-names>QZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Development of wheat near-isogenic lines for powdery mildew resistance.</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>640</fpage>
          <lpage>648</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15723273</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Tiwari1">
        <label>73</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tiwari</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Belenghi</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levine</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Oxidative stress increased respiration and generation of reactive oxygen species, resulting in ATP depletion, opening of mitochondrial permeability transition, and programmed cell death.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <volume>128</volume>
          <fpage>1271</fpage>
          <lpage>1281</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11950976</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Hoen1">
        <label>74</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hoen</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ariyurek</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thygesen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vreugdenhil</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vossen</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Deep sequencing-based expression analysis shows major advances in robustness, resolution and inter-lab portability over five microarray platforms.</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Audic1">
        <label>75</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Audic</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Claverie</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1997</year>
          <article-title>The significance of digital gene expression profiles.</article-title>
          <source>Genome Research</source>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>986</fpage>
          <lpage>995</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9331369</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Holzberg1">
        <label>76</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Holzberg</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brosio</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gross</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pogue</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Barley stripe mosaic virus-induced gene silencing in a monocot plant.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Journal</source>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>315</fpage>
          <lpage>327</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12000679</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Hong1">
        <label>77</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hong</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seo</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xiang</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Exploring valid reference genes for gene expression studies in Brachypodium distachyon by real-time PCR.</article-title>
          <source>BMC Plant Biology</source>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>112</fpage>
          <lpage>120</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18992143</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0028810-Paolacci1">
        <label>78</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Paolacci</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanzarella</surname>
              <given-names>OA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Porceddu</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ciaffi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Identification and validation of reference genes for quantitative RT-PCR normalization in wheat.</article-title>
          <source>BMC Molecular Biology</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19232096</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
