<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.0 20040830//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3273457</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-12952</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029432</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Agriculture</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Crops</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cereals</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genomics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genomics</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Plant Science</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Agronomy</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Identifying Loci Influencing 1,000-Kernel Weight in Wheat by Microsatellite Screening for Evidence of Selection during Breeding</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Loci Influencing 1,000-Kernel Weight in Wheat</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Lanfen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ge</surname>
            <given-names>Hongmei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>Chenyang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>Yushen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Xueyong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <addr-line>Key Laboratory of Crop Germplasm Resources and Utilization, Ministry of Agriculture, The National Key Facility for Crop Gene Resources and Genetic Improvement, Institute of Crop Science, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Hudson</surname>
            <given-names>Matthew E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">University of Illinois, United States of America</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>xueyongz@caas.net.cn</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: XZ YD. Performed the experiments: LW HG CH. Analyzed the data: LW HG CH. Wrote the paper: XZ. Keeps the materials: LW. Provided the analysis tools: HG.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>6</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <elocation-id>e29432</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Wang et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chinese wheat mini core collection (262 accessions) was genotyped at 531 microsatellite loci representing a mean marker density of 5.1 cM. One-thousand-kernel weights (TKW) of lines were measured in five trials (three environments in four growing seasons). Structure analysis based on 42 unlinked SSR loci indicated that the materials formed two sub-populations, viz., landraces and modern varieties. A large difference in TKW (7.08 g, <italic>P&lt;0.001</italic>) was found between the two sub-groups. Therefore, TKW is a major yield component that was improved in the past 6 decades; it increased from a mean 31.5 g in the 1940s to 44.64 g in the 2000s, representing a 2.19 g increase in each decade. Analyses based on a mixed linear model (MLM), population structure (Q) and relative kinship (K) revealed 22 SSR loci that were significantly associated with mean TKW (MTKW) of the five trials estimated by the best linear unbiased predictor (BLUP) method. They were mainly distributed on chromosomes of homoeologous groups 1, 2, 3, 5 and 7. Six loci, <italic>cfa2234-3A</italic>, <italic>gwm156</italic>-3B, <italic>barc</italic>56-5A, <italic>gwm234</italic>-5B, <italic>wmc</italic>17-7A and <italic>cfa2257</italic>-7A individually explained more than 11.84% of the total phenotypic variation. Favored alleles for breeding at the 22 loci were inferred according to their estimated effects on MTKW based on mean difference of varieties grouped by genotypes. Statistical simulation showed that these favored alleles have additive genetic effects. Frequency changes of alleles at loci associated with TKW are much more dramatic than those at neutral loci between the sub-groups. The numbers of favored alleles in modern varieties indicate there is still considerable genetic potential for their use as markers for genome selection of TKW in wheat breeding. Alleles that can be used globally to increase TKW were inferred according to their distribution by latitude and frequency of changes between landraces and the modern varieties.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>China is the largest wheat producer and consumer in the world, with 23.6 million ha, a mean 4,762 kg/ha, and a 112 million tonnes total production in 2008. There is long history of wheat cultivation in China extending over more than 2,000 years. Production extends from latitude 22&#xB0;49&#x2032; to 48&#xB0;03&#x2032; and much progress has been achieved in breeding and production in the last 60 years. Average wheat yields increased annually by 1.9% and production increased more than six-fold <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-He1">[1]</xref>. Thousand-kernel weight (TKW), as one of three major components of yield in wheat, has steadily increased over the period. Based on phenotyping of 1,800 cultivars released since the 1940s, TKW increased from a mean 31.5 g in the 1940s to 44.64 g in the 2000s, with a 2.19 g increase in each decade (Zhang et al. unpublished). Previous studies also showed that TKW was one of the three yield components with highest heritability, which varied from 59% to 80% <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Xiao1">[2]</xref>. Most genes affecting TKW have additive effects. Selection for TKW in the early generations of breeding is highly effective <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Xiao1">[2]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Crop domestication is an artificial evolutionary process of combining traits to meet human needs. During the domestication of cereals, for example, reductions in plant height to avoid lodging, large spikes, increased grain size, and disease resistance, were selected and conserved. Modern breeding involved further directional selection, which resulted in lower genetic diversity within the domesticated population than in the entire species. At the genome level, only a small number of genes (alleles) were positively selected and conserved <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Wright1">[3]</xref>. Many other alleles at specific loci were gradually eliminated, leading to reduced genetic diversity at these loci compared with those present in the entire species. Diversity in genomic regions flanking the target genes was simultaneously reduced because of linkage. This phenomenon is referred to as linkage drag, hitchhiking, or selection sweep <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Andolfatto1">[4]</xref>. Hitchhiking generally leads to reduced diversity at target loci, linkage disequilibrium at loci surrounding the selected gene, and changed distribution patterns of alleles within the selected region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Schltterer1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Zhang1">[6]</xref>. These effects also provide the bases for association of neutral markers, such as SSR and DArT, with agronomic traits <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Zhang1">[6]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Barrero1">[10]</xref>.</p>
      <p>We established a Chinese common wheat core collection (CC) and a mini core collection (MCC) after genotyping 5,029 candidate accessions at 78 SSR loci <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao1">[11]</xref>. Choice of candidate entries was based on documentary data in the national gene bank <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Dong1">[12]</xref>. The MCC contains 231 accessions, or 1% of the basic collection (23,135 accessions) with an estimated 70% representation of the genetic variation in that collection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao2">[13]</xref>. The higher genetic diversity and artificial diminishment of dominant allelic frequencies in the MCC makes it a suitable population for detection of major QTLs controlling yield traits. It was shown to be a good reference set for revealing geographic distribution and time changes of important functional genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Barrero1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Wang1">[14]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Su1">[18]</xref>. In this study, we target loci associated with TKW to show the value of the MCC in dissecting complex yield traits in wheat. This association analysis provides useful information for marker-assisted selection in breeding wheat for increasing yield.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Phenotypic Assessment</title>
        <p>TKWs of the Chinese mini core wheat collection were measured in 4 growing seasons and 3 environments, including Luoyang, Henan province 2002, 2005, and 2006; Shunyi, Beijing 2010; and Qingdao, Shandong 2010 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t001">Table 1</xref>). Minor differences in mean TKW occurred among different planting environments, and there were major differences between landraces and modern varieties. The MTKW of modern varieties (39.23 g) calculated using BLUP methods based on multiple environments was significantly higher (<italic>P&lt;0.001</italic>) than that of landraces (32.15 g), confirming that TKW was a yield trait improved by breeding. The maximum TKW was not in a modern variety, but was in a landrace. This indicates that further genes for this trait are present in landraces and can be accessed for breeding. The total agronomic data were considered in whole genome association analysis.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0029432-t001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029432.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison of 1,000-kernel weights between landraces and modern varieties in the Chinese wheat mini core collection in the 5 environments.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0029432-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0029432.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TKW-L02</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TKW-L05</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TKW-L06</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TKW-S10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TKW-Q10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MTKW</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landraces</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.72&#xB1;0.58</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.66&#xB1;0.51</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.06&#xB1;0.43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.23&#xB1;0.47</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.37&#xB1;0.51</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.15&#xB1;0.37</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M varieties</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.69&#xB1;0.74</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.67&#xB1;0.67</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.81&#xB1;0.65</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.67&#xB1;0.73</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.87&#xB1;0.64</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.23&#xB1;0.54</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.59E-15</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.98E-18</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03E-20</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51E-16</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.45E-17</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33E-23</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landraces</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.78</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.47</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.65</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.22</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.06</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.78</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M modern varieties</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.46</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.76</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.56</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landraces</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.56</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.94</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.66</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.02</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.48</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.57</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M varieties</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.68</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.91</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.58</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.99</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>L: Luoyang, Henan province; S: Shunyi, Beijing; Q: Qingdao, Shandong province.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Population Structure Analysis</title>
        <p>Population structure analysis can identify locus associations that are statistically significant, but biologically invalid due to strong correlation with population structure. However, if the population structure is properly dealt with, the likelihood of spurious associations can be minimised <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-FlintGarcia1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Ersoz1">[19]</xref>. Forty-two loci distributed across every arm of the 21 wheat chromosomes were chosen to examine the population structure of entries in the mini core collection. We selected K values of assumed groups from 1 to 10. After 80 cycles of simulation, we found that K&#x200A;=&#x200A;2 was the best separator providing the highest delta k value, and showing that the MCC entries comprised two sub-populations. One group was mainly the landraces, and the other included modern varieties and introduced lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Overlapping occurs between the two groups because in the early breeding period (1940&#x2013;1960s), most of the released varieties were derived from crosses between Chinese landraces and introduced European or American varieties <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Zhuang1">[20]</xref>. This was consistent with results based on 512 SSR loci using a similar set of materials <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao2">[13]</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0029432-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029432.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Population structure analysis of 262 wheat cultivars based on 42 unlinked SSR loci.</title>
            <p>a: Population structure as determined by Structure v2.2 analysis. Since &#x394;k peaks at k&#x200A;=&#x200A;2, the varietal set was split into two sub-groups. b: Structure analysis reveals that the 262 wheat cultivars are clustered into two sub-populations. I. Landrances. II. Modern varieties and introduced lines.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0029432.g001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>SSR Loci Associated with TKW</title>
        <p>We firstly used the MLM model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Yu1">[21]</xref> to make a marker/MTKW (TKW) association analysis. Thirty-two loci were significantly (<italic>P&lt;0.05</italic>) associated with MTKW. An association with <italic>cfa2257</italic> on 7AL was detected in all five trials; 8 loci were detected in four trials, i.e. <italic>wmc304-1A</italic>, <italic>wmc147-1D</italic>, <italic>gwm312-2A</italic>, <italic>gwm547-3B</italic>, <italic>gwm234</italic>-<italic>5B</italic>, <italic>gwm174</italic>-<italic>5D</italic>, gwm55-<italic>6D</italic>, and <italic>wmc17-7A</italic>; 6 loci were detected in three environments, viz., <italic>gwm268-1B</italic>, <italic>cfa2234-3A</italic>, <italic>gwm156-3B</italic>, <italic>cfd266-5D</italic>, <italic>gwm356-6A</italic> and <italic>gwm471-7A</italic>; 9 loci in two environments, and eight loci were detected in one trial (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029432.s002">Table S1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0029432-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029432.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Genome wide association analysis of 1,000-kernel weight with SSR loci.</title>
            <p>TKWs collected from 5 trials were used to estimate mean values (MTKW). TKW-L02, TKW-L05, TKW-L06, TKW-S10, and TKW-Q10 indicate 1,000-kernel weights in 2002, 2005 and 2006 in Luoyang (Henan province), 2010 in Shunyi (Beijing) and Qingdao (Shandong), respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0029432.g002"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Among the 24 loci associated with MTKW in at least two trials, we found breeder-favored alleles with strong positive effects on MTKW at 22 loci; and they were mapped to 11 chromosomes, viz. 1A, 1B, 1D, 2A, 3A, 3B, 5A, 5B, 5D, 6D, and 7A. The 7A effect spanned four loci, including <italic>gwm471</italic>, <italic>wmc168</italic>, <italic>wmc17</italic> and <italic>cfa2257</italic>. The genetic distance between <italic>wmc17</italic> and <italic>cfa2257</italic> is 2.72 cM. No stronger linkage disequilibrium (LD) was found between the two loci (r<italic><sup>2</sup></italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;0.10, P&gt;0.05) indicating they may not relate to a single yield gene, a result also suggested by previous QTL studies of TKW <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Huang1">[22]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Tsilo1">[26]</xref>. Three loci on chromosomes 1B and 2A were associated with MTKW. The allelic effect at each locus on MTKW was estimated by ANOVA (SPSS16). Significant or extremely significant differences in MTKW were detected between varieties with the favored allele and those with other alleles. Six loci with the strongest effects, and individually explaining more than 10% of the total variation were detected on chromosomes 3A, 3B, 5A, 5B and 7A (<italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic>&gt;10%) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0029432-t002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029432.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Favored alleles, their frequencies, genetic effects and <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> at 22 SSR loci significantly (<italic>P&lt;0.05</italic>) associated with MTKW.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0029432-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0029432.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loci</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr.</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genetic Position (cM)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Favored allele (bp)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Freq. (%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MTGW (mean&#xB1;S.E)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> (%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Times associated</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QTL reported [Reference No.]</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>cfa2153</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.24</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.58&#xB1;0.67</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">**</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.76</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.09&#xB1;0.41</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>wmc304</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.41</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.83&#xB1;0.87</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31E-4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Gupta1">[34]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.59</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.19&#xB1;0.38</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>gwm11</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1B</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.27</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.08&#xB1;0.89</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">**</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Sun1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Gupta1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Wang2">[36]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.73</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.38&#xB1;0.38</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>gwm403</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1B</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.14</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.29&#xB1;0.81</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Sun1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Quarrie2">[65]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.86</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.36&#xB1;0.39</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>gwm268</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1B</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.02</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.80&#xB1;1.45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.58E-5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.23</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.98</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.35&#xB1;0.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>wmc147</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1D</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.14</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.31&#xB1;0.81</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41-4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.07</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Sun2">[35]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.86</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.08&#xB1;0.38</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>gwm275</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.87&#xB1;0.85</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02E-5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Tsilo1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Gupta1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Snape1">[38]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.55</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.26&#xB1;0.37</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>gwm312</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.26</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.41</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.55&#xB1;0.91</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98E-6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.99</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Huang1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Tsilo1">[26]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.59</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.05&#xB1;0.37</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>gwm372</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">331</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.93&#xB1;1.80</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.16E-6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.03</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Huang1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Tsilo1">[26]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.89</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.39&#xB1;0.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>cfa2234</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.38</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.89</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.59&#xB1;0.49</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Gupta1">[34]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6&#xB1;0.43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>gwm156</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3B</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.05</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">311</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.91&#xB1;1.07</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56E-10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.27</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Gupta1">[34]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.55</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.00&#xB1;0.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>gwm547</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3B</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">null</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.54&#xB1;0.83</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.46</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Gupta1">[34]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.55</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.18&#xB1;0.37</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>barc56</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.86</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.02&#xB1;0.60</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.46E-9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.84</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Cuthbert1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Sun1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Gupta1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Wang2">[36]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.14</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.54&#xB1;0.40</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>gwm234</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5B</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.57</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237 and 239</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.79</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.05&#xB1;0.83</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.86E-12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.48</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Tsilo1">[26]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.73&#xB1;0.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>wmc415</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5B</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.29</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.46</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.38&#xB1;0.58</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.85E-4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.84</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Groos1">[37]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.54</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.71&#xB1;0.43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>cfd266</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5D</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">167</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.08</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.49&#xB1;0.82</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.99E-4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.83</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.92</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.15&#xB1;0.38</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>gwm174</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5D</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.85</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.92</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.01&#xB1;1.13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.86E-7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.71</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Quarrie2">[65]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.08</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.22&#xB1;0.36</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>gwm55</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6D</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.76</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.82&#xB1;0.74</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.09E-6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Wang2">[36]</xref>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.24</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.95&#xB1;0.39</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>gwm471</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.14&#xB1;1.39</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85E-6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.54</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Quarrie1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Gupta1">[34]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.89</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.38&#xB1;0.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>wmc168</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">307</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.93&#xB1;1.50</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">**</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Quarrie1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Gupta1">[34]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5&#xB1;0.36</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>wmc17</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.17</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182 and 184</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.12&#xB1;0.55</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.09E-14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.62</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Quarrie1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Cuthbert1">[24]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.80&#xB1;0.39</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>cfa2257</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.89</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.61</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.13&#xB1;0.71</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.99E-16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.99</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Huang1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Sun1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Tsilo1">[26]</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.39</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.41&#xB1;0.35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label/>
              <p>*: P&lt;0.05;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label/>
              <p>**: P&lt;0.01;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label/>
              <p>***: P&lt;0.001.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt105">
              <label/>
              <p><italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic>: indicates the percentage of total variation explained.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt106">
              <label/>
              <p>Genetic positions of SSR markers on chromosome 1A to 7D were based on R&#xF6;der et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Rder2">[54]</xref>; Somers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Somers1">[55]</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp/wheat/komugi/maps/markerMap.jsp">http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp/wheat/komugi/maps/markerMap.jsp</ext-link>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt107">
              <label/>
              <p>Two favored alleles were detected at <italic>gwm234 and wmc</italic>17, respectively. To simplify the data process, the two alleles were considered to be the same in estimating their genetic effects on MTKW.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>The Distribution of Favored Alleles at Associated Loci</title>
        <p>We estimated the frequencies of favored alleles at each of the 22 loci in the landrace and modern entries groups in the mini core collection. Except at <italic>gwm403-1B</italic>, favored allele frequencies were much higher in modern varieties than in the landraces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g003">Figure 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029432.s003">Table S2</xref>). This reflects positive selection of those alleles in breeding programs.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0029432-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029432.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparative frequencies of favorable alleles at 22 loci for landraces and modern varieties in the Chinese wheat mini core collection.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0029432.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Modern varieties usually have fewer allelic variations than landraces <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao2">[13]</xref>. However, the major allele frequency is not always higher in modern varieties than in landraces (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029432.s004">Table S3</xref>). At the 42 loci without obvious signs of selection, the average major allelic frequency increased from 28.46% in landraces to 32.87% in modern varieties, and the <italic>t</italic>-test indicated that the change was not significant (<italic>t</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;1.661, <italic>p</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;0.1), but with equal variances (<italic>F</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;1.23)&lt;<italic>F<sub>0.05</sub></italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;1.69). However, at the 22 loci associated significantly with MTKW, their average frequency increased from 11.58% to 30.52%, an extremely significant difference (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029432.s003">Table S2</xref>; <italic>t</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;4.591, <italic>p</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;7.95E-05), and unequal variances (<italic>F</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;5.13, <italic>F<sub>0.05</sub></italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;2.07).</p>
        <p>Among the four loci with favored allelic frequencies higher than 50% in modern varieties, <italic>cfa2234</italic>-<italic>3A</italic>, <italic>barc56-5A</italic> and <italic>wmc17-7A</italic> were among the six loci with the highest effects on phenotype variation of TKW (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t002">Table 2</xref>). In addition, dramatic increases were also detected at <italic>wmc17</italic> and <italic>cfa2257</italic> on 7A (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029432.s003">Table S2</xref>); these were also among the six loci (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t002">Table 2</xref>). The increased numbers and frequencies of favored alleles were accompanied by increased mean MTKW in modern varieties (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t003">Table 3</xref>). Therefore, we believe that the increase in favored allele frequencies at the 22 loci was mainly caused by selection for grain size over the five decades before 2000 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029432.s003">Table S2</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0029432-t003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029432.t003</object-id>
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Number, frequency and mean MTKW of landraces and modern varieties in the mine core collections.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0029432-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0029432.t003"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">No. of favored alleles</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landrances</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modern varieties</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Freq (%)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landrances</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.55</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.93</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.39</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.92</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.55</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.37</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.82</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modern varieties</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.82</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.32</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.77</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.36</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.55</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MTKW&#xB1;SE</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landrances</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.35&#xB1;0.83</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.81&#xB1;0.63</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.86&#xB1;0.59</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.86&#xB1;0.72</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.54&#xB1;0.82</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.91&#xB1;1.47</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.88&#xB1;1.53</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.14&#xB1;0.48</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.10&#xB1;2.78</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.32&#xB1;0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.84&#xB1;0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modern varieties</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.56&#xB1;1.01</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.45&#xB1;.0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.81&#xB1;.0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.67&#xB1;1.23</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.45&#xB1;1.84</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.94&#xB1;0.82</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.79&#xB1;1.17</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.52&#xB1;0.99</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.93&#xB1;1.16</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.34&#xB1;0.72</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.81&#xB1;3.50</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.70&#xB1;4.29</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.80&#xB1;2.42</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.90&#xB1;0.53</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.01&#xB1;. 0</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt108">
              <label/>
              <p>Several columns with zero SE because there is only one cultivar in the group.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Accumulation of Favored Alleles from Breeding</title>
        <p>Positive selection of favored alleles at key loci was also clearly implicated by changes in their number and frequency (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t003">Table 3</xref>). The best modern variety (44.01 g) had 15 favored alleles at 22 critical marker loci, whereas the best landrace (38.84 g) had 10. Almost 92% of the landraces had 0&#x2013;5 favored alleles, whereas 85.2% of modern varieties had more than 5 favored alleles, ranging from 5&#x2013;15. Modern breeding has significantly promoted the accumulation of favored alleles in varieties (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). These results illustrate the reliability of identifying favored alleles. Importantly, no modern cultivar has favored alleles at all 22 marker loci (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t003">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g004">Fig. 4</xref>), indicating further capacity for improvement of TKW by maker-assisted selection.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0029432-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029432.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Accumulation of favorable alleles in landraces and modern varieties from different regions of China.</title>
            <p>Modern breeding promoted the accumulation of favored alleles.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0029432.g004"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Geographic Distribution of Favored Alleles at the Six Loci with the Highest Contributions to TKW</title>
        <p>Closely located loci <italic>cfa2257</italic> and <italic>wmc17</italic> on chromosome 7AL with the highest contributions to TKW were chosen to analyze their distributions in different production regions in China (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g005">Figure 5</xref>). The favored alleles (182 bp and 184 bp) of <italic>wmc17</italic> occurred in both landraces and modern varieties, but their frequencies were significantly higher in modern varieties than in landraces. Among landraces the highest frequency of the favored allele with high TKW was in region VI with region VII in second place. Both of the regions grow spring wheats with high TKW. For modern varieties, regions IV and VI had the highest frequency, with VII in third place. Other regions showed large variations in the frequencies of favored alleles. Regarding <italic>cfa2257</italic>, the highest frequency of the favored 129 bp allele was in region V with region VI in second place, a little lower than its frequency in landraces in region V. This allele was not present in landraces from 5 wheat regions (I, II, VII, VIII, and IX), a situation clearly different from the modern variety group where all modern lines, for example in region IX, carried the favored allele. This allele was also common in varieties from regions VI and VIII and occurred in the other regions. The geographic distributions of favored alleles at four other loci are included in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029432.s001">Figure S1</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0029432-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029432.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Favored alleles and their frequencies at the <italic>cfa2257</italic> and <italic>wmc17</italic> loci on chromosome 7AL in the Chinese wheat mini core collection in ten ecological regions in China.</title>
            <p>A and B indicate <italic>wmc17</italic> frequencies in landraces and modern varieties, respectively; C and D indicate <italic>cfa2257</italic> frequencies in landraces and modern varieties, respectively. Zone I: North winter region Zone II: Yellow and Huai River valleys, winter wheat region. Zone III: Middle and Low Yangtze River valleys, winter wheat region. Zone IV: Southwestern winter wheat region. Zone V: Southern winter wheat region. Zone VI: Northeastern spring wheat region. Zone VII: Northern spring wheat region. Zone VIII: Northwestern spring wheat region. Zone IX: Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau, spring-winter wheat region. Zone X: Xinjiang winter-spring wheat region. Source: Zhuang QS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Zhuang1">[20]</xref>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0029432.g005"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Genetically Additive Effects of Favored Alleles on TKW</title>
        <p>To determine if additive effects occur among the favored alleles at the 22 loci, we estimated the mean TKW of varieties with different numbers of favored alleles. There was a high linear correlation (Y&#x200A;=&#x200A;1.294X+29.33, R<sup>2</sup>&#x200A;=&#x200A;0.95) between MTKW and number of favored alleles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g006">Figure 6</xref>) indicating clearly additive effects of favored alleles. However, an obvious negative interaction among loci after the number of favored alleles reached 10 and resulting in larger differences between real and expected TKW cannot be ignored (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). A confounding factor was that some subgroups included only one or two varieties (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0029432-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029432.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Linear regression analysis of MTKW based on five trials.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0029432.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>SSR Loci Associated with TKW may Represent Major QTLs affecting Yield</title>
        <p>According to Nordborg and Weigel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Nordborg1">[27]</xref>, association mapping represents next-generation plant genetics. It uses ancestral gene associations and natural genetic diversity within a population to dissect quantitative traits, and is built upon the presence of linkage disequilibria. It offers a potentially powerful approach for mapping causal genes with modest effects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Yan1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Yan2">[29]</xref>. The association results and allelic effects are influenced by population type and size, and the breeding system of the species. Core collections are very suitable for association analysis of highly heritable and domestication traits <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Breseghello1">[8]</xref>. In the Chinese wheat mini core collection, the mean LD decay distance for landraces at the whole genome level was &lt;5 cM compared to 5&#x2013;10 cM in modern varieties. Only 0.05% of marker pairs in significant (<italic>P&lt;0.001</italic>) LD reached threshold levels of r<italic><sup>2</sup></italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;0.2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao2">[13]</xref>. The observed LD is much lower than for CIMMYT historical breeding materials, but is similar to a population of European varieties released since the beginning of the last century <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Crossa1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Horvath1">[30]</xref>. The overall population structure is very weak, but the two sub-populations, landraces and modern varieties, were clearly distinguished <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao2">[13]</xref>. This separation makes the MCC population suitable for marker/trait association analysis. Earlier analyses revealed differences in regard to latitude distribution and changes over time in important genetic haplotypes, such as those of <italic>Pina</italic> and <italic>Pinb</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Wang1">[14]</xref>, <italic>Ppd-1</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Guo1">[15]</xref>, <italic>GS2</italic> (glutamine synthetase) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Li1">[17]</xref>, <italic>TaGW2</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Su1">[18]</xref>, <italic>TaSus2</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Barrero1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Jiang1">[16]</xref>. However, compared with the candidate core entries, the frequencies of predominant alleles declined to enable the maximum representation of allelic variation at each locus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Zhang1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao1">[11]</xref>. This likely reduced the association power, allowing the major QTLs to be targeted <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Breseghello1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Barrero1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Yan2">[29]</xref>. This was supported by the data in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t002">Table 2</xref>, i.e. most of the associated loci were detected within QTL intervals controlling TKW. Comparative analysis of modern varieties and landraces reveals major loci that have been almost fixed in modern varieties because of positive selection in breeding. For example, in wheat, two haplotypes coding an invertase gene on chromosome 5D were detected among 384 European wheat varieties released since the 1880s, with 382 being the same haplotype, and only two being the other. The latter would obviously have a very low chance of being detected in general association mapping populations. However, in our MCC, 58 accessions carried the above minority haplotype (Jiang YM and Zhang XY unpublished data).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Integration of Association Mapping and QTL Mapping Generates More Reliable Results</title>
        <p>Artificial selection (domestication and breeding) leaves strong foot-prints in plant genomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Andolfatto1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Zhang1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Barrero1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Doebley1">[31]</xref>. Understanding the relationship between DNA sequence variation and variation in phenotypes for quantitative or complex traits will increase the speed of selection in breeding programs for predicting adaptive evolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Mackay1">[32]</xref>. Both linkage and association mapping aim to identify markers sufficiently closely linked to functional sequence variations (causal genes) encoding changes in phenotype, allowing breeders to select and manipulate these alleles routinely in diverse breeding populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Yan2">[29]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Localization and interpretation of QTLs and associated loci provide confidence in results from association analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Zhang1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Nordborg1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Mackay1">[32]</xref>. In soybean,a high correlation (<italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;0.83) between the distribution of SSR markers and genes suggested close association of SSRs with genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Ott1">[33]</xref>. This makes us believe that SSR markers are suitable for association analyses. Most of the associated markers were found in genomic regions where genes or quantitative trait loci (QTL) influencing the same traits were found previously. This provides an independent validation of the approach. Additionally, new chromosome regions for TKW were identified in the wheat genome through association analysis. Overall, 22 SSR loci on 11 chromosomes were associated with TKW with high confidence. This is much greater than the number of QTLs mapped in any bi-parental population, indicating the dissection power of this methodology in natural populations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t002">Table 2</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Gupta1">[34]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Wang2">[36]</xref>. After genotyping 254 loci in 194 F<sub>7</sub> recombinant inbred lines, Groos et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Groos1">[37]</xref> detected nine chromosome regions controlling TKW (chromosomes 1D, 2B, 2D, 3A, 5B, 6A, 6D, 7A, 7D). These are largely consistent with our association results (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t002">Table 2</xref>) from which three QTLs, on chromosomes 2B (<italic>Xgwm148</italic> - <italic>Xgwm374</italic> - <italic>Xgwm388</italic>), 5B (<italic>Xgwm639</italic> - <italic>Xgwm271</italic> - <italic>Xgwm604</italic>) and 7A (<italic>Xcfa2049</italic> - <italic>Xbcd1930</italic>) were detected in six environments. The QTL on 7A mapped to the middle to terminal region of 7AL, and partially overlapped the region <italic>wmc17</italic> - <italic>cfa</italic>2257 detected in the present study. QTL controlling TKW were also detected at a homologous region of 7DL <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Groos1">[37]</xref>. Furthermore, the association mapping result for this region is much more precise than with QTL mapping; the genetic distance between the two nearest markers being only 2.72 cM (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t002">Table 2</xref>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp/wheat/komugi/maps/markerMap.jsp">http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp/wheat/komugi/maps/markerMap.jsp</ext-link>). This raises the question of whether a single causal gene is involved. The <italic>r<sup>2</sup></italic> value between the two markers is about 0.1 in the MCC. Thus there may be two linked causal genes, a possibility that is consistent with the obvious geographic distribution difference in favored alleles at two loci (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). Similarly, <italic>gwm312</italic> and <italic>gwm372</italic> on chromosome 2A also reflect effects of two causal genes, which formed weak LD (r<sup>2</sup>&#x200A;=&#x200A;0.23) in the MCC population. These examples illustrate how haplotype and LD analyses enable dissection of yield QTLs in practice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Barrero1">[10]</xref>.</p>
        <p>In another comprehensive QTL mapping report based on 12 data sets obtained over three years of trials with 2&#x2013;5 environments/year, Snape et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Snape1">[38]</xref> detected seven relatively stable QTLs controlling TKW in 11 DH populations. These QTLs were distributed on chromosomes 2A (<italic>gwm445</italic>), 2B (<italic>gwm148</italic>), 2D (<italic>wmc41</italic>), 3A (<italic>gwm428</italic> - psp<italic>3001</italic>), 5A (<italic>gwm293</italic>), and 6A (<italic>wmc32</italic>, <italic>gwm518</italic>). The <italic>gwm445</italic>-associated QTL was not detected in the MCC population, but was detected in the core collection (1,160 entries) with a 2.89 g increase in TKW (Zhang and You unpublished); <italic>gwm445</italic> is very close to an almost orthologous region of chromosome 2D marked by <italic>wmc41</italic>. Both <italic>gwm148</italic> on 2B and <italic>gwm275</italic> on 2A mapped to orthologous regions detected in our study (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t002">Table 2</xref>). Loci <italic>gwm55-6D</italic> and <italic>gwm415-6B</italic> associated with TKW may be homologous to a QTL on 6A flanked by <italic>wmc32</italic> and <italic>gwm518</italic> in the pericentromeric region, in which <italic>TaGW2</italic> is located <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Su1">[18]</xref>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/ggpages/SSRclub/GeneticPhysical/">http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/ggpages/SSRclub/GeneticPhysical/</ext-link>). In addition, distinct changes in frequencies of SSR alleles between the landraces and modern varieties at the 22 loci caused by hitchhiking effects provided positive evidence of selection for specifically favored alleles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g004">Fig. 4</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029432.s003">Table S2</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Andolfatto1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Zhang1">[6]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Linear Correlation between TKW and Favored Alleles Showing the Practical Value of Genome Selection in Breeding</title>
        <p>Compared with QTL mapping, another attribute of association analysis is the validation of favored alleles in germplasm collections <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Breseghello1">[8]</xref>. For example, R&#xF6;der et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Rder1">[39]</xref> mapped a major TKW QTL to the interval <italic>Xgwm295</italic> - <italic>Xgwm1002</italic> located in the distal telomeric bin (7DS4-0.61-1.00) in the physical map of wheat chromosome 7DS. Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Zhang1">[6]</xref> found that allele <italic>Xgwm130<sub>132</sub></italic> underwent very strong positive selection during modern breeding. <italic>Xgwm130</italic> maps between <italic>Xgwm295</italic> and <italic>Xgwm1002</italic>, with a genetic distance of 1.1 cM from <italic>Xgwm295</italic>. Thus the identification of favored alleles will help in choosing parents for crossing programs, to ensure maximum levels of favored alleles across sets of loci targeted for selection, and to promote fixation at these loci <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Koebner1">[40]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Whereas linear correlations between TKW and favored alleles indicate the additive effects of QTLs or genes, the possibility of other genetic effects should not be ignored in practice. Higher standard errors when the numbers of favored alleles exceed 10 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g006">Figure 6</xref>) reveals the possibility of threshold effects with excessive numbers of favored alleles. Another cause of the higher standard errors was that the number of varieties carrying more than 10 favored alleles was much fewer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g004">Fig. 4</xref>).</p>
        <p>The concept of genome-wide selection (GWS) was recently introduced in plant breeding; this method uses information from all markers, as opposed to significant markers, to evaluate the breeding value of each line <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Heffner1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Tester1">[42]</xref>. Frisch et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Frisch1">[43]</xref> used transcription data from 46,000 oligonucleotide arrays to develop a prediction model for the value of parental maize lines in relation to the grain yield performance of their hybrid progeny. They found that predictions based on 50 well chosen genes were as accurate as predictions based on 5,000 random genes. Therefore, the combination of GWA and GWS will in future enhance the practical application of GWS in crop improvement <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Yan2">[29]</xref>. This work paves the way for further targeted diversity mining in landrace populations and wild relatives via comparative genomics analysis. The most interesting example is that genes on a <italic>Thinopyrum ponticum</italic> group 7L chromosome enhance grain yield by 13% in the genetic background of newly released varieties <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Reynolds1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Glaszmann1">[45]</xref>. The 7L gene may be orthologous to the TKW chromatin block flanked by <italic>wmc17</italic> and <italic>cfa2257</italic> on 7AL (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t002">Table 2</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Gennaro1">[46]</xref>. These examples indicate that increased grain weight in wheat is feasible using genomic selection.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Frequency and Geographical Distribution of Favored Alleles Indicate Potential for Yield Increases by Selection of Loci Associated with TKW</title>
        <p>In wheat, some genes or SSR loci associated with yield vary across latitudes, such as <italic>TaSus2</italic> on chromosome 2B <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Jiang1">[16]</xref>, <italic>TaGW2</italic> on 6A <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Su1">[18]</xref> and <italic>gpw7596</italic> on 7B (EST-SSR) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Wang3">[47]</xref>. Favored alleles usually occur at relatively lower latitudes. This might indicate that the functional genes at these loci, including mapped alleles and those linked with markers, might be responsive to sunlight and temperature during the growing season <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Song1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Xue1">[49]</xref>. None of the 6 SSR loci with determination coefficients higher than 10% associated with favored MTKW alleles <italic>cfa2234<sub>142</sub></italic> (3AL), <italic>gwm156<sub>311</sub></italic> (3BS), <italic>barc56<sub>119</sub></italic> (5AS), <italic>wmc17<sub>182</sub></italic>, <italic><sub>184</sub></italic> (7AL) and <italic>cfa2257<sub>129</sub></italic> (7AL) had obvious correlations with latitude (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g005">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029432.s001">Fig. S1</xref>). They can therefore be used globally for increasing TKW. None of the 88 genotyped modern varieties, and 17 introduced lines, carried favored alleles at all 22 loci, and only one variety had 15 favored alleles (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029432-t003">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029432-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). Therefore, there are still opportunities for maker-assisted selection for TKW in wheat breeding.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Phenotypic Assessment</title>
        <p>A Chinese wheat mini core collection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Zhang1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao2">[13]</xref> was chosen for genome-wide association of 1,000-kernel weight (TKW) using SSR markers. The mini MCC contained 262 wheat lines including 157 landraces, 88 modern varieties, and 17 introduced lines representing 1% of the national collection, but more than 70% of its genetic diversity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao1">[11]</xref>. The phenotype data were collected in five environments, viz. 2002, 2005 and 2006 in Luoyang, Henan province, and 2010 in both Shunyi, Beijing, and Qingdao, Shandong. The field planting design and methods of TKW measurement were described in Su et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Su1">[18]</xref> and Jiang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Jiang1">[16]</xref>. Mean values of TKW and standard errors were analyzed by SPSS 16.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.brothersoft.com/downloads/spss-16.html">http://www.brothersoft.com/downloads/spss-16.html</ext-link>). The mixed mean TKW (MTKW) was estimated by the best linear unbiased predictor (BLUP) method according to Bernardo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Bernardo1">[50]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Bernardo3">[52]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>SSR Genotyping</title>
        <p>Genomic DNA was extracted from young leaves of 10 seedlings of each entry according to Sharp et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Sharp1">[53]</xref> and fingerprinted by PCR amplifications that identified alleles at 531 SSR loci. Genetic map positions for most of the markers (512 loci) can be found in Hao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao2">[13]</xref>. The loci were distributed evenly across all 21 wheat chromosomes. The primer sequences and genetic locations of the loci were obtained from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp">http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wheat.pw.usda.gov">http://wheat.pw.usda.gov</ext-link>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Rder2">[54]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Somers1">[55]</xref>. The annealing temperature for each primer pair was obtained from R&#xF6;der et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Rder2">[54]</xref> and GrainGenes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wheat.pw.usda.gov">http://wheat.pw.usda.gov</ext-link>). After purification, the amplified PCR products were separated on an ABI3730 DNA Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). Fragment sizes were determined using an internal size standard (LIZ500, ABI, USA), and the outputs were analyzed using GeneMapper software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.appliedbiosystems.com.cn/">http://www.appliedbiosystems.com.cn/</ext-link>). The minor allele frequency (MAF) was set as 0.05 during the following statistics.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Association Analysis</title>
        <p>To reduce the risk of false or spurious associations, population structure was estimated by STRUCTURE v2.2 software according to Pritchard and Rosenberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Pritchard1">[56]</xref> and Pritchard et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Pritchard2">[57]</xref>, based on 42 unlinked loci from both arms of each chromosome with a length of burn-in period equal to 50,000 iterations and a run of 500,000 replications of Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) after burn in. A total of 80 independent runs were set with the number of presumptive groups (k) varying from 1 to 10. In order to select the most appropriate number of sub-groups, the &#x394;k value, based on the average Ln probe of each run, was calculated allowing the internal population structure of the sample set to be determined <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Evanno1">[58]</xref>, then Q data were obtained according to the corresponding K value.</p>
        <p>In order to define the degree of genetic covariance between pairs of individuals, a kinship (K) analysis was conducted by genotypic data with SPAGeDi software <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hardy1">[59]</xref>. The calculation of pairwise kinship coefficients was according to Loiselle et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Loiselle1">[60]</xref> with 10,000 permutation tests. Negative values between individual pairs were then set to 0, as this indicated that they were less related than random individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Yu1">[21]</xref>.</p>
        <p>The mixed linear model (MLM) module with Q+K of the TASSEL 2.1 software package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www2.maizegenetics.net/">http://www2.maizegenetics.net/</ext-link>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Bradbury1">[61]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Zhang2">[62]</xref> was used for genome wide association of MTKW and TKW in each trial. The relative value of the favored allele for TKW (<italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic>) was calculated according to the equation, <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;(SSA&#x2212;f<sub>A</sub>&#xD7;MSE)/SST where SSA indicated the sum of squares between groups of favorable alleles and others, f<sub>A</sub> indicated the degrees of freedom of the group with the favored alleles, MSE indicated the error mean square, and SST indicated the sum of squares <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Zhang2">[62]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Agrama1">[63]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Because modern varieties usually have fewer alleles than the landraces generally, frequency at most alleles would be increased in modern varieties <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Hao2">[13]</xref>. To avoid circular reasoning in data interpretation, we randomly selected one locus on each arm of the 21 chromosomes, with PIC values higher than the global mean (0.65), for evaluating changes in major allele frequencies between the two sub-populations at loci associated significantly with MTKW and loci probably not removed by selection in domestication and breeding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0029432-Ge1">[64]</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029432.s003">Table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029432.s004">Table S3</xref>). We used <italic>F</italic>-tests and <italic>t</italic>-tests to estimate differences in allelic frequencies between the landrace and modern variety groups by SPSS15.0.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029432.s001">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Favored allele frequencies (in blue) in landraces (left) and modern varieties (right) at the</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>barc56, cfa2234, gwm156</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>and</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>gwm234</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>loci.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0029432.s001.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029432.s002">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>SSR loci associated with MTKW and TKW in 5 environments by Tassel 2.1(P&lt;0.05).</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0029432.s002.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029432.s003">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Frequency change of favored alleles at the 22 loci associated with MTKW in landraces and modern varieties.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0029432.s003.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029432.s004">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Frequency change of major alleles at the 44 loci with higher </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>PIC</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> than the mean (0.54) in landraces and modern varieties.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0029432.s004.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors are grateful to Ms. HN Zhang, YH Tian, J Lin and YJ Wang for their excellent genotyping and phenotyping of the mini core collection. We appreciated constructive discussions with Prof. Jianbing Yan. We also gratefully acknowledge help from Prof. Robert A McIntosh, University of Sydney, with English editing.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p><bold>Funding: </bold>This work was supported by the Chinese Ministry of Science and Technology (2009CB118306 and 2010CB125900) and the Chinese Agricultural Research Service, Ministry of Agriculture (CARS-3-1-2) and National Natural Science Foundation of China (30900898). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-He1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>ZH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonjean</surname>
              <given-names>APA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <source>Cereals in China</source>
          <publisher-loc>D.F., Mexico</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>CIMMYT</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Xiao1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xiao</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>ZH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Wheat yield and end use quality improvement in China (Chapter 13).</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhuang</surname>
              <given-names>QS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <publisher-name>published by China Agricultural Publish Press</publisher-name>
          <comment>In: Chinese wheat improvement and pedigree analysis</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Wright1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wright</surname>
              <given-names>SI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bi</surname>
              <given-names>IV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schroeder</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamasaki</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doebley</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>The effects of artificial selection on the maize genome.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>308</volume>
          <fpage>1310</fpage>
          <lpage>1314</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15919994</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Andolfatto1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Andolfatto</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>Adaptive hitchhiking effects on genome variability.</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin in Genet Dev</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>635</fpage>
          <lpage>641</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11682306</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Schltterer1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schl&#xF6;tterer</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Hitchhiking mapping &#x2013; functional genomics from the population genetics perspective.</article-title>
          <source>Trend Genet</source>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>32</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Zhang1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tong</surname>
              <given-names>YP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>You</surname>
              <given-names>GX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hao</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ge</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Hitchhiking effect mapping: A new approach for discovering agronomically important genes.</article-title>
          <source>Agri Sci China</source>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>255</fpage>
          <lpage>264</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-FlintGarcia1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Flint-Garcia</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thornsberry</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buckler</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Structure of linkage disequilibrium in plants.</article-title>
          <source>Ann Rev Plant Biol</source>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>357</fpage>
          <lpage>374</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14502995</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Breseghello1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Breseghello</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sorrells</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Association mapping of kernel size and milling quality in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) cultivars.</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>172</volume>
          <fpage>1165</fpage>
          <lpage>1177</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16079235</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Crossa1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Crossa</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burgue&#xF1;o</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dreisigacker</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vargas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Herrera-Foessel</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Association analysis of historical bread wheat germplasm using additive genetic covariance of relatives and population structure.</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>177</volume>
          <fpage>1889</fpage>
          <lpage>1913</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17947425</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Barrero1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barrero</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bellgard</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Diverse approaches to achieving grain yield in wheat.</article-title>
          <source>Funct Integr Genomics</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>27</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Hao1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hao</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>YC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>You</surname>
              <given-names>GX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>HN</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Genetic diversity and construction of core collection in Chinese wheat genetic resources.</article-title>
          <source>Chinese Sci Bull</source>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>1518</fpage>
          <lpage>1526</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Dong1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cao</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Establishment of candidate core collections in Chinese common wheat germplasm.</article-title>
          <source>J Plant Genet Res</source>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Hao2">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hao</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ge</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>YC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Genetic diversity and linkage disequilibrium in Chinese bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) revealed by SSR markers.</article-title>
          <source>PloS One</source>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>e17279</fpage>
          <comment>Doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0017279">10.1371/journal.pone.0017279</ext-link></comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21365016</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Wang1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>JZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>WL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Analysis of Pina and Pinb in the mini core collections of Chinese wheat germplasm by ecotilling and identification of a novel <italic>Pin</italic>b allele.</article-title>
          <source>J Cereal Sci</source>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>836</fpage>
          <lpage>842</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Guo1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
              <given-names>ZA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>YX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ren</surname>
              <given-names>ZL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jia</surname>
              <given-names>JZ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Discovery, evaluation and distribution of haplotypes of the wheat <italic>Ppd-D1</italic> gene.</article-title>
          <source>New Phytol</source>
          <volume>185</volume>
          <fpage>841</fpage>
          <lpage>851</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20002313</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Jiang1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>QY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hou</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hao</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ge</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>The wheat (<italic>T. aestivum</italic>) sucrose synthase 2 gene (<italic>TaSus2</italic>) active in endosperm development is associated with yield traits.</article-title>
          <source>Funct Integr Genomics</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>49</fpage>
          <lpage>61</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20821031</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Li1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>XP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>XQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>GY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Haplotype analysis of the genes encoding glutamine synthetase chloroplast isoformes and their association with nitrogen-use- and yield-related traits in bred wheat.</article-title>
          <source>New Phytol</source>
          <volume>189</volume>
          <fpage>449</fpage>
          <lpage>458</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21039562</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Su1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Su</surname>
              <given-names>ZQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hao</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>YC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Identification and development of a functional marker of <italic>TaGW2</italic> associated with grain weight in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.).</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <fpage>211</fpage>
          <lpage>223</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20838758</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Ersoz1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ersoz</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buckler</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Applications of linkage disequilibrium and association mapping in maize.</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Kriz</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Larkins</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Biotechnology in Agriculture and Forestry Volume 63, III</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag Berlin Heideberg, Germany</publisher-name>
          <fpage>173</fpage>
          <lpage>195</lpage>
          <comment>In: Molecular Genetic Approaches to Maize Improvement</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Zhuang1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhuang</surname>
              <given-names>QS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Chinese wheat improvement and pedigree analysis.</article-title>
          <comment>Agricultural Press, Beijing (in Chinese)</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Yu1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pressoir</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Briggs</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bi</surname>
              <given-names>IV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamasaki</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>A unified mixed-model method for association mapping that accounts for multiple levels of relatedness.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <lpage>208</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16380716</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Huang1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>XQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kempf</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ganal</surname>
              <given-names>MW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>R&#xF6;der</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Advanced backcross QTL analysis in progenies derived from a cross between a German elite winter wheat variety and a synthetic wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.).</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>933</fpage>
          <lpage>943</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15243706</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Quarrie1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Quarrie</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quarrie</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Radosevic</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rancic</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaminska</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Dissecting a wheat QTL for yield present in a range of environments: from the QTL to candidate genes.</article-title>
          <source>J Exp Bot</source>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>2627</fpage>
          <lpage>2637</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16831847</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Cuthbert1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cuthbert</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Somers</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brule-Babel</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crow</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Molecular mapping of quantitative trait loci for yield and yield components in spring wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.).</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>595</fpage>
          <lpage>608</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18516583</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Sun1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>XC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marza</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>HX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carver</surname>
              <given-names>BF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bai</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <article-title>Mapping quantitative trait loci for quality factors in an inter-class cross of US and Chinese wheat.</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <fpage>1041</fpage>
          <lpage>1051</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20012855</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Tsilo1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tsilo</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hareland</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simsek</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chao</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <article-title>Genome mapping of kernel characteristics in hard red spring wheat breeding lines.</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>121</volume>
          <fpage>717</fpage>
          <lpage>730</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20425103</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Nordborg1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nordborg</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weigel</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Next-generation genetics in plants.</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <volume>456</volume>
          <fpage>720</fpage>
          <lpage>723</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19079047</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Yan1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warburton</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buckler</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McMullen</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Genetic characterization of a global maize collection using SNP markers.</article-title>
          <source>PloS One</source>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>e8451</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20041112</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Yan2">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warburton</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crouch</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Association mapping for enhancing maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.) genetic improvement.</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>433</fpage>
          <lpage>449</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Horvath1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Horvath</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Didier</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koenig</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Exbrayat</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Charmet</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Analysis of diversity and linkage disequilibrium along chromosome 3B of bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.).</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>119</volume>
          <fpage>1523</fpage>
          <lpage>1537</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19756470</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Doebley1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Doebley</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gaut</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>BD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>The molecular genetics of crop domestication.</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <volume>127</volume>
          <fpage>1309</fpage>
          <lpage>1321</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17190597</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Mackay1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mackay</surname>
              <given-names>TFC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stone</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ayroles</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>The genetics of quantitative traits: challenges and prospects.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>565</fpage>
          <lpage>577</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19584810</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Ott1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ott</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trautschold</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sandhu</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Using microsatellites to understand the physical distribution of recombination on soybean chromosomes.</article-title>
          <source>PLoS ONE</source>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>e22306</fpage>
          <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0022306">10.1371/journal.pone.0022306</ext-link></comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21799819</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Gupta1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>PK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rustig</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Genetic and molecular basis of grain size and grain number and its relevance to grain productivity in higher plants.</article-title>
          <source>Genome</source>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>565</fpage>
          <lpage>571</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16936836</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Sun2">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kong</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>GZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>QTL analysis of kernel shape and weight using recombinant inbred lines in wheat.</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <volume>165</volume>
          <fpage>615</fpage>
          <lpage>624</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Wang2">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>RX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hai</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>You</surname>
              <given-names>GX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>CX</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>QTL mapping for grain filling rate and yield-related traits in RILs of the Chinese winter wheat population Heshangmai 3&#xD7; Yu8679.</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>118</volume>
          <fpage>313</fpage>
          <lpage>325</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18853131</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Groos1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Groos</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robert</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bervas</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Charmet</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Genetic analysis of grain protein-content, grain yield and thousand-kernel weight in bread wheat.</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <fpage>1032</fpage>
          <lpage>1040</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12671751</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Snape1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Snape</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Foulkes</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simmonds</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leverington</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fish</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Dissecting gene&#xD7;environmental effects on wheat yields via QTL and physiological analysis.</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <volume>154</volume>
          <fpage>401</fpage>
          <lpage>408</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Rder1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>R&#xF6;der</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>XQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>B&#xF6;rner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Fine mapping of the region on wheat chromosome 7D controlling grain weight.</article-title>
          <source>Funct Integr Genomic</source>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>79</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Koebner1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koebner</surname>
              <given-names>RMD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Summers</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>21st century wheat breeding: Plot selection or plate detection.</article-title>
          <source>Trends Biotechnol</source>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>59</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12573853</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Heffner1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Heffner</surname>
              <given-names>EL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sorrells</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jannink</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Genomic selection for crop improvement.</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Tester1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tester</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Langridge</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <article-title>Breeding technologies to increase crop production in a changing world.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>327</volume>
          <fpage>818</fpage>
          <lpage>822</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20150489</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Frisch1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Frisch</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thiemann</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schrag</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scholten</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <article-title>Transcriptome-based distance measures for grouping of germplasm and prediction of hybrid performance in maize.</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <fpage>709</fpage>
          <lpage>720</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19885651</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Reynolds1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Reynolds</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Calderini</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Condon</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rajaram</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>Physiological basis of yield gains in wheat associated with the <italic>LR19</italic> translocation from <italic>Agropyron elongatum</italic>.</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <volume>119</volume>
          <fpage>137</fpage>
          <lpage>141</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Glaszmann1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Glaszmann</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kilian</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Upadhyaya</surname>
              <given-names>HD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Varshney</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <article-title>Accessing genetic diversity for crop improvement.</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>167</fpage>
          <lpage>173</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20167531</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Gennaro1">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gennaro</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koebner</surname>
              <given-names>RMD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ceoloni</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>A candidate for <italic>Lr19</italic>, an exotic gene conditioning leaf rust resistance in wheat.</article-title>
          <source>Func Integr Genomic</source>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>325</fpage>
          <lpage>334</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Wang3">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balfourier</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Exbrayat-Vinson</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hao</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Comparison of genetic diversity level between European and East-Asian wheat collections using SSR markers.</article-title>
          <source>Sci Agric Sin</source>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>2667</fpage>
          <lpage>2678</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Song1">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>XJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>MZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>HX</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>A QTL for rice grain width and weight encodes a previously unknown RING-type E3 ubiquitin ligase.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>623</fpage>
          <lpage>630</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17417637</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Xue1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xue</surname>
              <given-names>WY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xin</surname>
              <given-names>YZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wen</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Natural variation in <italic>Ghd</italic>7 is an important regulator of heading date and yield potential in rice.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>761</fpage>
          <lpage>767</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18454147</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Bernardo1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bernardo</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1996</year>
          <article-title>Test cross additive and dominance effects in best linear unbiased prediction of maize single-cross performance.</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>1098</fpage>
          <lpage>1102</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Bernardo2">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bernardo</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1996</year>
          <article-title>Marker-based estimate of identity by descent and alikeness in state among maize inbreds.</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>262</fpage>
          <lpage>267</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Bernardo3">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bernardo</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1996</year>
          <article-title>Best linear unbiased prediction of maize single-cross performance.</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>50</fpage>
          <lpage>56</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Sharp1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharp</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chao</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Desai</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gale</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1989</year>
          <article-title>The isolation, characterization and application in Triticeae of a set of wheat RFLP probes identifying each homoeologous chromosome arm.</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>342</fpage>
          <lpage>348</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Rder2">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>R&#xF6;der</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Korzun</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wendehake</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plaschke</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tixier</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>1998</year>
          <article-title>A microsatellite map of wheat.</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>149</volume>
          <fpage>2007</fpage>
          <lpage>2023</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9691054</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Somers1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Somers</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Isaac</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edwards</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>A high-density microsatellite consensus map for bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.).</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>1105</fpage>
          <lpage>1114</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15490101</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Pritchard1">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pritchard</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosenberg</surname>
              <given-names>NA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1999</year>
          <article-title>Use of unlinked genetic markers to detect population stratification in association chain will tend to get stuck moving among very similar studies.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>220</fpage>
          <lpage>228</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10364535</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Pritchard2">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pritchard</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stephens</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Donnelly</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>Inference of population structure using multilocus genotype data.</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>155</volume>
          <fpage>945</fpage>
          <lpage>959</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10835412</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Evanno1">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Evanno</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Regnaut</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goudet</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Detecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software STRUCTURE: a simulation study.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Ecol</source>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>2611</fpage>
          <lpage>2620</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15969739</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Hardy1">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hardy</surname>
              <given-names>OJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vekemans</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>SPAGeDi: a versatile computer program to analyze spatial genetic structure at the individual or population levels.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Ecol Notes</source>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>618</fpage>
          <lpage>620</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Loiselle1">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Loiselle</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sork</surname>
              <given-names>VL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nason</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graham</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1995</year>
          <article-title>Spatial genetic structure of a tropical understory shrub, Psychotria officinalis (Rubiaceae).</article-title>
          <source>Am J Bot</source>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>1420</fpage>
          <lpage>1425</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Bradbury1">
        <label>61</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bradbury</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>ZW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kroon</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Casstevens</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramdoss</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>TASSEL: software for association mapping of complex traits in diverse samples.</article-title>
          <source>Bioinformatics</source>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>2633</fpage>
          <lpage>2635</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586829</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Zhang2">
        <label>62</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>ZW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ersoz</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lai</surname>
              <given-names>CQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fodhunter</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tiwari</surname>
              <given-names>HK</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <article-title>Mixed linear model approach adapted for genome-wide association studies.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>355</fpage>
          <lpage>360</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20208535</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Agrama1">
        <label>63</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agrama</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eizenga</surname>
              <given-names>GC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Association mapping of yield and its components in rice cultivars.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Breeding</source>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>341</fpage>
          <lpage>356</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Ge1">
        <label>64</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ge</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>You</surname>
              <given-names>GX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hao</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>YC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Genome selection sweep and association analysis shed light on future breeding by design in wheat.</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <comment>In press</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0029432-Quarrie2">
        <label>65</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Quarrie</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steed</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Calestani</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Semikhodskii</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lebreton</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>A high-density genetic map of hexaploid wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) from the cross Chinese Spring&#xD7;SQ1 and its use to compare QTLs for grain yield across a range of environments.</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>865</fpage>
          <lpage>880</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15719212</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
