<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3276090</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err350</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Papers</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The &#x2018;Green Revolution&#x2019; dwarfing genes play a role in disease resistance in <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> and <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Saville</surname>
            <given-names>R. J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gosman</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Burt</surname>
            <given-names>C. J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Makepeace</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Steed</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Corbitt</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chandler</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Brown</surname>
            <given-names>J. K. M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Boulton</surname>
            <given-names>M. I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nicholson</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>John Innes Centre, Norwich Research Park, Colney, Norwich NR4 7UH, UK</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>National Institute of Agricultural Botany, Huntingdon Road, Cambridge CB3 0LE, UK</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>paul.nicholson@jic.ac.uk</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>63</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>1271</fpage>
      <lpage>1283</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>9</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2011 The Author(s).</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
          <license-p>This paper is available online free of all access charges (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html">http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html</ext-link> for further details)</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Green Revolution dwarfing genes, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic>, encode mutant forms of DELLA proteins and are present in most modern wheat varieties. DELLA proteins have been implicated in the response to biotic stress in the model plant, <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana.</italic> Using defined wheat <italic>Rht</italic> near-isogenic lines and barley <italic>Sln1</italic> gain of function (GoF) and loss of function (LoF) lines, the role of DELLA in response to biotic stress was investigated in pathosystems representing contrasting trophic styles (biotrophic, hemibiotrophic, and necrotrophic). GoF mutant alleles in wheat and barley confer a resistance trade-off with increased susceptibility to biotrophic pathogens and increased resistance to necrotrophic pathogens whilst the converse was conferred by a LoF mutant allele. The polyploid nature of the wheat genome buffered the effect of single <italic>Rht</italic> GoF mutations relative to barley (diploid), particularly in respect of increased susceptibility to biotrophic pathogens. A role for DELLA in controlling cell death responses is proposed. Similar to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, a resistance trade-off to pathogens with contrasting pathogenic lifestyles has been identified in monocotyledonous cereal species. Appreciation of the pleiotropic role of DELLA in biotic stress responses in cereals has implications for plant breeding.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Biotroph/necrotroph</kwd>
        <kwd>DELLA</kwd>
        <kwd>Green Revolution</kwd>
        <kwd><italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L.</kwd>
        <kwd>polyploidy</kwd>
        <kwd><italic>Reduced height</italic> (<italic>Rht</italic>)</kwd>
        <kwd>resistance trade-off</kwd>
        <kwd><italic>Slender 1</italic> (<italic>Sln1</italic>)</kwd>
        <kwd><italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="13"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The introduction of the <italic>Reduced height</italic> (<italic>Rht</italic>) genes (<italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> alleles) underpinned the increases in wheat yields that occurred during the &#x2018;Green Revolution&#x2019; and they continue to be used in most modern varieties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hedden, 2003</xref>). These alleles are less sensitive to the phytohormone, gibberellin (GA), than their wild-type counterparts (<italic>Rht-B1a</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1a</italic>) resulting in a reduction in stem elongation. The yield benefits associated with these alleles arise from increased resistance to lodging when additional nitrogen is applied to varieties carrying these alleles and an altered harvest index whereby a greater proportion of the plant biomass is partitioned into the grain.</p>
      <p><italic>Rht-B1</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1</italic> encode DELLA proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Peng <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>), which act to repress GA-responsive growth, and the <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> mutations are thought to confer dwarfism by producing constitutively active forms of these growth repressors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Peng <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). Most of our knowledge of DELLA genes derives from studies on <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genome contains five DELLA genes that encode distinct proteins (GAI, RGA, RGL1, RGL2, and RGL3; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Peng <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Silverstone <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Wen and Chang, 2002</xref>). DELLA proteins are nuclear localized repressors of growth that are core components of the GA signal transduction pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Peng <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). In the presence of GA, DELLA interacts with the soluble GA receptor, GIBBERELLIN INSENSITIVE DWARF1, GID1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Ueguchi-Tanaka <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) and the F-box protein SLY1/GID2, leading to the polyubiquitination, and subsequent degradation of DELLA protein by the 26S proteasome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Ueguchi-Tanaka <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). In addition to their role in plant development, recent studies in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> have implicated DELLA proteins in resistance to biotic stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Navarro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), suggesting that DELLA encoding genes have a role in disease resistance.</p>
      <p>Depending on their mode of infection, plant pathogens can be broadly classified into three trophic lifestyles; biotrophs, necrotrophs, and hemibiotrophs. Biotrophs derive nutrients from living cells whilst necrotrophs kill host cells in order to derive energy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lewis, 1973</xref>). A hemibiotrophic pathogen requires an initial biotrophic phase before switching to necrotrophy to complete its life cycle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Perfect and Green, 2001</xref>). When subjected to pathogen attack, a plant is required to respond appropriately. An interplay between the phytohormones salicylic acid (SA), jasmonic acid (JA), and ethylene (ET) activates distinct defence pathways, depending on the lifestyle of the invading pathogen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Glazebrook, 2005</xref>). The antagonistic cross-talk between the SA and JA/ET signalling pathways enhances resistance to biotrophic and necrotrophic pathogens, respectively. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Navarro <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> suggested that DELLA proteins differentially affect responses to biotrophic and necrotrophic pathogens through their influence on the SA&#x2013;JA balance. Accumulation of DELLA results in potentiated JA signalling and, consequently, to a dampening of SA signalling. Accordingly, in DELLA accumulating mutants, resistance to necrotrophs in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> is enhanced, and resistance to biotrophs is reduced.</p>
      <p>In contrast to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, monocot cereal species appear to contain a single DELLA encoding gene. The <italic>Reduced height</italic> (<italic>Rht</italic>) gene of <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> (bread wheat) and the <italic>Slender 1</italic> (<italic>Sln1</italic>) gene of <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> (barley) are both orthologous to <italic>GAI</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Peng <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Chandler <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Mutations disrupting the conserved DELLA domain, essential for GID1 interaction, reduce the susceptibility of DELLA to GA-induced degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Peng <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Chandler <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>) and result in a dwarf phenotype, a trait which has been exploited by wheat breeders, for example, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic>.</p>
      <p>Reduced height in wheat has been associated with increased susceptibility to splash dispersed pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Vanbeuningen and Kohli, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Eriksen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gervais <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Draeger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Klahr <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). This was thought to be due to the reduced distances between consecutive leaves facilitating progress of the pathogen (the &#x2018;ladder effect&#x2019;, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bahat <italic>et al.</italic>, 1980</xref>) and to alterations in canopy structure providing a micro-climate more favourable for pathogen establishment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Scott <italic>et al.</italic>, 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">1985</xref>). However, not all plant height QTL are coincident with those for pathogen susceptibility, as has been demonstrated with fusarium head blight (FHB; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Draeger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), suggesting that resistance is not an effect of height <italic>per se</italic> but rather of linkage or pleiotropy. Significantly, the <italic>Rht-B1</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1</italic> loci on chromosome 4B and 4D, respectively, are coincident with FHB resistance loci suggesting that they may have a pleiotropic effect on susceptibility to FHB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Srinivasachary <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p>
      <p>The relative resistance of both wheat and barley lines, differing in DELLA status, against cereal fungal pathogens, representing each of the three classes of pathogen lifestyle, was assessed here. Barley was used to study the effect of DELLA (<italic>Sln1</italic>) gain of function (GoF) and loss of function (LoF) mutants in a diploid species. The effect of <italic>Rht</italic> in hexaploid wheat was also investigated using GoF mutants of differing severity originating from different sources. In combination the results suggest that DELLA confers a pleiotropic effect on disease resistance which may in part be due to DELLA&#x2019;s role in the control of cell death.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Plant material</title>
        <p>Near-isogenic lines (NILs) of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) varieties Mercia, Maris Huntsman, and April Bearded differing in the alleles at the <italic>Reduced height</italic> (<italic>Rht</italic>) loci on chromosome 4B and 4D were kindly supplied by Dr J Flintham of the John Innes Centre, Norwich, England. The semi-dwarf GoF alleles <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> (formerly <italic>Rht1</italic> and <italic>2</italic>) and the severe dwarf alleles <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1c</italic> (formerly <italic>Rht3</italic> and <italic>10</italic>, respectively) are dominant gibberellin-(GA) insensitive alleles which are thought to accumulate DELLA to higher levels than the wild type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Peng <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>) while the wild type (<italic>rht-tall</italic>) parental lines carry GA-sensitive alleles at all three homoeologous loci (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Flintham <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). The severe dwarf allele, <italic>Rht-B1c,</italic> is a result of an insertion in <italic>Rht-B1</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1c</italic> results from a gene duplication of <italic>Rht-D1</italic> (Pearce <italic>et al.</italic>, unpublished results), in both cases probably resulting in an increase in DELLA accumulation. Barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>) variety Himalaya, the dwarf (GoF) mutant (M640), and the constitutive growth (LoF) mutant (M770) were kindly supplied by Dr P Chandler of CSIRO, Canberra, Australia. M640 carries a dominant GA-insensitive allele (<italic>Sln1d</italic>) at the <italic>Slender 1</italic> (<italic>Sln1</italic>) locus that is orthologous to <italic>Rht</italic> of wheat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Chandler <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). The LoF mutant M770 contains an early termination codon at the <italic>Sln1</italic> locus, resulting in a truncated protein lacking the COOH-terminal 17 amino acid residues. This loss of function allele has been designated <italic>sln1c.</italic> In the homozygous state, the loss of functional DELLA results in male sterility and therefore homozygous <italic>sln1c</italic>/<italic>sln1c</italic> plants have to be selected in a 1:3 ratio from a heterozygous parent. All of the lines used in this study are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Description of plant material used</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locus</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allele</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenotype</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Origin</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Rht-B1</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>rht-tall</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild type</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>&#x2013;</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rht-B1b</italic> (<italic>Rht 1</italic>)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Semi-dwarf</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cv. Norin 10&#x2014;nucleotide substitution<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">a</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rht-B1c</italic> (<italic>Rht 3</italic>)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe-dwarf</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cv. Tom Thumb&#x2014;insertion<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">b</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Rht-D1</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>rht-tall</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild type</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rht-D1b</italic> (<italic>Rht 2)</italic></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Semi-dwarf</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cv. Norin 10&#x2014;nucleotide substitution<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">a</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rht-D1c</italic> (<italic>Rht 10</italic>)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe-dwarf</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cv. Aibian&#x2014;gene duplication<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">b</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Sln1</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild type</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Sln1d</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dwarf (GoF)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cv. Himalaya&#x2014;point mutation<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn3">c</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>sln1c</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slender (LoF)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cv. Himalaya&#x2014;point mutation<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn3">c</xref></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tblfn1">
              <label>a</label>
              <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Peng <italic>et al</italic>., 1999</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="tblfn2">
              <label>b</label>
              <p>Pearce <italic>et al</italic>., unpublished data.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="tblfn3">
              <label>c</label>
              <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Chandler <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Influence of DELLA alleles on resistance of wheat and barley to <italic>Blumeria graminis</italic></title>
        <p>Near-isogenic lines of wheat cvs Mercia (<italic>rht-tall, Rht-B1c</italic>, and <italic>Rht-D1c</italic>), Maris Huntsman (<italic>rht-tall, Rht-B1c</italic>, and the double mutant <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>+<italic>D1b</italic>), and April Bearded (<italic>rht-tall</italic> and the double mutant <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>+<italic>D1b</italic>), and barley cv. Himalaya WT, <italic>Sln1d</italic>, and <italic>sln1c</italic> plants were grown to growth stage (GS) 12 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Zadoks <italic>et al.</italic>, 1974</xref>; i.e. second seedling leaf as long as the prophyll) in controlled environment cabinets under a 16 h photoperiod and a 17/12 &#xB0;C day/night temperature regime. Detached sections (2.5 cm) of the second leaf were placed in agar boxes and inoculated with the spores of virulent <italic>Blumeria graminis</italic> isolates (f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic> (<italic>Bgt</italic>) or f. sp. <italic>hordei</italic> (<italic>Bgh</italic>) for wheat and barley, respectively) as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brown and Wolfe (1990)</xref>. Experiments were conducted in a randomized block design of four replicates with four detached leaves of each line per replicate. Each experiment was repeated three times.</p>
        <p><italic>Bgh</italic> inoculated barley leaves were collected at 48 h and 60 h post-inoculation (hpi) for microscopic analysis. Leaf tissue was cleared and fungal structures were scored for papillae defence and host cell death response at each time point as described by Boyd <italic>et al.</italic> (1994<italic>a</italic>). One-hundred interaction sites were observed across four leaves per genotype. Fungal structures and plant cellular autofluorescence were observed using a Nikon Microphot-SA with Nomarski (DIC) and a fluorescence filter; FITC (450&#x2013;490 nm &gt;520LP). In this study, a successful interaction was scored if the fungus developed an haustorium. The stages of <italic>Bgh</italic> development are well defined (Boyd <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994<italic>b</italic>), balloon/digitate haustoria form within the epidermal cells and hyphal development follows. The stage to which infection progressed was scored for each interaction. Macroscopic symptoms were assessed at 8 d post-inoculation (dpi) by quantifying colonies cm<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> of leaf area of 12 leaves per genotype.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Influence of DELLA alleles on resistance of barley to <italic>Ramularia collo-cygni</italic></title>
        <p>Barley cv. Himalaya WT and <italic>Sln1d</italic> were grown and inoculated with <italic>R. collo-cygni</italic> according to the methods reported previously by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Makepeace <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref>. This experiment was conducted in a randomized block design with three blocks each containing five plants per line. Symptoms were assessed at 15 dpi as the percentage of leaf area covered with lesions. This experiment was repeated three times with the addition of <italic>sln1c</italic> in the third experiment.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Influence of DELLA alleles on resistance of wheat and barley to <italic>Oculimacula acuformis</italic> and <italic>O. yallundae</italic></title>
        <p>Wheat cv. Mercia <italic>rht-tall</italic>, <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>, and <italic>Rht-D1c</italic> NILs, and barley cv. Himalaya WT and <italic>Sln1d</italic> lines were grown and inoculated with either <italic>O. acuformis</italic> or <italic>O. yallundae</italic> as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chapman <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref>. Plants were harvested 6&#x2013;8 weeks after inoculation and scored for fungal penetration of leaf sheaths according to the scale devised by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Scott (1971)</xref>. The experiments were conducted in a randomized block design with five blocks, each containing ten plants per line of which five were inoculated with <italic>O. acuformis</italic> and five were inoculated with <italic>O. yallundae.</italic> The experiment was repeated once to confirm the findings.</p>
        <p>In a third experiment, Himalaya WT, <italic>Sln1d</italic>, and <italic>sln1c</italic> lines were inoculated with <italic>O. acuformis</italic>. Due to the elongated nature of the <italic>sln1c</italic> mutant line, the method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chapman <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> was modified by using longer tubes to contain the inoculum. This experiment was arranged in a randomized block design with five blocks as described above.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Influence of DELLA alleles on Type 1 resistance of wheat heads to <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></title>
        <p>Two independent experiments were carried out to assess resistance to initial infection [Type 1 resistance <italic>sensu</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Schroeder and Christensen (1963)</xref>]. In experiment 1, Mercia and Maris Huntsman NILs (<italic>rht-tall, Rht-B1b</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>) were grown in the field. Experiment 2 was conducted in an unheated polytunnel, only Mercia NILs (<italic>rht-tall, Rht-B1b</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>) were tested. In both experiments, lines were inoculated by spraying until run-off with a conidial suspension of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> (1&#xD7;10<sup>5</sup> conidia ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) at GS 65 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Zadoks <italic>et al.</italic>, 1974</xref>) as described previously by Gosman <italic>et al.</italic> (2005). Disease severity was visually assessed as the percentage of spikelets infected at 14 dpi. Experiment 1 was conducted in a randomized complete block design field trial with three replicate plots per line. Experiment 2 was conducted in a randomized complete block design consisting of four blocks within which were seven plants of each line.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Influence of DELLA alleles on Type 2 resistance of wheat and barley heads to <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></title>
        <p>Mercia and Maris Huntsman NILs (<italic>rht-tall</italic>, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>) were phenotyped in independent experiments for resistance to spread within the spike [Type 2 resistance <italic>sensu</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Schroeder and Christensen (1963)</xref>] in an unheated polytunnel. Experiments were arranged in a randomized complete block design with four replicate blocks with seven plants per line in each.</p>
        <p>Inoculation and disease assessment were as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Gosman <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref>. Lines were inoculated at GS 65 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Zadoks <italic>et al.</italic>, 1974</xref>) by point inoculation with 50 &#x3BC;l of conidial suspension (1&#xD7;10<sup>6</sup> ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) of a deoxynivalenol (DON) producing isolate of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> (UK1), injected into a single floret within the central portion of each spike. High humidity was maintained for 72 hpi by misting. Disease severity was measured as the number of diseased spikelets 14 dpi.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Influence of DELLA alleles on foliar disease resistance of wheat and barley to <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></title>
        <p>Plants of wheat cv. Maris Huntsman (<italic>rht-tall</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> NILs) and barley cv. Himalaya (WT and <italic>Sln1d</italic>) were grown to GS 12 in controlled environment cabinets under a 16 h photoperiod and a 15/12 &#xB0;C day/night temperature with 70% relative humidity. Sections (5 cm) of the second leaf were inoculated with conidia of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> (5 &#x3BC;l of 1&#xD7;10<sup>6</sup> conidia ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Chen <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref>. Leaves were returned to the growth cabinet and lesion areas were measured after 6 d using ImageJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abramoff <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Influence of DELLA on resistance of wheat heads to deoxynivalenol</title>
        <p>Maris Huntsman (<italic>rht-tall, Rht-B1b</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>) NILs were tested for resistance to DON in an unheated polytunnel. DON was kindly supplied by Dr M Lemmens (IFA-Tulln, Austria). At GS 65, two spikes per plant were treated with DON according to the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lemmens <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> with the following modification; DON solution was applied to a single clipped spikelet on each wheat head instead of two. Pots containing individual plants were arranged in a randomized complete block design of four replicates of seven plants per line. Following treatment, the number of damaged spikelets per head was assessed at 14 dpi.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Influence of DELLA on root growth of wheat and barley in response to deoxynivalenol</title>
        <p>Seed of wheat cv. Maris Huntsman (<italic>rht-tall</italic>, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> NILs) and barley cv. Himalaya (WT and <italic>Sln1d</italic>) were germinated on 0.7% water agar and transferred to 90 mm Petri-dishes of water agar containing 25 &#x3BC;M DON or to new water agar dishes (controls) and incubated at 5 &#xB0;C in the dark. Samples consisted of three replicate dishes of 20 germinated seeds per line. The lengths of primary roots were measured after a period of 10 d (experiment 1) or 14 d (experiment 2). The root length of seedlings grown on DON was expressed as a percentage of the average root length of their respective controls (mean relative length).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Influence of DELLA on deoxynivalenol-induced expression of negative cell death regulators</title>
        <p>Maris Huntsman (<italic>rht-tall, Rht-B1b</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>) NILs were incubated in darkness at 20 &#xB0;C for 5 d on moist filter paper. Roots were submerged in water or DON solution (50 &#x3BC;M) and incubated for 8 h prior to RNA extraction. Total RNA was isolated using Qiagen RNA easy spin columns from 100 mg of root tissue, ground in a pestle and mortar under liquid nitrogen. DNase treatment was carried out using the Turbo DNA-free kit (Ambion) and cDNA was synthesised from 5 &#x3BC;g of RNA using SuperScript III (Invitrogen) following the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions with the addition of random nonamers (50 &#x3BC;M, Invitrogen). RNA was digested with RNase-H (Invitrogen) from the RNA-DNA duplex to leave single-strand cDNA. cDNA was diluted 1:20 for qRT-PCR. qRT-PCR reactions were carried out using a DNA engine Opticon2 Continuous Fluorescence Detector (MJ Research Inc., Alameda, CA, USA). Amplification was carried out using SYBR Green Jumpstart <italic>Taq</italic> ready mix with gene-specific primers (<italic>BAX INHIBITOR-1</italic> fwd &#x2013; TACATGGTGTACGACACGCA and rev &#x2013; GTCCATGTCGCCGTGG (accession: HM447649) and <italic>RADICAL-INDUCED CELL DEATH 1</italic> fwd &#x2013; GCGTCTGTCTGTGAATCTGC and rev &#x2013; TGTTGATTGGACAAAAACCAA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Walter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>)). An initial activation step at 95 &#xB0;C for 4 min was followed by 40 cycles of 30 s at 95 &#xB0;C, 30 s at 60 &#xB0;C, and 30 s at 72 &#xB0;C. Target gene expression was calculated relative to the expression of the reference gene, 18S rRNA (fwd &#x2013; AGTAAGCGCGAGTCATCAGCT and rev &#x2013; CATTCAATCGGTAGGAGCGAC) using the &#x394;&#x394;C<sub>T</sub> method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Pfaffl, 2001</xref>). cDNA was diluted 1:100 for the quantification of the expression of 18S rRNA.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>All statistical analyses were performed using GenStat for Windows, 12th edition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Payne <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). For count data, a Poisson regression and for percentage data a logistic regression was used in a generalized linear model (GLM) to estimate variance attributable to replicate, experiment, and genotype. Means were compared using t-probabilities calculated within the GLM.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Interaction between DELLA and <italic>Blumeria graminis</italic></title>
        <p><italic>B. graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic> (<italic>Bgt</italic>) and f. sp. <italic>hordei</italic> (<italic>Bgh</italic>) are obligate biotrophic fungi that infect wheat and barley, respectively, causing powdery mildew. The DELLA GoF barley line, <italic>Sln1d</italic>, showed a significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) increase in susceptibility to <italic>Bgh</italic> compared with the Himalaya wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Whilst the LoF DELLA mutant line, <italic>sln1c</italic>, was significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01) more resistant compared with the Himalaya wild type, which itself expressed a high level of resistance relative to the susceptible cultivar Golden Promise. The <italic>sln1c</italic> line exhibited a spreading hypersensitive cell death phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>), which is absent in the other lines. The wild type and severe dwarf (<italic>Rht-B1c</italic> or <italic>Rht-D1c</italic>) NILs of Mercia and Maris Huntsman were equally infected by <italic>B. graminis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). However, lines containing two copies of mutant alleles (the semi-dwarf and severe dwarfing alleles; <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic>) were significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05) more susceptible (assessed as colonies cm<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>) than the respective wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B, C</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig1" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The effect of <italic>Sln1</italic> alleles on infection of barley with <italic>B. graminis</italic> f. sp<italic>. hordei</italic>. (A) Leaves of barley cvs Golden Promise (susceptible control) and Himalaya allelic at the <italic>Sln1</italic> locus inoculated with <italic>B. graminis</italic> f. sp<italic>. hordei</italic>. The number of colonies per leaf area (cm<sup>2</sup>) were measured 8 dpi. Bars &#xB1;1 SEM. ***, ** Significant difference (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001 and <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01, respectively) from Himalaya wild type (WT). (B) Representative disease phenotypes, white arrow heads denote the hypersensitive response in <italic>sln1c</italic>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterr350f01_3c"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="fig2" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The effect of GoF <italic>Rht</italic> alleles on infection of wheat with <italic>B. graminis</italic> f. sp<italic>. tritici</italic>. The number of colonies cm<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> at 8 dpi is presented for (A) wheat cvs Maris Huntsman and Mercia <italic>rht-tall</italic> (wild type) and severe dwarf NILs inoculated with <italic>B. graminis</italic> f. sp<italic>. tritici</italic> and (B) wheat cvs April Bearded and Maris Huntsman, <italic>rht-tall</italic> (wild type) and double mutant (<italic>Rht-B1c+Rht-D1b</italic>) NILs inoculated with <italic>B. graminis</italic> f. sp<italic>. tritici</italic>. Bars &#xB1;1 SEM. *, ** Significant difference (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05 and <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01, respectively) from the respective wild type lines. (C) The representative disease phenotype of two detached leaves correspond to (B).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterr350f02_3c"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Cytological analysis of the barley lines showed that a significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) higher proportion of spores infected plant host epidermal cells in <italic>Sln1d</italic> (57%) compared with WT Himalaya (18%), and none of the spores infected the cells of <italic>sln1c</italic> leaves. In the <italic>sln1c</italic> line, a high proportion (73%) of the unsuccessful interactions were due to host cell death. In <italic>Sln1d</italic> leaves, by contrast, a significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) lower proportion (15%) of unsuccessful interactions were due to cell death restriction, with the majority attributable to papillae formation (77%, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>) and the remaining spores not being advanced enough to elicit either response. Interestingly, while the <italic>B. graminis</italic>-associated cell death differed significantly in a DELLA-dependent manner, restriction of the fungus by papillae formation alone was independent of the DELLA status of the line. Furthermore, the fungal colonization process was more rapid in the <italic>Sln1d</italic> interaction than in the wild type. By 60 hpi, all successfully infecting spores reached the hyphal stage on <italic>Sln1d</italic> whilst only 17% of successfully infecting spores had reached this stage on wild-type leaves, with most (83%) only at the balloon/digitate haustorium stage.</p>
        <fig id="fig3" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Cytological analysis of the effect of <italic>Sln1</italic> alleles on infection of barley with <italic>B. graminis</italic> f. sp<italic>. hordei</italic>. The interaction outcome of 100 spores was analysed at 60 hpi. Spores which produced a haustorium were defined as successful. Unsuccessful interactions were attributed to either host cell death, papillae response or because spores were not advanced enough to elicit a response.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterr350f03_ht"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Interaction between DELLA and <italic>Ramularia collo-cygni</italic></title>
        <p>The responses of barley lines, differing in DELLA status, to the hemibiotroph <italic>Ramularia collo-cygni</italic> were assessed<italic>. R. collo-cygni</italic> is a barley infecting pathogen which exhibits a long biotrophic, endophytic phase before switching to a necrotrophic lifestyle late in infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Stabentheiner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). The DELLA GoF mutant, <italic>Sln1d</italic> was significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) more susceptible (assessed as % diseased leaf area) to <italic>R. collo-cygni</italic> than the wild-type line. In a third experiment, the LoF DELLA mutant line, <italic>sln1c</italic> was included. Confirming the role of DELLA in increasing susceptibility to <italic>R. collo-cygni</italic> infection, the DELLA LoF mutant line was found to be significantly (<italic>P</italic>=0.03) more resistant than the wild-type line (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float">
          <label>Table 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The effect of <italic>Sln1</italic> alleles on resistance to <italic>Ramularia collo-cygni</italic> assessed as % Diseased leaf area</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Diseased leaf area</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#xB1;1.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Sln1d</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#xB1;1.0</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>sln1c</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#xB1;2.2</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Interaction between DELLA and <italic>Oculimacula</italic> spp<italic>.</italic></title>
        <p><italic>O. acuformis</italic> and <italic>O. yallundae</italic> infect the stem base of cereal hosts and present contrasting pathogenic lifestyles. The former is considered a necrotroph whilst there is evidence that the latter exhibits a short biotrophic phase of establishment before switching to necrotrophic nutrition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Blein <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Wheat GoF severe dwarfing mutant lines, <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1c,</italic> showed significantly greater resistance to both <italic>O. acuformis</italic> and <italic>O. yallundae</italic> (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01 and <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05, respectively) compared with <italic>rht</italic>-<italic>tall</italic> lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Interestingly, the disease resistance conferred by DELLA stabilisation was greater for the fully necrotrophic species <italic>O. acuformis</italic> than for <italic>O. yallundae</italic> which exhibits a short initial biotrophic phase. GoF mutants in barley also exhibited significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) increased resistance to both forms of the disease relative to wild-type plants and in further support of the role of DELLA in disease resistance, the LoF DELLA mutant line <italic>sln1c</italic> exhibited significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) greater susceptibility to <italic>O. acuformis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig4" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The effect of <italic>Rht</italic> and <italic>Sln1</italic> alleles on resistance of wheat and barley to <italic>Oculimacula</italic> species. (A) Wheat cv. Mercia <italic>rht-tall</italic> (wild type) and severe dwarf NILs inoculated with either <italic>O. acuformis</italic> (black bars) or <italic>O. yallundae</italic> (grey bars) were scored for disease severity using a scale devised by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Scott (1971)</xref>. Bars &#xB1;1 SEM. *, ** Significant difference (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05 and <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01, respectively) from Mercia <italic>rht-tall</italic>. (B) Barley cv. Himalaya WT<italic>, Sln1d</italic> and <italic>sln1c</italic> were scored and presented as above. The <italic>sln1c</italic> line was not inoculated with <italic>O. yallundae</italic> (ND; no data). Bars &#xB1;1 SEM. *** Significant difference (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) from Himalaya WT.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterr350f04_ht"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Interaction between DELLA and FHB caused by <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></title>
        <p><italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> is one of the predominant causes of FHB. While <italic>F. graminearum</italic> was, for a considerable period, thought to be entirely necrotrophic in lifestyle, it is now considered to exhibit a short biotrophic phase during the infection of wheat heads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Brown <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Schroeder and Christensen (1963)</xref> describe two main components of resistance to FHB: resistance to initial infection (Type 1) and resistance to spread within the head (Type 2). These components can be broadly dissected using different inoculation techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Miedaner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>), namely spray or point inoculation.</p>
        <p>Spray inoculation of wheat heads is generally used to assess the combined effects of Type 1 and Type 2, but scoring disease symptoms before the fungus begins to spread within the head provides a measure of Type 1 resistance, which includes the biotrophic phase of the interaction. Following establishment, <italic>F. graminearum</italic> switches to a necrotrophic mode during which it produces the mycotoxin deoxynivelenol (DON) that functions as a virulence factor in FHB of wheat facilitating the spread of the fungus within the head (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bai <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Point inoculation of individual spikelets, which bypasses the plant&#x2019;s defence against initial infection, is used to assess resistance to disease spread (Type 2 resistance).</p>
        <p>Near-isogenic wheat lines were subjected to spray or point inoculation with conidia of <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. Following spray inoculation, <italic>rht-tall</italic> showed the greatest resistance to initial infection in both field and polytunnel experiments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>). In both experiments the severe dwarf <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> NIL showed significantly greater (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.009) susceptibility to initial infection compared with the semi-dwarf <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> line.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float">
          <label>Table 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The effect of <italic>Rht</italic> alleles on Type 1 resistance to <italic>Fusarium</italic> Head Blight assessed as % Spikelets infected</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experiment</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Spikelets infected</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>rht-tall</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#xB1;2.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#xB1;2.1</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.185</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#xB1;2.1</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polytunnel</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>rht-tall</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.8</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#xB1;0.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#xB1;1.0</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.9</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#xB1;1.1</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Following point inoculation, the wild-type line of Maris Huntsman was highly susceptible to the spread of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> with an average of 10.0 spikelets showing disease at 14 dpi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A, B</xref>). <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> NILs showed significantly less (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) symptom spread than the wild-type line, with an average of 8.9 spikelets showing disease at this stage. The reduction in symptoms was even greater for the <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> NILs with only 5.2 spikelets exhibiting disease (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001). A similar trend was observed with Mercia wild-type, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> NILs (data not shown).</p>
        <fig id="fig5" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 5.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The effect of GoF mutant alleles on resistance to <italic>Fusarium</italic> disease spread. (A) Number of damaged spikelets following point inoculation with either <italic>F. graminearum</italic> or deoxynivalenol (DON) of the ears of wheat cv. Maris Huntsman NILs allelic at the <italic>Rht-B1</italic> loci at 14 dpi. Black bars represent <italic>F. graminearum</italic> inoculated ears. *** Significant difference (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) from <italic>rht-tall</italic>. Grey bars represent DON treated ears. &#x2020;&#x2020;, &#x2020;&#x2020;&#x2020; Significant difference (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01 and <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001, respectively) from <italic>rht-tall</italic>. Bars &#xB1;1 SEM. (B, C) Typical symptom spread and contained phenotype in <italic>rht-tall</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> lines following point inoculation with <italic>F. graminearum</italic> and DON, respectively. Injected spikelet is arrowed. (D) Mean cell death lesion area (cm<sup>2</sup>) following <italic>F. graminearum</italic> inoculation of the leaves of wheat and barley lines 6 dpi. **, *** Significant difference (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01 and <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) from the corresponding wild type. Bars &#xB1;1 SEM. (E) Representative lesions on leaves of wild-type and mutant plants corresponding to labels in (D) stained with trypan blue to detect cell death. The central circles show inoculation points.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterr350f05_3c"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Influence of DELLA on lesion development induced by <italic>F. graminearum</italic> on leaves of wheat and barley</title>
        <p>Wound inoculation of leaves with <italic>F. graminearum</italic> also bypasses defence against initial infection, and thus disease development can be used to assess resistance to fungal spread independently of resistance to initial infection. Following wound inoculation of leaves, the zone of cell death about the inoculation point at 6 dpi was significantly greater (<italic>P</italic>=0.006) in Maris Huntsman wild type than the <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> NIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5D, E</xref>). Similarly, the zone was significantly greater (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) in Himalaya wild type than the <italic>Sln1d</italic> line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5D, E</xref>). Cell death was not observed beyond the point of inoculation in wheat or barley following wounding alone (data not shown).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Interaction between DELLA and deoxynivalenol induced lesion development</title>
        <p>Production of DON by <italic>F. graminearum</italic> is required for disease spread in wheat heads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bai <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). To determine whether DELLA accumulating lines are more resistant to DON, bleaching symptoms induced by this mycotoxin were assessed following point inoculation with DON. In the wild-type Maris Huntsman line, bleaching symptoms spread an average of 4.3 spikelets from the point of inoculation at 14 dpi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A, C</xref>), whereas in the <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> line, symptom spread was significantly less (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01) than in the wild-type line, with an average of 3.1 spikelets exhibiting symptoms at 14 dpi. Most strikingly, following injection of the <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> line, symptoms were restricted to the inoculated spikelet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A, C</xref>). Overall, these symptoms closely resembled those appearing following point inoculation with a DON-producing isolate of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A, B</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Influence of DELLA on deoxynivalenol-induced inhibition of root elongation of wheat and barley</title>
        <p>DON has been demonstrated to inhibit root growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Eudes <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). To assess the effect of DELLA on root growth in the presence of DON, treated and untreated roots of Maris Huntsman NILs (<italic>rht-tall</italic>, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>) and Himalaya WT and <italic>Sln1d</italic> were measured. DON-induced root inhibition was significantly less (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) for <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> than for the wild type (<italic>rht-tall</italic>) or <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> lines of Maris Huntsman (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>). The mean growth of DON-treated roots, relative to untreated roots across experiments was 56.4% for <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>, 40.0% for <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>, and 37.7% for the <italic>rht-tall</italic> line of Maris Huntsman. Similarly, the effect of DON on root growth of Himalaya WT and <italic>Sln1d</italic> also differed significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). The mean growth of DON-treated roots, relative to untreated roots across experiments was 44.4% for <italic>Sln1d</italic>, and 36.8% for the Himalaya wild-type line.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float">
          <label>Table 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Root growth inhibition assay of <italic>rht</italic>-<italic>tall</italic>, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> near-isogenic lines of Maris Huntsman and Himalaya WT and <italic>Sln1d</italic> in the presence of deoxynivalenol</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cultivar</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Growth inhibition relative to untreated control</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value comparison with wild-type</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maris Huntsman</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>rht-tall</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.0</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Rht-B1c</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.6</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Himalaya</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Sln1d</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.6</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Influence of DELLA on deoxynivalenol-induced expression of negative cell death regulators</title>
        <p>Deoxynivalenol has been demonstrated to induce H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production and to promote host cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Desmond <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). To gain an insight into the mechanism of DELLA-conferred tolerance to DON, the expression of two candidate negative regulators of cell death, <italic>BAX INHIBITOR-1</italic> (<italic>BI-1)</italic> and <italic>RADICAL INDUCED CELL DEATH 1</italic> (<italic>RCD1</italic>), was quantified in <italic>rht-tall</italic>, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> Maris Huntsman NILs following exposure to DON (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig6" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 6.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The effect of deoxynivalenol on the expression of genes involved in the negative regulation of cell death. <italic>BAX INHIBITOR-1</italic> (A) and <italic>RADICAL INDUCED CELL DEATH 1</italic> (B) expression was measured in the root tissue of wheat cv. Maris Huntsman NILs allelic at the <italic>Rht-B1</italic> locus treated with water (control) or deoxynivalenol (DON). Target gene expression was normalized to 18S expression. Bars &#xB1;1 SEM.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterr350f06_ht"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Expression of <italic>BI-1</italic> differed between the untreated <italic>rht-tall</italic>, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> NILs: expression was significantly lower in the <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> lines than in the <italic>rht-tall</italic> line (<italic>P</italic>=0.01 and <italic>P</italic>=0.003, respectively) while expression levels were similar for all three lines following treatment with DON (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>). Treatment with DON did not significantly alter expression of <italic>BI-1</italic> in the <italic>rht-tall</italic> line. By contrast, treatment with DON resulted in a significant increase in expression of <italic>BI-1</italic> in both the <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> (<italic>P</italic>=0.048) and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> (<italic>P</italic>=0.001) lines.</p>
        <p>Expression of <italic>RCD1</italic> in the untreated roots also differed between the <italic>rht-tall</italic>, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic>, and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> NILs. Although it was not significantly different, expression was lower in the <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> lines than in the untreated <italic>rht-tall</italic> line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>). No significant difference was observed in the <italic>rht-tall</italic> lines following DON treatment while, by contrast, DON treatment resulted in a significant increase in expression of <italic>RCD1</italic> in both the <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> (<italic>P</italic>=0.001) and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) lines. Following DON treatment the expression of <italic>RCD1</italic> was significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) greater in both the <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> or <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> lines than in the <italic>rht-tall</italic> line.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The reduced GA sensitivity of the DELLA <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1b</italic> semi-dwarfing alleles in wheat were central to enhanced crop yields achieved as part of the Green Revolution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hedden, 2003</xref>). However, research using <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> has indicated that DELLA may have pleiotropic effects, including an altered response to pathogens. Using DELLA mutants in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Navarro <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> showed that DELLAs promote susceptibility to biotrophs and resistance to necrotrophs. Such findings are potentially significant in agriculture but information relating to potential pleiotropic effects in monocotyledonous species is currently lacking.</p>
      <p>In the current study, the role of DELLA proteins in response to pathogens was investigated in two important monocotyledonous crop species. In contrast to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <italic>H. vulgare</italic> (barley) is a diploid species which contains a single DELLA-encoding gene. Both GoF and LoF mutants are available in barley arising from point mutations enabling us to observe the effect of <italic>Sln1</italic> without the gene redundancy present in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and wheat. Using these mutants, it was demonstrated that DELLA confers a resistance trade-off to a range of fungal pathogens with differing trophic lifestyles that are responsible for some economically important diseases of cereals. <italic>T. aestivum</italic> (bread wheat) is a polyploid species originating from the hybridization of three diploid progenitors and as such contains three DELLA-encoding genes. Using GoF mutants in polyploids, a correlation between dwarfing severity and influence on resistance was also demonstrated. In addition, the effect of polyploidy has been assessed, observing how disease resistance is influenced by DELLA alleles conferring semi-dwarf and severe-dwarf phenotypes, functioning in the presence of background wild-type homoeologous DELLA-encoding genes. The results reported in this study using diverse DELLA mutants in two cereal species indicates that the effect on disease resistance to pathogens with differing lifestyles is due to pleiotropy rather than linkage. Thus our findings support those previously reported in dicot species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Navarro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) that suggested a pleiotropic role of DELLA in disease resistance.</p>
      <p>Biotrophic pathogens derive their nutrients from living host cells. All obligate biotrophic pathogens possess specialist feeding structures, known as haustoria, which penetrate the cell wall. Recognition of the invading pathogen results in an increase in reactive oxygen species (ROS) production leading to the hypersensitive response (HR), a type of programmed cell death which deprives biotrophic pathogens of their food source. Studies in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> have implicated DELLA proteins in processes leading to cell death. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Achard <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> demonstrated that DELLAs delay ROS-induced cell death and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Navarro <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> reported that DELLAs suppress the accumulation of salicylic acid (SA) and cell death in response to infection by <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv. <italic>tomato</italic>. In the present study, microscopic analysis of the host defence response in the barley<italic>&#x2013;B. graminis</italic> (biotroph) interaction showed that the DELLA LoF line is hypersensitive to cell death resulting in complete resistance, whilst the frequency of hypersensitive cell death was reduced in the DELLA GoF line, resulting in a higher number of successful haustorial establishment events (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). As in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> DELLA accumulating mutants, the barley DELLA GoF line may exhibit a delay in ROS-induced cell death which, in turn, reduces the effectiveness of the HR thereby increasing susceptibility both to an obligate biotroph, <italic>B. graminis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2</xref>) and to a hemibiotroph with a long biotrophic or endophytic phase, <italic>R. collo cygni</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
      <p>The height reduction associated with the <italic>Sln1d</italic> (GoF) allele in barley is similar to that associated with <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1c</italic> alleles in wheat (<italic>c</italic>. 50% of the respective wild type). However, in contrast to the significantly enhanced susceptibility to <italic>B. graminis</italic> of the barley <italic>Sln1d</italic> line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), wheat lines carrying single mutant alleles, <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> or <italic>Rht-D1c</italic> did not exhibit an equivalent increase in susceptibility. The combination of dwarf and semi-dwarf mutant alleles (<italic>Rht-B1c+Rht-D1b</italic>) in a single line, however, did enhance susceptibility. In polyploid species like wheat, the presence of wild-type homoeologous copies of the <italic>Rht</italic> genes might buffer the negative effect of a single mutation on susceptibility to <italic>B. graminis</italic>. It is conceivable that DELLA accumulation must pass a threshold in order significantly to delay cell death induced by <italic>B. graminis</italic> and that this threshold is exceeded in <italic>Rht-B1c+Rht-D1b</italic> (dwarf+semi dwarf) NILs carrying mutations in two of their three <italic>Rht</italic> (DELLA) homoeologues but not in lines carrying a mutation in only a single homoeologue. Further investigation with other biotrophic pathogens is necessary to determine whether this phenomenon is specific to <italic>B. graminis</italic> or common to other biotrophs.</p>
      <p>Hemibiotrophic pathogens exhibit an initial biotrophic phase before switching to a necrotrophic lifestyle. The barley pathogen, <italic>R. collo-cygni</italic>, is a hemibiotroph with a prolonged biotrophic phase during which time the fungus grows intercellularly, colonizing the spaces between the mesophyll cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Sutton and Waller, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Stabentheiner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). The barley lines carrying the GoF or LoF DELLA mutations showed differential responses to <italic>R. collo-cygni</italic> with the GoF mutant being significantly more susceptible and the LoF mutant significantly more resistant than the wild type (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). These results suggest that DELLA-mediated prevention of cell death benefits the initial biotrophic phase of <italic>R. collo-cygni</italic> infection and supports the current view that <italic>R. collo-cygni</italic> has a long biotrophic phase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Walters <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>).</p>
      <p>Necrotrophic pathogens derive their nutrients from dead host cells. These pathogens have evolved a number of strategies to kill host cells including the secretion of toxins, cell-wall-degrading enzymes, and eliciting ROS production. If, as reported, DELLA prevents ROS-induced cell death then it would be predicted that plants with increased DELLA accumulation would be more resistant to necrotrophs than their tall counterparts. <italic>O. acuformis</italic> is considered to be a typical necrotrophic pathogen while the closely related species <italic>O. yallundae</italic> exhibits a very short non-necrotrophic initial phase during the infection of wheat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Blein <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Both species cause eyespot disease on the stem base of cereals and are considered a serious disease of winter wheat in northern Europe and north-west USA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Fitt, 1992</xref>). GoF mutations of DELLA in both wheat and barley resulted in significantly increased resistance to both <italic>Oculimacula</italic> species as might be anticipated given their necrotrophic lifestyles. Supportive of DELLA increasing resistance to necrotrophs, the barley LoF mutant exhibits enhanced susceptibility to eyespot caused by <italic>O. acuformis.</italic></p>
      <p>Interestingly, the effect on the GoF mutation in wheat was greater for <italic>O. acuformis</italic> than for <italic>O. yallundae</italic>. It is speculated that this reflects the different growth habits of the two species. Whilst <italic>O. acuformis</italic> exhibits an invasive growth habit, <italic>O. yallundae</italic> penetrates the coleoptile in a more ordered, intramural manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Daniels <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>), with no sign of host cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Blein <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Once at the first leaf sheath the pathogen initiates the formation of an infection plaque from which hyphae grow and penetrate the first, then successive leaf sheaths facilitated by the secretion of cell-wall-degrading enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Mbwaga <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). These observations suggest that <italic>O. yallundae</italic> may be considered to be a hemibiotroph with a very short initial phase of biotrophic growth before switching to a necrotrophic phase once the pathogen reaches the first leaf sheath (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Blein <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) while <italic>O. acuformis</italic> exhibits the traits of a conventional necrotroph.</p>
      <p><italic>F. graminearum</italic> was originally considered to be entirely necrotrophic. However, evidence is accumulating to indicate that this may not always be the case. Analysis of the interaction at the cellular level shows that <italic>F. graminearum</italic> exhibits extracellular growth during the early stages of infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Pritsch <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>) and sub-cuticular growth reminiscent of <italic>O. yallundae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Rittenour and Harris, 2010</xref>). It appears that <italic>F. graminearum</italic> requires a transient biotrophic phase of establishment before switching to necrotrophic nutrition during the infection of wheat leading to FHB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Goswami and Kistler, 2004</xref>). This view is supported by studies on the interaction of FHB with the SA and JA signalling pathways. SA content and expression of the SA-inducible <italic>PR1</italic> gene in <italic>Arabidopisis</italic> inoculated with <italic>F. graminearum</italic> showed that SA signalling is activated in the early stages of infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Makandar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Furthermore, over-expression of a gene that regulates SA signalling (<italic>NPR1</italic>), in wheat and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, increases resistance to <italic>F. graminearum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Makandar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Methyl jasmonate (MJ), however, has dichotomous effects on the susceptibility of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> to <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. The application of MJ during the early stages of infection enhanced disease severity, presumably due to JA attenuating SA signalling, whilst, when applied at later stages of infection, MJ reduced disease severity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Makandar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p>
      <p>Short wheat varieties tend to be more susceptible to FHB in the field than tall ones and it has been demonstrated that semi-dwarf lines carrying the <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> allele are more susceptible to initial infection than those carrying the wild-type allele (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Srinivasachary <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). In the present study, it has been demonstrated that both <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> NILs exhibit increased Type 1 susceptibility (initial infection) relative to the wild type, and that this is associated with the severity of the DELLA effect on plant height. By contrast, following point inoculation, <italic>Rht-B1b</italic> and <italic>Rht-B1c</italic> NILs exhibited increased resistance to disease spread relative to the wild type and this also correlates with the DELLA effect on plant height. DELLA GoF dwarf lines of both wheat and barley also showed enhanced resistance to cell death following wound-inoculation of leaves with <italic>F. graminearum.</italic> Overall, these results indicate that, whilst DELLA accumulating lines are more susceptible to the initial establishment phase they are more resistant to the later colonization phase. It is proposed that these contrasting differential susceptibilities reflect the different trophic modes of growth employed by <italic>F. graminearum</italic> and support the evidence that <italic>F. graminearum</italic> exhibits an initial biotrophic phase during FHB infection prior to entering a longer necrotrophic phase.</p>
      <p>The trichothecene mycotoxin DON functions as a virulence factor for <italic>F. graminearum</italic> during colonization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bai <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). The up-regulation of trichothecene biosynthetic genes and subsequent accumulation of DON in head tissues have been observed 48 hpi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Boddu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). This is thought to signal the switch from biotrophic to necrotrophic growth. DON has been shown to induce H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production in the host, promoting cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Desmond <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). In addition, <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments have demonstrated that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> induces DON production by the fungus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Ponts <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>) leading to a cycle that ultimately favours necrotrophy. Plant lines with enhanced capabilities of alleviating oxidative stress would be anticipated to exhibit increased resistance to <italic>F. graminearum</italic> and DON. This view is supported by a number of studies. For example, increases in the activity of the antioxidant enzymes superoxide dismutase (SOD) and catalase (CAT) positively correlated with FHB resistance in a set of wheat varieties inoculated with DON-producing isolates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). Similarly, the <italic>Arabidopsis RADICAL-INDUCED CELL DEATH 1</italic> (<italic>AtRCD1</italic>) wheat homologue, referred to as <italic>CLONE EIGHTY ONE</italic>, that is thought to regulate oxidative stress responses negatively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Overmyer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>) accumulated in higher amounts in DON-tolerant lines compared with susceptible lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Walter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>).</p>
      <p>In the present study, it was found that GoF DELLA lines were more resistant both to colonization by <italic>F. graminearum</italic> and to DON-induced cell death than their tall counterparts, probably due, at least in part, to a reduced propensity of these plants to initiate or undergo cell death. DELLA proteins have been shown to up-regulate genes involved in the ROS scavenging system such as <italic>CSD1/2</italic> which encode SOD in response to stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Achard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). It was observed that expression of <italic>RCD1</italic> (<italic>CEO</italic>) and <italic>BI-1</italic>, that has a putative role in the regulation of cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Huckelhoven, 2004</xref>), is greater in the roots of wheat DELLA GoF lines than in the wild type following treatment with DON (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). Interestingly a trade-off in resistance to pathogens with opposing lifestyles has been observed in barley lines over-expressing <italic>HvBI-1.</italic> These plants exhibit enhanced susceptibility to <italic>Blumeria</italic> and enhanced resistance to <italic>Fusarium</italic> that is associated with their decreased propensity to undergo cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Babaeizad <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Trade-off between susceptibility to biotrophs and resistance to necrotrophs, and vice versa, has also been demonstrated in barley lines lacking MLO function, which exhibit increased resistance to <italic>Blumeria</italic> whilst enhancing susceptibility to necrotrophic pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Jarosch <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kumar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>).</p>
      <p>Our data demonstrate that DELLA plays a central and dichotomous role in resistance to necrotrophic and biotrophic pathogens in cereal monocot species in a manner similar to that observed in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Navarro <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Single DELLA GoF mutants of both barley (diploid) and wheat (hexaploid) exhibited enhanced resistance to necrotrophic pathogens (<italic>F. graminearum,</italic> and <italic>Oculimacula</italic> species). However, while the barley GoF mutant exhibited significantly enhanced susceptibility to a biotrophic pathogen (<italic>Blumeria</italic> f. sp.), increased susceptibility in wheat was only observed when two of the three DELLA homoeologues were mutated. These findings indicate that, while the semi-dwarfing alleles deployed in present-day wheat cultivars provide increased tolerance to necrotrophic pathogens, due to the polyploid nature of wheat, they confer only a negligible effect on susceptibility to <italic>Blumeria</italic> (and possibly other obligate biotrophs). Appreciation of the role of DELLA in responses to biotic stress in cereals is important in plant breeding where the pleiotropic effect on disease resistance of <italic>Rht</italic> alleles used to achieve appropriate plant stature will have to be balanced through enhancing disease resistance as suggested for FHB by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Miedaner and Voss (2008)</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This work has been funded by the <funding-source>UK Biotechnology and Biological Science Research Council (BBSRC)</funding-source>. We thank JIC horticultural and field services for assistance with trials. We also thank Dr Peter Chandler, CSIRO, Australia, and Dr John Flintham, JIC, Norwich for providing seed and Dr Marc Lemmens, IFA-Tulln, Austria for providing DON.</p>
    </ack>
    <glossary>
      <def-list>
        <title>Abbreviations</title>
        <def-item>
          <term>DON</term>
          <def>
            <p>deoxynivalinol</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>ET</term>
          <def>
            <p>ethylene</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>FHB</term>
          <def>
            <p>Fusarium head blight</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>GoF</term>
          <def>
            <p>gain of function</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>GA</term>
          <def>
            <p>gibberellin</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>GS</term>
          <def>
            <p>growth stage</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>JA</term>
          <def>
            <p>jasmonic acid</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>LoF</term>
          <def>
            <p>loss of function</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>NILs</term>
          <def>
            <p>near-isogenic lines</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>qRT-PCR</term>
          <def>
            <p>quantitative real-time PCR</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>ROS</term>
          <def>
            <p>reactive oxygen species</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>SA</term>
          <def>
            <p>salicylic acid</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abramoff</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magelhaes</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ram</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Image processing with Image J</article-title>
          <source>Biophoton International</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>36</fpage>
          <lpage>42</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Achard</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gong</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheminant</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alioua</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hedden</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Genschik</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The cold-inducible CBF1 factor-dependent signaling pathway modulates the accumulation of the growth-repressing DELLA proteins via its effect on gibberellin metabolism</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>2117</fpage>
          <lpage>2129</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18757556</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Babaeizad</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Imani</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kogel</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eichmann</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huckelhoven</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Over-expression of the cell death regulator BAX inhibitor-1 in barley confers reduced or enhanced susceptibility to distinct fungal pathogens</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>118</volume>
          <fpage>455</fpage>
          <lpage>463</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18956174</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bahat</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gelernter</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eyal</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Factors affecting the vertical progression of septoria leaf blotch in short-statured wheats</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <fpage>179</fpage>
          <lpage>184</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bai</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Desjardins</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plattner</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Deoxynivalenol-nonproducing <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> causes initial infection, but does not cause disease spread in wheat spikes</article-title>
          <source>Mycopathologia</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>153</volume>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <lpage>98</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12000132</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Blein</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levrel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lemoine</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gautier</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chevalier</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barloy</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Oculimacula yallundae</italic> lifestyle revisited: relationships between the timing of eyespot symptom appearance, the development of the pathogen and the responses of infected partially resistant wheat plants</article-title>
          <source>Plant Pathology</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boddu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cho</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kruger</surname>
              <given-names>WM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muehlbauer</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transcriptome analysis of the barley-<italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> interaction</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant&#x2013;Microbe Interactions</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>407</fpage>
          <lpage>417</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16610744</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boyd</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>JKM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular and cellular expression of quantitative resistance in barley to powdery mildew</article-title>
          <source>Physiological and Molecular Plant Pathology</source>
          <year>1994a</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          <lpage>58</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boyd</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Green</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>JKM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The relationship between the expression of defense-related genes and mildew development in barley</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant&#x2013;Microbe Interactions</source>
          <year>1994b</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>401</fpage>
          <lpage>410</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>JKM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolfe</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Structure and evolution of a population of <italic>Erysiphe graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>hordei</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Pathology</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>376</fpage>
          <lpage>390</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>NA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Urban</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van De Meene</surname>
              <given-names>AML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The infection biology of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>: defining the pathways of spikelet to spikelet colonisation in wheat ears</article-title>
          <source>Fungal Biology</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <fpage>555</fpage>
          <lpage>571</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20943167</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chandler</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marion-Poll</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ellis</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gubler</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutants at the <italic>Slender1</italic> locus of barley cv. Himalaya. Molecular and physiological characterization</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>129</volume>
          <fpage>181</fpage>
          <lpage>190</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011349</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chapman</surname>
              <given-names>NH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burt</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicholson</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The development of PCR-based markers for the selection of eyespot resistance genes Pch1 and Pch2</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>425</fpage>
          <lpage>433</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18483719</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nie</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparison for activities of superoxide dismutase and catalase between scab-resistant and susceptible wheat varieties</article-title>
          <source>Acta Phytopathologica Sinica</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>209</fpage>
          <lpage>213</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steed</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Travella</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keller</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicholson</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> exploits ethylene signalling to colonize dicotyledonous and monocotyledonous plants</article-title>
          <source>New Phytologist</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>182</volume>
          <fpage>975</fpage>
          <lpage>983</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19383094</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Daniels</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lucas</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peberdy</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Morphology and ultrastructure of W-pathotype and R-pathotype of <italic>Pseudocercosporella herpotrichoides</italic> on wheat seedlings</article-title>
          <source>Mycological Research</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <fpage>385</fpage>
          <lpage>397</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Desmond</surname>
              <given-names>OJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manners</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stephens</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>MaClean</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schenk</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gardiner</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Munn</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kazan</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Fusarium mycotoxin deoxynivalenol elicits hydrogen peroxide production, programmed cell death and defence responses in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant Pathology</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>435</fpage>
          <lpage>445</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18705859</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Draeger</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gosman</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steed</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification of QTLs for resistance to Fusarium head blight, DON accumulation and associated traits in the winter wheat variety Arina</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>115</volume>
          <fpage>617</fpage>
          <lpage>625</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17607557</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eriksen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borum</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jahoor</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Inheritance and localisation of resistance to <italic>Mycosphaerella graminicola</italic> causing <italic>Septoria tritici</italic> blotch and plant height in the wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) genome with DNA markers</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>107</volume>
          <fpage>515</fpage>
          <lpage>527</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12783168</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eudes</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Comeau</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rioux</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Collin</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phytotoxicity of eight mycotoxins associated with fusarium in wheat head blight</article-title>
          <source>Canadian Journal of Plant Pathology&#x2013;Revue Canadienne De Phytopathologie</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>286</fpage>
          <lpage>292</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fitt</surname>
              <given-names>BDL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>US</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chaube</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Eyespot of cereals</article-title>
          <source>Plant dseases of international importance, Vol. 1. Diseases of cereals and culses</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <publisher-loc>New Jersey</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Prentice-Hall Inc</publisher-name>
          <fpage>337</fpage>
          <lpage>355</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Flintham</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Worland</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gale</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Optimizing wheat grain yield: effects of Rht (gibberellin-insensitive) dwarfing genes</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Agricultural Science</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>128</volume>
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gervais</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dedryver</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morlais</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bodusseau</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Negre</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bilous</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Groos</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trottet</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mapping of quantitative trait loci for field resistance to Fusarium head blight in an European winter wheat</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <fpage>961</fpage>
          <lpage>970</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12671743</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Glazebrook</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Contrasting mechanisms of defense against biotrophic and necrotrophic pathogens</article-title>
          <source>Annual Review of Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>205</fpage>
          <lpage>227</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gosman</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bayles</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jennings</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kirby</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicholson</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation and characterization of resistance to fusarium head blight caused by <italic>Fusarium culmorum</italic> in UK winter wheat cultivars</article-title>
          <source>Plant Pathology</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>264</fpage>
          <lpage>276</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goswami</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kistler</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Heading for disaster: <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> on cereal crops</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant Pathology</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>515</fpage>
          <lpage>525</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20565626</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hedden</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The genes of the Green Revolution</article-title>
          <source>Trends in Genetics</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>5</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12493241</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huckelhoven</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>BAX Inhibitor-1, an ancient cell death suppressor in animals and plants with prokaryotic relatives</article-title>
          <source>Apoptosis</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>299</fpage>
          <lpage>307</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15258461</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib29">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jarosch</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kogel</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schaffrath</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The ambivalence of the barley Mlo locus: mutations conferring resistance against powdery mildew (<italic>Blumeria graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>hordei</italic>) enhance susceptibility to the rice blast fungus <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic></article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant&#x2013;Microbe Interactions</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>508</fpage>
          <lpage>514</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib30">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Klahr</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zimmermann</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wenzel</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohler</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of environment, disease progress, plant height and heading date on the detection of QTLs for resistance to Fusarium head blight in an European winter wheat cross</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>154</volume>
          <fpage>17</fpage>
          <lpage>28</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib31">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huckelhoven</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beckhove</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagarajan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kogel</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A compromised Mlo pathway affects the response of barley to the necrotrophic fungus <italic>Bipolaris sorokiniana</italic> (Teleomorph: <italic>Cochliobolus sativus</italic>) and its toxins</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>127</fpage>
          <lpage>133</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944385</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib32">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lemmens</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scholz</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berthiller</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The ability to detoxify the mycotoxin deoxynivalenol colocalizes with a major quantitative trait locus for fusarium head blight resistance in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant&#x2013;Microbe Interactions</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>1318</fpage>
          <lpage>1324</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16478051</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib33">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lewis</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Concepts in fungal nutrition and origin of biotrophy</article-title>
          <source>Biological Reviews of the Cambridge Philosophical Society</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>261</fpage>
          <lpage>278</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib34">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Makandar</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Essig</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schapaugh</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trick</surname>
              <given-names>HN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetically engineered resistance to Fusarium head blight in wheat by expression of Arabidopsis NPR1</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant&#x2013;Microbe Interactions</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>123</fpage>
          <lpage>129</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16529374</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib35">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Makandar</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nalam</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chaturvedi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeannotte</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sparks</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Involvement of salicylate and jasmonate signaling pathways in Arabidopsis interaction with <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant&#x2013;Microbe Interactions</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>861</fpage>
          <lpage>870</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20521949</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib36">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Makepeace</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Havis</surname>
              <given-names>ND</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burke</surname>
              <given-names>JI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oxley</surname>
              <given-names>SJP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>JKM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A method of inoculating barley seedlings with <italic>Ramularia collo-cygni</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Pathology</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>991</fpage>
          <lpage>999</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib37">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mbwaga</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Menke</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grossmann</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Investigations on the activity of cell wall-degrading enzymes in young wheat plants after infection with Pseudocercosporella herpotrichoides (Fron) Deighton</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Phytopathology&#x2013;Phytopathologische Zeitschrift</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>145</volume>
          <fpage>123</fpage>
          <lpage>130</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib38">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miedaner</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moldovan</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ittu</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparison of spray and point inoculation to assess resistance to fusarium head blight in a multienvironment wheat trial</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>1068</fpage>
          <lpage>1072</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944089</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib39">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miedaner</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Voss</surname>
              <given-names>HH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effect of dwarfing Rht genes on Fusarium head blight resistance in two sets of near-isogenic lines of wheat and check cultivars</article-title>
          <source>Crop Science</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>2115</fpage>
          <lpage>2122</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib40">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Navarro</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bari</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Achard</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lison</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nemri</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harberd</surname>
              <given-names>NP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>JDG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>DELLAs control plant immune responses by modulating the balance and salicylic acid signaling</article-title>
          <source>Current Biology</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>650</fpage>
          <lpage>655</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18450451</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib41">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Overmyer</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tuominen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kettunen</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Betz</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Langebartels</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sandermann</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kangasjarvi</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ozone-sensitive Arabidopsis rcd1 mutant reveals opposite roles for ethylene and jasmonate signaling pathways in regulating superoxide-dependent cell death</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>1849</fpage>
          <lpage>1862</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11041881</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib42">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Payne</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murray</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harding</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baird</surname>
              <given-names>DB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soutar</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>GenStat for Windows (12th Edition). Introduction</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <publisher-loc>Hemel Hempstead</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>VSN International</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib43">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peng</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carol</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Richards</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cowling</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murphy</surname>
              <given-names>GP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harberd</surname>
              <given-names>NP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Arabidopsis GAI gene defines a signaling pathway that negatively regulates gibberellin responses</article-title>
          <source>Genes and Development</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>3194</fpage>
          <lpage>3205</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9389651</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib44">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peng</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Richards</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hartley</surname>
              <given-names>NM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>'Green revolution' genes encode mutant gibberellin response modulators</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>400</volume>
          <fpage>256</fpage>
          <lpage>261</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10421366</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib45">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Perfect</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Green</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Infection structures of biotrophic and hemibiotrophic fungal plant pathogens</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant Pathology</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>101</fpage>
          <lpage>108</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20572997</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib46">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pfaffl</surname>
              <given-names>MW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A new mathematical model for relative quantification in real-time RT-PCR</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <comment>29, e45</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib47">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ponts</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pinson-Gadais</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verdal-Bonnin</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barreau</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Richard-Forget</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Accumulation of deoxynivalenol and its 15-acetylated form is significantly modulated by oxidative stress in liquid cultures of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>
          <source>FEMS Microbiology Letters</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>258</volume>
          <fpage>102</fpage>
          <lpage>107</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16630263</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib48">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pritsch</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muehlbauer</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bushnell</surname>
              <given-names>WR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Somers</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vance</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fungal development and induction of defense response genes during early infection of wheat spikes by <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant&#x2013;Microbe Interactions</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>159</fpage>
          <lpage>169</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10659706</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib49">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rittenour</surname>
              <given-names>WR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harris</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An <italic>in vitro</italic> method for the analysis of infection-related morphogenesis in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant Pathology</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>361</fpage>
          <lpage>369</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20447284</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib50">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schroeder</surname>
              <given-names>HW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Christensen</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Factors affecting resistance of wheat to scab caused by <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>1963</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>831</fpage>
          <lpage>838</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib51">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scott</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effect of temperature on eyespot (<italic>Cercosporella herpotrichoides</italic>) in wheat seedlings</article-title>
          <source>Annals of Applied Biology</source>
          <year>1971</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>169</fpage>
          <lpage>175</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib52">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scott</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benedikz</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A genetic-study of the relationship between height, time of ear emergence and resistance to <italic>Septoria nodorum</italic> in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Plant Pathology</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib53">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scott</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benedikz</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>HG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ford</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Some effects of canopy structure and microclimate on infection of tall and short wheats by <italic>Septoria nodorum</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Pathology</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>578</fpage>
          <lpage>593</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib54">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Silverstone</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ciampaglio</surname>
              <given-names>CN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>TP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Arabidopsis RGA gene encodes a transcriptional regulator repressing the gibberellin signal transduction pathway</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Cell</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>155</fpage>
          <lpage>169</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9490740</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib55">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Srinivasachary</surname>
              <given-names>Gosman N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steed</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hollins</surname>
              <given-names>TW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bayles</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jennings</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicholson</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Semi-dwarfing Rht-B1 and Rht-D1 loci of wheat differ significantly in their influence on resistance to Fusarium head blight</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>118</volume>
          <fpage>695</fpage>
          <lpage>702</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19034409</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib56">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stabentheiner</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Minihofer</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huss</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Infection of barley by <italic>Ramularia collo-cygni</italic>: scanning electron microscopic investigations</article-title>
          <source>Mycopathologia</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>168</volume>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>143</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19396571</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib57">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sutton</surname>
              <given-names>BC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waller</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Taxonomy of <italic>Ophiocladium hordei</italic>, causing leaf lesions on triticale and other graminaeae</article-title>
          <source>Transactions of the British Mycological Society</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <fpage>55</fpage>
          <lpage>61</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib58">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ueguchi-Tanaka</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ashikari</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakajima</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>GIBBERELLIN INSENSITIVE DWARF1</italic> encodes a soluble receptor for gibberellin</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>437</volume>
          <fpage>693</fpage>
          <lpage>698</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16193045</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib59">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ueguchi-Tanaka</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakajima</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katoh</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular interactions of a soluble gibberellin receptor, GID1, with a rice DELLA protein, SLR1, and gibberellin</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>2140</fpage>
          <lpage>2155</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17644730</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib60">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vanbeuningen</surname>
              <given-names>LT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohli</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Deviation from the regression of infection on heading and height as a measure of resistance to <italic>Septoria tritici</italic> blotch in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Plant Disease</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>488</fpage>
          <lpage>493</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib61">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Walter</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brennan</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arunachalam</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Components of the gene network associated with genotype-dependent response of wheat to the Fusarium mycotoxin deoxynivalenol</article-title>
          <source>Functional and Integrative Genomics</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>421</fpage>
          <lpage>427</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18592282</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib62">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Walters</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Havis</surname>
              <given-names>ND</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oxley</surname>
              <given-names>SJP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Ramularia collo-cygni</italic>: the biology of an emerging pathogen of barley</article-title>
          <source>FEMS Microbiology Letters</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>279</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18070071</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib63">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wen</surname>
              <given-names>CK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Arabidopsis <italic>RGL1</italic> encodes a negative regulator of gibberellin responses</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>87</fpage>
          <lpage>100</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11826301</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib64">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zadoks</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>TT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Konzak</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Decimal code for growth stages of cereals</article-title>
          <source>Weed Research</source>
          <year>1974</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>415</fpage>
          <lpage>421</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
