<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Genet Genomics</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol. Genet. Genomics</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Molecular Genetics and Genomics</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1617-4615</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1617-4623</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3664738</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">746</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00438-013-0746-8</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Paper</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Increased copy number at the <italic>HvFT1</italic> locus is associated with accelerated flowering time in barley</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nitcher</surname>
            <given-names>Rebecca</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Distelfeld</surname>
            <given-names>Assaf</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tan</surname>
            <given-names>ChorTee</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            <given-names>Liuling</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
            <given-names>Jorge</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+1-530-7525159</phone>
            <fax>+1-530-7524361</fax>
            <email>jdubcovsky@ucdavis.edu</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Plant Sciences, University of California, Davis, Davis, CA 95616 USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Molecular Biology and Ecology of Plants, Tel-Aviv University, 69978 Tel-Aviv, Israel </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label/>Department of Plant and Soil Sciences, Oklahoma State University, Stillwater, OK 74078 USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label/>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Chevy Chase, MD 20815 USA </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="com">
          <p>Communicated by S. Hohmann.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>288</volume>
      <issue>5-6</issue>
      <fpage>261</fpage>
      <lpage>275</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits any use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <p>A precise regulation of flowering time is critical for plant reproductive success, and therefore, a better understanding of the natural variation in genes regulating the initiation of the reproductive phase is required to develop well-adapted varieties. In both monocot and dicot species, the <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (<italic>FT</italic>) is a central integrator of seasonal signals perceived by the leaves. The encoded mobile protein (florigen) is transmitted to the apical meristem where it induces flowering. The <italic>FT</italic> homolog in barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L.), designated <italic>HvFT1,</italic> was shown to correspond to the vernalization locus <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H3,</italic> and natural alleles for spring and winter growth habit were identified. In this study, we demonstrate that the <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele present in the barley genetic stock (BGS213) associated with a dominant spring growth habit carries at least four identical copies of <italic>HvFT1</italic>, whereas most barley varieties have a single copy. Increased copy number is associated with earlier transcriptional up-regulation of <italic>HvFT1</italic> and a spring growth habit. This allele is epistatic to winter alleles for <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic>. Among accessions with one <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy, haplotype differences in the <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter and first intron are also associated with differences in flowering time, which are modulated by genetic background. These different <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles can be used to develop barley varieties adapted to different or changing environments. Our results, together with studies of other wheat and barley flowering genes, show that copy number variation plays an important role in the regulation of developmental processes in the temperate cereals.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Vernalization</kwd>
        <kwd>Barley</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Hordeum</italic>
          <italic>vulgare</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>Flowering</kwd>
        <kwd>FT</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2013</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Plant reproductive success is highly dependent on a precise targeting of flowering time to a narrow seasonal window that maximizes resources for the developing seeds. In cereal crops, the correct targeting of this optimal reproductive period is translated into increased grain yields. A clear understanding of the natural variation in the genes that regulate flowering time is important to develop varieties adapted to different or changing environments.</p>
      <p>In the temperate cereals, which include barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L.) and wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.), the initiation of the reproductive phase is regulated by the integration of two main seasonal signals: photoperiod (day-length) and vernalization (extended exposures to low temperatures). Based on the response to photoperiod, barley varieties are divided into photoperiod sensitive (accelerated flowering under long days) and insensitive (limited response of flowering time to long days) classes. Based on the response to vernalization, barley varieties are divided into winter (vernalization accelerates flowering) and spring (early flowering irrespective of vernalization) classes.</p>
      <p>Most of barley&#x2019;s natural variation in photoperiod response is associated with allelic differences in the photoperiod genes <italic>PPD</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>PPD</italic>-<italic>H2. PPD</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> encodes a pseudo-response regulator (PRR) protein that is part of the circadian clock (Turner et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2005</xref>) and promotes flowering under long days. Recessive mutations in the <italic>PPD</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> gene reduce expression of <italic>HvFT1</italic> and result in delayed flowering under long days (Hemming et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2008</xref>; Turner et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2005</xref>). The <italic>PPD</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> gene acts in conjunction with <italic>CO</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> (Campoli et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2012</xref>), which is one of the barley homologs of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> photoperiod gene <italic>CONSTANS</italic> (<italic>CO</italic>). In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, long days result in the stabilization of CO proteins, which up-regulate <italic>FT</italic> resulting in the acceleration of flowering (Corbesier and Coupland <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>). This function seems to be conserved in barley since overexpression of <italic>CO</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> results in the up-regulation of <italic>HvFT1</italic> and the acceleration of flowering (Campoli et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2012</xref>). The second photoperiod gene, <italic>PPD</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> (<italic>HvFT3</italic>) is a paralog of <italic>HvFT1,</italic> but its effect on flowering is not as strong as <italic>HvFT1</italic> (Kikuchi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2009</xref>). The induction of flowering by <italic>PPD</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> seems to be restricted to winter genotypes under non-inductive conditions (short days or long days without vernalization, Casao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2011</xref>).</p>
      <p>Natural variation in barley vernalization requirement is predominantly found in the vernalization loci <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic>, <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic>, and <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H3</italic> (Dubcovsky et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2005</xref>; Fu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2005</xref>; Takahashi and Yasuda <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1971</xref>; Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>). The <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> gene is closely related to the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> gene <italic>APETALA1,</italic> which encodes a MADS-box protein responsible for the transition of the shoot apical meristem (SAM) from the vegetative to the reproductive stage (Danyluk et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2003</xref>; Trevaskis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2003</xref>; Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2003</xref>). Deletions of regulatory regions in the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> first intron result in a dominant spring growth habit (Fu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2005</xref>; Hemming et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2009</xref>; von Zitzewitz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2005</xref>). The second vernalization locus, <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic>, includes three closely related genes characterized by a putative zinc finger and a CCT-domain, designated as <italic>ZCCT</italic> genes (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2004</xref>). These genes function as flowering repressors and deletions of all three copies result in spring growth habit independently of the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> alleles (Dubcovsky et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2005</xref>; Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2004</xref>). Finally, <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H3</italic> is a functional homolog of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowering promoting gene <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (<italic>FT</italic>) (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>) and will be referred hereafter as <italic>FT1</italic> (<italic>HvFT1</italic> in barley and <italic>TaFT1</italic> in wheat).</p>
      <p>In both monocot and dicot species, the signals from the vernalization and photoperiod pathways converge at the regulation of <italic>FT1</italic>, which is considered to be a central flowering integrator (Turck et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2008</xref>). When temperate cereals germinate during the fall, <italic>FT1</italic> is repressed by VRN2, which competes with the photoperiod protein CO for the regulation of <italic>FT1</italic> (Hemming et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2008</xref>; Trevaskis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2007</xref>; Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>, Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>). During the winter, vernalization up-regulates <italic>VRN1</italic> (Oliver et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2009</xref>), which results in the repression of <italic>VRN2</italic> in the leaves and the release of <italic>FT1</italic> transcription in the spring (Loukoianov et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2005</xref>; Trevaskis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2006</xref>; Hemming et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2008</xref>; Sasani et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2009</xref>; Chen and Dubcovsky <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2012</xref>).</p>
      <p>In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and rice, it has been demonstrated that <italic>FT</italic> encodes a mobile protein (florigen) that travels through the phloem and transmits signals perceived in the leaves to the SAM (Corbesier et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2007</xref>; Tamaki et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2007</xref>; Turck et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2008</xref>). Once FT arrives to the SAM it forms a complex with the bZIP transcription factor FD that physically interacts with the promoters of the meristem identity genes <italic>AP1 (Arabidopsis;</italic> Wigge et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2005</xref><italic>), VRN1</italic> (wheat; Li and Dubcovsky <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2008</xref>) or <italic>FUL2</italic> (rice; Tsuji et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2011</xref>), and up-regulates transcription to levels that induce the transition of the SAM to the reproductive stage. In rice, it has been shown that the FT-FD complex also includes 14-3-3 proteins (Taoka et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2011</xref>).</p>
      <p>In barley and wheat, there are other <italic>FT</italic>-like genes (Faure et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2007</xref>; Kikuchi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2009</xref>). However, <italic>FT1</italic> shows the most robust induction of flowering when transformed into rice and wheat (Kikuchi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2009</xref>; Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>) and is highly expressed under long days, which indicates that it is likely the key gene in the induction of flowering under long days.</p>
      <p>In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, the <italic>FT</italic> promoter and first intron have been shown to contain <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory sites that are important for the transcriptional regulation of this gene (Adrian et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2010</xref>; Helliwell et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2006</xref>; Schwartz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2009</xref>; Tiwari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2010</xref>). However, the <italic>FT1</italic> regulatory regions of barley and wheat are not as well characterized. Based on the few sequences available at the time of the cloning of <italic>HvFT1</italic>, Yan et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>) found an association between growth habit and intron haplotypes. However, the sequencing of <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles from populations previously used to map QTL for flowering time, such as Dicktoo&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Morex (Pan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1994</xref>) and Sloop x Halcyon (Read et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2003</xref>; Hemming et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2008</xref>) failed to reveal any significant association between the intron one haplotypes and flowering time. Inconsistent results were also observed in recent surveys of <italic>HvFT1</italic> allelic variation (Cuesta-Marcos et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2010</xref>; Casas et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>). In this study, we demonstrate that these inconsistencies were generated by previously unknown copy number variation at the <italic>HvFT1</italic> locus. We found that high <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number is associated with early flowering, and is epistatic to the <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> alleles for winter growth habit (independently of <italic>PPD</italic>-<italic>H1</italic>). Finally, once we separated the effects of copy number variation, we were able to better characterize the effect of haplotype variation in <italic>HvFT1</italic> regulatory regions on barley flowering time.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Plant materials</title>
        <p>Parental lines used in the different crosses were selected based on their <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles, including different combinations of promoter and first intron haplotypes. Their growth habits, vernalization and photoperiod alleles, and <italic>HvFT1</italic> haplotypes are indicated in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. All accessions except <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> Koch (OSU6, PBI004-7-0-015) belong to the sub-species <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp. <italic>vulgare</italic>. Hayakiso 2 and Iwate Mensury C (IMC) are commercial barley varieties from Japan and Igri is a variety from Germany, whereas E878 (Ethiopia) and U672 (Russia) are accessions received from the Okayama University barley collection (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp/barley/">http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp/barley/</ext-link>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Parental lines used in the different segregating populations</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="4">Line</th><th align="left" rowspan="4">Growth habit</th><th align="left" rowspan="4"><italic>PPD</italic>-<italic>H1</italic><sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="4"><italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic><sup>b</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="4"><italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic><sup><italic>c</italic></sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="4"><italic>HvFT1</italic> haploid copy number</th><th align="left" rowspan="4"><italic>HvFT1</italic> haplo. abbr.</th><th align="left" colspan="9">Promoter</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Intron 1</th></tr><tr><th align="left">5</th><th align="left">4</th><th align="left">4</th><th align="left">3</th><th align="left">2</th><th align="left">1</th><th align="left">1</th><th align="left">1</th><th align="left">1</th><th align="left">2</th><th align="left">3</th></tr><tr><th align="left">4</th><th align="left">9</th><th align="left">4</th><th align="left">9</th><th align="left">5</th><th align="left">6</th><th align="left">5</th><th align="left">4</th><th align="left">3</th><th align="left">7</th><th align="left">8</th></tr><tr><th align="left">8</th><th align="left">3</th><th align="left">1</th><th align="left">2</th><th align="left">3</th><th align="left">7</th><th align="left">0</th><th align="left">2</th><th align="left">7</th><th align="left">0</th><th align="left">4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">BGS213</td><td align="left">S</td><td align="left"><italic>ppd1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>vrn1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Vrn2</italic></td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub></td><td align="left">4GC</td><td align="left">G</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">i</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">G</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IMC</td><td align="left">S</td><td align="left"><italic>Ppd1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>vrn1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>vrn2</italic></td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub></td><td align="left">4GC</td><td align="left">G</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">i</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">G</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Morex</td><td align="left">S</td><td align="left"><italic>ppd1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Vrn1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>vrn2</italic></td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub></td><td align="left">4GC</td><td align="left">G</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">i</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">G</td></tr><tr><td align="left">E878</td><td align="left">S</td><td align="left"><italic>ppd1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Vrn1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Vrn2</italic></td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub></td><td align="left">4GC</td><td align="left">G</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">i</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">C</td></tr><tr><td align="left">U672</td><td align="left">S</td><td align="left"><italic>ppd1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Vrn1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Vrn2</italic></td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub></td><td align="left">4GC</td><td align="left">G</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">i</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">C</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hayakiso2</td><td align="left">W</td><td align="left"><italic>Ppd1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>vrn1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Vrn2</italic></td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub></td><td align="left">4GC</td><td align="left">G</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">i</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">C</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Igri</td><td align="left">W</td><td align="left"><italic>Ppd1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>vrn1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Vrn2</italic></td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub></td><td align="left">8GC</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">G</td><td align="left">G</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">d</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">G</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">C</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>H. v. spont.</italic></td><td align="left">W</td><td align="left"><italic>Ppd1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>vrn1</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Vrn2</italic></td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub></td><td align="left">8GC</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">G</td><td align="left">G</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">d</td><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">G</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">C</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Growth habit, alleles at different vernalization genes, and <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number and haplotypes at the promoter (P<sub>E</sub> and P<sub>L</sub>) and intron one regions (I<sub>AG</sub> and I<sub>TC</sub>) are described for each line. Positions of the polymorphisms are reported as bp upstream of the start codon (promoter) or downstream of the start of intron one (intron) in Igri (i&#xA0;=&#xA0;insertion, d&#xA0;=&#xA0;deletion)</p><p><sup>a</sup><italic>PPD</italic>-<italic>H1</italic>: the recessive <italic>ppd1</italic> allele is associated with photoperiod insensitivity and the dominant <italic>Ppd1</italic> allele with photoperiod sensitivity</p><p><sup>b</sup><italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic>: the recessive <italic>vrn1</italic> allele is associated with vernalization requirement (winter growth habit) and the dominant <italic>Vrn1</italic> allele is associated with the lack of vernalization requirement (spring growth habit)</p><p><sup>c</sup><italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic>: the dominant <italic>Vrn2</italic> allele is associated to vernalization requirement (winter growth habit) and the recessive <italic>vrn2</italic> allele is associated with the lack of vernalization requirement (spring growth habit)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>BGS213 is the designated genetic stock for the barley <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H3</italic> (=<italic>Sgh3</italic>) allele associated with a dominant spring growth habit (Franckowiak and Konishi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1997</xref>). BGS213 is a line derived from the cross Tammi&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Hayakiso 2 (GSHO 764) which has been selected for the dominant <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H3</italic> allele from Tammi (early flowering variety from Finland) and for recessive <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and dominant <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> alleles for winter growth habit (Takahashi and Yasuda <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1971</xref>). Two additional sets of spring <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H3</italic> isogenic lines were developed by backcrossing the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H3</italic> allele from Tammi into the winter varieties Hayakiso 2 and Dairokkaku 1 for eleven generations (Takahashi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1983</xref>), designated hereafter as Hayakiso 2-Tammi and Dairokkaku 1-Tammi.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Haplotypes</title>
        <p>Based on a limited number of barley lines, it was initially hypothesized that haplotype variation in <italic>HvFT1</italic> was associated to differences in flowering time (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>). To facilitate the description of the different haplotypes used in this study, we assigned names to each of the haplotypes found in the promoter and intron one regions. The promoter haplotype present in E878, U672, BGS213, Hayakiso 2, and IMC is referred hereafter to as P<sub>E</sub> (promoter-early) whereas the promoter haplotype in Igri and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> is referred to as P<sub>L</sub> (promoter-late). These two promoter haplotypes differ in nine linked SNPs and indels (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The two linked SNPs in the first intron are used to name the intron haplotypes as either I<sub>TC</sub> or I<sub>AG</sub>. Copy number variation is indicated separately in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Segregating populations and growing conditions</title>
        <p>A summary of the crosses and segregating populations included in this study is available in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. The two crosses between BGS213 and winter lines <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> and Igri were published before (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>) but are re-analyzed here in the light of the new copy number variation in <italic>HvFT1</italic> presented in this study. Two additional crosses include the varieties Morex (Morex&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic>) and IMC (IMC&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Hayakiso 2), which have identical <italic>HvFT1</italic> haplotypes as BGS213 but different copy number. A third cross was made between BGS213 and IMC to test the effect of <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number variation on flowering time in lines with identical promoter and intron one haplotypes.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Segregating populations</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Parental lines</th><th align="left">CNV</th><th align="left"><italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles</th><th align="left">Number of plants tested (selected alleles)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">BGS213&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp. <italic>spontaneum</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;1</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub></td><td align="left">72 (F<sub>2</sub>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BGS213&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Igri<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;1</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub></td><td align="left">96 (F<sub>2:3</sub>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BGS213&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;IMC</td><td align="left">4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;1</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub></td><td align="left">164 (F<sub>2</sub>, <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H2/</italic>&#x2212;<italic>, Ppd</italic>-<italic>H1/</italic>&#x2212;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Morex&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp. <italic>spontaneum</italic></td><td align="left">1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;1</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub></td><td align="left">81 (F<sub>2</sub>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IMC&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Hayakiso 2</td><td align="left">1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;1</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub></td><td align="left">70 (F<sub>2</sub>, <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H2/</italic>&#x2212;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">E878&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp. <italic>spontaneum</italic></td><td align="left">1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;1</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub></td><td align="left">47 (F<sub>3</sub>, <italic>Ppd</italic>-<italic>H1</italic>)<break/>89 (F<sub>3</sub>, <italic>ppd</italic>-<italic>H1</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">U672&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp. <italic>spontaneum</italic></td><td align="left">1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;1</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub></td><td align="left">42 (F<sub>2</sub>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hayakiso 2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp. <italic>spontaneum</italic></td><td align="left">1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;1</td><td align="left">P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub></td><td align="left">125 (F<sub>2</sub>)&#xA0;+&#xA0;134 (F<sub>2</sub>)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Crosses made to study the effect of different combinations of <italic>HvFT1</italic> haplotypes and copy number variation (CNV) on heading time</p><p><sup>a</sup>Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Finally, the effect of the different <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter haplotypes in varieties with identical <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number was tested in two F<sub>2</sub> segregating spring x winter populations from crosses E878&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> and U672&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> and in one winter x winter population from the cross Hayakiso 2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum.</italic> The effect of the different intron one haplotypes was only explored in the IMC&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Hayakiso 2 segregating population.</p>
        <p>All populations were produced and grown in greenhouse under long day (LD) photoperiod (15&#x2013;16&#xA0;h&#xA0;day length) generated by extending natural light conditions with supplementary lights as needed. Temperatures were held at non-vernalizing conditions (21&#x2013;25&#xA0;&#xB0;C during the day and 12&#x2013;18&#xA0;&#xB0;C during the night).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Markers</title>
        <p>The <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> alleles were identified using the <italic>UCW132</italic> marker (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), which detects a small indel near the end of the first intron that is linked to the larger functional deletion in the same intron. The two recessive <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> alleles in the Hayakiso 2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> population were characterized using HvV1PromF2 and HvV1PromR2 primers that detect a promoter indel (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). <italic>PPD</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> alleles were identified using a Cleaved Amplified Polymorphic Sequence (CAPS) marker digested with restriction enzyme <italic>Bst</italic>UI (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>; Turner et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2005</xref>). <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> was genotyped using primers VRN-H2aF and VRN-H2aR (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), or when a codominant marker was necessary, with a marker for the tightly linked <italic>SNF2</italic> gene (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The <italic>HvFT1</italic> marker based on a 4-bp indel in the promoter was used for genotyping the populations segregating for the <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter haplotypes (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>; Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>), whereas the <italic>UCW133</italic> marker was used to differentiate the intron haplotypes (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Primer names, sequence, amplification temperatures, and amplification efficiencies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="6">Genotyping</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Gene</th><th align="left">Primer name</th><th align="left">Forward primer</th><th align="left">Reverse primer</th><th align="left">A.T.</th><th align="left">Enzyme</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic></td><td align="left">UCW132_F/R</td><td align="left">TGTTTTGCAAACTATTTGACCAG</td><td align="left">TAGCGCTCATACCGTTCAAG</td><td align="left">59&#xB0;</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic></td><td align="left">HvV1PromF2/R2</td><td align="left">ACTTCACCCAACCACCTGAC</td><td align="left">CTGGCGGTTGATCTTGTTCT</td><td align="left">55&#xB0;</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H2</italic></td><td align="left">VRN-H2a_F/R</td><td align="left">CATGAAACAGCAGCTCCAGA</td><td align="left">TTTGCCTCTCTCTCCTGCAT</td><td align="left">59&#xB0;</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>SNF2</italic></td><td align="left">SNF_F/R</td><td align="left">TTGGTACTTGAATGCCTGAAAA</td><td align="left">ATGGCACAACTTGGATTTGA</td><td align="left">60&#xB0;</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Ppd</italic>-<italic>H1</italic></td><td align="left">PPD/H1/F/R</td><td align="left">CTGAGCCTGAAGAGGTCGAG</td><td align="left">GTGGCGGGAGGTTATCTCT</td><td align="left">57&#xB0;</td><td align="left"><italic>Bst</italic>UI</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>HvFT1</italic> Prom.</td><td align="left">HvFT1F/R1</td><td align="left">ATGGACATGGAACCTGCCACT</td><td align="left">TGGTGATGATGAGTGTTGCCC</td><td align="left">55&#xB0;</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>HvFT1</italic> Intron</td><td align="left">UCW133_F/R</td><td align="left">TGCACACACTTAGCGCAGTA</td><td align="left">GCAGACCGTGGAACTCAACT</td><td align="left">55&#xB0;</td><td align="left"><italic>RsaI</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">EBmac603</td><td align="left">EBmac603F/R</td><td align="left">ACCGAAACTAAATGAACTACTTCG</td><td align="left">TGCAAACTGTGCTATTAAGGG</td><td align="left">56&#xB0;</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bmag914</td><td align="left">Bmag914F/R</td><td align="left">GGGCAATATACAGTTCAACTC</td><td align="left">ATGAACTGGAGGCAGTAAATA</td><td align="left">57&#xB0;</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="5">qRT-PCR<sup>a</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left">Gene</th><th align="left">Primer name</th><th align="left">Forward primer</th><th align="left">Reverse primer</th><th align="left">Efficiency %</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>UCW118</italic></td><td align="left">CNV_UCW118_F1/R1</td><td align="left">CAGTAAGGCGAACCATGTCATC</td><td align="left">TGCGCACCAACACAGAACA</td><td align="left">99.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>FT1</italic>_Prom.</td><td align="left">CNV_FT1p_F2/R2</td><td align="left">CGGCCGAGTCTGTGTGATCT</td><td align="left">GGCATAAATCCCGCCTCTTT</td><td align="left">99.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>FT1</italic>_ATG</td><td align="left">CNV_FT1p_F5/R4</td><td align="left">TGTTCTAAGAAGGAAGGAGAAATGG</td><td align="left">GAAGGTCACCCTGAGGTTGGT</td><td align="left">99.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>FT1</italic>_Ex1</td><td align="left">CNV_FT1_F2/R2</td><td align="left">CGTACGTACACAATCACCACTATCTAATG</td><td align="left">GAGAGCCCGATCGTGCAT</td><td align="left">99.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>FT1</italic>_Ex3</td><td align="left">CNV_FT1_F4/R3</td><td align="left">GCAGGTTGGTGACAGATATCCC</td><td align="left">GGAAGAGCACGAGCACGAA</td><td align="left">89.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>UCW123</italic></td><td align="left">CNV_UCW123_F1/R1</td><td align="left">ACTGCAAGAGCTACAGCCTTCA</td><td align="left">GTCACCGGCAGCAAGATCTAG</td><td align="left">99.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>UCW120</italic></td><td align="left">CNV_UCW120_F1/R1</td><td align="left">GCGACGACCAGTAAAAAATGC</td><td align="left">CCGTTTCCGTGGATGGAA</td><td align="left">99.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>SNF2</italic></td><td align="left">CNV_SNF2_F1/R1</td><td align="left">ATTACCGCTCTGCTGTCGCGATTA</td><td align="left">AAATGTGGCTCTGAAGGTGTTGGC</td><td align="left">93.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup><bold>a</bold></sup>PCR program:(95&#xB0; 20&#xA0;s)&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;one cycle, (95&#xB0; 3&#xA0;s, 60&#xB0; 30&#xA0;s)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;40 cycles</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Determination of copy number variation (CNV) by quantitative PCR</title>
        <p>Genomic DNA was extracted using the CTAB (cetyltrimethylammonium bromide) extraction method (Murray and Thompson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1980</xref>). Samples were treated with RNAse A, and a phenol:chloroform:isoamyl alcohol purification step was used to remove possible RNA contamination, which might interfere with normalization. DNA concentration was normalized using a Nanodrop instrument (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA) to a concentration of 20&#xA0;ng/&#x3BC;l, and 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;l was used for each 20&#xA0;&#x3BC;l Fast Sybr<sup>&#xAE;</sup>Green reaction. These reactions were performed on an AB7500 Fast Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems by Life Technologies, Grand Island, New York), using identical programs for all primer pairs ((95&#xB0; 20&#xA0;s)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;one cycle, (95&#xB0; 3&#xA0;s, 60&#xB0; 30&#xA0;s)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;40 cycles). The parental lines were tested with various pairs of primers in the <italic>HvFT1</italic> region (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), and a pair of primers in the <italic>SNF2</italic> control gene, which has been shown before to have a single copy in the barley genome (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2002</xref>). The 2<sup>&#x2212;&#x394;&#x394;C&#x442;</sup> method was used to estimate copy number (Weaver et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2010</xref>), with Morex as a calibrator and C<sub>T</sub>&#xA0;=&#xA0;threshold cycle. We first calculated &#x394;Morex&#xA0;=&#xA0;Morex&#x2013;<italic>HvFT1</italic> C<sub>T</sub>&#x2212;Morex&#x2013;<italic>SNF2</italic> C<sub>T</sub> and &#x394;Target&#xA0;=&#xA0;Target&#x2013;<italic>HvFT1</italic> C<sub>T</sub>&#x2212;Target&#x2013;<italic>SNF2</italic> C<sub>T</sub>, and then calculated the difference between the two as &#x2212;&#x394;&#x394;C<sub>T</sub>&#xA0;=&#xA0;&#x394;Morex&#x2212;&#x394;Target. Previous sequencing of Bacterial Artificial Chromosomes (BACs) containing <italic>HvFT1</italic> has shown that only one copy of this gene is present in Morex, making it a good calibrator variety (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>). Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> describes the primers used for quantitative PCR and their efficiency.</p>
        <p>The first <italic>HvFT1</italic> primer pair (CNV_FT1_F2 and CNV_FT1_R2) was designed on the border between the first exon and the first intron. This region was selected because it includes several SNPs that differentiate <italic>HvFT1</italic> from other members of the <italic>FT</italic> family. Copy number in the recombinant BGS213&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;IMC F<sub>2</sub> lines was determined using these primers.</p>
        <p>To determine the borders of the duplication in the BGS213 lines, additional primers were designed inside and flanking the <italic>HvFT1</italic> gene. In the <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter region, a set of primers was designed 656&#x2013;727&#xA0;bp upstream of the start codon (CNV_FT1p_F2 and CNV_FT1p_R2). Another set of primers amplified a region from a 22-bp upstream to 97-bp downstream of the start codon (CNV_FT1p_F5 and CNV_FT1p_R4). Within the gene, an additional set of primers was designed at exon three to determine if the complete gene was duplicated (CNV_FT1_F4 and CNV_FT1_R3, 778-902&#xA0;bp downstream from the start codon). Markers were also designed outside the <italic>HvFT1</italic> gene. One pair of primers was designed for gene <italic>UCW123</italic>, located 6.6&#xA0;kb downstream from <italic>HvFT1</italic> on Morex BAC clone 440G4 (GenBank DQ900686, CNV_UCW123_F1 and CNV_UCW123_R1). The nearest known genes on flanking BACs 455J22 (GenBank DQ900687) and 761F04 (GenBank DQ900685, Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>) were also tested, including <italic>UCW120</italic> (CNV_UCW120_F1 and CNV_UCW120_R1) and <italic>UCW118</italic> (CNV_UCW118_F1 and CNV_UCW118_R1).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title><italic>HvFT1</italic> expression profiles</title>
        <p>To test the effect of the dosage of the duplicated <italic>HvFT1</italic> locus, the isogenic lines of Hayakiso 2 with and without the Tammi <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele were intercrossed and the F<sub>2</sub> lines were genotyped for <italic>HvFT1</italic> and then tested for <italic>HvFT1</italic> expression by quantitative RT-PCR (qRT-PCR) with Fast Sybr<sup>&#xAE;</sup>Green Master Mix on the AB7500 Fast Real-Time PCR System (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>). <italic>ACTIN</italic> was used as an endogenous expression control (Trevaskis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2006</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec9" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title>Variation in flowering time among lines with identical <italic>HvFT1</italic> haplotypes</title>
        <p>The <italic>HvFT1</italic> sequences from Morex, IMC, and BGS213 are identical (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). However, segregating populations including the first two varieties (Morex&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> and IMC&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Hayakiso 2) showed that plants with winter alleles for the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> genes flowered very late independently of <italic>HvFT1</italic>. This observation was inconsistent with the results from Yan et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>), which have previously shown that the <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele from BGS213 was sufficient to confer a spring growth habit when introgressed into winter barley varieties. To test if additional polymorphism were present among these three <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles, we sequenced a 9,250-bp region starting 1,499-bp upstream of the start codon and ending 6,690-bp downstream of the stop codon. No polymorphisms were detected in the <italic>HvFT1</italic> coding and flanking sequences of Morex, IMC, and BGS213. The segregating populations including these varieties are described in detail below.</p>
        <sec id="Sec11">
          <title>Morex (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub>)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> (P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>)</title>
          <p>This population of 81 F<sub>2</sub> plants segregated for the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1, VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic>, and <italic>HvFT1</italic> loci. To study the effect of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles in a winter background, we first selected plants homozygous for <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and homozygous or heterozygous for the <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> alleles for winter growth habit. The 11 selected plants carrying these alleles flowered relatively late (91&#x2013;106&#xA0;days after sowing) and showed no significant differences between the different <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.32), even when the 11 plants were divided in photoperiod sensitive and photoperiod insensitive groups.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec12">
          <title>IMC (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub>)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Hayakiso 2 (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>)</title>
          <p>A similar result was observed in a population of 92 F<sub>2</sub> lines from the cross between the photoperiod sensitive varieties IMC and Hayakiso 2. IMC is a spring barley variety that carries an <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele with identical sequence to the BGS213 allele and a <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> allele for spring growth habit, whereas Hayakiso 2 is a winter variety (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In the F<sub>2</sub> segregating population, 22 plants homozygous for the IMC <italic>vrn2</italic> allele were identified using the tightly linked <italic>SNF2</italic> molecular marker and were discarded. The remaining 70 plants, carrying <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> alleles for winter growth habit, flowered relatively late (100&#x2013;250&#xA0;days, average 167&#xA0;days) and showed no significant differences between the different <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&gt;&#xA0;0.05). Plants homozygous for the functional <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> allele flowered 29&#xA0;days later than the plants carrying the heterozygous allele (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.02) suggesting some dosage effect of <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2.</italic> No significant interaction was detected between <italic>HvFT1</italic> and <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.74).</p>
          <p>The results from the IMC&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Hayakiso 2 and Morex&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> populations suggest that, in spite of their identical sequence, the <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles present in Morex and IMC have a smaller effect on inducing flowering than the <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele present in BGS213. To test this hypothesis, we developed a third population segregating for the <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles of BGS213 and IMC, which have identical sequence and contrasting phenotypes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec13">
          <title>BGS213 (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub>)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;IMC (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub>)</title>
          <p>Since no polymorphisms were found between the two parental lines in <italic>HvFT1</italic> or in the genes tightly linked to <italic>HvFT1</italic> (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>), we screened linked SSR markers and found <italic>Bmag914</italic> and <italic>EBmac0603</italic> (GrainGenes database, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/">http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/</ext-link>) to be polymorphic between BGS213 and IMC. These two markers flanking the <italic>HvFT1</italic> locus were located approximately 14&#xA0;cM apart in this mapping population.</p>
          <p>The complete segregating population was genotyped with the <italic>HvFT1</italic> flanking SSR markers and with markers for <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> and <italic>PPD</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> genes. To focus on the effect of <italic>HvFT1</italic>, plants homozygous for the <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> allele for spring growth habit or for the photoperiod insensitive allele (<italic>ppd</italic>-<italic>H1</italic>) were eliminated. The remaining 167 F<sub>2</sub> lines showed a highly significant (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001) effect on flowering associated with the SSR markers flanking the <italic>HvFT1</italic> locus. The <italic>HvFT1</italic> locus alone explained 96&#xA0;% of the variation in flowering time among the selected 167 plants, indicating that no other major flowering gene was segregating in this selected sub-population.</p>
          <p>Plants heterozygous or homozygous for the BGS213 <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele showed a spring growth habit (33&#xA0;days to 76&#xA0;days from sowing to heading time) whereas plants homozygous for the IMC SSR markers flanking the <italic>HvFT1</italic> locus showed no signs of flowering 125&#xA0;days after planting, when the experiment was terminated. This population showed a clear 3:1 ratio between spring and winter plants (122 spring/45 winter, <italic>&#x3C7;</italic><sup>2</sup><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.56). In summary, these results confirmed that the largest differences in flowering time in this segregating population were linked to the <italic>HvFT1</italic> region in spite of the identical <italic>HvFT1</italic> sequences between BGS213 and IMC.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec14">
        <title>Variation in <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number</title>
        <p>Possible explanations for the previously described differences in flowering time include an unknown gene tightly linked to <italic>HvFT1</italic>, a regulatory sequence beyond the <italic>HvFT1</italic> sequenced region or copy number variation (CNV) in <italic>HvFT1</italic>. To test the last hypothesis, we determined the number of <italic>HvFT1</italic> copies in BGS213, IMC, Morex, and other accessions used as parental lines in different segregating populations.</p>
        <p>DNAs were extracted from approximately 10 plants from each variety, and <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number was determined by quantitative PCR for the exon one region (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>) using the single copy gene <italic>SNF2</italic> as an internal reference and Morex as a calibrator (see Materials and Methods). The results indicated that BGS213 has four to five copies of <italic>HvFT1</italic> whereas IMC has a single copy (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The increase of <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number found in the BGS213 allele was confirmed in the two backcross substitution lines of the Tammi <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele into the winter varieties Hayakiso 2 and Dairokkaku 1, which also showed four to five copies of <italic>HvFT1</italic> each. All other varieties tested in this experiment (E878, <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic>, Hayakiso 2, Golden Promise, Igri, U672 and Morex) showed only one copy of <italic>HvFT1.</italic><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p><italic>HvFT1</italic> haploid copy number is increased in BGS213. Copy number was determined using the 2<sup>&#x2212;&#x394;&#x394;CT</sup> method (Weaver et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2010</xref>) and primers for the first exon (FT1_Ex1, Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The single copy gene <italic>SNF2</italic> was used as internal control and the variety Morex as calibrator (see &#x201C;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>&#x201D;). Averages and standard errors of the means are based on 7&#x2013;10 biological independent DNA extractions</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="438_2013_746_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
        <p>To test if the multiple <italic>HvFT1</italic> copies were linked, we estimated <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number with the same exon one primers in 45 BGS213 x IMC F<sub>2</sub> lines selected for recombination between the <italic>HvFT1</italic> flanking markers <italic>Bmag914</italic> and <italic>EBmac0603.</italic> The lines that flowered earlier (30&#x2013;39&#xA0;days) showed the highest average copy number (~5 copies), whereas the lines that flowered later (&gt;110&#xA0;days) showed an average of one <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy. Plants with intermediate flowering times are likely heterozygous since they showed an intermediate copy number (~3 copies). These results confirmed that <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number co-segregates with flowering time (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), and that the different <italic>HvFT1</italic> copies are linked.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Co-segregation of <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number and heading time in 45 F<sub>2</sub> lines from the BGS213&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;IMC population selected for recombination between SSR markers flanking the <italic>HvFT1</italic> gene. Late flowering lines showed a single <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy, lines with intermediate flowering showed on average&#xA0;~3 copies, and early flowering lines showed an average of&#xA0;~5 copies. Haploid copy number was determined as described in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="438_2013_746_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
        <p>We performed an additional experiment to determine the extension of the duplicated region. Primer pairs within loci <italic>UCW118</italic> and <italic>UCW120</italic> located in Morex&#x2019;s <italic>HvFT1</italic> flanking BACs 455J22 and 761F04 (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>), showed no evidence of duplication in BGS213 (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). These results indicated that the duplication of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> region did not include the adjacent BACs. Therefore, we designed additional primers within the Morex BAC 440G04, which includes the <italic>HvFT1</italic> gene. The primer set for the <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter region located 655&#x2013;700&#xA0;bp upstream of the ATG start site showed no increase in copy number (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Since the start codon region shows four to five copies, the duplicated region must start within the 600-bp region of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter upstream of the start codon. The primers for the third exon of <italic>HvFT1</italic> and for the <italic>UCW123</italic> marker located 6.6-kb downstream from <italic>HvFT1</italic> showed that the duplicated region extended beyond the coding region of <italic>HvFT1</italic> and into this marker (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Extension of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> duplicated region in BGS213. Primers in the flanking BACs (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>) and the <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter (<italic>FT1</italic>-PMTR, 655&#x2013;700&#xA0;bp upstream of start codon) showed no evidence of duplication. Primers flanking the start codon (<italic>FT1</italic>-ATG), in the first exon (<italic>FT1</italic>-ex1), in the third exon (<italic>FT1</italic>-ex3) and in the <italic>UCW123</italic> marker 6.6-kb downstream of the stop codon showed evidence of duplication. Averages and standard errors of the means are based on 7&#x2013;10 independent DNA extractions</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="438_2013_746_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec15">
        <title>Differences in <italic>HvFT1</italic> expression in alleles with different copy number</title>
        <p>To study the relationship between <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number variation and expression, we crossed Hayakiso 2 with its near isogenic line containing the Tammi allele (Hayakiso 2-Tammi), selected eight plants homozygous for each of the parental alleles and eight heterozygous plants from the segregating F<sub>2</sub> population, and characterized <italic>HvFT1</italic> expression profiles in the leaves by qRT-PCR.</p>
        <p>Hayakiso 2-Tammi lines showed earlier expression of <italic>HvFT1</italic>, with significantly higher transcript levels of <italic>HvFT1</italic> expression than the two other genotypes just 2&#xA0;weeks after planting (three leaf stage; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.002). Plants homozygous for the Tammi <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele flowered around seven to 8&#xA0;weeks, after which <italic>HvFT1</italic> transcripts fell back to lower levels. The heterozygous plants showed an increase of <italic>HvFT1</italic> transcript levels at the last time point of the experiment (11&#xA0;weeks), when approximately one-third of the plants had already headed. At this same time point, plants homozygous for the <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles from Hayakiso 2 showed no detectable levels of <italic>HvFT1</italic> and no signs of flowering induction (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). These results show that the transcript levels of <italic>HvFT1</italic> are affected by copy number, with larger copy number resulting in earlier <italic>HvFT1</italic> expression and early flowering.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p><italic>HvFT1</italic> expression profiles correlate with copy number in a segregating population from the cross between isogenic lines Hayakiso 2 and Hayakiso 2-Tammi. Plants homozygous for the Tammi allele (<italic>black solid line</italic> with <italic>black diamonds</italic>) showed earlier induction of <italic>HvFT1</italic> than those homozygous for Hayakiso 2 allele (<italic>dashed black line</italic> with <italic>triangles</italic>). In the heterozygotes plants (<italic>dotted black line</italic> with <italic>squares</italic>) <italic>HvFT1</italic> transcript levels started to be induced by the end of this time course experiment. <italic>Bars</italic> are plus-minus one standard error of the means</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="438_2013_746_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec16">
        <title>Association between differences in <italic>HvFT1</italic> haplotypes and heading time</title>
        <p>Since <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number differences have such a large effect on flowering time, the effect of the different <italic>HvFT1</italic> haplotypes needs to be tested using varieties with the same copy number.</p>
        <p>Only one population was available to study the effect of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> first intron haplotypes in lines with a single <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy and identical <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter haplotypes (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p>
        <sec id="Sec17">
          <title>IMC (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>AG</sub>)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Hayakiso 2 (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>)</title>
          <p>Both IMC and Hayakiso 2 are photoperiod sensitive, and carry a single copy of <italic>HvFT1</italic> with the same promoter haplotype, but they differ in their first intron haplotypes (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Plants homozygous for the I<sub>AG</sub> allele flowered on average 10 and 13&#xA0;days later than the plants heterozygous and homozygous for the I<sub>TC</sub> allele, respectively. However, these differences were not significant (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.19 within the <italic>VRN2</italic> heterozygous class) likely due to the large variability of late flowering plants (100&#x2013;250&#xA0;days) that resulted in a reduced statistical power. The late flowering observed in all plants indicates that none of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles segregating in this population was epistatic to the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> alleles for winter growth habit.</p>
          <p>Three additional populations were used to study the effect of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter haplotypes in lines with a single <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) and identical <italic>HvFT1</italic> intron one haplotypes (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec18">
          <title>E878 (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp. <italic>spontaneum</italic> (P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>)</title>
          <p>This F<sub>2</sub> population segregated for <italic>HvFT1, VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>PPD</italic>-<italic>H1</italic>. To simplify the analysis, two separate F<sub>3</sub> segregating populations were derived in which the photoperiod sensitive (<italic>Ppd</italic>-<italic>H1</italic>) and photoperiod insensitive (<italic>ppd</italic>-<italic>H1</italic>) alleles were fixed. The ANOVA models including the <italic>VRN1</italic> and <italic>HvFT1</italic> loci, and their interactions explained 92 and 94&#xA0;% of the variation in heading time in the photoperiod sensitive and insensitive subpopulations, respectively, which indicates that these two genes account for most of the variation in heading time in these two sub-populations. Both sub-populations showed highly significant interactions between the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>HvFT1</italic> loci (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001) and therefore, the effects of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles on heading time are described separately for the recessive and dominant (homozygous plus heterozygous) <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> classes.</p>
          <p>The statistical analysis of the photoperiod sensitive F<sub>3</sub> family (47 plants, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a) showed significant effects of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles within both the dominant <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> class (9.5&#xA0;days, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.0031) and the recessive <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> class (39&#xA0;days, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001). Here, the differences in heading time were approximately fourfold larger within the recessive <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> class than within the dominant <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> class. The <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele from E878 was associated in both cases with early flowering.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#xA0;5</label><caption><p><italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles show significant interaction in E878 (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>) x <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp. <italic>spontaneum</italic> (P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>) populations segregating for the <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter haplotypes. <bold>a</bold> Photoperiod sensitive F<sub>3</sub> family, <bold>b</bold> photoperiod insensitive F<sub>3</sub> family. The lack of parallelism between <italic>lines</italic> reflects the significant interaction between <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles (larger effect of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles within the <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> class than within the <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> class). <italic>Bars</italic> are plus-minus one standard error of the means</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="438_2013_746_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
          <p>The plants from the photoperiod insensitive F<sub>3</sub> family (89 plants, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b) flowered on average 20&#xA0;days later than the photoperiod sensitive F<sub>3</sub> family (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). As in the photoperiod sensitive plants, the effect of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter haplotypes was larger among the plants homozygous for the recessive <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> allele (48.5&#xA0;days, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001) than among those homozygous or heterozygous for the dominant <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> allele (5.5&#xA0;days, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.0002). As in the previous family, the <italic>HvFT1</italic> P<sub>E</sub> haplotype from E878 was associated with early flowering.</p>
          <p>The reciprocal epistatic effect was observed when the effect of the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> alleles was studied within each of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> classes. No significant differences in heading time were detected between <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> alleles among the plants homozygous for the <italic>HvFT1</italic> P<sub>E</sub> promoter allele, but large differences were observed among the plants homozygous for the <italic>HvFT1</italic> P<sub>L</sub> promoter allele, both in the photoperiod sensitive (30&#xA0;days, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001) and the photoperiod insensitive sub-populations (43.6&#xA0;days, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec19">
          <title>U672 (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp. <italic>spontaneum</italic> (P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>)</title>
          <p>Similar results were observed in an additional small F<sub>2</sub> population (42 plants) segregating for the promoter haplotypes. In this population, the effect of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles was also larger within the plants homozygous for the <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> allele for winter growth habit (17&#xA0;days difference, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.008) than among the plants including a dominant <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> allele in homozygous or heterozygous state (6&#xA0;days difference, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.10). In both classes, the P<sub>E</sub> allele was associated with early flowering.</p>
          <p>In both E878 and U672 populations, the <italic>HvFT1</italic> P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub> haplotype was associated with early flowering and was epistatic to the winter <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> alleles. However, the same P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub> haplotype is also present in the variety Hayakiso 2 (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), which has a winter growth habit. To test if this effect was caused by unlinked epistatic genes in Hayakiso 2 or by a specific characteristic of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> region in Hayakiso 2, we crossed this variety with <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> to generate a third population segregating for the <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter haplotype. These two varieties are photoperiod sensitive and have a winter growth habit.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec20">
          <title>Hayakiso 2 (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> (P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>)</title>
          <p>This population was characterized in two separate experiments performed in California (125 F<sub>2</sub>) and Oklahoma (134 F<sub>2</sub>). The effect of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles was consistent across experiments (no significant experiment&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>HvFT1</italic> interaction), so the results from the two experiments were analyzed in a single factorial ANOVA including experiment, <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>HvFT1</italic> as factors. This analysis showed significant differences in heading time between the two recessive <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> alleles (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001) and also between the <italic>HvFT1</italic> P<sub>E</sub> and P<sub>L</sub> alleles (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001), but no significant interaction between the two loci (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.36). On average, F<sub>2</sub> plants carrying the <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> allele from <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> (average 106&#xA0;days after sowing) flowered 31&#xA0;days earlier than those carrying the corresponding allele from Hayakiso 2 (135&#xA0;days after sowing, Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). These results indicated that even though both varieties have recessive <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> alleles for winter growth habit, the <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> region from Hayakiso 2 is associated with a stronger vernalization requirement than the one from <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum.</italic> The earlier <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> allele was dominant, since the difference in heading time between plants heterozygous and homozygous for the <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum VRN1</italic> allele was less than 1&#xA0;day (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Surprisingly, plants carrying the <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele from Hayakiso 2 (P<sub>E</sub> promoter) were on average 10&#xA0;days later than the heterozygous plants and 14&#xA0;days later than the plants homozygous for the <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele from <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> (P<sub>L</sub> promoter), and the differences were highly significant (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001, Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Hayakiso 2 (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp. <italic>spontaneum</italic> (P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>): average heading time plus-minus standard error of the means</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"><italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> allele<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>HvFT1</italic> allele</th><th align="left">Heading time (days)</th><th align="left">&#xB1;SEM</th><th align="left">Tukey</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>H. v. spontaneum</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>H. v. spontaneum</italic></td><td char="." align="char">97.9</td><td char="." align="char">4.1</td><td align="left">a</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>H. v. spontaneum</italic></td><td align="left">Heterozygous</td><td char="." align="char">103.5</td><td char="." align="char">3.7</td><td align="left">ab</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>H. v. spontaneum</italic></td><td align="left">Hayakiso 2</td><td char="." align="char">115.3</td><td char="." align="char">4.3</td><td align="left">b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Avg. <italic>H. v. spontaneum vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">105.6</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heterozygous</td><td align="left"><italic>H. v. spontaneum</italic></td><td char="." align="char">98.1</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td><td align="left">a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heterozygous</td><td align="left">Heterozygous</td><td char="." align="char">106.9</td><td char="." align="char">2.5</td><td align="left">ab</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heterozygous</td><td align="left">Hayakiso 2</td><td char="." align="char">109.5</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td><td align="left">b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Avg. heterozygous <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic></td><td align="left">104.8</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hayakiso 2</td><td align="left"><italic>H. v. spontaneum</italic></td><td char="." align="char">124.7</td><td char="." align="char">3.7</td><td align="left">a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hayakiso 2</td><td align="left">Heterozygous</td><td char="." align="char">140.9</td><td char="." align="char">3.8</td><td align="left">b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hayakiso 2</td><td align="left">Hayakiso 2</td><td char="." align="char">137.9</td><td char="." align="char">3.4</td><td align="left">b</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Avg. Hayakiso 2 <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic></td><td align="left">134.5</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">b</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Different letters in the last column indicate significant differences between the mean values using the Tukey test (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.05)</p><p><sup>a</sup>Both <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> alleles in this population are recessive <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec21" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="Sec22">
        <title><italic>HvFT1</italic> increases in copy number are associated with a spring growth habit</title>
        <p>Previous studies demonstrated that the BGS213 <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele is sufficient to confer spring growth habit and therefore that it is epistatic to the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> alleles for winter growth habit (Takahashi and Yasuda <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1971</xref>; Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>). In the two F<sub>2</sub> populations reported by Yan et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>) (BGS213&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> and BGS213&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Igri), plants heterozygous or homozygous for the BGS213 <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele had a spring growth habit (average heading time 40 and 59&#xA0;days, respectively) and the plants homozygous for the <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> or Igri alleles showed very late flowering or failed to flower (average heading time 106 and&#xA0;&gt;130&#xA0;days, respectively; Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>). In addition, the introgression of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> early flowering allele from Tammi into the winter-photoperiod sensitive varieties Hayakiso 2 and Dairokkaku 1 also resulted in spring growth habit (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>). Results from the BGS213&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;IMC population in this study confirmed the previous results. Taken together, these experiments indicated that the epistatic effect of the BGS213 <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele on the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> alleles for winter growth habit is effective across multiple genotypes.</p>
        <p>Although the sequences of the coding and flanking regions of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles from barley varieties Morex, IMC, and BGS213 were identical, only the BGS213 allele was sufficient to induce early flowering in the presence of <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> alleles for winter growth habit. These differences motivated the study of <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number in these varieties and led to the discovery of the increased <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number in BGS213. Surprisingly, the BGS213 allele included 4&#x2013;5 copies of <italic>HvFT1</italic>, which was confirmed in the two backcross introgression lines Hayakiso 2-Tammi and Dairokkaku 1-Tammi (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). No <italic>HvFT1</italic> duplications were observed among the other eight varieties characterized for <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number in this study. This observation, together with the lack of sequence differences among the 4&#x2013;5 <italic>HvFT1</italic> copies present in the BGS213 allele, suggest that this duplication is of recent origin.</p>
        <p>The <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele for spring growth habit found in BGS213 comes from the spring variety Tammi (Olli/Asplund, both spring), which was released in Finland prior to 1950 (received by the National Small Grain Collection in 1949 as PI 175505). This variety can be found in the pedigrees of barley varieties from Finland, Sweden, Canada, and Alaska, where the short growing seasons require varieties with very early flowering and short life cycles.</p>
        <p>Additional <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles dominant for spring growth habit have been reported in barley accessions from North Pakistan, North India, Tibet, and Ethiopia in the germplasm collection at Okayama University (Takahashi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1983</xref>). Here, we confirmed the presence of dominant spring <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles in one accession from Ethiopia (E878) and another one from Russia (U672), and showed that these two alleles were not associated with differences in <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number (both alleles showed the P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub> haplotype combination).</p>
        <p>With the identification in this study of CNV at the <italic>HvFT1</italic> locus, all four major flowering genes in the <italic>Triticeae</italic> have been reported to have some level of CNV. Two to four copies of the <italic>Photoperiod</italic>-<italic>B1</italic> gene were identified on wheat chromosome 2B and two to three copies of the vernalization gene <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>A1</italic> were detected recently on wheat chromosome 5A (D&#xED;az et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2012</xref>). We reported before the presence of CNV of the <italic>ZCCT</italic> genes in both wheat and barley (Dubcovsky et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2005</xref>; Distelfeld et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2009</xref>). Other important agronomic genes in the <italic>Triticeae</italic> also show CNV, including a tandem segmental duplication of the wheat dwarfing gene <italic>Rht</italic>-<italic>D1</italic> (Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2012</xref>), and duplications of the frost tolerance <italic>CBF</italic> transcription factors in barley and wheat (Knox et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2010</xref>). The rapid increase in CNV examples reported in barley and wheat genes likely reflects the relatively high frequency of gene copy number differences in these species. It has been proposed that the abundance of repetitive elements in the large genomes of the <italic>Triticeae</italic> species might be associated with the faster rates of duplications and deletions observed in these species (Dubcovsky and Dvorak <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>; Saintenac et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2011</xref>; Wicker et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2011</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec23">
        <title>Effect of increased copy number on gene expression and phenotype</title>
        <p>In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, which has a small genome and limited numbers of repetitive sequences, copy number variation affects approximately 9&#xA0;% of the genes (Gan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2011</xref>). Many of these CNV are likely pseudogenes since only a small proportion is expressed. Among the 388 expressed genes with CNV, only 54 showed differences in expression that were attributed to CNV, which suggested that CNV has a modest effect on differences in gene expression in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. However, several examples of differential expression of genes associated with CNV and phenotypic changes have started to emerge in barley and wheat, suggesting the possibility that the faster rates of duplications (Dubcovsky and Dvorak <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>), together with the strong selection pressures imposed by agriculture may contribute to a larger role of CNV on expression and phenotypic differences in these species than in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</p>
        <p>In wheat, the increased copy number observed in the <italic>Ppd</italic>-<italic>B1</italic> locus was associated with significantly higher transcript levels particularly at dawn when expression in the wild type was very low (D&#xED;az et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2012</xref>). In contrast, the increased copy number of recessive <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>A1</italic> alleles was associated with slower induction of expression, which is consistent with the increased vernalization requirement and the delayed flowering time observed in the varieties with higher <italic>vrn</italic>-<italic>A1</italic> copy number (D&#xED;az et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2012</xref>). Large dosage effects of the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> locus were observed here in the IMC x Hayakiso 2 segregating population, suggesting that the natural variation in <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> copy number should also have an effect on flowering time. Natural variation in <italic>VRN2</italic> copy number has been previously described in wheat (Distelfeld et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2009</xref>). Additional CNV affecting gene expression and phenotype have been reported in genes affecting other important agronomic traits in barley and wheat (Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2012</xref>; Knox et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2010</xref>; Stockinger et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2007</xref>; Ragupathy et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2008</xref>). These examples show that CNV can contribute to important adaptive variation in the <italic>Triticeae</italic> species through changes in the patterns of gene expression.</p>
        <p>Using the Hayakiso 2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Hayakiso 2-Tammi population, we showed that CNV can influence the timing of expression. Plants homozygous for the Tammi <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele (4&#x2013;5 <italic>HvFT1</italic> copies) had earlier <italic>HvFT1</italic> expression during development than the near isogenic lines with a single <italic>HvFT1</italic> gene. Heterozygous plants (average&#xA0;~3 copies per genome) showed an intermediate initiation time of <italic>HvFT1</italic> expression levels (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) providing additional evidence of the association between <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number, expression levels and flowering time.</p>
        <p>A correlation between earlier increases in <italic>HvFT1</italic> transcript levels and earlier heading time was also observed in wheat. Recombinant substitution lines carrying the <italic>TaFT</italic>-<italic>B1</italic> allele from the variety Hope, which has a retrotransposon insertion in the promoter showed higher <italic>FT1</italic> transcript levels and earlier flowering time than the isogenic lines carrying the wild type <italic>TaFT</italic>-<italic>B1</italic> allele (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>). Similarly, a winter wheat line transformed with the <italic>TaFT</italic>-<italic>B1</italic> Hope allele showed early flowering even in the absence of vernalization (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>). To test if the early flowering was associated with CNV we estimated <italic>TaFT</italic>-<italic>B1</italic> copy number in the transgenic lines relative to the non-transgenic Hope allele. Analysis of genomic DNAs from multiple plants from two independent transgenic events (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>) showed that these transgenic lines have approximately four (3.7&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.27, 8 plants) and five (4.70&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.14, 12 plants) <italic>TaFT</italic>-<italic>B1</italic> copies. Although these differences in copy number may explain the earlier induction of <italic>TaFT</italic>-<italic>B1</italic> in the transgenic wheat plants, we cannot rule out alternative explanations. Since these transgenic events were produced by bombardment, some of the inserted copies may not be functional. Altered transcript levels can be also generated by the truncation of critical regulatory regions in the construct and/or rearrangements during the transformation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec24">
        <title>Haplotype differences in <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter and first intron</title>
        <p>Based on the early flowering associated with the Tammi and BGS213 <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles, Yan et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>) hypothesized that the I<sub>AG</sub> intron one haplotype present in these varieties might be associated with their early flowering time, but cautioned that the number of varieties analyzed was insufficient to make valid conclusions. The results from the present study indicate that the early flowering associated with the <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles from Tammi and BGS213 described by Yan et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>) is most likely the result of their increased copy number. When lines with a single <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy are compared, the intron one I<sub>AG</sub> haplotype seems to be associated with a delay in flowering relative to the I<sub>TC</sub> haplotype. In the IMC x Hayakiso 2 population described here, plants homozygous for the I<sub>AG</sub> haplotype flowered 10&#x2013;13&#xA0;days later than the plants heterozygous or homozygous for the I<sub>TC</sub> haplotype (both P<sub>E</sub> promoter). Although these differences were not significant (likely due to high variability of the late flowering plants), a similar result was described recently in the cross between the French variety Esterel and the Spanish landrace SBCC016. These two varieties have identical <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter haplotypes (P<sub>L</sub>) but different intron one haplotypes. In this population, plants homozygous for the I<sub>AG</sub> haplotype flowered 7&#xA0;days later (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.01) than the plants homozygous for the I<sub>TC</sub> haplotype (Casas et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>). This result was further validated in a collection of 140 winter barley landraces, in which the I<sub>AG</sub> haplotype was associated with 6&#x2013;8&#xA0;days later flowering than the I<sub>TC</sub> haplotype and showed a high correlation with latitude (<italic>R</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.55; Casas et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>). Cuesta-Marcos et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2010</xref>) also reported the presence of the I<sub>AG</sub> haplotype in a winter variety confirming that this haplotype is not associated with early flowering. The association between haplotype differences in the <italic>HvFT1</italic> intron and flowering time is not surprising given the important role of <italic>FT</italic> intron 1 polymorphisms on flowering reported in other species (Adrian et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2010</xref>; Helliwell et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2006</xref>; Schwartz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2009</xref>; Tiwari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2010</xref>). However, a conclusive determination of a causal relationship between the I<sub>TC</sub> haplotype and early flowering will require experimental validation using transgenic approaches.</p>
        <p>Results from this study also showed significant associations between <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter haplotypes and heading time in lines with a single copy of <italic>HvFT1</italic>, but these differences were not consistent among three populations that used the same <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> accession as one of the parental lines. Plants carrying the P<sub>E</sub> haplotype flowered earlier than those carrying the P<sub>L</sub> haplotype both in the E878&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> and U672&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> segregating populations. However, in the Hayakiso 2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> population, plants homozygous for the P<sub>E</sub> haplotype flowered 10&#x2013;14&#xA0;days later than those carrying the P<sub>L</sub> haplotype (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001). This unexpected result was confirmed by independent experiments in two laboratories. The same trend was observed when the differences between the <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles were analyzed only within the class homozygous for the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> allele from <italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>), which was the same accession used in the E878 and U672 populations. This last result indicates that the inconsistent effect of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> P<sub>E</sub> allele from Hayakiso 2 is not caused by epistatic effects of the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> allele.</p>
        <p>Taken together, the previous results suggest that the observed differences in the promoter haplotypes are not the cause of the differences in flowering time, but are just markers linked to a yet unknown cause of these differences. The heterogeneous effects of the promoter haplotypes may also explain the limited effect of the promoter haplotypes observed in the study of 140 Spanish winter barley landraces (SBCC; Casas et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>). In this collection, the P<sub>E</sub> haplotype was associated with 2&#x2013;3&#xA0;days earlier flowering in the fall sowing experiment, but with an opposite effect in the April sowing experiment (3.2&#xA0;days later flowering within the I<sub>AG</sub> lines). In a subsequent doubled haploid population from the cross SBCC145 (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>) x Beatrix (P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>), the P<sub>E</sub> haplotype was associated with an earlier heading time, though the differences were significant only within the photoperiod insensitive class (Ponce-Molina et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2012</xref>). In our E878 (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> (P<sub>L</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>) segregating population, the effects of <italic>HvFT1</italic> on heading time was significant both in photoperiod sensitive and insensitive backgrounds.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec25">
        <title>Epistatic interactions between <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles</title>
        <p>The heterogeneity of the effects of the promoter haplotypes on heading time was also evident in their epistatic effects. In the E878&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> and U672&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> populations, the plants carrying the <italic>HvFT1</italic> P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub> haplotype showed a spring growth habit irrespectively of the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> allele. This result indicates that this <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele is epistatic to the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> alleles for winter growth habit present in these populations (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). In spite of having an identical <italic>HvFT1</italic> haplotype (P<sub>E</sub> I<sub>TC</sub>), the Hayakiso 2 allele was not able to overcome the vernalization requirement in the Hayakiso 2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> population (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Based on this result, we conclude that the currently known differences in the sequences of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> promoter haplotypes are not sufficient to explain the different epistatic interactions involving this locus.</p>
        <p>The increased <italic>HvFT1</italic> copy number found in the BGS213 and Tammi alleles was associated with stronger and more consistent epistatic interactions than the haplotype differences among single copy alleles described above. In the BGS213&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;<italic>H. vulgare</italic> ssp<italic>. spontaneum</italic> and BGS213&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Igri populations, the early flowering <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele from BGS213 was epistatic to the alleles for winter growth habit (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>). Similar epistatic interactions and early flowering were observed when the <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele with increased copy number was introgressed into the varieties Hayakiso 2 and Dairokkaku 1, which have a strong vernalization requirement (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2006</xref>), and in the early experiments using the barley variety Tammi (Takahashi and Yasuda <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1971</xref>). These results indicate that epistatic effects of the <italic>HvFT1</italic> allele from BGS213/Tammi are consistent across different genotypes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec26">
        <title>Conclusions and practical applications</title>
        <p>From a practical point of view, our results have clarified the effects of <italic>HvFT1</italic> natural variation on barley flowering time. We demonstrated that the BGS213 genetic stock used to define the dominant <italic>Vrn</italic>-<italic>H3</italic> spring allele includes multiple copies of <italic>HvFT1</italic> that result in earlier expression and earlier flowering time. The large effect of this allele on flowering time may restrict its use to areas or cropping systems that require short growing cycles. In contrast, the allelic differences in <italic>HvFT1</italic> first intron are associated with smaller effects on flowering time that can be used to fine tune flowering time of barley varieties to different or changing environments. The presence of multiple <italic>HvFT1</italic> alleles with diverse effects on flowering time suggests that natural variation at this locus may have contributed to the wide adaptation of barley to different environments.</p>
        <p>From a more basic point of view, our results add to a rapidly growing literature on CNV in the <italic>Triticeae</italic> species. CNV has been found for most of the flowering genes studied so far in the temperate grasses, suggesting that this mechanism plays an important role in the generation of novel diversity. This is not surprising given the dynamic nature of the large genomes of the <italic>Triticeae</italic> species that exhibit rates of duplications and deletions several orders of magnitude faster than the rates of nucleotide substitution (Dubcovsky and Dvorak <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>; Saintenac et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2011</xref>; Wicker et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2011</xref>). In the long term, gene duplications play an important evolutionary role, as they provide opportunities for diversification and sub-functionalization that can increase adaptative plasticity.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This project was supported by the National Research Initiative Competitive Grants No. 2011-67013-30077 and No. 2011-68002-30029 (<italic>Triticeae</italic>-CAP) from the USDA National Institute of Food and Agriculture and by the Howard Hughes Medical Institute and the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Adrian</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farrona</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reimer</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Albani</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coupland</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turck</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>cis</italic>-Regulatory elements and chromatin state coordinately control temporal and spatial expression of <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>1425</fpage>
          <lpage>1440</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.110.074682</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20472817?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20472817</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Campoli</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drosse</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Searle</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coupland</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>von Korff</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Functional characterisation of <italic>HvCO1</italic>, the barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>) flowering time ortholog of <italic>CONSTANS</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <fpage>868</fpage>
          <lpage>880</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04839.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22040323?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22040323</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Casao</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karsai</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Igartua</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gracia</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Veisz</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Casas</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adaptation of barley to mild winters: a role for <italic>PPD</italic>-<italic>H2</italic></article-title>
          <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>164</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-11-164</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22098798?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22098798</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Casas</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Djemel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ciudad</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yahiaoui</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ponce</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Contreras-Moreira</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gracia</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lasa</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Igartua</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>HvFT1</italic> (<italic>VrnH3</italic>) drives latitudinal adaptation in Spanish barleys</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <fpage>1293</fpage>
          <lpage>1304</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-011-1531-x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21279626?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21279626</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wheat TILLING mutants show that the vernalization gene <italic>VRN1</italic> down-regulates the flowering repressor <italic>VRN2</italic> in leaves but is not essential for flowering</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Genet</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>e1003134</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003134</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23271982?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23271982</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Corbesier</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coupland</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Photoperiodic flowering of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>: integrating genetic and physiological approaches to characterization of the floral stimulus</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell Environ</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>54</fpage>
          <lpage>66</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3040.2005.01283.x</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Corbesier</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vincent</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jang</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fornara</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Searle</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giakountis</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farrona</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gissot</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turnbull</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coupland</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>FT protein movement contributes to long-distance signaling in floral induction of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>316</volume>
          <fpage>1030</fpage>
          <lpage>1033</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1141752</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17446353?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17446353</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cuesta-Marcos</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szucs</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Close</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Filichkin</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muehlbauer</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>KP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayes</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genome-wide SNPs and re-sequencing of growth habit and inflorescence genes in barley: implications for association mapping in germplasm arrays varying in size and structure</article-title>
          <source>BMC Genomics</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>707</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-11-707</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21159198?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21159198</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Danyluk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kane</surname>
              <given-names>NA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Breton</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Limin</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fowler</surname>
              <given-names>DB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarhan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>TaVRT</italic>-<italic>1</italic>, a putative transcription factor associated with vegetative to reproductive transition in cereals</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>132</volume>
          <fpage>1849</fpage>
          <lpage>1860</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.023523</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12913142?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12913142</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>D&#xED;az</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zikhali</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turner</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Isaac</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laurie</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Copy number variation affecting the <italic>Photoperiod</italic>-<italic>B1</italic> and <italic>Vernalization</italic>-<italic>A1</italic> genes is associated with altered flowering time in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>)</article-title>
          <source>PLoS ONE</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>e33234</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0033234</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22457747?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22457747</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Distelfeld</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tranquilli</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic and molecular characterization of the <italic>VRN2</italic> loci in tetraploid wheat</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>149</volume>
          <fpage>245</fpage>
          <lpage>257</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.129353</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19005084?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19005084</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dvorak</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genome plasticity a key factor in the success of polyploid wheat under domestication</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>316</volume>
          <fpage>1862</fpage>
          <lpage>1866</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1143986</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17600208?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17600208</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>LL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular characterization of the allelic variation at the <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> vernalization locus in barley</article-title>
          <source>Mol Breed</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>395</fpage>
          <lpage>407</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-005-0084-6</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Faure</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Higgins</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laurie</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic>-like gene family in barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>)</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>176</volume>
          <fpage>599</fpage>
          <lpage>609</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.106.069500</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17339225?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17339225</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Franckowiak</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Konishi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Barley Genetic Stock 213: spring growth habit 3</article-title>
          <source>Barley Genet Newsl</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>212</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fu</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sz&#xFC;cs</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Helguera</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Skinner</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>von Zitzewitz</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayes</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Large deletions within the first intron in <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>1</italic> are associated with spring growth habit in barley and wheat</article-title>
          <source>Mol Genet Genomics</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>273</volume>
          <fpage>54</fpage>
          <lpage>65</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00438-004-1095-4</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 15690172?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15690172</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gan</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stegle</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Behr</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steffen</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drewe</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hildebrand</surname>
              <given-names>KL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lyngsoe</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schultheiss</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Osborne</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sreedharan</surname>
              <given-names>VT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kahles</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bohnert</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jean</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Derwent</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kersey</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Belfield</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harberd</surname>
              <given-names>NP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kemen</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toomajian</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kover</surname>
              <given-names>PX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clark</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raetsch</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mott</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multiple reference genomes and transcriptomes for <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>477</volume>
          <fpage>419</fpage>
          <lpage>423</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10414</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21874022?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21874022</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Helliwell</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wood</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robertson</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>James Peacock</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dennis</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> FLC protein interacts directly in vivo with <italic>SOC1</italic> and <italic>FT</italic> chromatin and is part of a high-molecular-weight protein complex</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>183</fpage>
          <lpage>192</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02686.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16623882?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16623882</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hemming</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peacock</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dennis</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trevaskis</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Low-temperature and day length cues are integrated to regulate <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> in barley</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>147</volume>
          <fpage>355</fpage>
          <lpage>366</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.116418</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 18359843?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18359843</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hemming</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fieg</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peacock</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dennis</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trevaskis</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regions associated with repression of the barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>) <italic>VERNALIZATION1</italic> gene are not required for cold induction</article-title>
          <source>Mol Genet Genomics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>282</volume>
          <fpage>107</fpage>
          <lpage>117</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00438-009-0449-3</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19404679?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19404679</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kikuchi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kawahigashi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ando</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tonooka</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Handa</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular and functional characterization of PEBP genes in barley reveal the diversification of their roles in flowering</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>149</volume>
          <fpage>1341</fpage>
          <lpage>1353</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.132134</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19168644?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19168644</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Knox</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dhillon</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheng</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tondelli</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pecchioni</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stockinger</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>CBF</italic> gene copy number variation at <italic>Frost Resistance</italic>-<italic>2</italic> is associated with levels of freezing tolerance in temperate-climate cereals</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>121</volume>
          <fpage>21</fpage>
          <lpage>35</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-010-1288-7</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20213518?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20213518</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wheat FT protein regulates <italic>VRN1</italic> transcription through interactions with FDL2</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>543</fpage>
          <lpage>554</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2008.03526.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 18433437?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18433437</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Distelfeld</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Comis</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wheat flowering repressor VRN2 and promoter CO2 compete for interactions with NUCLEAR FACTOR-Y complexes</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>763</fpage>
          <lpage>773</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04630.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21554456?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21554456</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xiao</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duan</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ye</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jia</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kong</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A tandem segmental duplication (TSD) in green revolution gene <italic>Rht</italic>-<italic>D1b</italic> region underlies plant height variation</article-title>
          <source>New Phytol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>196</volume>
          <fpage>282</fpage>
          <lpage>291</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2012.04243.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22849513?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22849513</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Loukoianov</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blechl</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanchez</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of <italic>VRN</italic>-<italic>1</italic> vernalization genes in normal and transgenic polyploid wheat</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>138</volume>
          <fpage>2364</fpage>
          <lpage>2373</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.105.064287</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16055679?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16055679</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Murray</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>WF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rapid isolation of high molecular weight plant DNA</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>4321</fpage>
          <lpage>4325</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/8.19.4321</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 7433111?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7433111</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Oliver</surname>
              <given-names>SN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Finnegan</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dennis</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peacock</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trevaskis</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Vernalization-induced flowering in cereals is associated with changes in histone methylation at the <italic>VERNALIZATION1</italic> gene</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <fpage>8386</fpage>
          <lpage>8391</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0903566106</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19416817?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19416817</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pan</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayes</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>THH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blake</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wright</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karsai</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bedo</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic-analysis of the components of winterhardiness in barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L.)</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>900</fpage>
          <lpage>910</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ponce-Molina</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mar&#xED;a Casas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pilar Gracia</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silvar</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mansour</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>WBT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schweizer</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Herz</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Igartua</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Quantitative trait loci and candidate loci for heading date in a large population of a wide barley cross</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>2469</fpage>
          <lpage>2480</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2012.01.0029</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ragupathy</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Naeem</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reimer</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lukow</surname>
              <given-names>OM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sapirstein</surname>
              <given-names>HD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cloutier</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evolutionary origin of the segmental duplication encompassing the wheat <italic>GLU</italic>-<italic>B1</italic> locus encoding the overexpressed Bx7 (Bx7OE) high molecular weight glutenin subunit</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>116</volume>
          <fpage>283</fpage>
          <lpage>296</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-007-0666-2</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17985111?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17985111</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Read</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raman</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McMichael</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chalmers</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ablett</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Platz</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raman</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Genger</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boyd</surname>
              <given-names>WJR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grime</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wallwork</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prangnell</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lance</surname>
              <given-names>RCM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mapping and QTL analysis of the barley population Sloop&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Halcyon</article-title>
          <source>Aust J Agric Res</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>1145</fpage>
          <lpage>1153</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AR03037</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saintenac</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akhunov</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Targeted analysis of nucleotide and copy number variation by exon capture in allotetraploid wheat genome</article-title>
          <source>Genome Biol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>R88</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2011-12-9-r88</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21917144?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21917144</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sasani</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hemming</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oliver</surname>
              <given-names>SN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greenup</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tavakkol-Afshari</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahfoozi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poustini</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharifi</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dennis</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peacock</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trevaskis</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The influence of vernalization and day length on expression of flowering-time genes in the shoot apex and leaves of barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>)</article-title>
          <source>J Exp Bot</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>2169</fpage>
          <lpage>2178</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erp098</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19357429?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19357429</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schwartz</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balasubramanian</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warthmann</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Michael</surname>
              <given-names>TP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lempe</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sureshkumar</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maloof</surname>
              <given-names>JN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borevitz</surname>
              <given-names>JO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chory</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weigel</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Cis</italic>-regulatory changes at <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> mediate natural variation in flowering responses of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>183</volume>
          <fpage>723</fpage>
          <lpage>732</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.109.104984</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19652183?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19652183</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stockinger</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Skinner</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gardner</surname>
              <given-names>KG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Francia</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pecchioni</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Expression levels of barley <italic>Cbf</italic> genes at the <italic>Frost resistance</italic>-<italic>H2</italic> locus are dependent upon alleles at <italic>Fr</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> and <italic>Fr</italic>-<italic>H2</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>308</fpage>
          <lpage>321</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.0141.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17559507?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17559507</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Takahashi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Catalogue of the barley germplasm preserved in Okayama University. Institute of Agricultural and Biological Sciences</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <publisher-loc>Kurashiki</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Okayama University</publisher-name>
          <fpage>217</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Takahashi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yasuda</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Nilan</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetics of earliness and growth habit in barley</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 2nd International Barley Genetics Symposium</source>
          <year>1971</year>
          <publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Washington State University Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>388</fpage>
          <lpage>408</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tamaki</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsuo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>HL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yokoi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimamoto</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hd3a protein is a mobile flowering signal in rice</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>316</volume>
          <fpage>1033</fpage>
          <lpage>1036</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1141753</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17446351?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17446351</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Taoka</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohki</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsuji</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Furuita</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayashi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yanase</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakashima</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Purwestri</surname>
              <given-names>YA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tamaki</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogaki</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimada</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakagawa</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kojima</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimamoto</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>14-3-3 proteins act as intracellular receptors for rice Hd3a florigen</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>476</volume>
          <fpage>332</fpage>
          <lpage>335</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10272</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21804566?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21804566</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tiwari</surname>
              <given-names>SB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shen</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>H-C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hou</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harris</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>SF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McPartland</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hymus</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adam</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marion</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Belachew</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Repetti</surname>
              <given-names>PP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reuber</surname>
              <given-names>TL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ratcliffe</surname>
              <given-names>OJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The flowering time regulator CONSTANS is recruited to the <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> promoter via a unique <italic>cis</italic>-element</article-title>
          <source>New Phytol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>187</volume>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          <lpage>66</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2010.03251.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20406410?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20406410</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Trevaskis</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bagnall</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ellis</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peacock</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dennis</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MADS box genes control vernalization-induced flowering in cereals</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <fpage>13099</fpage>
          <lpage>13104</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1635053100</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 14557548?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14557548</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Trevaskis</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hemming</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peacock</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dennis</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>HvVRN2</italic> responds to day length, whereas <italic>HvVRN1</italic> is regulated by vernalization and developmental status</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>140</volume>
          <fpage>1397</fpage>
          <lpage>1405</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.105.073486</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16500994?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16500994</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR44">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Trevaskis</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hemming</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dennis</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peacock</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The molecular basis of vernalization-induced flowering in cereals</article-title>
          <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>352</fpage>
          <lpage>357</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2007.06.010</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17629542?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17629542</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR45">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tsuji</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>K-i</surname>
              <given-names>Taoka</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimamoto</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of flowering in rice: two florigen genes, a complex gene network, and natural variation</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2010.08.016</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20864385?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20864385</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR46">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Turck</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fornara</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coupland</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation and identity of florigen: <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> moves center stage</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>573</fpage>
          <lpage>594</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.59.032607.092755</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 18444908?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18444908</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR47">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Turner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beales</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Faure</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dunford</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laurie</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The pseudo-response regulator <italic>Ppd</italic>-<italic>H1</italic> provides adaptation to photoperiod in barley</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>310</volume>
          <fpage>1031</fpage>
          <lpage>1034</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1117619</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16284181?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16284181</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR48">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>von Zitzewitz</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sz&#xFC;cs</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Francia</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pecchioni</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Casas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>TH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayes</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Skinner</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular and structural characterization of barley vernalization genes</article-title>
          <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>449</fpage>
          <lpage>467</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-005-0351-2</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16235110</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR49">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weaver</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dube</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mir</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qin</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramakrishnan</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Livak</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Taking qPCR to a higher level: analysis of CNV reveals the power of high throughput qPCR to enhance quantitative resolution</article-title>
          <source>Methods</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>271</fpage>
          <lpage>276</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymeth.2010.01.003</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20079846?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20079846</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR50">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wicker</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mayer</surname>
              <given-names>KF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gundlach</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martis</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steuernagel</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scholz</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>&#x160;imkov&#xE1;</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kubal&#xE1;kov&#xE1;</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choulet</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taudien</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Platzer</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feuillet</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fahima</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Budak</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dole&#x17E;el</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keller</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stein</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Frequent gene movement and pseudogene evolution is common to the large and complex genomes of wheat, barley, and their relatives</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>1706</fpage>
          <lpage>1718</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.086629</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21622801?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21622801</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR51">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wigge</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jaeger</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Busch</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmid</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lohmann</surname>
              <given-names>JU</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weigel</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Integration of spatial and temporal information during floral induction in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>309</volume>
          <fpage>1056</fpage>
          <lpage>1059</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1114358</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16099980?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16099980</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR52">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Echenique</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Busso</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>SanMiguel</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramakrishna</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennetzen</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harrington</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cereal genes similar to <italic>Snf2</italic> define a new subfamily that includes human and mouse genes</article-title>
          <source>Mol Genet Genomics</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>268</volume>
          <fpage>488</fpage>
          <lpage>499</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00438-002-0765-3</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12471446?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12471446</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR53">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loukoianov</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tranquilli</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Helguera</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fahima</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Positional cloning of the wheat vernalization gene <italic>VRN1</italic></article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <fpage>6263</fpage>
          <lpage>6268</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0937399100</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12730378?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12730378</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR54">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loukoianov</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blechl</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tranquilli</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramakrishna</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>SanMiguel</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennetzen</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Echenique</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The wheat <italic>VRN2</italic> gene is a flowering repressor down-regulated by vernalization</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>303</volume>
          <fpage>1640</fpage>
          <lpage>1644</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1094305</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 15016992?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15016992</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR55">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>von Zitzewitz</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Skinner</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayes</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular characterization of the duplicated meristem identity genes <italic>HvAP1a</italic> and <italic>HvAP1b</italic> in barley</article-title>
          <source>Genome</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>905</fpage>
          <lpage>912</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g05-035</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16391696?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16391696</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR56">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fu</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blechl</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tranquilli</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonafede</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanchez</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valarik</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yasuda</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The wheat and barley vernalization gene <italic>VRN3</italic> is an orthologue of <italic>FT</italic></article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>19581</fpage>
          <lpage>19586</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0607142103</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17158798?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17158798</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
