<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3656044</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-37135</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063667</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Agriculture</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Crops</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cereals</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Wheat</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Developmental Biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Molecular Development</subject>
              <subject>Plant Growth and Development</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genetics</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genomics</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Plant Science</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plant Genetics</subject>
              <subject>Plant Growth and Development</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Overexpression of Three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> Homoeologous Genes with Distinct Expression Divergence in Hexaploid Wheat Exhibit Functional Retention in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Functional Retention of Wheat Homoeologous Genes</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>Zhaorong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Song</surname>
            <given-names>Na</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xing</surname>
            <given-names>Jiewen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Yanhong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Han</surname>
            <given-names>Zongfu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yao</surname>
            <given-names>Yingyin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Peng</surname>
            <given-names>Huiru</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ni</surname>
            <given-names>Zhongfu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Qixin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>State Key Laboratory for Agrobiotechnology, Key Laboratory of Crop Heterosis, Utilization (MOE), Beijing Key Laboratory of Crop Genetic Improvement, China Agricultural University, Beijing, People&#x2019;s Republic of China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>National Plant Gene Research Centre, Beijing, People&#x2019;s Republic of China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Baohong</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>East Carolina University, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>qxsun@cau.edu.cn</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: ZFN QXS. Performed the experiments: ZRH NS ZFH YHC. Analyzed the data: ZRH NS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JWX ZFH YYY HRP. Wrote the paper: ZRH ZFN QXS.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <elocation-id>e63667</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Hu et al</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Common wheat is a hexaploid species with most of the genes present as triplicate homoeologs. Expression divergences of homoeologs are frequently observed in wheat as well as in other polyploid plants. However, little is known about functional variances among homologous genes arising from polyploidy. Expansins play diverse roles in plant developmental processes related to the action of cell wall loosening. Expression of the three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs varied dynamically at different stages and organs, and epigenetic modifications contribute to the expression divergence of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs during wheat development. Nevertheless, their functions remain to be clarified. We found that over expression of <italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic>, <italic>-B</italic> and <italic>-D</italic> produced similar morphological changes in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants, including increased germination and growth rate during seedling and adult stages, indicating that the proteins encoded by these three wheat <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs have similar (or conserved) functions in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Collectively, our present study provided an example of a set of homoeologous genes expression divergence in different developmental stages and organs in hexaploid wheat but functional retention in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by the Major Program of the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31290210, 31290212) and National Science Foundation for Distinguished Young Scholars (30925023). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Polyploidization plays an important role in plant evolution. It has been demonstrated that approximately 70% of flowering plants experienced polyploidization events during their evolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Masterson1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Wendel1">[2]</xref>. Polyploidy, along with genomic segmental duplications, could benefit plants by increasing overall gene expression levels and cell sizes, and providing sources for novel variants and genome &#x201C;buffering&#x201D; of deleterious mutations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Udall1">[3]</xref>. When two or more different genomes are combined into a single cell, they must respond to the consequences of genome duplication <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Wendel1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Osborn1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Adams1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Liu1">[6]</xref>. There are three possible evolutionary fates for homoeologous genes in polyploids: retention of original or similar function, functional diversification, and gene silencing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Wendel1">[2]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Hexaploid bread wheat (<italic>T. aestivum</italic>, 2n&#x200A;=&#x200A;6x&#x200A;=&#x200A;42, genome constitution AABBDD) is an allopolyploid that was formed through hybridization and successive chromosome doubling of three ancestral diploid species (2n&#x200A;=&#x200A;14), <italic>T. urartu</italic> (AA), <italic>Aegilops speltoides</italic> (SS &#x2248; BB), and <italic>Ae. squarrosa</italic> (DD) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Huang1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Feldman1">[8]</xref>. Allopolyploidization leads to the generation of duplicated homoeologous genes (homoeologs). Therefore, most genes in hexaploid wheat are present as triplicate homoeologs. However, the presence of three homoeologs in wheat does not necessarily imply that three independent mRNAs are transcribed, and transcriptional divergence between homoeologous genes is widely documented in hexaploid wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Bottley1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Shitsukawa1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Hovav1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Chaudhary1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Hu1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Chen1">[14]</xref>. Organ-specific regulation of homoeologous gene expression is also frequently observed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Bottley1">[9]</xref>. Although there are numerous studies analyzing the genomic structures and transcriptional divergences of the homoeologous genes in hexaploid wheat, little is known about functional variances among homologous genes arising from polyploidy in wheat. Such information, however, is fundamentally important for a better understanding of the complex mechanisms involved in variant biological pathways in the hexaploid wheat and for the benefit of the genetic engineering of plants with polyploid backgrounds. For example, systematic study revealed that homoeologous <italic>Bx</italic> genes (<italic>TaBx1&#x2013;TaBx5</italic>) were highly conserved in the coding sequences and in the exon/intron structures, but were transcribed differentially in which the homoeologs from the B genome generally contributed the most to Bx biosynthesis in hexaploid wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Nomura1">[15]</xref>. Recently, Abdollahi et al (2012) reported that <italic>WAP2A<sup>Q</sup></italic> fully recovered their flower organs similar to the wild-type, <italic>WAP2D</italic> showed less recovery, and <italic>WAP2A<sup>q</sup></italic> rescued the least mutant flower phenotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Abdollahi1">[16]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Expansins are a family of closely related nonenzymatic proteins that induce cell wall extension and stress relaxation at acidic pH condition in plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-McQueenMason1">[17]</xref>. Based on phylogenetic analysis and shared intron patterns, expansins can be mainly divided into three discrete subfamilies, <italic>&#x3B1;-</italic>, <italic>&#x3B2;</italic> and <italic>&#x3B3;</italic>-expansins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Shcherban1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Lee1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Li1">[20]</xref>. They are similar to each other in size and have distant but significant sequence similarity throughout the length of the protein backbone. A number of sequence features are common to the three expansin families, including a signal peptide in the N-terminal region, a cellulose-binding domain in the C-terminal region, and a central catalytic domain that contains a histidine-phenylalanin-aspartate (HFD) motif and several cysteine residues thought to function in catalytic activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Cosgrove1">[21]</xref>. It has been shown that expansins play diverse roles in plant developmental processes related to the action of cell wall loosening <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Brummell1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Chen2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Cho1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Pien1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Reidy1">[26]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In previous study, we identified three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologous genes (<italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic>, <italic>TaEXPA1-B</italic> and <italic>TaEXPA1-D</italic>) from hexaploid wheat. Chromosome mapping using aneuploid lines revealed that the <italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic>, <italic>TaEXPA1-B</italic> and <italic>TaEXPA1-D</italic> genes located on chromosomes, 1A, 1B, and 1D, respectively. The orthologs of <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> also were found in the three ancestral diploid species. We demonstrated that epigenetic modifications contribute to the expression divergence of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs during wheat development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Hu2">[27]</xref>. Due to its highly conserved sequence but transcriptional divergences in different organs and tissues, it is of great interest to reveal functional variances among three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homologous genes in wheat. In present study, we found that over expression of <italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic>, <italic>-B</italic> and <italic>-D</italic> produced similar morphological changes in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants, including increased germination and growth rate during seedling and adult stages, indicating that the proteins encoded by these three wheat <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs have similar (or conserved) functions in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Plant Materials</title>
        <p>The hexaploid wheat genotype Nongda 3338 (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) was used in this study. Wheat seeds were germinated on moist filter papers and transplanted into pots to grow in the greenhouse under a 12-hr photoperiod provided by cool white fluorescent and incandescent light (intensity&#x2265;3000 lx). The plants were watered with a 1/10-strength Hoagland&#x2019;s solution when necessary. The Columbia (Col-0) ecotype of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> was used as the wild type. All genotype plants were grown in a growth room with a 16-h light/8-h-dark cycle at 22 to 24&#xB0;C for general growth and seed harvesting.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Phylogenetic Analysis of <italic>&#x3B1;</italic>-expansin Genes</title>
        <p>All deduced amino acid sequences were aligned using Clustal method with the MEGA4.0 program <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Tamura1">[28]</xref>. Distance analyses used the program ProtDist of the Phylip 3.5c package with a PAM250 substitution matrix. Phylogenetic trees were then calculated from the matrices by the neighbor-joining algorithm. Bootstrap analyses consisted of 1,000 to 5,000 replicates using the same protocol. The dendrogram was generated on the basis of the alignment of the deduced amino-acid sequences encoded by 26 <italic>&#x3B1;</italic>-expansin genes of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, 33 <italic>&#x3B1;</italic>-expansin genes of rice (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.personal.psu.edu/fsl/ExpCentral/">http://www.personal.psu.edu/fsl/ExpCentral/</ext-link>), and 3 <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs of wheat. The GenBank accession numbers of selected expansins can be found in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0063667.s004">Table S1</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>RNA Extraction</title>
        <p>Wheat Nongda 3338 were planted in pots in silt-loam/coarse soil mix and grown in green house. In two-leaf stage, the first leaf in the bottom, the second fully expanded leaf in the middle and the third unexpanded leaf were collected, and designated as mature, fully expanded and juvenile leaves, respectively. Total RNA extracted from different leaves for the gene expression analysis, using Trizol RNA isolation protocol (Life Technologies, USA). First-strand cDNA synthesis was performed using 2 &#xB5;g of DNase-digested total RNA with oligo (dT) primer according to the protocol for RT-PCR first-strand synthesis (Promega, WI, USA).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Quantitative PCR Analysis</title>
        <p>Real-time qPCR experiments using SYBR Green PCR master mix (Applied Biosystems) on 96-well optical reaction plates with optical adhesive covers (ABI PRISM) were designed, performed, and analyzed using the StepOnePlus Real-Time PCR system with its accompanying StepOne Software (version 2.2; Applied Biosystems). Gene-specific primers for quantitative PCR were designed based on nucleotide polymorphisms in the cDNA sequences of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologous genes, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0063667.s005">Table S2</xref>). The specificity of the primers was confirmed using plasmids containing genomic DNA sequences of <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs. The PCR efficiencies of each primer pair were determined from standard curve experiments. Any amplification with detected primer dimers from melt-curve analysis was excluded from the data analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Czechowski1">[29]</xref>. In comparative cycle threshold experiments for quantitative analysis of gene expression levels, <italic>&#x3B2;-actin</italic> was amplified as an endogenous control.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Binary Constructs and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Transformation</title>
        <p>To examine heterologous expression of <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologous genes, genomic DNA fragments of the genes were cloned downstream of the cauliflower mosaic virus 35S promoter in pB2GW7 vectors. Binary vectors were introduced into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> GV3101. Six-week-old <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants were transformed via <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation by the floral-dip method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Clough1">[30]</xref>. Transgenic plants were selected on Murashige and Skoog medium containing herbicides. The herbicides-resistant seedlings were transferred to soil. T3 generation transgenic plants were used for further experiments.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Germination Assays</title>
        <p>Seed lots to be compared were harvested on the same day from individual plants grown in identical environmental conditions. Seeds of each genotype were sterilized and cold treated for 3 d in the dark, then sown in triplicate (55&#x2013;65 seeds from one individual plant a quarter of Petri dish) on MS medium. The plates incubated in a climate-controlled room (22&#xB0;C, 16-h light/8-h-dark cycle). Germination was scored after 16 h imbibitions, we used radicle tip break through the seed coat as the seed germination standard. The number of geminating seeds was counted and converted into germination rate per 8 hour intervals for both transgenic lines and wild type plants. The average germination percentages &#xB1; SE of triplicates were calculated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Image Processing and Measurements</title>
        <p>For leaf size measurement and analysis of Col-0 wild-type and transgenic plants, cotyledons and sixth leaves were harvested and measured digitally on photographs taken using a digital camera (Nikon D90) with a standard 15-cm ruler for scaling on a black background. Acquired photographs were processed using Photoshop (Adobe version CS5) with manual tracing of leaf outlines to generate leaf silhouettes. Based on these measurements, leaf area was calculated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Fresh Weight and Height Measurement</title>
        <p>All genotype plants were grown in a growth chamber with a 16-h light/8-h-dark cycle at 22&#xB0;C. Plants were grown for 3 weeks after sowing and were measured. The actual times were 22, 25 and 29 days after sowing (DAS). The fresh rosette was cut with a pair of scissors just above ground and for weight determination with electronic balance and calculation of the amount of green biomass. Plant height was measured from the base of the plant (aerial parts) to the tip using a cotton thread. The actual times were 29, 32 and 35 DAS. Each line 15 plants were selected for fresh weight and height analysis.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Structure and Phylogenetic Analysis of <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> Genes</title>
        <p>The alignment of genomic and their corresponding cDNA sequences of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homeologous genes showed a significant conservation of the intron/exon organization within the open reading frame (ORF). The structures of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homeologous genes were also confirmed by the identification of potential exon/intron junction sequences, which were consistent with the universal rule GT.AG. The ORF sequences of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> genes showed single nucleotide substitutions only, whereas the introns had more frequent base substitutions and insertions/deletions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0063667.s001">Figure S1</xref>).</p>
        <p>Based our previous results, the TaEXPA1 belongs to the <italic>&#x3B1;</italic>-expansin class <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Lin1">[31]</xref>. To further investigate the relationship between three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homeologous genes and <italic>&#x3B1;-</italic>expansins of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and rice, we performed a neighbor-joining phylogenetic analysis using MEGA 4.0. These proteins were classified into six different classes according to the phylogenetic analysis, among which TaEXPA1 belongs to the class III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). Thus, these plant expansins proteins of class III were aligned using ClustalW, and the results showed that our identified wheat EXPA1 sequences contain highly conserved cellulose-binding domain, and a central catalytic domain that contains a histidine-phenylalanine-aspartate (HFD) motif and several cysteine residues thought to function in catalytic activity regions, which are thought to be critical for inducing cell wall extension and stress relaxation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g001">Figure 1B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0063667-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063667.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Sequence analysis of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologous genes.</title>
            <p>(A) Phylogenetic relationship of three TaEXPA1 homoeologs with <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and rice <italic>&#x3B1;</italic>-expansins. The accession numbers of selected expansins are listed as <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0063667.s004">Table S1</xref>. (B) Comparison of nine <italic>&#x3B1;</italic>-expansins amino acids in class III. Identical amino acids are indicated by asterisks, and black boxes indicate residues conserved among the seven proteins.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0063667.g001"/>
        </fig>
        <p>It should be noted that, there were two and four expansin protein members that can be clustered into class III in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and rice, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). Therefore, we speculate that there was at least another member that was not cloned in wheat.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Expression Analysis of Three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> Homoeologous Genes</title>
        <p>Previously, we examined the expression profiles of <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs in different organs at different developmental stages. The results indicated that all three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologous genes were expressed in dry seed embryos, shoots of 1d after germination seedlings, jointing stage stems, heading stage flag leaves and heading stage immature ears. However, expression levels of the three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs were significantly divergent in different tissues and different development stages. For example, all of the three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs were silenced in seedling roots. In the leaves of the same stage, <italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic> and <italic>TaEXPA1-D</italic> were expressed, but <italic>TaEXPA1-B</italic> was silenced <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Hu2">[27]</xref>. Due to its important role in regulating cell wall extension during growth, here we examined the expression of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs in different leaves of the two-leaf stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Interestingly, expression divergence was observed between the three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs in seedling leaves of different development stages. Most notably, <italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic> and <italic>TaEXPA1-D</italic> homoeologs were with higher expression in the third juvenile leaves than the other expanded leaves, whereas the mRNA of <italic>TaEXPA1-B</italic> was below detection level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g002">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0063667-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063667.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Expression patterns of <italic>EXPA1</italic> homoeologous genes by gene-specific PCR.</title>
            <p>Total RNA was isolated from different leaves of wheat genotype nongda 3338 in the two-leaf stage; <italic>&#x3B2;-actin</italic> was used as an endogenous control.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0063667.g002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Overexpression of Three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> Homoeologous Genes Displayed Increased Germination Rate in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></title>
        <p>In order to gain further insight into the functional divergence of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs genes in wheat, ectopic expression of <italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic>, <italic>TaEXPA1-B</italic> and <italic>TaEXPA1-D</italic> were performed using an <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> transgenic system. For every transgenic line, three independent T3 homozygous overexpression lines were used for further characterization. RT-PCR analysis indicated that three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs were expressed in all the transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants, respectively, but was absent in the wild-type (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0063667.s002">Figure S2</xref>). Overt phenotype was observed in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants compared with control wild-type plants, and the transgenic plants with three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs genes constructs exhibited similar phenotypes. Firstly, we measured the germination rate between transgenic plants and wild-type plants. The number of geminating seeds was counted and converted into germination rate at 8 hour intervals for both transgenic lines and wild-type plants. The germination rate for transgenic lines were more than 40% in the first 24 hours after sowing, but only less than 20% for wild-type during the same time period. The cumulative germination rate of transgenic plants was more than 80%, where in contrast with only 30% for wild-type after 32 hours after sowing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). The phenotype differences were also observed in other independent transgenic lines, these data indicated that the transgenic lines germinated faster than the wild-type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g003">Figure 3A, 3B</xref>). We also measured the primary root length of both transgenic and wild-type plants at 60, 72, 90 and 108 hours after sowing. At all four time points, primary root lengths of transgenic plants were longer than that of wild-type plants. This indicated that primary roots of transgenic plants grew faster than the wild-type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g004">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0063667-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063667.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> showed faster germination rates.</title>
            <p>(A) Germination was scored after 16 h imbibitions. The average germination percentages &#xB1; SE of triplicates were calculated. (B) <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seeds germinated on MS medium after 90 h.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0063667.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0063667-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063667.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> showed longer primary roots.</title>
            <p>(A) The primary root length of the transgenic lines and the wild-type plants were measured after 60 h at four time points. (B) Transgenic plants and wild-type sowed in MS medium after 72 h.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0063667.g004"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Overexpression of Three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> Homoeologous Genes Lines Showed Larger Cotyledons and Rosette Leaves in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></title>
        <p>Due to the divergent expression pattern of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs genes in leaves, we focused on leaf growth phenotype between transgenic plants and wild-type plants. In comparison with control wild-type plants, transgenic lines of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologous genes displayed larger cotyledons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g005">Figure 5A, B</xref>). Previous study showed that decreased expansin gene expression leads to a more marked repression of the leaf 6 growth during the later stage of leaf development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Goh1">[32]</xref>. To investigate the individual leaf basis of the changes after the overexpression of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs, we analyzed the lamina area of leaf 6 at maturity (30 DAS) of the transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants with that of wild-type plants. These results showed that leaf lamina areas were all significantly increased in the overexpression of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologous genes plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g005">Figure 5A, C</xref>). Organ size is determined by final cell size and cell numbers. Previous studies indicated that repression of expansin gene expression leads to decreased cell number in both lamina and petiole <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Goh1">[32]</xref>. To quantify this trait, we measured abaxial epidermal cell size of fully expanded sixth leaf (30 DAS) for both transgenic and wild-type plants using an inverted microscope. Cytological observation showed that epidermal cell size of transgenic and wild-type plants did not differ significantly (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0063667.s003">Figure S3</xref>), while the transgenic plants rosette leaves was significantly larger than that of wild-type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g005">Figure 5A, C</xref>), implying that larger transgenic plants are mainly caused by increased cell numbers. Biomass is usually used as an index of plant growth rate. We then measured the fresh weight of aerial tissues in transgenic seedlings and wild-type plants at 22 days after sowing. The three <italic>P35S:TaEXPA1</italic> homoeolog transformants appeared heavier of fresh weight than non-transgenic seedlings at 22 and 25 DAS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). In addition, <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants transformed with <italic>P35S:TaEXPA1</italic> exhibited a taller phenotype than the wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g006">Figure 6B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0063667-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063667.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants leads to an increase in rosette growth.</title>
            <p>(A) Transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> showed larger cotyledons and rosette leaves, Bar&#x200A;=&#x200A;1cm. (B) Data show a comparison of lamina size between cotyledons from overexpression transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants and wild-type plants and measured at 30 DAS. Values are means&#xB1;SE (n&#x200A;=&#x200A;10). (C) Data show a comparison of lamina size between sixth leaves from overexpression transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants and wild-type plants and measured at 30 DAS. Values are means&#xB1;SE (n&#x200A;=&#x200A;10). T-test compared with the wild type control: *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0063667.g005"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0063667-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063667.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> grow faster than non-transgenic seedlings.</title>
            <p>(A) Change of fresh weight of aerial tissues with time (DAS) between transgenic seedlings and wild-type plants. Values are means&#xB1;SE (n&#x200A;=&#x200A;15). T-test compared with the wild type control: *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01. (B) Change of bolt height with time (DAS) between transgenic seedlings and wild-type plants. Values are means&#xB1;SE (n&#x200A;=&#x200A;15). T-test compared with the wild type control: *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0063667.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Sequence Conservation, Expression Divergence and Functional Retention of Three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> Homoeologous Genes</title>
        <p>Previous classifications of the expansin gene family divided proteins into two subfamilies, <italic>&#x3B1;</italic> and <italic>&#x3B2;</italic>, based on substrate specificity and sequence conservation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Cosgrove1">[21]</xref>. Further studies revealed a total of 38 expansin or expansin-like sequences within the scope of whole genome in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, these expansins fall into three discrete subfamilies (<italic>&#x3B1;-</italic>, <italic>&#x3B2;</italic> and <italic>&#x3B3;</italic>) based on overall sequence similarity and shared structural features <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Li1">[20]</xref>. In previous work, we identified three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologous genes <italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic>, <italic>TaEXPA1-B</italic> and <italic>TaEXPA1-D</italic> from hexaploid wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Hu2">[27]</xref>. Here, the relationship between three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homeologous genes and <italic>&#x3B1;-</italic>expansins of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and rice was further investigated by neighbor-joining phylogenetic analysis. These <italic>&#x3B1;</italic>-expansins were classified into six different classes according to the phylogenetic tree, among which three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs belong to the class III with <italic>AtEXPA2</italic>, <italic>AtEXPA8</italic> and <italic>OsEXPA2</italic>, <italic>OsEXPA4</italic>, <italic>OsEXPA6</italic>, <italic>OsEXPA11</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g001">Figure 1A</xref>), suggested functional similar between them. Based on an analysis with the ClustalW program, it was found that three TaEXPA1 homoeologs expansin proteins had a cleavable signal peptide at the N-terminus. Two domains characteristic of expansin proteins, a cysteine-rich region and a tryptophan-rich C-terminal portion, were also observed in all three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs, implied they may have conserved function.</p>
        <p>Up to date, many wheat expansin genes were identified and their expression were analyzed. For example, 18 expansin genes were isolated from wheat and nine of them (<italic>TaEXPA1&#x2013;TaEXPA9</italic>) represent <italic>&#x3B1;</italic>-expansins, while <italic>TaEXPB1&#x2013;TaEXPB5</italic> and <italic>TaEXPB7&#x2013;TaEXPB10</italic> belong to the <italic>&#x3B2;</italic>-expansin class <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Lin1">[31]</xref>. Jin et al (2006) identified two wheat expansin genes that are expressed during male gametophyte development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Jin1">[33]</xref>. Gao et al (2008) evaluated the characteristics of wheat expansins protein TaEXPB23, and found the growth of wheat coleoptiles is intimately correlated with its expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Gao1">[34]</xref>. In our previous report, it was found that all the three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs were silenced in seedling roots, but <italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic> and <italic>-D</italic> were expressed in seedling leaves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Hu2">[27]</xref>. In present study, expression pattern of these three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs was further investigated in seedling leaves of different development stages. Interestingly, <italic>TaEXPA1-A and TaEXPA1-D</italic> homoeologs appeared to be highly expressed in the young leaves, as compare to fully expanded leaves. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, it was reported that expansin genes play important role during leaf development. Collectively, it can be concluded that the highly expression of <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> in the young leaves may impact cell proliferation or expansin, then affect leaf development in turn.</p>
        <p>Plenty of studies have shown that polyploidization is often accompanied by changes in genomic structure and gene expression, including loss of function, gene silencing and homoeologous gene expression diversification <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Wendel1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Bottley1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Hovav1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Chaudhary1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Kashkush1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Gaeta1">[36]</xref>. For example, comparison of three <italic>WLHS1</italic> homoeologous gene sequences in wheat indicated that <italic>WLHS1-A</italic> has a 3479 base pair insertion, leading to the loss of gene function <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Shitsukawa1">[10]</xref>. The expression of duplicated genes resulting from polyploidization can be partitioned between the duplicates so that only one copy is expressed and functions only in some organs, while the other copy is expressed only in other organs, indicative of subfunctionalization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Lynch1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Adams2">[38]</xref>. Evolution of the <italic>Q/q</italic> loci in polyploid wheat resulted in the hyperfunctionalization of <italic>5AQ</italic>, pseudogenization of <italic>5Bq</italic>, and subfunctionalization of <italic>5Dq</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Zhang1">[39]</xref>. In present study, overexpression of <italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic>, <italic>-B</italic> and <italic>-D</italic> produced similar morphological changes in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants, including increased germination and growth rate during the seedling and adult stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g003">Figure 3</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063667-g006">6</xref>). These results indicated that three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs all functioned in leaf growth of transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants, although the <italic>TaEXPA1-B</italic> silenced in seedling leaves of wheat. Therefore, our present study provided an example of a set of homoeologous genes expression divergence in different developmental stages and organs in hexaploid wheat but functional retention in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants. It should to be noted that, in our present study, only seed germination and seedling related traits (root and leaf) were analyzed between transgenic lines and wild-type, further analysis of other processes, such as pollination, floral opening, meristem dynamics, fruit softening, as well as in adaptive responses to submergence, GA and wounding, will provide more valuable information for the function retention of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Overexpression of <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> Genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Leads to Increased Growth Rate</title>
        <p><italic>Expansin</italic> genes have been isolated from a variety of plant species and are a large multigene family <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Cosgrove2">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Wu1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Li2">[42]</xref>. It has been shown that expansins play important roles in plant development, including seed germination <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Chen2">[23]</xref>, root hair emergence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Cho1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Zhang2">[43]</xref>, leaf growth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Pien1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Reidy1">[26]</xref>, stem elongation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Cho2">[44]</xref>, pollination <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Cosgrove3">[45]</xref>, floral opening <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Gookin1">[46]</xref>, meristem dynamics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Fleming1">[47]</xref>, fruit softening <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Brummell1">[22]</xref>, as well as in adaptive responses to submergence, GA and wounding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Lee2">[48]</xref>, and other developmental processes where cell wall loosening occurs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Cosgrove1">[21]</xref>. Different members of <italic>expansin</italic> are expressed in various parts of plants at different developmental stages. For example, <italic>LeEXP4</italic> was shown to be expressed specifically in the endosperm cap tissue enclosing the radicle tip <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Chen3">[49]</xref>. However, <italic>LeEXP8</italic> and <italic>LeEXP10</italic> were expressed in the embryo. The tissue localization and expression patterns of both <italic>LeEXP8</italic> and <italic>LeEXP10</italic> suggested that they played roles in the initial elongation stage of the radicle and seedling growth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Chen2">[23]</xref>. The <italic>GmEXP1</italic> was expressed mainly in the regions undergoing cell division and elongation in the primary and secondary roots, suggesting a role in root elongation in soybean <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Lee3">[50]</xref>. The complexity of <italic>expansin</italic> gene expression is reflected in the similarly diverse expression patterns found in wheat, in which three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs were differentially expressed in different tissues and developmental stages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Hu2">[27]</xref>. The distinct spatial and temporal expression patterns of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs suggested that <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> may play multiple roles in wheat development. In present study, we found that germination rate and primary root length of transgenic plants were faster than control plants, suggesting that <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> gene plays an important biological role in control of seed germination and initial elongation of the radicle. A previous study demonstrated that <italic>AtEXP10</italic> is expressed predominantly in young growing petioles and leaf blades, overexpression of <italic>AtEXP10</italic> produced larger rosettes and matured earlier as compared to the control plants, and leaf size was substantially reduced in antisense lines with suppressed <italic>AtEXP10</italic> expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Cho3">[51]</xref>. A quantitative growth analysis by down-regulating the expression of four expansin genes (<italic>EXPA1</italic>, <italic>&#x2212;3</italic>, <italic>&#x2212;5</italic>, and <italic>&#x2212;10</italic>) demonstrated that expansins are required for leaf growth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0063667-Goh1">[32]</xref>. Overexpression of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> increased leaf size during the seedling stage, combined higher mRNA abundance of <italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic> and <italic>TaEXPA1-D</italic> gene in tender leaves than mature leaves, suggesting that <italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic> and <italic>-D</italic> genes may play an important biological role in leaf growth in wheat. However, transgenic study using heterologous <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> system only provides the function of protein from transgene in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants. Therefore, the relationship of <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> genes to leaf growth in wheat is still an area to be further elucidated.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0063667.s001">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Alignment of genomic and their corresponding cDNA sequences of three </bold><bold><italic>TaEXPA1</italic></bold><bold> homoeologous genes.</bold> Exons and introns are showed in shaded and gray texts, respectively; ATG and TAG boxes are the start and stop codon, respectively.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0063667.s001.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0063667.s002">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Identification of </bold><bold><italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic></bold><bold>, </bold><bold><italic>TaEXPA1-B</italic></bold><bold> and </bold><bold><italic>TaEXPA1-D</italic></bold><bold> gene expression in homozygous T3 transgenic </bold><bold><italic>Arabidopsis</italic></bold><bold> by RT-PCR.</bold> 1 represented wide-type <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>; 2&#x2013;4 represented overexpression <italic>TaEXPA1-A</italic> transgenic line of OEA-2-12, OEA-8-10, and OEA-11-12, respectively; 5&#x2013;7 represented <italic>TaEXPA1-B</italic> transgenic line of OEB-4-6, OEB-9-9, and OEB-17-5, respectively; 8&#x2013;10 represented <italic>TaEXPA1-D</italic> transgenic line of OED-5-3, OED-7-5, and OED-12-7, respectively.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0063667.s002.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0063667.s003">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Cytological observation showed that the epidermal cell size of transgenic plants and wild-type did not differ significantly, while the transgenic plants rosette leaves were significantly greater than the wild-type, implying that transgenic plants were larger mainly due to an increased number of cells. Bar&#x200A;=&#x200A;100 &#xB5;m.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0063667.s003.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0063667.s004">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>The GenBank accession numbers of selected expansions.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0063667.s004.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0063667.s005">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Gene-specific primer pairs used in PCR.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0063667.s005.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Masterson1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Masterson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Stomatal size in fossil plants, evidence for polyploidy in majority of angiosperms</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>264</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17836906</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Wendel1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Genome evolution in polyploids</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source><volume>42</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688139</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Udall1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Udall</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Polyploidy and crop improvement</article-title>. <source>Crop Science</source><volume>46</volume>: <fpage>S3</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>14</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Osborn1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Osborn</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Birchler</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Understanding mechanisms of novel gene expression in polyploids</article-title>. <source>Trends in Genetics, 19</source><volume>(3)</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>147</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Adams1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Polyploidy and genome evolution in plants. Curr. Opin</article-title>. <source>Plant Bio</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>141</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Liu1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Expression partitioning between genes duplicated by polyploidy under abiotic stress and during organ development</article-title>. <source>Current Biology</source><volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1669</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17825563</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Huang1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sirikhachornkit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Faris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Genes encoding plastid acetyl-CoA carboxylase and 3-phosphoglycerate kinase of the <italic>Triticum/Aegilops</italic> complex and the evolutionary history of polyploid wheat. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</article-title>. <source>USA</source><volume>99</volume>: <fpage>8133</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8138</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Feldman1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Allopolyploidy -A shaping force in the evolution of wheat genomes</article-title>. <source>Cytogenet Genome Res</source><volume>109</volume>: <fpage>250</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15753584</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Bottley1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bottley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koebner</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Homoeologous gene silencing in hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>47</volume>: <fpage>897</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16899084</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Shitsukawa1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shitsukawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tahira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kassai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirabayashi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genetic and epigenetic alteration among three homoeologous genes of a class E MADS box gene in hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1723</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586655</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Hovav1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hovav</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Udall</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rapp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flagel, </surname></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Partitioned expression of duplicated genes during development and evolution of a single cell in a polyploid plant</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>105</volume>: <fpage>6191</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18420816</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Chaudhary1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flagel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stupar</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Udall</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Reciprocal silencing, transcriptional bias and functional divergence of homoeologs in polyploid cotton (<italic>gossypium</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>182</volume>: <fpage>503</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19363125</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Hu1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Expression divergence of <italic>TaMBD2</italic> homoeologous genes encoding methyl CpG-binding domain proteins in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>Gene</source><volume>471(1&#x2013;2)</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20951189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Chen1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Truksa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>EI-Mezawy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Three homologous genes encoding sn-Glycerol-3-Phosphate Acyltransferase 4 exhibit different expression patterns and functional divergence in <italic>Brassica napus</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>155</volume>: <fpage>851</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21173024</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Nomura1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanagita</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iwamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Three genomes differentially contribute to the biosynthesis of benzoxazinones in hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>102(45)</volume>: <fpage>16490</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>16495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16260753</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Abdollahi1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abdollahi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawaura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ogihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of <italic>Q/q</italic>-related homoeoalleles of hexaploid wheat reveals distinct recovery of flower transformation in the <italic>apetala2</italic> mutant of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Plant Biotechnology</article-title>. <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>252</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-McQueenMason1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McQueen-Mason</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durachko</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Two endogenous proteins that induce wall extension</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1425</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11538167</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Shcherban1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shcherban</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durachko</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guiltinan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McQueen-Mason</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Molecular cloning and sequence analysis of expansins&#x2013;a highly conserved multigene family of proteins that mediate cell wall extension in plants</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>92</volume>: <fpage>9245</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7568110</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Lee1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kende</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Expansins: ever-expanding numbers and functions</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>527</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11641069</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Li1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Darley</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ongaro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schipper</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Plant Expansins Are a Complex Multigene Family with an Ancient Evolutionary Origin</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>128</volume>: <fpage>854</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11891242</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Cosgrove1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Loosening of plant cell walls by expansins</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>407</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11014181</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Brummell1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brummell</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harpster</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Civello</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palys</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Modification of expansin protein abundance in tomato fruit alters softening and cell wall polymer metabolism during ripening</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>2203</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10559444</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Chen2">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dahal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Two tomato expansin genes show divergent expression and localization in embryos during seed development and germination</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>127</volume>: <fpage>928</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>936</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11706175</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Cho1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Regulation of root hair initiation and expansin gene expression in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>3237</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12468740</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Pien1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pien</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wyrzykowska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McQueen-Mason</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Local expression of expansin induces the entire process of leaf development and modifies leaf shape</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>98</volume>: <fpage>11812</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11562463</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Reidy1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Reidy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McQueen-Mason</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nosberger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Differential expression of <italic>&#x3B1;</italic>- and <italic>&#x3B2;</italic>-expansin genes in the elongating leaf of <italic>Festuca pratensis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source><volume>46</volume>: <fpage>491</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11485205</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Hu2">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Epigenetic modification contributes to the expression divergence of three <italic>TaEXPA1</italic> homoeologs in hexaploid wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source><volume>197</volume>: <fpage>1344</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23360546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Tamura1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source><volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1596</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488738</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Czechowski1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Czechowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scheible</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide identification and testing of superior reference genes for transcript normalization in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>139</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16166256</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Clough1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Floral dip: A simplified method for <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>16</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>743</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10069079</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Lin1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Isolation and characterization of 18 genes encoding <italic>&#x3B1;</italic>- and <italic>&#x3B2;</italic>-expansins in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.). Mol. Gen</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source><volume>274</volume>: <fpage>548</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>556</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Goh1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dorca-Fornell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Inducible repression of multiple expansin genes leads to growth suppression during leaf development</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>159(4)</volume>: <fpage>1759</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22740614</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Jin1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tashpulatov</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katholnigg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heberle-Bors</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Touraev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Isolation and characterisation of two wheat <italic>&#x3B2;</italic>-expansin genes expressed during male gametophyte development</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source><volume>228</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16937050</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Gao1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Expansins and coleoptile elongation in wheat</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source><volume>233</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18726548</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Kashkush1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kashkush</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Gene loss, silencing and activation in a newly synthesized wheat allotetraploid</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>160</volume>: <fpage>1651</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11973318</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Gaeta1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gaeta</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iniguez-Luy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osborn</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genomic changes in resynthesized <italic>Brassica napus</italic> and their effect on gene expression and phenotype</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>3403</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18024568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Lynch1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Force</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The probability of duplicate gene preservation by subfunctionalization</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>154</volume>: <fpage>459</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10629003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Adams2">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cronn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Percifield</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Genes duplicated by polyploidy show unequal contributions to the transcriptome and organ-specific reciprocal silencing</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>4369</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4371</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Zhang1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Belcram</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gornicki</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Just</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Duplication and partitioning in evolution and function of homoeologous <italic>Q</italic> loci governing domestication characters in polyploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>108(46)</volume>: <fpage>18737</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>18742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22042872</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Cosgrove2">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Cell wall loosening by expansins</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>118</volume>: <fpage>333</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9765519</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Wu1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meeley</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis and expression of the <italic>&#x3B1;</italic>-expansin and <italic>&#x3B2;</italic>-expansin gene families in maize</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>126</volume>: <fpage>222</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11351085</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Li2">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McQueen-Mason</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Expansins and cell growth</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>603</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14611960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Zhang2">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Distribution of expansins in graviresponding maize roots</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1305</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11134415</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Cho2">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kende</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Expansins and internodal growth of deepwater rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>113</volume>: <fpage>1145</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12223665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Cosgrove3">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bedinger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durachko</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Group I allergens of grass pollen as cell wall-loosening agents</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>94</volume>: <fpage>6559</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9177257</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Gookin1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gookin</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Temporal analysis of alpha and beta-expansin expression during floral opening and senescence</article-title>. <source>Plant Sci</source><volume>164</volume>: <fpage>769</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>781</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Fleming1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McQueen-Mason</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mandel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuhlemeier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Induction of leaf primordia by the cell wall protein expansin</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>276</volume>: <fpage>1415</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1418</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Lee2">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kende</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Expression of <italic>&#x3B2;</italic>-expansins is correlated with internodal elongation in deepwater rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>127</volume>: <fpage>645</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11598238</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Chen3">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Expression of an expansin is associated with endosperm weakening during tomato seed germination</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>124</volume>: <fpage>1265</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11080302</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Lee3">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Expression of an expansin gene is correlated with root elongation in soybean</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>131</volume>: <fpage>985</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>997</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12644651</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0063667-Cho3">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Altered expression of expansin modulates leaf growth and pedicel abscission in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>97</volume>: <fpage>9783</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10931949</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
