<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Breed</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol. Breed</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Molecular Breeding</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1380-3743</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1572-9788</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5097096</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">573</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-016-0573-9</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Characterization of <italic>Tamyb10</italic> allelic variants and development of STS marker for pre-harvest sprouting resistance in Chinese bread wheat</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>X. L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Meng</surname>
            <given-names>J. Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y. J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>Z. H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>yangyanchutao@126.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>College of Life Sciences, Inner Mongolia Agricultural University, 306 Zhaowuda Road, Hohhot, Inner Mongolia 010018 China </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Institute of Crop Science, National Wheat Improvement Center, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences (CAAS), 12 Zhongguancun South Street, Beijing, 100081 China </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>5</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>5</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>36</volume>
      <issue>11</issue>
      <elocation-id>148</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2016</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <p>Wheat grain color does not only affect the brightness of flour but also seed dormancy and pre-harvest sprouting (PHS) tolerance. The transcription factor <italic>Tamyb10</italic> is an important candidate for <italic>R-1</italic> gene, and the expression of its homologs determines wheat seed coat color. In the present study, the allelic variations of <italic>Tamyb10</italic> were explored in a set of Chinese bread wheat varieties and advanced lines with different PHS tolerance, and a sequenced-tagged site (STS) marker for <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> gene was developed, designated as <italic>Tamyb10D</italic>, which could be used as an efficient and reliable marker to evaluate the depth dormancy of wheat seeds. Using the marker <italic>Tamyb10D</italic>, 1629- and 1178-bp PCR fragments were amplified from the tolerant varieties, whereas a 1178-bp fragment was from the susceptible ones. Of the Chinese bread wheat varieties and advanced lines, 103 were used to validate the relationship between the polymorphic fragments of <italic>Tamyb10D</italic> and PHS tolerance. Statistical analysis indicated that <italic>Tamyb10D</italic> was significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.001) associated with depth of seed dormancy in these germplasms. To further confirm the association between allelic variants of <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> and PHS tolerance, 200 recombinant inbred lines (RILs) from the cross between Zhongyou 9507 (1178-bp fragment) and Yangxiaomai (1178- and 1629-bp fragments) were genotyped using the marker <italic>Tamyb10D</italic>. General linear model analysis indicated that variation in <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> had a significant (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.001) association with the germination index (GI) values, explaining 13.7, 4.7, and 9.8&#xA0;% of the phenotypic variation in GI in Shijiazhuang, Beijing, and the averaged data from those environments, respectively. In addition, among the 103 wheat varieties, 8 <italic>Tamyb10</italic> genotypes (<italic>Tamybl0-A1</italic>, <italic>Tamybl0-B1</italic>, and <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> loci) were detected, namely, aaa, aab, aba, abb, baa, bab, bba, and bbb, and these were significantly associated with GI value.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Allelic variation</kwd>
        <kwd>Germination index (GI)</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>
        </kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id>
              <institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
          <award-id>31160247</award-id>
          <award-id>31260320</award-id>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution>Innovative Research Group Fund of Inner Mongolia Agriculture University</institution>
          </funding-source>
          <award-id>NDPYTD2010-3</award-id>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution>Excellent Young Scientist Foundation of Inner Mongolia Agricultural University of China</institution>
          </funding-source>
          <award-id>2014XYQ-18</award-id>
        </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer Science+Business Media Dordrecht 2016</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Pre-harvest sprouting (PHS) results in loss of grain weight and reduction in the end-use quality of kernels in cereals, especially in wheat. It is believed that PHS tolerance of wheat is predominantly attributed to seed dormancy (Bailey et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">1999</xref>; Flintham <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2000</xref>; Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2004</xref>; Gubler et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2005</xref>; Tan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2006</xref>; Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2007</xref>; Sun et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2012</xref>; Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2014</xref>). Improvement of tolerance to PHS in wheat is a major breeding objective in China and many other countries such as Japan, Australia, Canada, and USA. Therefore, an understanding of genetic control of seed dormancy or PHS tolerance and development of functional markers are very important for marker-assisted breeding targeting for improvement of PHS tolerance in wheat.</p>
      <p>Seed dormancy can be divided into embryo-imposed and coat-imposed dormancy. Many genes involved in seed dormancy are known to be involved in abscisic acid (ABA) synthesis and ABA signal transduction (Gubler et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2005</xref>). The viviparous (<italic>Vp-1</italic>) gene is an important regulator of late embryogenesis in maize and a regulator of late embryo development in bread wheat (McCarty et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1991</xref>). <italic>AtABI3</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> is an orthologous gene of <italic>ZmVp-1</italic> in maize and <italic>OsVp-1</italic> in rice (Koornneef et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">1989</xref>; McCarty et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1991</xref>; Hattori et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1994</xref>). Furthermore, the <italic>AtLEC2</italic>, <italic>AtDOG1</italic>, <italic>AtHUB1</italic>, and <italic>KYP/SUVH4</italic> genes are also important for controlling seed dormancy (Stone et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2001</xref>; Bentsink et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2006</xref>; Liu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2007</xref>; Zheng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2012</xref>). In wheat, <italic>TaSdr</italic> genes were cloned and proved to be associated with tolerance to PHS in bread wheat (Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2014</xref>). Moreover, the <italic>TaVp</italic>-<italic>1</italic> genes involved in ABA signal transduction are also important seed dormancy-related transcription factors, and a positive correlation was present between seed dormancy and embryo sensitivity to ABA (Nakamura and Toyama <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2001</xref>; McKibbin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2002</xref>). Six alleles of <italic>TaVp</italic>-<italic>1B</italic> were identified, designated as <italic>TaVp</italic>-<italic>1Ba</italic>, <italic>TaVp</italic>-<italic>1Bb</italic>, <italic>TaVp</italic>-<italic>1Bc</italic>, <italic>TaVp</italic>-<italic>1Bd</italic>, <italic>TaVp</italic>-<italic>1Be</italic>, and <italic>TaVp</italic>-<italic>1Bf</italic>, respectively (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2007</xref>; Xia et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2008</xref>; Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2009</xref>; Chang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2010</xref>). Based on the allelic variation, a STS marker Vp1B3 associated with seed dormancy was developed; variations with <italic>TaVp</italic>-<italic>1Bb</italic> and <italic>TaVp</italic>-<italic>1Bc</italic> were associated with higher PHS tolerance (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2007</xref>). For <italic>TaVp</italic>-<italic>1A</italic>, rich allelic variations were detected (Chang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2011</xref>; Sun et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2012</xref>; Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2014</xref>) and another STS marker Vp1A3 for PHS tolerance was developed; the variations with the allele combinations <italic>TaVp-1Agm</italic>/<italic>TaVp-1Bb</italic>, <italic>TaVp-1Agm</italic>/<italic>TaVp-1Ba</italic>, <italic>TaVp-1Aim</italic>/<italic>TaVp-1Bb</italic>, and <italic>TaVp-1Aam</italic>/<italic>TaVp-1Bb</italic> showed higher PHS resistance (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2014</xref>).</p>
      <p>The dormancy of lighter colored seed was weaker than that of darker colored seed in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (Debeaujon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2000</xref>), indicating the association of grain dormancy with grain color. Wheat grain color is controlled by <italic>R-1</italic> genes located in the distal region of the long arms of wheat chromosomes 3A, 3B, and 3D (<italic>R-A1</italic>, <italic>R-B1</italic>, and <italic>R-D1</italic>, respectively). The recessive alleles for white grains have been denoted <italic>R-A1a</italic>, <italic>R-B1a</italic>, and <italic>R-D1a</italic>, while the dominant alleles for red grains, <italic>R-A1b</italic>, <italic>R-B1b</italic>, and <italic>R-D1b</italic>, respectively. For dominant alleles <italic>R-A1b</italic>, <italic>R-B1b</italic>, and <italic>R-D1b</italic>, any one is sufficient to result in red grains, and grain&#x2019;s redness increases in a gene dosage-dependent manner (McIntosh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2010</xref>). The <italic>R-1</italic> genes affect the sensitivity of embryos to ABA and the development of grain dormancy. It was proposed that one of the Myb-type genes of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, AtMYB2, might be involved in ABA signal transduction (Abe et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2003</xref>).</p>
      <p>The pigment of red grain color is composed of anthocyan in anidin and catechin, which are synthesized by the enzymes chalcone synthase (CHS), chalcone flavanone isomerase (CHI), flavanone3-hydroxylase (F3H), and dihydroflavonol-4-reductase (DFR) in the flavonoid synthesis pathway (Holton and Cornish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1995</xref>; Chopra et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1996</xref>; Mol et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1998</xref>). Anthocyanins, phlobaphenes, flavonols, and proanthocyanidins (PAs) are all synthesized through the same early flavonoid biosynthetic pathway branched out into the individual pathway. CHS, CHI, F3H, and DFR are expressed mainly in the immature red grains and are almost totally suppressed in white grains (Himi and Noda <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2005</xref>). In addition, several regulatory proteins involved in flavonoid biosynthesis have been reported in various species, such as maize, petunia, snapdragon, and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (Winkel-Shirley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2001</xref>; Mol et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1998</xref>). Two types of transcription factors grouped as the R/B family (basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH)-type) and the <italic>C1</italic>/<italic>Pl</italic> family (Myb-type) were able to upregulate all the structural genes required for the production of anthocyanin. <italic>Myb/c1</italic> are transcriptional activators of flavonoid synthesis genes (Himi and Noda <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2005</xref>), approximately 30&#xA0;cM proximal to the <italic>Vp1</italic> locus, consistent with observed linkage between grain dormancy and red grain (Groos et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2002</xref>; Himi and Noda <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2004</xref>). <italic>Vp-1</italic> is a key element that plays an important role in the seed maturation processes, such as seed dormancy and seed desiccation (McCarty et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1991</xref>; Giraudat et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">1992</xref>). It was reported that <italic>Vp1</italic>/ABA/GA coordinated the control of grain color and PHS via Myb-dependent and Myb-independent pathways (Xia et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2009</xref>). Mutations in <italic>Vp-1</italic> inhibit anthocyanin in synthesis (Robertson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1955</xref>; McCarty et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1989</xref>). <italic>Vp-1</italic> interacts with the Sph cis-element in the promoter region of the Myb/c1 gene and regulates its expression (Hattori et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1992</xref>; Carson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1997</xref>).</p>
      <p><italic>Hvmyb10</italic> was also a key factor of grain dormancy in barley (Himi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2012</xref>). <italic>Tamyb10- A1</italic>, <italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic>, and <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> genes, located on chromosomes 3A, 3B, and 3D in wheat, respectively, encode R2R3-type MYB domain proteins, similar to TT2 of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> that controls PA synthesis and induces the expression of flavonoid biosynthetic genes such as <italic>CHS</italic>, <italic>CHI</italic>, <italic>F3H</italic>, and <italic>DFR</italic>, which are also essential for the synthesis of both anthocyanins and proanthocyanidins (Himi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2011</xref>). In addition, <italic>Tamyb10</italic> was demonstrated to activate anthocyanin biosynthesis genes with synergy of the bHLH-type protein through a transient assay, and it is likely to be a strong candidate for the <italic>R-1</italic> gene of wheat, which regulates wheat grain color (Himi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2011</xref>); the red-grained wheat varieties are usually more tolerant to PHS than white-grained wheat varieties (Flintham <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2000</xref>; Warner et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2000</xref>; Himi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2002</xref>). However, not all the red-grained wheat varieties are higher PHS resistant than white grained, and <italic>Tamyb10-A1</italic> also expressed in white-grained EMS-AUS in immature grain (DPA 5) (Himi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2011</xref>), indicating that expression of <italic>Tamyb10</italic> may play an important role in interacting with <italic>Vp-1</italic> in PHS tolerance mechanism in white-grained wheat. In our previous study, some landraces, such as Suiningtuotuomai (average GI&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.10) and Waitoubai (average GI&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.07), had the strong PHS resistance, but they did not carry any of the PHS-resistant allele combinations of <italic>TaVp-1Agm</italic>/<italic>TaVp-1Bb</italic>, <italic>TaVp-1Agm</italic>/<italic>TaVp-1Ba</italic>, <italic>TaVp-1Aim</italic>/<italic>TaVp-1Bb</italic>, and <italic>TaVp-1Aam</italic>/<italic>TaVp-1Bb</italic> (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2014</xref>), which might lay in the fact that there were still other factors affecting PHS except for <italic>Vp-1</italic> gene.</p>
      <p>The objectives of the present study were to identify the allelic variations at <italic>Tamyb10</italic> locus among Chinese wheat varieties and advanced lines with different level of PHS tolerance and develop efficient markers for marker-assisted breeding. Furthermore, the identification of these new <italic>Tamyb10</italic> resources could also contribute to our understanding of the mechanisms underlying seed dormancy or PHS tolerance in bread wheat.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Plant materials</title>
        <p>Ten bread wheat varieties were used for PCR amplification of <italic>Tamyb10-A1</italic>, <italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic>, and <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic>. There were five PHS-resistant varieties, Xiaobaiyuhua, Yumai 18, Yangxiaomai, Xiaoyuhua, and Xiaoye 6, with the germination index (GI) values of 0.04, 0.07, 0.08, 0.10, and 0.14, respectively, and five PHS-susceptible varieties, Zhou 8425B, Jimai 19, Jing 411, Hengshui 7228, and Zhongyou 9507, with the GI values of 0.56, 0.58, 0.64, 0.68, and 0.71, respectively.</p>
        <p>In total, 103 Chinese varieties and advanced lines, with different PHS resistance from the China Autumn-sown Wheat Region (CAWR), representing more than 85&#xA0;% of wheat production areas in China, were used for association study as presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Among these, 18 varieties had a GI less than 0.15 and 85 between 0.15 and 0.71. The GI was determined based on the average data across two cropping seasons at two locations, Anyang in Hennan Province and Beijing (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2014</xref>). Moreover, 200 recombinant inbred lines (RILs), derived from the Yangxiaomai/Zhongyou 9507 cross, were used to confirm relationship between the allelic variations in <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> and PHS tolerance; Yangxiaomai is a Chinese landrace and had a low GI value (0.08), whereas Zhongyou 9507 had a high GI value (0.71).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>GI values and <italic>Tamyb10</italic> alleles in 103 Chinese bread wheats</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Number</th><th>Cultivar</th><th>GI (%)</th><th><italic>Tamyb10-A1</italic></th><th><italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic></th><th><italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic></th><th>Genotype</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>Zhongyou 9507</td><td>0.71</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>CA0459</td><td>0.71</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>CA0474</td><td>0.70</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Hengshui 7228</td><td>0.69</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Han 6172</td><td>0.67</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>CA0349</td><td>0.67</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>Zhenmai 98</td><td>0.66</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>Baiyingdong 2</td><td>0.65</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>Jing 411</td><td>0.64</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>CA0475</td><td>0.63</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>Jinai 16</td><td>0.62</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>CA0306</td><td>0.62</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>bbb</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>Hongliang 4</td><td>0.60</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>Xiaoyan 22</td><td>0.59</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>Jimai 19</td><td>0.58</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>Taishan 008</td><td>0.56</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>Zhou 8425B</td><td>0.56</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>aab</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>Shijiazhuang 8</td><td>0.56</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>Yannong 19</td><td>0.54</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td>CA0465</td><td>0.54</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>21</td><td>Jishi 02&#x2013;1</td><td>0.52</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>22</td><td>Hongsuibai</td><td>0.52</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>bbb</td></tr><tr><td>23</td><td>Zhenmai 004</td><td>0.51</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>24</td><td>Hengguan 35</td><td>0.51</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>25</td><td>Yumai 2</td><td>0.51</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>26</td><td>Lumai 14</td><td>0.50</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>27</td><td>Zhoumai 16</td><td>0.49</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>28</td><td>CA0420</td><td>0.49</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>29</td><td>Shan 213</td><td>0.49</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>30</td><td>Han 5316</td><td>0.48</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>31</td><td>Jinmai 5</td><td>0.47</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>32</td><td>Xinmai 9</td><td>0.47</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>33</td><td>Taishan 9818</td><td>0.47</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>34</td><td>CA0471</td><td>0.46</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>baa</td></tr><tr><td>35</td><td>CA0175</td><td>0.45</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>36</td><td>Yumai 34</td><td>0.45</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>37</td><td>Tutoumai(jia)</td><td>0.44</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>38</td><td>Zhongyu 6</td><td>0.43</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>39</td><td>Shi 4185</td><td>0.43</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>40</td><td>Huaimai 20</td><td>0.43</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>41</td><td>Xinong 88</td><td>0.42</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>42</td><td>Gaocheng 8901</td><td>0.42</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>aab</td></tr><tr><td>43</td><td>Yanfu 188</td><td>0.42</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>44</td><td>Xumai 856</td><td>0.42</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>45</td><td>Yanshi 4110</td><td>0.41</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>abb</td></tr><tr><td>46</td><td>Zimai 12</td><td>0.40</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>47</td><td>Jinan17</td><td>0.40</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>48</td><td>Baiyuhua</td><td>0.39</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>bba</td></tr><tr><td>49</td><td>Xinmai 18</td><td>0.38</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>abb</td></tr><tr><td>50</td><td>Weimai 8</td><td>0.38</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>51</td><td>Yannong 15</td><td>0.37</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>baa</td></tr><tr><td>52</td><td>Zheng 9023</td><td>0.37</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>baa</td></tr><tr><td>53</td><td>Shan 160</td><td>0.37</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>54</td><td>CA0481</td><td>0.37</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>baa</td></tr><tr><td>55</td><td>Yumai 47</td><td>0.37</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>56</td><td>Heng 95Gian 26</td><td>0.37</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>57</td><td>Han 3475</td><td>0.37</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>58</td><td>Xinmai 11</td><td>0.36</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>59</td><td>Zhongyu 5</td><td>0.36</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>60</td><td>Yanzhan 1</td><td>0.33</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>61</td><td>Xinong 979</td><td>0.33</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>62</td><td>Linmai 2</td><td>0.33</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>aab</td></tr><tr><td>63</td><td>Liangxin 99</td><td>0.33</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>bab</td></tr><tr><td>64</td><td>Lumai 21</td><td>0.32</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>65</td><td>Shixin 733</td><td>0.31</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>baa</td></tr><tr><td>66</td><td>Kenong 9204</td><td>0.30</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>67</td><td>Huixianhong</td><td>0.29</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>bab</td></tr><tr><td>68</td><td>PH82&#x2013;2</td><td>0.29</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>69</td><td>Baisuibai</td><td>0.25</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>baa</td></tr><tr><td>70</td><td>Shanyou 225</td><td>0.25</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>baa</td></tr><tr><td>71</td><td>CA0178</td><td>0.24</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>baa</td></tr><tr><td>72</td><td>Yinbinbaimaizi</td><td>0.24</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>aab</td></tr><tr><td>73</td><td>Zheng 366</td><td>0.24</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>74</td><td>Zhoumai 19</td><td>0.24</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>baa</td></tr><tr><td>75</td><td>Neixiang 19</td><td>0.24</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>baa</td></tr><tr><td>76</td><td>Yongchuanbaimaizi</td><td>0.23</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>aab</td></tr><tr><td>77</td><td>Bainong 64</td><td>0.23</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>aba</td></tr><tr><td>78</td><td>Shan 253</td><td>0.23</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>79</td><td>Pumai 9</td><td>0.20</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>baa</td></tr><tr><td>80</td><td>Xiaoyan 54</td><td>0.19</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>81</td><td>Jimai 21</td><td>0.18</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>82</td><td>Shannong 757</td><td>0.17</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>83</td><td>Nvermai</td><td>0.16</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>aab</td></tr><tr><td>84</td><td>Aikang 58</td><td>0.15</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>85</td><td>Lankao 906</td><td>0.15</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>86</td><td>Xiaoyan 6</td><td>0.14</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>87</td><td>Rongchangbaimaizi</td><td>0.10</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>bbb</td></tr><tr><td>88</td><td>Suiningtuotuomai</td><td>0.10</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>bab</td></tr><tr><td>89</td><td>Xiaoyuhua</td><td>0.10</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>90</td><td>Tuhulutou</td><td>0.09</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>aab</td></tr><tr><td>91</td><td>Langzhongbaimai</td><td>0.08</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>aab</td></tr><tr><td>92</td><td>Neixiang 173</td><td>0.08</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>baa</td></tr><tr><td>93</td><td>Wanxianbaimai</td><td>0.08</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>aab</td></tr><tr><td>94</td><td>Yangxiaomai</td><td>0.08</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>bab</td></tr><tr><td>95</td><td>Waitoubai</td><td>0.07</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>aab</td></tr><tr><td>96</td><td>Yumai 18</td><td>0.07</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>97</td><td>Xinmai13</td><td>0.07</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>98</td><td>Peilingxuxubaimai</td><td>0.07</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>aab</td></tr><tr><td>99</td><td>Xuyong</td><td>0.07</td><td>b</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>bab</td></tr><tr><td>100</td><td>Chuan 362</td><td>0.05</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>aab</td></tr><tr><td>101</td><td>Xiaobaiyuhua</td><td>0.04</td><td>a</td><td>b</td><td>b</td><td>abb</td></tr><tr><td>102</td><td>Fengchan 3</td><td>0.04</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr><tr><td>103</td><td>Xumai 954</td><td>0.04</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>a</td><td>aaa</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Primer design</title>
        <p>Nine gene-specific primers, Tamyb10-AF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>1</sub>, Tamyb10-AF<sub>2</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>, Tamyb10-AF<sub>3</sub>/R<sub>3</sub>, Tamyb10-BF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>1</sub>, Tamyb10-BF<sub>2</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>, Tamyb10-BF<sub>3</sub>/R<sub>3</sub>, Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>1</sub>, Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>, and Tamyb10-DF<sub>3</sub>/R<sub>3</sub>, were used to amplify the <italic>Tamyb10-A1</italic>, <italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic>, and <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> genes, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The other primer sets Myb10-A1, Myb10-A1, Myb10-A1, and Myb10-B were <italic>Tamyb10</italic>-specific markers used for determining the allelic variants of <italic>Tamyb10</italic> (Himi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2011</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Primer sets for cloning <italic>Tamyb10</italic> genes and characterization of <italic>Tamyb10</italic> allelic variants in this study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Primer set</th><th>Primer sequence</th><th>Anneal temperature (&#xB0;C)</th><th>Fragment size (bp)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Tamyb10-A F1</td><td>ATGGCTGCTCCCAAAGCTCTCA</td><td>63.6</td><td>1948&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-A R1</td><td>CGATGAGCTCCTCTTCGTCGTT</td><td>61.7</td><td>1948&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-A F2</td><td>AATCGCTGCGGTAAGAGCTG</td><td>59.9</td><td>1082&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-A R2</td><td>GCAGCATCCTCTTGCTCAGG</td><td>60.8</td><td>1082&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-A F3</td><td>TCAAGAACTACTGGAACACC</td><td>54.1</td><td>540&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-A R3</td><td>CGTATTTTACTGCACGTAAC</td><td>52.3</td><td>540&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-B F1</td><td>ATGGGGAGGAAACCATGCTG</td><td>59.2</td><td>447&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-B R1</td><td>CCGGCAGCTCTTTCCGCAC</td><td>63.6</td><td>447&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-B F2</td><td>AATCGGTGCGGAAAGAGCTG</td><td>60.1</td><td>1198&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-B R2</td><td>CCGTATCGGGCTGCTGCTC</td><td>62.2</td><td>1198&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-B F3</td><td>TGCCGGGGCGAACAGACAAT</td><td>63.9</td><td>515&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-B R3</td><td>TGTCACCCGGGCCATCAAAG</td><td>62.2</td><td>515&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-D F1</td><td>ATGGGGAGGAAGCCATGCTG</td><td>61.4</td><td>1419&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-D R1</td><td>CGGTCACTGTTATCTGACGCTGGAT</td><td>64.4</td><td>1419&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-D F1</td><td>ATGGGGAGGAAGCCATGCTG</td><td>61.4</td><td>1629&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-D R2</td><td>ACTGCTGCTCGTGCCCTCC</td><td>63.6</td><td>1629&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-D F3</td><td>GGGCGAACAGACAATGAGAT</td><td>57.3</td><td>630&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Tamyb10-D R3</td><td>CTTTGTTTACAGCACCAC</td><td>51.0</td><td>630&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Myb10-A1 F</td><td>CTATGTGGATGGCCTTGCAT</td><td>57.2</td><td>665&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Myb10-A1 R</td><td>CTACCAGCTCGTTTGGGAAG</td><td>57.7</td><td>665&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Myb10-A2 F</td><td>TTTCAATCGAGTGGGCATAA</td><td>54.3</td><td>536&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Myb10-A2 R</td><td>CCTGACGATGAGCTCCTCTT</td><td>58.0</td><td>536&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Myb10-A3 F</td><td>TCCCTACATGGGAGACAGAGA</td><td>58.4</td><td>565 or 2750&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Myb10-A3 R</td><td>TGTTATCACATGCTGATCCTGA</td><td>56.8</td><td>565 or 2750&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Myb10-B F</td><td>AGCAAGAGGAACCTGCAGTC</td><td>59.3</td><td>262 or 282&#xA0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Myb10-B R</td><td>GATGCCCTCCAGATCAAGGT</td><td>58.5</td><td>262 or 282&#xA0;bp</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>DNA extraction and PCR amplification</title>
        <p>Genomic DNA was extracted from seedlings using the method described by Gale et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2001</xref>). PCR reactions were performed in an Applied Biosystems 2720 thermal cycler in a total volume of 25&#xA0;&#x3BC;l, including 2.5&#xA0;&#x3BC;l 10&#xD7; PCR buffer, 125&#xA0;&#x3BC;M of each dNTP, 4&#xA0;pmol of each primer, 1.0&#xA0;U of TaKaRa La<italic>Taq</italic> polymerase, and 50&#xA0;ng of template DNA. PCR amplification were 94&#xA0;&#xB0;C for 5&#xA0;min, followed by 35&#xA0;cycles of 94&#xA0;&#xB0;C for 1&#xA0;min, 53&#xA0;&#xB0;C&#x2013;68&#xA0;&#xB0;C for 45&#xA0;s, and 72&#xA0;&#xB0;C for 1.5&#xA0;min, with a final extension of 72&#xA0;&#xB0;C for 10&#xA0;min. Amplified PCR fragments were separated on 1.5&#xA0;% agarose gel.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>DNA sequencing</title>
        <p>The PCR products were sequenced from both strands by Huada Gene Biological Technology Co. Ltd. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genomics.cn/index.php">http://www.genomics.cn/index.php</ext-link>). Sequence analysis and characterization were performed using software DNAMAN (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lynon.com">http://www.lynon.com</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>Analysis of variance was conducted by PROC MIXED in the Statistical Analysis System (SAS Institute, 8.0) with genotype clusters indicated by two types of fragments, which were amplified with STS marker <italic>Tamyb10D</italic>, as a categorical variable to derive mean GI value from each cluster and to test significant levels. The genotype clusters were treated as fixed effects, while genotypes nested in clusters and years were treated as random. Pearson&#x2019;s linear correlation coefficients for GI between years were obtained by SAS PROC CORR. Significance of the association between <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> and PHS tolerance in the RIL population was evaluated using general linear model (GLM) analysis, based on the phenotypic variation in GI explained by <italic>Tamyb10D</italic> estimated.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec8">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec9">
        <title>Amplification and sequence analysis of three <italic>Tamyb10</italic> homologs in varieties with different PHS tolerance</title>
        <p>Full sequences of three <italic>Tamyb10</italic> homologs were isolated using genome-specific primers (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Firstly, <italic>Tamyb10-A1</italic> was amplified with the primer sets Tamyb10-AF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>1</sub>, Tamyb10-AF<sub>2</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>, and Tamyb10-AF<sub>3</sub>/R<sub>3</sub> in 10 bread wheats with different PHS tolerance. Sequence alignment showed no difference among the 10 bread wheat varieties, but the full sequence of these wheat varieties had 12 SNPs compared with the <italic>Tamyb10-A1</italic> (AB191458) (2 SNPs located in exons and 10 in introns); for two SNPs in exons, one G to T change at position 177&#xA0;bp in the first exon did not induce any change of amino acids, whereas the other G to A at position 2957&#xA0;bp in the third exon induced the change of amino acid. The other 10 SNPs were located in the first and second introns. In addition, two 1-bp insertions (T and A) were found in the position of 1528 and 2354&#xA0;bp in the introns.</p>
        <p>The <italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic> was amplified from the 10 bread wheats with the primer sets Tamyb10-BF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>1</sub>, Tamyb10-BF<sub>2</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>, and Tamyb10-BF<sub>3</sub>/R<sub>3</sub>, respectively. For the PCR fragment amplified with primer sets Tamyb10-BF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>1</sub> and Tamyb10-BF<sub>3</sub>/R<sub>3</sub>, the sequence alignment showed that cultivar Jimai 19 had very similar sequence with Yangxiaomai except that Jimai 19 has two 6-bp insertions located in 368 and 399&#xA0;bp, respectively. In addition, compared with the <italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic> (AB191459.1), the sequence stitching amplified with primer set Tamyb10-BF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>1</sub> and Tamyb10-BF<sub>2</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>, in 10 bread wheat varieties, had 5 SNPs and 2-bp (GT) insertion, of which 2 were located in the first exon, i.e., G to A at position 41&#xA0;bp that did not induce any change of amino acid and A to T at position 179&#xA0;bp, while other three located in the introns, i.e., A to T at position 179&#xA0;bp, A to G at position 685&#xA0;bp, and C to T at position 1147&#xA0;bp. The 2-bp insertion (GT) at position 286&#xA0;bp was also located in the first intron. Polymorphic fragment was detected in the 10 bread wheats with different PHS tolerance amplified with primer set Tamyb10-BF<sub>3</sub>/R<sub>3</sub>. A 534-bp fragment was amplified in varieties Xiaobaiyuhua, Jimai 19, and Zhongyou 9507, whereas a 515-bp fragment was detected in the other varieties. Sequence alignment showed a 19-bp deletion in exon 2 of <italic>Tamyb10-Ba</italic>, comprising five GCC repeats and four bases of GACG, and caused a frame shift in its open-reading frame. This result was described in Himi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2011</xref>); compared with <italic>Tamyb10-Ba</italic>, <italic>Tamyb10-Bb</italic> had a 19-bp insertion. Therefore, varieties Xiaobaiyuhua, Jimai 19, and Zhongyou 9507 amplified with a 534-bp fragment had allele <italic>Tamyb10-Bb</italic>, while the others amplified with a 515-bp fragment were <italic>Tamyb10-Ba</italic>.</p>
        <p>The full sequence of <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> was amplified from the 10 bread wheats with the genome-specific primer sets Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>1</sub>, Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>, and Tamyb10-DF<sub>3</sub>/R<sub>3</sub>. The polymorphism was detected from the PCR products of primer sets Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub> and Tamyb10-DF<sub>3</sub>/R<sub>3</sub> in agarose gel but not from Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>1</sub>. A fragment (1419&#xA0;bp) of <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> was amplified in the 10 bread wheats by the primer set Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>1</sub>. Compared with the <italic>Tamyb10-Db</italic> (AB191460, red-grained wheat Chinese spring), the part sequence of <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> had five SNPs; among them, G to A at position 2160&#xA0;bp was located in the first exon that changed the triplet code AGA (polar uncharged amino acid glycine) into AAA (nonpolar alanine), while the other four, C to T, G to A, T to C, and T to A at positions 2637, 2698, 2823, and 3220&#xA0;bp, respectively, were located in the second intron. Two kinds of fragments were detected with the primer set Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>. A 1629- and a 1178-bp fragment were amplified in Zhou8425B, Xiaobaiyuhua, and Yangxiaomai, whereas only a 1178-bp fragment was amplified in the other seven varieties; sequence alignment showed that the 1178-bp fragment was nonspecific amplification product, but the 1629-bp fragment was specific amplification fragment (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). For the primer set Tamyb10-DF<sub>3</sub>/R<sub>3</sub>, the specific PCR products were obtained from varieties Zhou 8425B, Xiaobaiyuhua, and Yangxiaomai, but no PCR fragment product was detected from the other seven.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>PCR fragments amplified with Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub> in 10 Chinese wheat varieties with different PHS tolerance. The full sequence of <italic>Tamyb10-D</italic> had been subcloned in varieties Zhou 8425B, Xiaobaiyuhua, and Yangxiaomai with the primer sets Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>. <italic>M</italic> Trans 2&#xA0;k, <italic>1</italic> Zhou 8425B (average germination index 0.56), <italic>2</italic> Jimai 19 (0.58), <italic>3</italic> Jing 411(0.64), <italic>4</italic> Zhongyou 9507 (0.71), <italic>5</italic> Hengshui 7228 (0.68), <italic>6</italic> Yumai 18 (0.07), <italic>7</italic> Xiaoyuhua (0.10), <italic>8</italic> Xiaobaiyuhua (0.04), <italic>9</italic> Xiaoyan 6 (0.14), <italic>10</italic> Yangxiaomai (0.08). Note that the <italic>number in the bracket</italic> indicates the average GI values</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11032_2016_573_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p>
        <p>The full sequence of <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> was amplified in Zhou 8425B, Xiaobaiyuhua, and Yangxiaomai, which had 99.58&#xA0;% similarity with that of <italic>Tamyb10-Db</italic>; therefore, varieties Zhou 8425B, Xiaobaiyuhua, and Yangxiaomai had the allele <italic>Tamyb10-Db</italic>. In the other seven varieties, no specific PCR fragments were detected with the primer sets Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub> and Tamyb10-DF<sub>3</sub>/R<sub>3</sub>; these varieties had the allele <italic>Tamyb10-Da</italic>, in which just a 1419-bp fragment was amplified with the primer set Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>1</sub>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title>Development and validation of <italic>Tamyb10D</italic> STS marker for PHS resistance</title>
        <p>Based on the sequence analysis, a STS marker of <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic>, designated as <italic>Tamyb10D</italic> (primer set Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>), was developed and used for association analysis with 103 Chinese varieties and advanced lines. The PCR amplification indicated two types of fragments (1629- and 1178-bp fragments and 1178-bp fragment) amplified with primer set Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub> (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Among the 103 varieties and lines tested, 23 were the genotype of <italic>Tamyb10-D1b</italic> amplified with 1629- and 1178-bp fragments, whereas 80 had <italic>Tamyb10-D1a</italic> with only one 1178-bp fragment (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), which accounted for 22.3 and 77.7&#xA0;%, and had an average GI values of 0.245 and 0.398, respectively. The GI values of the 103 varieties were consistent over the 2&#xA0;years (<italic>r</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.966, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001), with mean value and standard deviation being 0.361&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.2 in 2006 and 0.359&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.19 in 2007, respectively. Analysis of variance in <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> indicated significant differences between two clusters for GI (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.00012). The genotypes with 1178-bp fragment were more susceptible to PHS with an average GI value of 0.398, compared with that of 1178- and 1629-bp fragments, showing more tolerance to PHS with an average GI value of 0.245. This indicated that the genotypes with the 1178- and 1629-bp fragments were more resistant to PHS than those with the 1178-bp fragment.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Association between PHS tolerance (germination rate) and the size of PCR fragments amplified with <italic>Tamyb10D</italic> in 103 white-grained bread wheat varieties. The <italic>white columns</italic> indicate the number of accessions with 1629&#xA0;bp, and the <italic>black columns</italic> indicate the number of accessions with no specific amplified fragment</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11032_2016_573_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p>
        <p>To further confirm the association, a RIL population developed from the cross of Yangxiaomai/Zhongyou 9507 was genotyped using <italic>Tamyb10D</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Statistical analysis confirmed the significant association (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.001) of allelic variations of <italic>Tamyb10-Db</italic> with GI value and PHS tolerance. In this population, <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> gene explained 13.7, 4.7, and 9.8&#xA0;% of the phenotypic variations in Shijiazhuang, Beijing, and the averaged data from those environments, respectively, based on the test of STS marker <italic>Tamyb10D</italic> (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Detection of allelic variation of <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> in RIL alleles including 1629&#xA0;bp (Yangxiaomai) and no specific PCR product (Zhongyou 9507) are marked with the <italic>lanes 1&#x2013;2</italic>, respectively. <italic>Lanes 3&#x2013;14</italic> are the RILs developed from cross between Yangxiaomai and Zhongyou 9507</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11032_2016_573_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Association analysis between <italic>Tamyb10D</italic> and GI values in 200 RILs using GIM model</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Trait</th><th><italic>Tamyb10D</italic></th><th>No. of alleles</th><th>Mean of phenotype (%)</th><th><italic>F</italic> value</th><th>Explanation of phenotypic variation (<italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>) (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">Shijiazhuang GI values</td><td>a type of fragment</td><td>125</td><td>9.49</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">32.497*</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">13.7</td></tr><tr><td>b type of fragment</td><td>75</td><td>22.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Beijing GI values</td><td>a type of fragment</td><td>125</td><td>28.99</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">10.804*</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">4.7</td></tr><tr><td>b type of fragment</td><td>75</td><td>39.39</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Average GI values</td><td>a type of fragment</td><td>125</td><td>19.24</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">22.567*</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">9.8</td></tr><tr><td>b type of fragment</td><td>75</td><td>30.87</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Significant association between <italic>Tamyb10D</italic> and phenotypic variation at the 0.001 level</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>Characterization of <italic>Tamyb10</italic> allelic variants</title>
        <p>The allelic variants of <italic>Tamyb10-A1</italic> and <italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic> were identified with the primer sets Myb10-A1, Myb10-A2, Myb10-A3, and Myb10-B (Himi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2011</xref>). The alleles of <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> were detected with the primer set Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>. Firstly, three primer sets Myb10-A1, Myb10-A2, and Myb10-A3 were used to identify the allelic variants of <italic>Tamyb10-A1</italic> in the 103 varieties with different dormancy level. Thirty-eight <italic>Tamyb10-A1b</italic> varieties showed a 665-bp fragment with primer set Myb10-A1 and a 565-bp fragment with primer set Myb10-A3 but not with primer set Myb10-A2 (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). Sixty-five <italic>Tamyb10-A1a</italic> varieties showed a 665-bp fragment with primer set Myb10-A1, 636-bp fragment with primer set Myb10-A2, and 565- or 565- and 2750-bp fragments with primer set Myb10-A3 (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). Among them, five varieties including Lumai 21, Nvermai, Chuan 362, Shan 253, and PH82&#x2013;2 had the heterozygote fragments with 2750 and 565&#xA0;bp using the primer set Myb10-A3. Other three <italic>Tamyb10-A1a</italic> varieties Zheng 366, Yumai 47, and Waitoubai showed amplified fragments with primer sets Myb10-A2 and Myb10-A3 but not with primer set Myb10-A1 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). Thirty-eight <italic>Tamyb10-A1b</italic> varieties had mean GI value and standard deviation of 0.390&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.028, and 65 <italic>Tamyb10-A1a</italic> varieties had mean GI value and standard deviation of 0.342&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.024, and analysis of variance indicated that there were not significant differences between two clusters for GI.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Distribution of different <italic>Tamyb10</italic> alleles in 103 white-grained wheat varieties</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">PHS resistance</th><th rowspan="2">No. of varieties</th><th rowspan="2">GI (%)</th><th rowspan="2">GI range (%)</th><th colspan="2"><italic>Tamyb10-A1</italic></th><th colspan="2"><italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic></th><th colspan="2"><italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic></th></tr><tr><th>b</th><th>a</th><th>b</th><th>a</th><th>b</th><th>a</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Resistant</td><td>35</td><td>14.1</td><td>0&#x2013;26</td><td>11</td><td>24</td><td>3</td><td>32</td><td>14</td><td>21</td></tr><tr><td>Moderately resistant</td><td>56</td><td>43.2</td><td>27&#x2013;60</td><td>22</td><td>34</td><td>35</td><td>21</td><td>8</td><td>48</td></tr><tr><td>Susceptible</td><td>12</td><td>66.2</td><td>61&#x2013;100</td><td>5</td><td>7</td><td>10</td><td>2</td><td>1</td><td>11</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>103</td><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td>38</td><td>65</td><td>48</td><td>55</td><td>23</td><td>80</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Germination index (GI) is the mean of two locations over 2&#xA0;years</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Identification of haplotypes of <italic>Tamyb10</italic> in part wheat varieties using four pairs of specific primers. <italic>1</italic> Hengguan 35, <italic>2</italic> Yannong 19, <italic>3</italic> CA0420, <italic>4</italic> Xinong 88, <italic>5</italic> Han 5316, <italic>6</italic> Lumai 21, <italic>7</italic> Nvermai, <italic>8</italic> Chuan 362, <italic>9</italic> Shan 253, <italic>10</italic> PH82&#x2013;2, <italic>11</italic> Zheng 366, <italic>12</italic> Yumai 47, <italic>13</italic> Waitoubai</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11032_2016_573_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
</p>
        <p>The primer set Myb10-B was used to identify the allelic variants of <italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic> in these germplasm. Two types of fragments (282 and 263&#xA0;bp) were detected in 103 varieties (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b). Genotypes with a 282-bp fragment were the allele <italic>Tamyb10-B1b</italic>, whereas genotypes with 263&#xA0;bp were <italic>Tamyb10-B1a</italic>. Forty-eight <italic>Tamyb10-B1b</italic> varieties had mean GI value and standard deviation of 0.491&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.020 and 55 <italic>Tamyb10-B1a</italic> varieties had mean GI value and standard deviation of 0.245&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.020 (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>), and analysis of variance indicated significant differences between two clusters for GI (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.9&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;13</sup>). The data showed that the allelic variants of <italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic> were associated with PHS tolerance.</p>
        <p>With the marker <italic>Tamyb10D</italic>, a 1629-bp fragment was amplified in genotypes of <italic>Tamyb10-D1b</italic>, while nonspecific amplification was found in the genotype <italic>Tamyb10-Da</italic>. Twenty-three <italic>Tamyb10-D1b</italic> varieties and 80 <italic>Tamyb10-D1a</italic> varieties were detected (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p>
        <p>In the 103 Chinese bread wheats with different PHS tolerance, 8 <italic>Tamyb10</italic> genotypes (<italic>Tamyb10-A1</italic>, <italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic>, and <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> loci) were detected, namely, aaa, aab, aba, abb, baa, bab, bba, and bbb, which showed a continuous color change with increase of dominant allele &#x201C;b&#x201D; (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Multiple comparisons indicated that the average GI was significantly different among genotypes with different allele combinations such as aaa and aba, aaa and bba, aab and aba, aab and bba, aba and abb, aba and bab, abb and bba, baa and bba, and bab and bba (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.01). As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>, the genotypes with the allele combinations aaa, aab, abb, baa, and bab showed resistance to PHS with average GI values of 0.264, 0.198, 0.275, 0.283, and 0.172, respectively, whereas the genotypes with aba and bba showed susceptible to PHS with average GI values of 0.508 and 0.519, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Grain color of genotypes with different <italic>Tamyb10</italic> allele combinations. From <italic>left to right</italic>, the names of varieties were Xiaoyan 6, Zhou 8425B, Zhongyou 9507, Xiaobaiyuhua, Zhoumai 19, Yangxiaomai, Jimai 19, and Hongsuibai, respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11032_2016_573_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Germination index (GI) in different <italic>Tamyb10</italic> genotypes in 103 germplasm</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Genotype</th><th>No. of varieties</th><th>GI (%)</th><th>GI range (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>aaa</td><td>26</td><td>26.4&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;3.2 a</td><td>3.8&#x2013;68.4</td></tr><tr><td>aab</td><td>12</td><td>19.8&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;4.7 a</td><td>4.5&#x2013;56</td></tr><tr><td>aba</td><td>24</td><td>50.8&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;2.4 b</td><td>22.9&#x2013;70.8</td></tr><tr><td>abb</td><td>3</td><td>27.5&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;11.8 a</td><td>4&#x2013;40.7</td></tr><tr><td>baa</td><td>12</td><td>28.3&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;2.9 a</td><td>8.3&#x2013;46.2</td></tr><tr><td>bab</td><td>5</td><td>17.2&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;5.6 a</td><td>6.7&#x2013;32.5</td></tr><tr><td>bba</td><td>18</td><td>51.9&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;2.3 b</td><td>38.9&#x2013;69.9</td></tr><tr><td>bbb</td><td>3</td><td>41.2&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;15.7 ab</td><td>10.2&#x2013;61.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>GI value is the mean&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;SE of experiments in two locations over 2&#xA0;years. Different lowercase letters after average GI&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;SE represent significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.01)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec12">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>An association between grain color and depth of dormancy has been noted in a <italic>Vp-1</italic> mutant of maize and in transparent testa (tt) mutants of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (McCarty et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1991</xref>; Debeaujon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2000</xref>). Normally, red-grained varieties are usually more tolerant to PHS than white-grained wheat varieties (Flintham <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2000</xref>; Warner et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2000</xref>; Himi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2002</xref>); however, it is proven that the statement is not all true in the present study. Some white-grained varieties, such as Xumai 954, Fengchan 3, Xinmai 13, Yumai 18, and Xiaoyuhua, had higher PHS tolerance with germination rates below 10&#xA0;% (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), although they had an allele combination of aaa. White-grained wheat varieties are homozygous for the recessive alleles of <italic>R-1</italic> gene, while red-grained wheat varieties are heterozygous or homozygous for the dormant alleles of <italic>R-1</italic> gene ((McIntosh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1998</xref>), and no amplified fragments from genomic DNA and cDNA of white-grained wheats were obtained by PCR using specific primers of <italic>Tamyb10-Da</italic> before (Himi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2011</xref>). In the present study, a part of genomic sequences of <italic>Tamyb10-Da</italic> (1419&#xA0;bp) were amplified fortunately from bread wheat (<italic>R-D1a</italic> varieties) with higher GI values. Compared with the <italic>Tamyb10-D1b</italic> (AB191460), ORF of <italic>Tamyb10-Da</italic> also had very high similarity with <italic>Tamyb10-B1a</italic> besides sequence of AB191460. Among the 103 Chinese bread wheat varieties, only 23 (average GI value was 0.245) were the allele <italic>Tamyb10-D1b</italic>, and the others (average GI value was 0.398) were <italic>Tamyb10-D1a</italic> with only one 1419-bp fragment amplified, suggesting that mutation locus of <italic>Tamyb10-D1a</italic> might occur in the region between 1419 and 1629&#xA0;bp, leading an early termination in the coding region; that is why the nonspecific PCR product were amplified with the primer sets Tamyb10-DF<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub> and Tamyb10-DF<sub>3</sub>/R<sub>3</sub> in these varieties.</p>
      <p>Chinese spring with deletions of chromosome 3DL produces seeds with white color (Himi and Noda <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2004</xref>), indicating that deletion of either the <italic>DFR</italic> gene or <italic>Myb/c</italic> or <italic>TaVp-1D</italic> or all of these three genes on chromosome 3D have loss or gain of functions in grain color (Xia et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2008</xref>); moreover, in red-grained wheat, <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic> has the greatest effect on PHS resistance, followed by <italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic>, and <italic>Tamyb10-A1</italic> had the least effect (Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2014</xref>). In this germplasm, there is no significant difference of GI between <italic>Tamyb10-A1b</italic> and <italic>Tamyb10-A1a</italic> genotypes, but for <italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic> and <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic>, the significant difference of GI is present between <italic>Tamyb10-B1a</italic> and <italic>Tamyb10-B1b</italic> (<italic>F</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;1.400, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.9&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;13</sup>) and between <italic>Tamyb10-D1b</italic> and <italic>Tamyb10-D1a</italic> (<italic>F</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.296, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.00012), respectively. Moreover, varieties with allele <italic>Tamyb10-B1a</italic> were more resistant than that with <italic>Tamyb10-B1b</italic>, and the varieties with <italic>Tamyb10-D1b</italic> were more resistant than those with <italic>Tamyb10-D1a</italic>. The above data showed that <italic>Tamyb10-B1</italic> had the greatest effect on seed dormancy, followed by <italic>Tamyb10-D1</italic>, and <italic>Tamyb10-A1</italic> had the least effect, and these also showed that there is no correlation between the numbers of <italic>R-b</italic> (including <italic>R-A1b</italic>, <italic>R-B1b</italic>, and <italic>R-D1b</italic>) and the level of seed dormancy in a variety. It may be a reason that the red-grained wheat varieties are usually more tolerant to PHS than white-grained wheat varieties, but not all the red grained wheats had higher PHS resistance than white grained. In this study, there was another interesting result; the RIL population of Yangxiaomai/Zhongyou 9507 was also used to confirm the association of <italic>Tamyb10-B</italic> variations (<italic>Tamyb10-Ba</italic> and <italic>Tamyb10-Bb</italic>) and GI values, but statistical analysis showed no significant differences of GI (<italic>F</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;6.67, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.254) between two genotypes.</p>
      <p>In our previous study, STS markers <italic>Vp1A3</italic> and <italic>Vp1B3</italic> were associated with seed dormancy in Chinese wheats with different GI values (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2014</xref>); the efficiency of marker-assisted selection for PHS-resistant varieties was improved using <italic>Vp1A3</italic> and <italic>Vp1B3</italic>. The allele combinations <italic>TaVp-1Agm</italic> and <italic>TaVp-1Bb</italic>, <italic>TaVp-1Agm</italic> and <italic>TaVp-1Ba</italic>, <italic>TaVp-1Aim</italic> and <italic>TaVp-1Bb</italic>, and <italic>TaVp-1Aam</italic> and <italic>TaVp-1Bb</italic> could confer higher PHS resistance (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2014</xref>). But, some varieties such as Suiningtuotuomai (average GI&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.10) and Waitoubai (average GI&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.07) with the alleles <italic>TaVp-1Aam</italic> and <italic>TaVp-1Bc</italic> did not carry any of the PHS-resistant allele combinations but also had the higher PHS resistance (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2014</xref>). Interestingly, Suiningtuotuomai and Waitoubai both carry <italic>Tamyb10-Db</italic> amplified with the STS marker <italic>Tamyb10D</italic> associated with PHS tolerance. Therefore, for PHS resistance breeding in wheat, using STS marker combinations (<italic>Vp1A3</italic>, <italic>Vp1B3</italic>, and <italic>Tamyb10D</italic>) will improve the efficiency of selection very much. Because <italic>Vp1A3</italic> and <italic>Vp1B3</italic> are also associated with embryo-imposed dormancy, and <italic>Tamyb10D</italic> is associated with coat-imposed dormancy, the mechanism of seed dormancy can be divided into embryo-imposed and coat-imposed dormancy.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>Y. Wang and X. L. Wang contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <p>The work was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31160247, 31260320), Innovative Research Group Fund of Inner Mongolia Agriculture University (NDPYTD2010-3), and Excellent Young Scientist Foundation of Inner Mongolia Agricultural University of China (2014XYQ-18).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abe</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Urao</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ito</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seki</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shinozaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> AtMYC2 (bHLH) and AtMYB2 (MYB) function as transcriptional activators in abscisic acid signaling</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>63</fpage>
          <lpage>78</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.006130</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12509522?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12509522</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bailey</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McKibbin</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lenton</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holdsworth</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Flintham</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gale</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic map locations for orthologous <italic>Vp1</italic> genes in wheat and rice</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <fpage>281</fpage>
          <lpage>284</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220051069</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bentsink</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jowett</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanhart</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koornneef</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cloning of <italic>DOG1</italic>, a quantitative trait locus controlling seed dormancy in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>17042</fpage>
          <lpage>17047</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0607877103</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17065317?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17065317</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carson</surname>
              <given-names>CB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hattori</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosenkrans</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vasil</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peterson</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McCarty</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The quiescent/colorless alleles of <italic>viviparous1</italic> show that the conserved B3 domain of <italic>Vp1</italic> is not essential for ABA-regulated gene expression in the seed</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>1231</fpage>
          <lpage>1240</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.1997.12061231.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 9450338?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9450338</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feng</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Si</surname>
              <given-names>HQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yin</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>HP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>CX</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Validating a novel allele of <italic>viviparous</italic>-<italic>1</italic> (<italic>Vp</italic>-<italic>1Bf</italic>) associated with high seed dormancy of Chinese wheat landrace, Wanxianbaimaizi</article-title>
          <source>Mol Breeding</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>517</fpage>
          <lpage>525</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-009-9350-3</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>HP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>QX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feng</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Si</surname>
              <given-names>HQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>CX</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rich allelic variations of <italic>Viviparous</italic>-<italic>1A</italic> and their associations with seed dormancy/pre-harvest sprouting of common wheat</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>179</volume>
          <fpage>343</fpage>
          <lpage>353</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-011-0348-7</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chopra</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Athma</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peterson</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Alleles of the maize <italic>P</italic> gene with distinct tissue specificities encode Myb-homologous proteins with C-terminal replacements</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>1149</fpage>
          <lpage>1158</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.8.7.1149</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 8768374?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8768374</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Debeaujon</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leon-Kloosterziel</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koornneef</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Influence of the testa on seed dormancy, germination, and longevity in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <fpage>403</fpage>
          <lpage>414</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.122.2.403</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 10677433?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10677433</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Flintham</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Different genetic components control coat-imposed and embryo-imposed dormancy in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Seed Sci Res</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          <lpage>50</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0960258500000052</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gale KR, Ma W, Zhang W, Rampling L, Hill AS, Appels R, Morris P, Morrel M (2001) Simple high-throughput DNA markers for genotyping in wheat. In: Eastwood R et al. (eds) 10th Australian Wheat Breeding Assembly Proceedings, pp 26&#x2013;31</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Giraudat</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hauge</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valon</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smalle</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parcy</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goodman</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isolation of the <italic>Arabidopsis ABI3</italic> gene by positional cloning</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>1251</fpage>
          <lpage>1261</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.4.10.1251</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 1359917?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1359917</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Groos</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gay</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perretant</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gervais</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bernard</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dedryver</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Charmet</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Study of the relationship between pre-harvest sprouting and grain color by quantitative trait loci analysis in a white &#xD7; red grain bread-wheat cross</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>104</volume>
          <fpage>39</fpage>
          <lpage>47</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220200004</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12579426?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12579426</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gubler</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Millar</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jacobsen</surname>
              <given-names>JV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dormancy release, ABA and pre-harvest sprouting</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>183</fpage>
          <lpage>187</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2005.01.011</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 15752999?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15752999</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hattori</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Terada</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hamasuna</surname>
              <given-names>ST</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sequence and functional analyses of the rice gene homologous to the maize <italic>Vp1</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>805</fpage>
          <lpage>810</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00029862</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 8193305?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8193305</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hattori</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vasil</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosenkrans</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hannah</surname>
              <given-names>LC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McCarty</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vasil</surname>
              <given-names>IK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The <italic>Viviparous-1</italic> gene and abscisic acid activate the <italic>C1</italic> regulatory gene for anthocyanin biosynthesis during seed maturation in maize</article-title>
          <source>Gene Dev</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>609</fpage>
          <lpage>618</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.6.4.609</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 1532784?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1532784</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Himi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maekawa</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miura</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Noda</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of PCR markers for <italic>Tamyb10</italic> related to <italic>R-1</italic>, red grain color gene in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <fpage>1561</fpage>
          <lpage>1576</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-011-1555-2</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21359957?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21359957</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Himi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mares</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yanagisawa</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Noda</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effect of grain color gene (<italic>R</italic>) on grain dormancy and sensitivity of the embryo to abscisic acid (ABA) in wheat</article-title>
          <source>J Exp Bot</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>1569</fpage>
          <lpage>1574</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erf005</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12096095?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12096095</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Himi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Noda</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isolation and location of three homoeologous dihydroflavonol-4-reductase (<italic>DFR</italic>) genes of wheat and their tissue-dependent expression</article-title>
          <source>J Exp Bot</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>365</fpage>
          <lpage>375</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erh046</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 14718498?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14718498</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Himi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Noda</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Red grain color gene (<italic>R</italic>) of wheat is a Myb-type transcription factor</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>143</volume>
          <fpage>239</fpage>
          <lpage>242</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-005-7854-4</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Himi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamashita</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haruyama</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yanagisawa</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maekawa</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taketa</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Ant28</italic> gene for proanthocyanid in synthesis encoding the R2R3 MYB domain protein (Hvmyb10) highly affects grain dormancy in barley</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>188</volume>
          <fpage>141</fpage>
          <lpage>151</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-011-0552-5</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Holton</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cornish</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetics and biochemistry of anthocyanin biosynthesis</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>1071</fpage>
          <lpage>1083</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.7.7.1071</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12242398?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242398</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koornneef</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanhart</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hilhorst</surname>
              <given-names>HWM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karssen</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>In vivo inhibition of seed development and reserve protein accumulation in recombinants of abscisic acid biosynthesis and responsiveness mutants in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <fpage>463</fpage>
          <lpage>469</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.90.2.463</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16666794?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16666794</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ni</surname>
              <given-names>PX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Francki</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hunter</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schibeci</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tarr</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cakir</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bellgard</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lance</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Appels</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genes controlling seed dormancy and pre-harvest sprouting in a rice-wheat-barley comparison</article-title>
          <source>Funct Integr Genomics</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>84</fpage>
          <lpage>93</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10142-004-0104-3</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 14770301?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14770301</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>YX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koornneef</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soppe</surname>
              <given-names>WJJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The absence of histone H2B monoubiquitination in the <italic>Arabidopsis hub1</italic> (<italic>rdo4</italic>) mutant reveals a role for chromatin remodeling in seed dormancy</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>433</fpage>
          <lpage>444</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.106.049221</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17329563?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17329563</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McCarty</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carson</surname>
              <given-names>CB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stinard</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robertson</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular analysis of <italic>Viviparous-1</italic>: an abscisic acid insensitive mutant of maize</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>523</fpage>
          <lpage>532</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.1.5.523</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12359900?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12359900</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McCarty</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hattori</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carson</surname>
              <given-names>CB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vasil</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lazar</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vasil</surname>
              <given-names>IK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The <italic>Viviparous-1</italic> developmental gene of maize encodes a novel transcriptional activator</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>895</fpage>
          <lpage>905</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(91)90436-3</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 1889090?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1889090</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McIntosh RA, Hart GE, Devos KM, Gale MD, Rogers WJ (1998) Catalogue of gene symbols for wheat. In: Proceedings of the ninth international wheat genetics symposium, Canada, University of Saskatchewan Extension Press</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McIntosh RA, Yamazaki Y, Dubcovsky J, Rogers J, Morris CF, Somers DJ, Appels R, Devos KM (2010) Catalogue of Gene Symbols for Wheat National BioResource Project. Committee for the National BioResource Project (NBRP)/KOMUGI, Tokyo. www.shigen.nig.ac.jp/wheat/komugi/genes/symbolClassList.jsp</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McKibbin</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilkinson</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bailey</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Flintham</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrew</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lazzeri</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gale</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lenton</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holdsworth</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transcripts of <italic>Vp</italic>-<italic>1</italic> homeologues are misspliced in modern wheat and ancestral species</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>10203</fpage>
          <lpage>10208</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.152318599</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12119408?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12119408</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mol</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grotewold</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koes</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>How genes paint flowers and seeds</article-title>
          <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>212</fpage>
          <lpage>217</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1360-1385(98)01242-4</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nakamura</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toyama</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isolation of a <italic>VP1</italic> homologue from wheat and analysis of its expression in embryos of dormant and non-dormant cultivars</article-title>
          <source>J Exp Bot</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>875</fpage>
          <lpage>876</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jexbot/52.362.1952</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 11413225?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11413225</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Robertson</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The genetics of vivipary in maize</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>1955</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>745</fpage>
          <lpage>760</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 17247587?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17247587</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stone</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kwong</surname>
              <given-names>LW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yee</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pelletier</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lepiniec</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fischer</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldberg</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harada</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>LEAFY COTYLEDON2</italic> encodes a B3 domain transcription factor that induces embryo development</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <fpage>11806</fpage>
          <lpage>11811</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.201413498</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 11573014?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11573014</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>YW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>HD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dreisigacker</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>XM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shewry</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>LQ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Haplotype analysis of <italic>Viviparous-1</italic> gene in CIMMYT elite bread wheat germplasm</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>186</volume>
          <fpage>25</fpage>
          <lpage>43</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-011-0482-2</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tan</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharp</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>MQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Howes</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetics of grain dormancy in a white wheat</article-title>
          <source>Aust J Agric Res</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>1157</fpage>
          <lpage>1165</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AR06101</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>GP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bi</surname>
              <given-names>HH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>YW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>LQ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization of <italic>Tamyb10</italic> haplotypes and their association with pre-harvest sprouting resistance in a set of Chinese red-grained wheats</article-title>
          <source>Acta Agron Sin</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>984</fpage>
          <lpage>993</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3724/SP.J.1006.2014.00984</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Warner</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kudrna</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spaeth</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dormancy in wheat grain-mutant of Chinese spring wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>
          <source>Seed Sci Res</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>51</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Winkel-Shirley</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Flavonoid biosynthesis. A colorful model for genetics, biochemistry, cell biology, and biotechnology</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>126</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>485</fpage>
          <lpage>493</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.126.2.485</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 11402179?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402179</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>LQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ganal</surname>
              <given-names>MW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shewry</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>ZH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>R&#xF6;der</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of the <italic>Viviparous-1</italic> gene alleles in the European wheat varieties</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>159</volume>
          <fpage>411</fpage>
          <lpage>417</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-007-9576-2</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>LQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>YZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>XM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>ZH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roder</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>HD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shewry</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>What can the <italic>Viviparous-1</italic> gene tell us about wheat pre-harvest sprouting?</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>168</volume>
          <fpage>385</fpage>
          <lpage>394</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-009-9928-1</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>XM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>ZH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>LQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>R&#xF6;der</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Distribution of <italic>Vp-1</italic> alleles in Chinese white-grained landraces, historical, and current wheat cultivars</article-title>
          <source>Cereal Res Comm</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>169</fpage>
          <lpage>177</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1556/CRC.37.2009.2.3</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>XL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>LQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>XM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>XC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>ZH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development and validation of a <italic>Viviparous-1</italic> STS marker for pre-harvest sprouting tolerance in Chinese wheats</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>115</volume>
          <fpage>971</fpage>
          <lpage>980</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-007-0624-z</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17712543?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17712543</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>SX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>YQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meng</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>LQ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization of the rich haplotypes of <italic>Viviparous-1A</italic> in Chinese wheats and development of a novel sequence-tagged site marker for pre-harvest sprouting resistance</article-title>
          <source>Mol Breeding</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>75</fpage>
          <lpage>88</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-013-9935-8</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR44">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miao</surname>
              <given-names>XL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>XC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>ZH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cloning of seed dormancy gene (<italic>TaSdr</italic>) associated with tolerance to pre-harvest sprouting in common wheat and development of a functional marker</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>127</volume>
          <fpage>855</fpage>
          <lpage>866</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-014-2262-6</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24452439?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24452439</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR45">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zheng</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cao</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deng</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soppe</surname>
              <given-names>WJJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel role for histone methyltransferase KYP/SUVH4 in the control of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> primary seed dormancy</article-title>
          <source>New Phytol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>193</volume>
          <fpage>605</fpage>
          <lpage>616</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2011.03969.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22122546?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22122546</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
