<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3719023</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2013.00205</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Microbiology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Original Research Article</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The complete nucleotide sequence of the genome of Barley yellow dwarf virus-RMV reveals it to be a new <italic>Polerovirus</italic> distantly related to other yellow dwarf viruses</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Krueger</surname>
            <given-names>Elizabeth N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Beckett</surname>
            <given-names>Randy J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gray</surname>
            <given-names>Stewart M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Miller</surname>
            <given-names>W. Allen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <sup>1</sup>
        <institution>Plant Pathology and Microbiology Department, Iowa State University</institution>
        <country>Ames, IA, USA</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <sup>2</sup>
        <institution>USDA/ARS and Plant Pathology Department, Cornell University</institution>
        <country>Ithaca, NY, USA</country>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Edited by: IL-Ryong Choi, International Rice Research Institute, Philippines</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Reviewed by: Wei Zhang, Yale University, USA; Armelle Marais, Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique, France</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: W. Allen Miller, Plant Pathology and Microbiology Department, Iowa State University, 351 Bessey Hall, Ames, IA 50011, USA e-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">wamiller@iastate.edu</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn002">
          <p>This article was submitted to Frontiers in Virology, a specialty of Frontiers in Microbiology.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epreprint">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <elocation-id>205</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2013 Krueger, Beckett, Gray and Miller.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in other forums, provided the original authors and source are credited and subject to any copyright notices concerning any third-party graphics etc.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The yellow dwarf viruses (YDVs) of the <italic>Luteoviridae</italic> family represent the most widespread group of cereal viruses worldwide. They include the Barley yellow dwarf viruses (BYDVs) of genus <italic>Luteovirus</italic>, the Cereal yellow dwarf viruses (CYDVs) and Wheat yellow dwarf virus (WYDV) of genus <italic>Polerovirus</italic>. All of these viruses are obligately aphid transmitted and phloem-limited. The first described YDVs (initially all called BYDV) were classified by their most efficient vector. One of these viruses, BYDV-RMV, is transmitted most efficiently by the corn leaf aphid, <italic>Rhopalosiphum maidis</italic>. Here we report the complete 5612 nucleotide sequence of the genomic RNA of a Montana isolate of BYDV-RMV (isolate RMV MTFE87, Genbank accession no. KC921392). The sequence revealed that BYDV-RMV is a polerovirus, but it is quite distantly related to the CYDVs or WYDV, which are very closely related to each other. Nor is BYDV-RMV closely related to any other particular polerovirus. Depending on the gene that is compared, different poleroviruses (none of them a YDV) share the most sequence similarity to BYDV-RMV. Because of its distant relationship to other YDVs, and because it commonly infects maize via its vector, <italic>R. maidis</italic>, we propose that BYDV-RMV be renamed Maize yellow dwarf virus-RMV (MYDV-RMV).</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Luteoviridae phylogenetics</kwd>
        <kwd>P0</kwd>
        <kwd>maize yellow dwarf virus</kwd>
        <kwd>maize virus</kwd>
        <kwd>rhopalosiphum maidis</kwd>
        <kwd>luteovirid</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="6"/>
        <table-count count="2"/>
        <equation-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="76"/>
        <page-count count="11"/>
        <word-count count="8314"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Barley yellow dwarf viruses (BYDVs), Wheat yellow dwarf virus (WYDV), and Cereal yellow dwarf viruses (CYDVs), collectively known as yellow dwarf viruses (YDVs) are among the most economically important causal agents of disease in cereal crops. YDVs have been reported in both agriculturally important cereal crops and non-crop grasses throughout the world (El-Muadhidi et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">2001</xref>; Hawkes and Jones, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">2005</xref>; Hesler et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">2005</xref>; Kumari et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">2006</xref>; Power et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">2011</xref>; Siddiqui et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">2012</xref>; Jaro&#x161;ov&#xE1; et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">2013</xref>). YDVs vectored primarily by the bird cherry-oat aphid, <italic>Rhopalosiphum padi</italic>, can cause yield reductions of 15 to 25% in barley, wheat and oat (Lister and Ranieri, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">1995</xref>). The presence of BYDV correlated with a reduction in yield of winter wheat (Banks et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1995</xref>) as well as wheat and oats (McKirdy et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">2002</xref>). Perry et al. (Perry et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">2000</xref>) found an average of 30% yield loss in affected winter wheat fields. Significant agricultural research efforts are aimed at reducing the impact of the YDVs on the yield of the various crop systems by (i) altering planting time and/or pesticide application regimes to avoid the accumulation of high densities of aphids, (ii) tilling practices, and (iii) developing virus-resistance crop varieties (Chain et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">2005</xref>; Royer et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">2005</xref>; Kennedy and Connery, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">2012</xref>).</p>
      <p>The YDVs are members of the <italic>Luteoviridae</italic> family. All members of the <italic>Luteoviridae</italic> (luteovirids) have linear, positive-sense, 5.5&#x2013;6 kb RNA genomes and are obligately aphid-transmitted in a circulative, persistent manner, with the exception of Pea enation mosaic virus 1 (PEMV1), which is mechanically transmissible in the presence of the umbravirus, PEMV2. The key genes conserved in all luteovirids are the major coat protein (CP) and readthrough domain (RTD) generated by translational readthrough of the CP open reading frame (ORF) stop codon, which provides a long carboxy-terminal extension to the CP (Brault et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">1995</xref>; Brown et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">1996</xref>). The CP and CP-RTD proteins provide the virion structure and aphid transmission properties, and they play a role in virus movement and tissue specificity within the plant (Brault et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">1995</xref>; Chay et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1996a</xref>; Van Den Heuvel et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">1997</xref>; Peter et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">2009</xref>). ORF 4, which is embedded in the CP ORF but in a different reading frame, is also conserved in all luteovirids, except PEMV1. The product of ORF 4 (P4) has features of a cell-to-cell movement protein (Chay et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1996a</xref>; Schmitz et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">1997</xref>), which may confer the property that all Luteoviridae except PEMV1 are confined to the phloem. Because the sequence encoding CP-RTD and P4 is the only part of the genome conserved in all luteovirids with the aforementioned exception of PEMV1, we call this region the <italic>Luteoviridae</italic> block (Miller et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">2002</xref>).</p>
      <p><italic>Luteoviridae</italic> fall into three genera: <italic>Luteovirus, Polerovirus</italic>, and <italic>Enamovirus</italic> (Domier, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">2012</xref>). Outside of the <italic>Luteoviridae</italic> block, the viral genomes are completely different between <italic>Polerovirus</italic> and <italic>Luteovirus</italic> genera. The RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) genes (the key gene used for virus classification) of poleroviruses and the only enamovirus (PEMV1) are similar to each other but quite distantly related to those of genus <italic>Luteovirus</italic> (Miller et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">2002</xref>; Domier, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">2012</xref>). The polero/enamovirus RdRps are more similar to those of genus <italic>Sobemovirus</italic>, which has not been assigned to a family, than to those of genus <italic>Luteovirus</italic>. Moreover, outside of the <italic>Luteoviridae</italic> block, the genomes of genus <italic>Luteovirus</italic> (including the RdRp ORF) are most closely related to those of genus <italic>Dianthovirus</italic> in the <italic>Tombusviridae</italic> (Miller et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">2002</xref>). In particular, the RdRp and translational control signals of genus <italic>Luteovirus</italic> resemble those of the <italic>Tombusviridae</italic> more than they resemble those of the <italic>Polerovirus</italic> or <italic>Enamovirus</italic> genera. Moreover, poleroviruses and the enamovirus contain a genome-linked protein (VPg), and also encode a viral suppressor of gene silencing (VSR) in ORF 0 (Pfeffer et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">2002</xref>; Mangwende et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">2009</xref>). Viruses in genus <italic>Luteovirus</italic>, like the <italic>Tombusviridae</italic>, have neither a VPg nor an ORF 0.</p>
      <p>The original YDVs identified as the causal agents of yellow dwarf disease were all called BYDV and placed into five strains (now considered species) based on serotype, symptomatology and predominant aphid vector species (Rochow, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">1969</xref>; Rochow and Muller, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">1971</xref>). BYDV-RPV, -MAV, -SGV, and -RMV were found to be transmitted most efficiently by <italic>R. padi, Sitobion avenae, Schizaphus graminum</italic> and <italic>R. maidis</italic>, respectively. The most common virus is BYDV-PAV which is transmitted efficiently by <italic>R. padi</italic> and <italic>S. avenae</italic> (Rochow, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">1969</xref>; Rochow and Muller, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">1971</xref>).</p>
      <p>Upon sequencing the complete genomes of some of the BYDV strains, it became clear that BYDV-RPV is a <italic>Polerovirus</italic>, renamed Cereal yellow dwarf (CYDV)-RPV, while BYDV-PAV and BYDV-MAV which have virtually identical RdRp sequences, are in genus <italic>Luteovirus</italic>. More recently discovered YDVs include CYDV-RPS, a CYDV-RPV-like virus that causes cork screw-shaped leaves and leaf notching in wheat; the former BYDV-GPV (now Wheat yellow dwarf virus-GPV (WYDV-GPV) (Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">2009</xref>); and BYDV-PAS, a severe BYDV-PAV-like virus that breaks resistance in oat (Chay et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">1996b</xref>).</p>
      <p>In addition to the BYDVs, the genus <italic>Luteovirus</italic> includes Bean leafroll virus (BLRV), Soybean dwarf virus (SbDV), and (unofficially) Rose spring dwarf-associated virus (RSDaV). In addition to the CYDVs, the <italic>Polerovirus</italic> genus includes about two dozen viruses of diverse crops. Subsequently additional species have been identified in China, such as BYDV-GAV, and WYDV-GPV, transmitted primarily by <italic>S. graminum</italic> and <italic>S. avenae</italic>, and <italic>S. graminum</italic> and <italic>R. padi</italic>, respectively, and BYDV-PAV-CN which is transmitted efficiently by all three aphid species (Jin et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">2004</xref>; Liu et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">2007</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">2009</xref>). BYDV-GAV is very similar to BYDV-MAV (Jin et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">2004</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">2009</xref>), WYDV-GPV is closely related to CYDV-RPV (Lucio-Zavaleta et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2001</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">2009</xref>), while BYDV-PAV-CN is highly diverged from other BYDVs (Liu et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">2007</xref>). It should be noted that the vector specificity of the YDVs can vary by isolate within a virus species, by genotype of an aphid species, or under different environmental conditions (Lucio-Zavaleta et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2001</xref>). Thus, the YDVs are now classified by nucleotide sequence identity and genome organization, rather than by the most efficient aphid vector.</p>
      <p>Until this report, the complete BYDV-RMV genome had not been sequenced, only the nucleotide region encoding the coat protein had been reported (Geske et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">1996</xref>; Domier et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">1997</xref>). RMV is the only BYDV transmitted efficiently by <italic>R. maidis</italic>, the corn leaf aphid. Hence it infects maize (Itnyre et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">1999a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">b</xref>). Moreover, maize serves as a reservoir for BYDV-RMV from which it can be transmitted to nearby wheat plots where stunting and yield losses ensue (Brown et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">1984</xref>). BYDVs can reduce sweet corn yield dramatically by causing incomplete ear filling which can render entire harvests unmarketable (Beuve et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">1999</xref>; Itnyre et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">1999b</xref>). BYDV-RMV virions are difficult to purify, hence it has been little studied. Here, we report the first complete sequence of a BYDV-RMV genome. The genome organization and sequence of the RMV MTFE87 isolate indicates that BYDV-RMV is a member of genus <italic>Polerovirus</italic>, but it is not closely related to the CYDVs, WYDV or any other polerovirus. Therefore, we submit that BYDV-RMV is a unique species, with the proposed new name Maize yellow dwarf virus (MYDV).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Biological characterization</title>
        <p>The RMV MTFE87 isolate was obtained from Dr. T. W. Carroll, Montana State University in 1990. It was originally collected from an infected wheat plant growing on the Fort Ellis Experiment Station of Montana State University in 1987. The isolate has been continually propagated in Coast Black oats by regular transfer to new plants using <italic>R. maidis.</italic> Serological and aphid transmission properties of RMV MTFE87 were determined using a collection of antibodies to each of the YDV strains (Rochow and Carmichael, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">1979</xref>; Webby and Lister, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">1992</xref>). Double antibody sandwich (DAS) ELISA was carried out as described previously (Brumfield et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">1992</xref>). Five different aphid species were used to determine the vector specificity of the RMV MTFE87 isolate. <italic>R. maidis, R. padi, S. avenae, S. graminum</italic> were previously described (Rochow and Carmichael, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">1979</xref>; Power and Gray, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">1995</xref>) and have been maintained as clonal lineages in the laboratory since their collection. The <italic>Metapalophium dirhodum</italic> colony was a gift from Fred Gildow (Gildow, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">1993</xref>) and has been maintained in the laboratory in Ithaca, NY since 1993. Fourth instar or adult apterous aphids were allowed a 36&#x2013;48 h acquisition access period on detached leaves of Coast Black oat plants infected with RMV MTFE87 4&#x2013;5 weeks previously. Ten aphids were subsequently transferred to each of eight plants for a 72 h inoculation access period. Plants were fumigated and grown in a greenhouse and observed for symptoms for 3&#x2013;4 weeks and tested using DAS-ELISA.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Virus purification and viral RNA extraction</title>
        <p>Virions were extracted from infected Coast Black oat plants as described previously (Hammond et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">1983</xref>; Webby and Lister, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">1992</xref>). Viral RNA was extracted using the hot phenol method. All centrifugation was at 13,200 rpm (16,100 &#xD7; <italic>g</italic>) in a 24 &#xD7; 1.5 ml tube rotor in an Eppendorf 5415R centrifuge. Briefly: purified virions were added to 3 volumes of extraction buffer yielding a final concentration of 167 mM Tris base (pH 8.5), 1% SDS, and 12.5 mM EDTA (all reagents from Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO). Hot (65&#xB0;C) phenol was then added equal to the total volume, and after vortexing, the solution was incubated at 65&#xB0;C for 15 min. The solution was vortexed again, centrifuged, and the aqueous phase saved. The phenol phase was back extracted using the above extraction buffer lacking SDS. After vortexing and centrifugation, the second aqueous phase was combined with the first. The combined aqueous phases were then extracted twice with equal volumes of phenol/chloroform/isoamyl alcohol (25:24:1). The RNA was precipitated at &#x2212;20&#xB0;C after adding 1/15 volume 3M sodium acetate (pH 5.5) and 2.5 volumes 95% ethanol. After centrifugation, the pellet was washed in 70% ethanol, vacuum dried and dissolved in a small volume of nuclease-free water.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Amplification of genome downstream of the viral coat protein (CP)</title>
        <p>The 3&#x2032; terminal region (1788 base pairs) of RMV MTFE87 was amplified and prepared for cloning using ligated-anchor PCR (LA-PCR) according to published protocols (Beckett and Miller, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2007</xref>). LA-PCR was performed on purified RMV MTFE87 viral RNA (500 ng). An anchor oligomer (5&#x2032;-CTATAGTGTCACCTAAATGCGTGAAGAGCCTCCTACCAGCTGCTCCTATG-3&#x2032;) was ligated directly to the 3&#x2032; end of the viral RNA. PCR amplification was conducted using an upstream primer (5&#x2032;-AGATCACAAAAGTCATACTGGAGTTCATCT-3&#x2032;) homologous to the viral coat protein (CP) and a downstream primer (5&#x2032;-CATAGGAGCAGCTGGTAGGAGGCTCTTC-3&#x2032;) complementary to the anchor.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Amplification of genome upstream of the viral coat protein</title>
        <p>Overlapping genomic sections extending from the viral CP to the 5&#x2032; end of the genome were amplified and prepared for cloning using the SMART&#x2122; RACE cDNA Amplification Kit (Clontech) according to manufacturer's instructions. The following viral-specific primers were used in conjunction with the kit to walk step-by-step to the 5&#x2032; end of the genome: 5&#x2032;-ATGCGAGGGTGCTGAGCTTGTTGTG-3&#x2032;, 5&#x2032;-GGATGTCATCCTCATCATCAGCCCAGTTTC-3&#x2032;, 5&#x2032;-AGCCGGAGTTGGAAGCGTTTATAGC-3&#x2032;.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Cloning and sequencing of viral genome fragments</title>
        <p>PCR amplified genome fragments were cloned using the Zero Blunt&#xAE; TOPO&#xAE; PCR Cloning Kit (Invitrogen) according to manufacturer's instructions. Chimeric plasmids were purified from positive transformants. The cloned viral fragments were sequenced either by primer-walking or by 96-well sequencing on an ABI 3730 &#xD7; l DNA Analyzer at the ISU DNA Sequencing Facility. Plasmid template was transposon tagged in preparation for sequencing using the Template Generation System&#x2122; II (Finnzymes) according to manufacturer's instructions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Sequence assembly and analysis</title>
        <p>The Phred, Phrap, and Consed software programs were used in tandem to process and assemble raw sequencing reads for all clones which were sequenced in a 96-well plate format (Ewing and Green, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">1998</xref>; Gordon et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">1998</xref>). Vector NTI&#xAE; (Invitrogen) was used to assemble the sequence reads from primer-walked clones. The complete nucleotide sequence of the RMV MTFE87 genome, as well as the amino acid sequences of all six major proteins, were compared with a range of other fully sequenced luteovirids (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The sequences were organized within the JalView alignment editor, version 2.4 (Clamp et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">2004</xref>). The full length genomes were aligned with Clustal W (Thompson et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">1994</xref>). The amino acid sequences were aligned using the MUSCLE algorithm (Edgar, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">2004</xref>). Phylogenetic relationships were inferred from these alignments using the Neighbor-Joining method with 1000 replicates for bootstrapping in the MEGA4 (Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis version 4.0) software package (Tamura et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">2007</xref>). Sequence identity was determined via the Needleman-Wunsch global alignment in the EMBOSS Pairwise Alignment Algorithms, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/emboss/align/index.html">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/emboss/align/index.html.</ext-link></p>
        <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Virus abbreviations and GenBank accession numbers for viruses used for sequence comparisons in this study</bold>.</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Virus name</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Abbreviation</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Accession Number</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barley yellow dwarf virus&#x2014;GAV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BYDV-GAV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_004666</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barley yellow dwarf virus&#x2014;MAV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BYDV-MAV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_003680</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barley yellow dwarf virus&#x2014;PAS</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BYDV-PAS</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_002160</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barley yellow dwarf virus&#x2014;PAV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BYDV-PAV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_004750</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bean leafroll virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BLRV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_003369</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beet chlorosis virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BChV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_002766</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beet mild yellowing virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMYV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_003491</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beet western yellows virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BWYV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_004756</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carrot red leaf virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CtRLV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_006265</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cereal yellow dwarf virus&#x2014;RPS</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CYDV-RPS</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_002198</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cereal yellow dwarf virus&#x2014;RPV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CYDV-RPV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_004751</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chickpea chlorotic stunt virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ChCSV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_008249</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cucurbit aphid-borne yellows virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CABYV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_003688</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melon aphid-borne yellows virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MABYV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_010809</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pea enation mosaic virus 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEMV1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_003629</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potato leafroll virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLRV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_001747</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barley yellow dwarf virus-RMV (proposed new name: Maize yellow dwarf virus-RMV)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BYDV-RMV (MYDV-RMV)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KC921392</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rose spring dwarf-associated virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSDaV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_010806</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean dwarf virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SbDV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_003056</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sugarcane yellow leaf virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ScYLV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_000874</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tobacco vein distorting virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TVDV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_010732</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turnip yellows virus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TuYV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_003431</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat yellow dwarf virus&#x2014;GPV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WYDV-GPV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC_012931</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Biological characterization of the RMV MTFE87 isolate</title>
        <p>BYDV-RMV MTFE87 reacted in DAS-ELISA with antibodies to BYDV-RMV, but not to antibodies made against the other viruses (BYDV-PAV, BYDV-MAV, BYDV-SGV or CYDV-RPV). RMV MTFE87 was transmitted efficiently by <italic>R. maidis</italic> to eight of eight plants, to a lesser extent by <italic>S. graminum</italic> (4/8) and <italic>R. padi</italic> (1/8) and was not transmitted by <italic>Metapalophium dirhodum</italic> or <italic>S. avenae</italic> (both 0/8) FE87 was passaged six times in Coast Black oats using 10 <italic>R. maidis</italic> or <italic>S. graminum</italic> apterous adults for each passage. Transmission efficiency remained at 100% for <italic>R. maidis</italic> and increased to 95% for <italic>S. graminum</italic> by the sixth serial passage. The virus continued to react only with anti-BYDV-RMV antibodies following all of the serial passages by either aphid. Symptoms induced by RMV MTFE87 isolate were more severe on oat and wheat than the type RMV isolate from NY (RMV-NY) (Rochow and Norman, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">1961</xref>). The RMV-NY isolate rarely induces visible symptoms in wheat and many cultivars of oat. Symptoms in Coast Black oat are mild chlorosis or reddening of mature leaf tips, whereas the RMV MTFE87 isolate induced yellowing or reddening of flag leaves in wheat, noticeable stunting of the plants and incomplete filling of heads. Oat plants infected with RMV MTFE87 were severely stunted, with reddening and necrosis of leaves and incomplete formation of seed. The severe symptoms in oat and wheat are typical of RMV isolates collected in Montana (Brumfield et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">1992</xref>) in contrast to RMV isolates collected in NY (Lucio-Zavaleta et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2001</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Genome organization of BYDV-RMV</title>
        <p>The nucleotide sequence of RMV MTFE87 genomic RNA was found to be 5612 nt long, encoding six ORFs (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The 5&#x2032; and 3&#x2032; untranslated regions (UTRs) are 54 and 158 nt long, respectively, and the only intergenic region spans nucleotides 3322&#x2013;3515. The arrangement and sequences of ORFs resemble those of poleroviruses (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Based on sequence comparisons with poleroviruses, the ORFs encode a putative viral suppressor of silencing (VSR, ORF 0), serine protease and VPg (both in ORF 1), RdRp (ORF 2), coat protein (ORF 3), putative movement protein (ORF 4, which overlaps with ORF 3), and the CP readthrough domain (ORF 5) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). A feature found in only three other luteovirids&#x2014;Chickpea chlorotic stunt virus (ChCSV), Melon aphid-borne yellows virus (MABYV), and Cucurbit aphid-borne yellows virus (CABYV), is that ORF 4 of BYDV-RMV extends beyond the end of ORF 3, in this case by 4 nt. In all other <italic>Luteoviridae</italic>, the stop codon of ORF 4 is upstream of the CP ORF stop codon.</p>
        <fig id="F1" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Genome organization of BYDV-RMV.</bold> Numbers in small font indicate genomic positions of each ORF (numbered in large font) and the position of the predicted subgenomic RNA 5&#x2032; end and the readthrough sequence. VPg, viral genome-linked protein; VSR, putative viral suppressor of RNA silencing; RdRp, RNA-dependent RNA polymerase; CP, coat protein; MP, movement protein; RTD, readthrough domain; fs, site of &#x2212;1 ribosomal frameshift; sgRNA 5&#x2032; end, predicted 5&#x2032; end of subgenomic RNA1 at nt 3309; (CCXXXX)<sub>12</sub>, repeat motif required for readthrough of the CP ORF stop codon at nts 4131&#x2013;4199.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-04-00205-g0001"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="T2" position="float">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Sequence identity (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref> of BYDV-RMV proteins to those of other luteovirids</bold>.</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Genus</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Virus<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>P0</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>P1</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>P2</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>P3</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>P4</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>P5</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Luteovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BLRV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Luteovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BYDV-GAV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Luteovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BYDV-MAV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Luteovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BYDV-PAS</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Luteovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BYDV-PAV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Luteovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSDaV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Luteovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SbDV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BChV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMYV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BWYV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CABYV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ChCSV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CtRLV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CYDV-RPS</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CYDV-RPV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MABYV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLRV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ScYLV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TuYV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TVDV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Polerovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WYDV-GPV</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Enamovirus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEMV1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="TN1">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>The identity of the sequences to BYDV-RMV was determined with the EMBOSS Needle global pairwise alignment algorithm. Molecular weights for the BYDV-RMV proteins were estimated using the ExPASy Server (Gasteiger et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">2003</xref>).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="TN2">
              <label>b</label>
              <p>NA, not applicable.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Whole genome alignments of <italic>Luteoviridae</italic></title>
        <p>The full-length luteovirid genomes found in GenBank REFSEQ database were aligned by the neighbor-joining method using MEGA4 (Tamura et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">2007</xref>) with 1000 replications (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). BYDV-RMV was grouped with the <italic>Polerovirus</italic> genus and in 100% of the replicates was closest to, but highly distinct from, Sugarcane yellow leaf virus (ScYLV). The BYDV-RMV/ScYLV branch was separated deeply from the CYDV and WYDV grouping indicating that BYDV-RMV is more closely related to other poleroviruses than it is to CYDVs and WYDV. As expected in this comparison, genus <italic>Luteovirus</italic> was well-separated from the <italic>Polerovirus</italic> and <italic>Enamovirus</italic> groups.</p>
        <fig id="F2" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Neighbor-joining tree of Clustal W-aligned whole genome sequences of luteovirids generated in the MEGA 4 software package.</bold> Numbers representing bootstrap values when greater than 50% for 1000 replicates are shown.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-04-00205-g0002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Protein alignments and analyses of RMV MTFE87 and selected luteovirids</title>
        <p>The amino acid sequences of selected polerovirus and enamovirus proteins were aligned using the MUSCLE (Edgar, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">2004</xref>) algorithm and from these alignments we created neighbor-joining trees via the MEGA4 software package (Tamura et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">2007</xref>). P0 of RMV MTFE87 is separated readily from the CYDV/WYDV group and is most closely related to the Beet chlorosis virus (BChV)/Turnip yellows virus (TuYV) branch (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). The CYDV-RPS, CYDV-RPV, and WYDV group separates from the remainder of the sequences in 99% of the bootstrap replicates.</p>
        <fig id="F3" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Analysis of P0 amino acid sequences. (A)</bold> Amino acid sequences of the P0s for viruses in the <italic>Polereovirus</italic> and <italic>Enamovirus</italic> genera were aligned with the MUSCLE algorithm within JalView. The aligned sequences were used for inferring evolutionary relationships using the Neighbor-Joining method. The resultant tree, drawn to scale, is shown with the percentage (greater than 50% only) of 1000 bootstrap replicates. <bold>(B)</bold> A portion of the MUSCLE aligned P0 showing the conserved F-box domain LPxxL/I among the <italic>Polerovirus</italic> members. Accession numbers of viral genome sequences used in the alignment are in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-04-00205-g0003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>P1 of poleroviruses is a polyprotein that is cleaved by its internal protease into functional polypeptides that include the N terminus, the protease, the VPg, and a downstream RNA-binding fragment of unknown function (Pr&#xFC;fer et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">2006</xref>; Li et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">2000</xref>). The key amino acids of the catalytic triad in the protease (Li et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">2000</xref>) are at positions 272, 306 and 373 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). Based on the known N-termini of the Potato leafroll virus (PLRV) VPg (Van Der Wilk et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">1997b</xref>) and the enamovirus PEMV1 (Wobus et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">1998</xref>), the N-terminus of the VPg of RMV MTFE87 is predicted to be amino acid T417 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). RMV MTFE87 P1 is most closely related to P1 of TuYV and TVDV, distinct from the CYDV/WYDV group linked in 100% of the bootstrap replicates (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="F4" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Analysis of P1 amino acid sequences. (A)</bold> Amino acid sequences of P1 were aligned with the MUSCLE algorithm within JalView. The region with the protease domain is shown. Shaded boxes indicated conserved amino acids. Asterisks indicate amino acids of the catalytic triad in the protease active site. VPg and arrow indicate predicted proteolytic cleavage site that forms the C-terminus of the protease and the N-terminus of the VPg. <bold>(B)</bold> The MUSCLE aligned P1s for virus in the <italic>Polerovirus</italic> and <italic>Enamovirus</italic> genera were used for inferring evolutionary relationships using the Neighbor-Joining method. The resultant tree, drawn to scale, is shown with the percentage (greater than 50% only) of 1000 bootstrap replicates.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-04-00205-g0004"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In all studied poleroviruses, P2, which encodes the active site of the RdRp, is expressed only as a fusion with P1, as it is translated by frameshifting of ribosomes from ORF 1 to ORF 2 in the region of overlap (Pr&#xFC;fer et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">1992</xref>; Kujawa et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">1993</xref>; Miller and Giedroc, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">2010</xref>). The CYDV/WYDV RdRp (P2) sequences clustered tightly in 100% of the replicates, but they all were strikingly distinct from RMV MTFE87 P2, which groups rather distantly with CtRLV (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="F5" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Phylogenetic relationships of four luteoviral proteins.</bold> For each protein, the amino acid sequences were aligned using the MUSCLE algorithm in the JalView program and subsequently used to generate a Neighbor-Joining tree with the percentage of 1000 bootstrap replicates reported on a drawn-to-scale tree. Phylogenetic trees of: <bold>(A)</bold> RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (P2), <bold>(B)</bold> putative movement protein of P4, <bold>(C)</bold> the major coat protein (P3), and <bold>(D)</bold> the readthrough domain (P5) are shown.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-04-00205-g0005"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The relationship of the RMV MTFE87 CP to that of other poleroviruses is not well resolved. The CP sequences of PEMV1 (<italic>Enamovirus</italic>), and ScYLV are distinct from all of the remaining <italic>Polerovirus</italic> members, while 57 and 52% of bootstrap replicates support BYDV-RMV separation from TVDV and the large group of the remaining poleroviruses, respectively. But the close relatedness of the CYDV/WYDV CP to each other is present in 98% of the bootstrap replicates (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>).</p>
        <p>The P4 proteins of TVDV and ScYLV are discretely separated from the remaining poleroviruses. BYDV-RMV and CtRLV form an intermediate between two larger clusters, one housing PLRV and CYDV/WYDV group while the other contains all others used in our study (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). The readthrough domain, P5, is expressed as a fusion with the CP by leaky scanning through the amber stop codon of P3 (Brault et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">1995</xref>; Brown et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">1996</xref>). For the RTD, the <italic>Polerovirus</italic> and <italic>Enamovirus</italic> members branch into two distinct clades. RMV MTFE87 P5 groups with Sugarcane yellow leaf virus (ScYLV), CABYV, MABYV, ChCSV and PEMV1, in one clade. The remaining poleroviruses are in the other major clade including the CYDV/WYDV group present in 100% of bootstrap replicates (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Proteins of the <italic>Luteoviridae</italic></title>
        <p>P0 of RMV MTFE87 is a putative viral suppressor of RNA silencing (VSR) because it shares homology with other poleroviruses in which P0 is a VSR. P0 of TuYV (formerly Beet western yellows virus-FL, BWYV-FL), PLRV and PEMV1 has been shown to suppress the host plant's defensive posttranscriptional gene silencing (PTGS) system (Pfeffer et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">2002</xref>; Mangwende et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">2009</xref>; Fusaro et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">2012</xref>) by inducing the host to degrade the key <italic>Argonaute 1</italic> (AGO1) protein (Baumberger et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2007</xref>; Bortolamiol et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2007</xref>). The F-box domain, LPxxL/I, which is conserved in the otherwise highly variable P0 of all luteovirids including BYDV-RMV (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>), is required for VSR activity, as it recruits proteins to form the E3 ubiquitin ligase activity that ubiquitylates AGO1, which leads to its degradation (Pazhouhandeh et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">2006</xref>; Bortolamiol et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2007</xref>) by the autophagy pathway (Derrien et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">2012</xref>). Moreover, transgenic expression of ORF0 of PLRV in potatoes, but not <italic>Nicotiana</italic>, is sufficient to produce virus-like symptoms (Van Der Wilk et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">1997a</xref>). However, not all P0 proteins show VSR activity, for example those of Beet chlorosis virus (BChV) and some strains of Beet mild yellowing virus (BMYV) (Kozlowska-Makulska et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33a">2010</xref>) and CYDV-RPV (V&#xE9;ronique Ziegler-Graff, personal communication) do not display VSR activity in standard assays. Thus, VSR function may vary depending on the virus strain&#x2013;host species interaction.</p>
        <p>The putative movement proteins of BYDV (Chay et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1996a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">b</xref>) and PLRV (Lee et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">2002</xref>) encoded by ORF 4 have been shown to allow host-dependent movement of the virus throughout the plant. P4 of BYDV-GAV was reported to contain an RNA-binding motif at its C-terminus with four arginine residues (Xia et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">2008</xref>). The P4 proteins of other luteovirids were also shown to contain multiple arginine residues. In line with these observations, there are four arginine residues within the C-terminal 11 amino acids of the RMV P4 sequence.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Modular evolution of <italic>Luteoviridae</italic></title>
        <p>As has been apparent since the first luteoviruses were sequenced, it is clear that luteovirid genes evolve at different rates. Note the striking lack of sequence homology among the P0 proteins (other than the F-box motif) which have around 15&#x2013;23% homology to that of RMV MTFE87 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). This high sequence divergence of VSRs relative to other ORFs in related viruses occurs in other virus families with VSRs that act by entirely different mechanisms (Nayak et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">2010</xref>). We speculate that VSRs are at the forefront of the evolutionary back-and-forth between virus and host immune system, which leads to rapid change, as the VSR must constantly out-evolve the host's defenses. In contrast, P2 is more conserved with 51&#x2013;62% sequence identity among all of the members of the genus <italic>Polerovirus</italic>. The CPs of other poleroviruses have 40&#x2013;60% sequence identity to the RMV MTFE87 CP, while the overlapping P4s have significantly less similarity (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). This suggests that base changes in the ORF 3/4 sequence that alter the meaning of ORF 4 codons are more often tolerated than those that alter the amino acid sequence of the CP. Overall, the lack of high similarity of any luteovirid ORF with those of RMV MTFE87 emphasizes its uniqueness as a virus.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>CIS-acting signals</title>
        <p>Cis acting sequences required for polerovirus translation, subgenomic mRNA (sgRNA) transcription and RNA synthesis have been identified in PLRV and others. The genomes of all poleroviruses begins with the sequence ACAAAA. Similarly, where known, the 5&#x2032; end of the sgRNA of the poleroviruses begins with ACAAAA (Miller and Mayo, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">1991</xref>). This leads us to predict that the sgRNA required for translation of BYDV-RMV ORFs 3, 4, and 5 begins at position <sub>3309</sub>ACAAAA<sub>3314</sub>. This is 202 nt upstream of the CP ORF that starts at position 3516, giving an sgRNA leader sequence similar to the 212 nt leader of PLRV sgRNA1.</p>
        <p>A 40 nt stem-loop containing a bulged adenosine, ending 3 nt upstream of the 3&#x2032; end of the genome, was shown to be required for initiation of CYDV-RPV negative strand synthesis (Osman et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">2006</xref>). This stem-loop is conserved in CYDV-RPS and WYDV, which are very closely related to CYDV-RPV (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). In contrast, RMV MTFE87 has a different predicted stem-loop that is 39 nt long with a much larger loop and a bulged guanosine (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). Like all other poleroviruses (except WYDV), the two bases at the 3&#x2032; end of the RMV MTFE87 genome are GU (bold, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). Thus, the first two bases incorporated by the RdRp initiating synthesis of either strand are AC. Surprisingly, WYDV is reported to contain an 11 nt A-rich tract at the 3&#x2032; end downstream of the GU (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). We speculate that this is either sequence added during 3&#x2032; RACE, or sequence of a defective WYDV genome. The distinct 3&#x2032; stem-loop of RMV MTFE87 further supports that above phylogenetic comparisons about the un-CYDV-like nature of BYDV-RMV.</p>
        <fig id="F6" position="float">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Predicted secondary structures in BYDV-RMV RNA. (A)</bold> Stem-loop at the 3&#x2032; terminus of CYDV-RPV genome as determined by Osman et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">2006</xref>), flanked by base differences in CYDV-RPS (left) and WYDV (right) which show covariations in base pairing that maintain secondary structure. Conserved 3&#x2032; terminal bases, GU are shown in bold. Eleven extra bases at the 3&#x2032; end of the WYDV genome, not present in any other polerovirus, are shown below the CYDV-RPV sequence in underlined text. The proposed secondary structure of the 3&#x2032; end of the BYDV-RMV genome was predicted using Mfold (Zuker, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">2003</xref>). Base numbering (negative) is from the 3&#x2032; end of the genomes. <bold>(B)</bold> Predicted (BYDV-RMV) and known (PEMV1 and TuYV) (Su et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">1999</xref>; Nixon et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">2002</xref>; Miller and Giedroc, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">2010</xref>) tertiary structures of pseudoknots downstream of the frameshift sites (boxed). Italics indicate base numbers in the genome. Other numbering is the position in the fragment used for nmr (except BYDV-RMV where the number allows comparison with the other structures). Short curved lines indicate phosphodiester backbone as necessary for two-dimensional rendering. Bold, dashed lines indicate non-Watson-Crick interactions between bases. <sup>+</sup>indicated protonated cytidine that participates in base triples. Due to the recent change of the name of the BWYV isolate used in previous structural studies (Domier, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">2012</xref>) it is now indicated by the new name, TuYV.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-04-00205-g0006"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We also identified probable translational control sequences. In all <italic>Luteoviridae</italic>, ORF2 encoding the active site of the RdRp is translated via ribosomal frameshifting at a shifty heptanucleotide, fitting the motif XXXYYYZ (where X is any base, Y is A or U, and Z is any base except G), in the region of ORF1&#x2013;ORF2 overlap. Seven nt downstream of this site, the polero- and enamovirus genomes fold into a small, compact pseudoknot that pauses the ribosome to facilitate frameshifting (Su et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">1999</xref>; Nixon et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">2002</xref>; Miller and Giedroc, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">2010</xref>). Indeed, in the region of ORF1&#x2013;ORF2 overlap in the RMV MTFE87 genome, we found the shifty heptanucleotide <sub>1603</sub>GGGAAAC<sub>1609</sub>, followed by a predicted pseudoknot that spans bases 1616&#x2013;1643 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). This pseudoknot closely resembles those of other poleroviruses and the enamovirus, the structures of which have been determined at high resolution by NMR (Su et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">1999</xref>; Nixon et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">2002</xref>). The Watson&#x2013;Crick helices of the RMV MTFE87 pseudoknot, CGCGG:CCGCG and CCG:CGG are identical to those in TuYV, but the helical junction region includes a predicted C+-AU triplet that resembles the junction in the PEMV1 pseudoknot (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>).</p>
        <p>The sequence required for translational readthrough of the CP ORF stop codon also resembles those of other <italic>Luteoviridae</italic>. Readthrough of the BYDV-PAV CP ORF stop codon was shown to require at least five repeats of the sequence CCXXXX, where X is any base, beginning about 16&#x2013;22 nt downstream of the stop codon (Brown et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">1996</xref>). Indeed, in the RMV MTFE87 genome, a tract of 12 CCXXXX repeats starting at nt 4131 begins 16 nt downstream of the CP ORF stop codon (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). This codes for an amino acid sequence of alternating proline residues, which is a likely spacer to permit separate folding of the CP and RTD protein domains. In summary, BYDV-RMV has all the known cis-acting signals of a polerovirus to control translation of viral proteins.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Proposed name change of BYDV-RMV to maize yellow dwarf virus-RMV</title>
        <p>The RMV MTFE87 sequence shows that the viruses once called BYDV are even more diverse than previously thought. The sequence also shows clearly that BYDV-RMV is not in genus <italic>Luteovirus</italic>, to which all other sequenced viruses currently called BYDV are assigned. Nor is it a type of CYDV or WYDV. Therefore, we propose to change the name of BYDV-RMV to Maize yellow dwarf virus-RMV (MYDV-RMV) (Miller et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">2013</xref>). This name (1) acknowledges that the virus is clearly a new species (2) is consistent with observations that BYDV-RMV often infects maize (Brown et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">1984</xref>; Beuve et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">1999</xref>; Itnyre et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">1999a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">b</xref>), (3) retains the RMV notation for the predominant vector, <italic>R. maidis</italic> (although <italic>S. graminum</italic> and <italic>R. padi</italic> can also be efficient vectors, particularly in the western United States), and (4) retains the YDV descriptor long used for luteovirids that infect cereals.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Conflict of interest statement</title>
        <p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This journal paper of the Iowa Agriculture and Home Economics Experiment Station, Ames, Iowa, Project No. IOW06664, was supported by National Science Foundation grant number DEB&#x2013;0843140 and USDA National Research Initiative grant no. 2004-35600-14227. The authors thank Dai Nguyen for administrative support, Dawn Smith for assistance with the aphid transmission experiments, and V&#xE9;ronique Ziegler-Graff for helpful comments on this manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bariana</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Effects of barley yellow dwarf virus on the yield of winter wheat</article-title>. <source>Aust. J. Agri. Res</source>. <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>935</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AR9950935</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baumberger</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>C.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lie</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Havecker</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baulcombe</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The Polerovirus silencing suppressor P0 targets ARGONAUTE proteins for degradation</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol</source>. <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1609</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1614</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2007.08.039</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17869110?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17869110</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beckett</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Rapid full-length cloning of non-polyadenylated RNA virus genomes</article-title>, in <source>Current Protocols in Microbiology</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Coico</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalik</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quarles</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>; <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons, Inc</publisher-name>), 16F.3.1&#x2013;16F.3.18.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beuve</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Na&#xEF;bo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Foulgocq</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapierre</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Irrigated hybrid maize crop yield losses due to barley yellow dwarf virus-PAV luteovirus</article-title>. <source>Crop. Sci</source>. <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>1830</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1834</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1999.3961830x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bortolamiol</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pazhouhandeh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrocco</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geschik</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegler-Graff</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The polerovirus F Box protein P0 targets ARGONAUTE1 to suppress RNA silencing</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol</source>. <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1615</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1621</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2007.07.061</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17869109?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17869109</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brault</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Den Heuvel</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbeek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegler-Graff</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reutenauer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrbach</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Aphid transmission of beet western yellows luteovirus requires the minor capsid read-through protein P74</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>650</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>659</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 7882968?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7882968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinesh-Kumar</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Local and distant sequences are required for efficient readthrough of the barley yellow dwarf virus PAV coat protein gene stop codon</article-title>. <source>J. Virol</source>. <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>5884</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5892</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8709208?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8709208</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyatt</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazelwood</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Irrigated corn as a source of barley yellow dwarf virus and vector in eastern Washington</article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source>
<volume>74</volume>, <fpage>46</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>49</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/Phyto-74-46</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brumfield</surname><given-names>S. K. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Biological and serological characterization of three Montana RMV-like isolates of barley yellow dwarf virus</article-title>. <source>Plant Dis</source>. <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>39</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PD-76-0033</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chain</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riault</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trottet</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacquot</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Analysis of accumulation patterns of barley yellow dwarf virus-PAV (BYDV-PAV) in two resistant wheat lines</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Plant Pathol</source>. <volume>113</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>355</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10658-005-7966-7</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chay</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunasinge</surname><given-names>U. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinesh-Kumar</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996a</year>). <article-title>Aphid transmission and systemic plant infection determinants of barley yellow dwarf luteovirus-PAV are contained in the coat protein readthrough domain and 17-kDa protein, respectively</article-title>. <source>Virology</source>
<volume>219</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>65</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/viro.1996.0222</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8623554?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8623554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chay</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996b</year>). <article-title>Diversity among isolates within the PAV serotype of barley yellow dwarf virus</article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source>
<volume>86</volume>, <fpage>370</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>377</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/Phyto-86-370</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18944888?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clamp</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The jalview java alignment editor</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>426</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>427</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btg430</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14960472?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14960472</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derrien</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumberger</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schepetilnikov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Viotti</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Cillia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegler-Graff</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Degradation of the antiviral component ARGONAUTE1 by the autophagy pathway</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source>. <volume>109</volume>, <fpage>15942</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>15946</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1209487109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23019378?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23019378</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domier</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Family - Luteoviridae</article-title>, in <source>Virus Taxonomy</source>, <italic>9th Edn</italic>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Andrew</surname><given-names>M. Q. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carstens</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>San Diego, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>), <fpage>1045</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1053</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domier</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukasheva</surname><given-names>L. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>D'arcy</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Coat protein sequence of RMV-like strains of barley yellow dwarf virus separate them from other luteoviruses</article-title>. <source>Intervirology</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>2</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 7928284?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7928284</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>1792</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1797</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh340</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15034147?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Muadhidi</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makkouk</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myasser</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murad</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Survey for legume and cereal viruses in Iraq</article-title>. <source>Phytopathol. Mediterr</source>. <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>224</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>233</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Base-calling of automated sequencer traces using phred. II. error probabilities</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>186</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>194</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 9521922?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9521922</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fusaro</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Correa</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakasugi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawchuk</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasline</surname><given-names>M. F. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The Enamovirus P0 protein is a silencing suppressor which inhibits local and systemic RNA silencing through AGO1 degradation</article-title>. <source>Virology</source>
<volume>426</volume>, <fpage>178</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>187</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2012.01.026</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22361475?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22361475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasteiger</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gattiker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoogland</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanyi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Appel</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bairoch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>ExPASy: The proteomics server for in-depth protein knowledge and analysis</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>3784</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3788</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg563</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12824418?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824418</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geske</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Purification and coat protein gene sequence of a Montana RMV-like isolate of barley yellow dwarf virus</article-title>. <source>Arch. Virol</source>. <volume>141</volume>, <fpage>541</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>556</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01718316</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8645094?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8645094</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gildow</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Evidence for receptor-mediated endocytosis regulating luteovirus acquisition by aphids</article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source>
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>270</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>277</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/Phyto-83-270</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abajin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Consed: a graphical tool for sequence finishing</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>195</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>202</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.8.3.195</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9521923?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9521923</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Purification, identity and some properties of an isolate of barley yellow dwarf virus from Indiana</article-title>. <source>J. Gen. Virol</source>. <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>667</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>676</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/0022-1317-64-3-667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawkes</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R. A. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Incidence and distribution of Barley yellow dwarf virus and cereal yellow dwarf virus in over-summering grasses in a Mediterranean-type environment</article-title>. <source>Aust. J. Agric. Res</source>. <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>270</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AR04259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hesler</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riedell</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Langham</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Insect infestations, incidence of viral plant diseases, and yield of winter wheat in relation to planting date in the northern great plains</article-title>. <source>J. Econ. Entomol</source>. <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>2020</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2027</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0022-0493-98.6.2020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16539128?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16539128</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Itnyre</surname><given-names>R. L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>D'arcy</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pataky</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999a</year>). <article-title>Symptomatology of barley yellow dwarf virus-RMV infection in sweet corn</article-title>. <source>Plant Dis</source>. <volume>83</volume>, <fpage>781</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>781</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS.1999.83.8.781C</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Itnyre</surname><given-names>R. L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>D'arcy</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweets</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999b</year>). <article-title>Reaction of sweet corn to inoculation with barley yellow dwarf virus RMV-IL</article-title>. <source>Plant Dis</source>. <volume>83</volume>, <fpage>566</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>568</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS.1999.83.6.566</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaro&#x161;ov&#xE1;</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chrpov&#xE1;</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x160;&#xED;p</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A comparative study of the Barley yellow dwarf virus species PAV and PAS: distribution, accumulation and host resistance</article-title>. <source>Plant Pathol</source>. <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>436</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>443</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3059.2012.02644.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The complete nucleotide sequence and its organization of the genome of barley yellow dwarf virus-GAV</article-title>. <source>Sci. China C Life Sci</source>. <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>182</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1360/03yc0076</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15379250?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15379250</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connery</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Control of barley yellow dwarf virus in minimum-till and conventional-till autumn-sown cereals by insecticide seed and foliar spray treatments</article-title>. <source>J. Agric. Sci</source>. <volume>150</volume>, <fpage>249</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>262</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0021859611000505</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33a">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozlowska-Makulska</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guilley</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szyndel</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beuve</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaire</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrbach</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>P0 proteins of European beet-infecting poleroviruses display variable RNA silencing suppression activity</article-title>. <source>J. Gen. Virol</source>. <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>1082</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1091</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/vir.0.016360-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19955562?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19955562</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kujawa</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Drugeon</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulanicka</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haenni</surname><given-names>A.-L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Structural requirements for efficient translational frameshifting in the synthesis of the putative viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerase of potato leafroll virus</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>2165</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2171</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/21.9.2165</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8502558?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8502558</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muharram</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makkouk</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Ansi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Pasha</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Motwkel</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Identification of viral diseases affecting barley and bread wheat crops in yemen</article-title>. <source>Aust. Plant Pathol</source>. <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>563</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>568</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AP06061</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palukaitis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Host-dependent requirement for the Potato leafroll virus 17-kDa protein in virus movement</article-title>. <source>Mol. Plant Microbe Interact</source>. <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1086</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1094</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI.2002.15.10.1086</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12437307?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12437307</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Potato leafroll virus protein P1 contains a serine proteinase domain</article-title>. <source>J. Gen. Virol</source>. <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>1857</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1864</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 10859393?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10859393</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranieri</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Distribution and economic importance of barley yellow dwarf</article-title>, in <source>Barley Yellow Dwarf: 40 Years of Progress</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>D'Arcy</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>St. Paul, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>APS Press</publisher-name>), <fpage>29</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>53</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>A Chinese isolate of barley yellow dwarf virus-PAV represents a third distinct species within the PAV serotype</article-title>. <source>Arch. Virol</source>. <volume>152</volume>, <fpage>1365</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1373</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00705-007-0947-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17347769?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17347769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucio-Zavaleta</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Variation in transmission efficiency among barley yellow dwarf virus-RMV isolates and clones of the normally inefficient aphid vector, <italic>Rhopalosiphum padi</italic></article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source>
<volume>91</volume>, <fpage>792</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>796</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO.2001.91.8.792</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18944037?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944037</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mangwende</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borth</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirkov</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The P0 gene of Sugarcane yellow leaf virus encodes an RNA silencing suppressor with unique activities</article-title>. <source>Virology</source>
<volume>384</volume>, <fpage>38</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>50</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2008.10.034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19046592?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19046592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKirdy</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R. A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nutter</surname><given-names>F. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Quantification of yield losses caused by barley yellow dwarf virus in wheat and oats</article-title>. <source>Plant Dis</source>. <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>769</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>773</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS.2002.86.7.769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>The location of the 5' end of the potato leafroll luteovirus subgenomic coat protein mRNA</article-title>. <source>J. Gen. Virol</source>. <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>2633</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2638</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/0022-1317-72-11-2633</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1940859?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1940859</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giedroc</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Ribosomal frameshifting in decoding plant viral RNAs</article-title>, in <source>Recoding: Expansion of Decoding Rules Enriches Gene Expression</source>, eds. <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gesteland</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>193</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>220</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-0-387-89382-2_9</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>E. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <source>ICTV taxonomic proposal 2013.016a,bP: In the family Luteoviridae, create species Maize yellow dwarf virus-RMV in the genus Polerovirus and remove the unassigned species Barley yellow dwarf virus-RMV</source>. Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://talk.ictvonline.org/files/proposals/taxonomy_proposals_plant1/m/plant01/4600.aspx">http://talk.ictvonline.org/files/proposals/taxonomy_proposals_plant1/m/plant01/4600.aspx</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B45">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckett</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Barley yellow dwarf virus: Luteoviridae or Tombusviridae?</article-title>
<source>Mol. Plant Pathol</source>. <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>177</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>183</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1364-3703.2002.00112.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20569325?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20569325</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B46">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tassetto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunitomi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acevedo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Cricket paralysis virus antagonizes Argonaute 2 to modulate antiviral defense in drosophila</article-title>. <source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</source>. <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>547</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>554</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nsmb.1810</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20400949?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20400949</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B47">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornish</surname><given-names>P. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suram</surname><given-names>S. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giedroc</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Thermodynamic analysis of conserved loop-stem interactions in P1-P2 frameshifting RNA pseudoknots from plant Luteoviridae</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>10665</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10674</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi025843c</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12186552?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12186552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B48">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>T. A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutts</surname><given-names>R. H. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>K. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> synthesis of minus-strand RNA by an isolated Cereal yellow dwarf Virus RNA-dependent RNA polymerase requires VPg and a stem-loop structure at the 3' end of the virus RNA</article-title>. <source>J. Virol</source>. <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>10743</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10751</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01050-06</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16928757?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16928757</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B49">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pazhouhandeh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dieterle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrocco</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lechner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brault</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>F-box-like domain in the polerovirus protein P0 is required for silencing suppressor function</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source>. <volume>103</volume>, <fpage>1994</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1999</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0510784103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16446454?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16446454</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B50">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sammons</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cisar</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohm</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Yield effects of barley yellow dwarf virus in soft red winter wheat</article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source>
<volume>90</volume>, <fpage>1043</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1048</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO.2000.90.9.1043</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18944532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944532</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B51">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gildow</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palukaitis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The C terminus of the polerovirus p5 readthrough domain limits virus infection to the phloem</article-title>. <source>J. Virol</source>. <volume>83</volume>, <fpage>5419</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5429</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02312-08</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19297484?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19297484</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B52">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeffer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunoyer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegler-Graff</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>P0 of beet western yellows virus is a suppressor of posttranscriptional gene silencing</article-title>. <source>J. Virol</source>. <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>6815</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6824</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.76.13.6815-6824.2002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12050394?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12050394</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B53">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Power</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borer</surname><given-names>E. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seabloom</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The community ecology of barley/cereal yellow dwarf viruses in Western US grasslands</article-title>. <source>Virus Res</source>. <volume>159</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>100</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2011.05.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21641945?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21641945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B54">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Power</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Aphid transmission of barley yellow dwarf viruses: interactions between viruses, vectors, and host plants</article-title>, in <source>Barley Yellow Dwarf: 40 Years of Progress</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>D'Arcy</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>St. Paul, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>APS Press</publisher-name>), <fpage>259</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>291</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B55">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pr&#xFC;fer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawchuk</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monecke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowok</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Immunological analysis of potato leafroll luteovirus (PLRV) P1 expression identifies a 25 kDa RNA-binding protein derived via P1 processing</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>421</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>425</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/27.2.421</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9862960?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9862960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B56">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pr&#xFC;fer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawchuk</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Polerovirus ORF0 genes induce a host-specific response resembling viral infection</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Plant Pathol</source>. <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>302</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>309</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07060660609507299</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B57">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pr&#xFC;fer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tacke</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kull</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhode</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Ribosomal frameshifting in plants: a novel signal directs the -1 frameshift in the synthesis of the putative viral replicase of potato leafroll luteovirus</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>1111</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1117</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 1547775?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1547775</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B58">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rochow</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>). <article-title>Biological properties of four isolates of barley yellow dwarf virus</article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>1580</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1589</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 5377734?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5377734</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B59">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rochow</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Specificity among barley yellow dwarf viruses in enzyme immunosorbent assays</article-title>. <source>Virology</source>
<volume>95</volume>, <fpage>415</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>420</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0042-6822(79)90496-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18627901?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18627901</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B60">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rochow</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>). <article-title>A fifth variant of barley yellow dwarf virus in New York</article-title>. <source>Plant Dis. Rep</source>. <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>874</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>877</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B61">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rochow</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1961</year>). <article-title>The barley yellow dwarf virus disease of small grains</article-title>. <source>Adv. Agron</source>. <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>217</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>248</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0065-2113(08)60960-8</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B62">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Royer</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyamanzi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunger</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krenzer</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Economic evaluation of the effects of planting date and application rate of imidacloprid for management of cereal aphids and barley yellow dwarf in winter wheat</article-title>. <source>J. Econ. Entomol</source>. <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>102</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0022-0493-98.1.95</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15765670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15765670</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B63">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stussi-Garaud</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tacke</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prufer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohfritsch</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title><italic>In situ</italic> localization of the putative movement protein (pr17) from potato leafroll luteovirus (PLRV) in infected and transgenic potato plants</article-title>. <source>Virology</source>
<volume>235</volume>, <fpage>311</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>322</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/viro.1997.8679</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9281511?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9281511</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B64">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>N. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilyas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansoor</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Azhar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Cloning and phylogenetic analysis of coat protein of barley yellow dwarf virus isolates from different regions of pakistan</article-title>. <source>J. Phytopathol</source>. <volume>160</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>18</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0434.2011.01853.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B65">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Egli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Minor groove RNA triplex in the crystal structure of a ribosomal frameshifting viral pseudoknot</article-title>. <source>Nat. Struct. Biol</source>. <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>285</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>292</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/6722</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10074948?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10074948</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B66">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>MEGA4: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Evol</source>. <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1596</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1599</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msm092</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17488738?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488738</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B67">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>4673</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4680</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/22.22.4673</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7984417?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B68">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Den Heuvel</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruyere</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogenhout</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegler-Graff</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brault</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbeek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The N-terminal region of the luteovirus readthrough domain determines virus binding to buchnera GroEL and is essential for virus persistence in the aphid</article-title>. <source>J. Virol</source>. <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>7258</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7265</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 9311800?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9311800</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B69">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Der Wilk</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houterman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Molthoff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hans</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Den Heuvel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1997a</year>). <article-title>Expression of the potato leafroll virus ORF0 induces viral-disease-like symptoms in transgenic potato plants</article-title>. <source>Mol. Plant Microbe Interact</source>. <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>153</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>159</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI.1997.10.2.153</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9057321?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9057321</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B70">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Der Wilk</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbeek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dullemans</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Den Heuvel</surname><given-names>J. F. J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997b</year>). <article-title>The genome-linked protein of potato leafroll virus is located downstream of the putative protease domain of the ORF1 product</article-title>. <source>Virology</source>
<volume>234</volume>, <fpage>300</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>303</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/viro.1997.8654</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9268161?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9268161</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B71">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>G. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Purification of the NY-RMV and NY-SGV isolates of barley yellow dwarf virus and the production and properties of their antibodies</article-title>. <source>Plant Dis</source>. <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>1125</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1132</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PD-76-1125</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B72">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wobus</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skaf</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Zoeten</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Sequencing, genomic localization and initial characterization of the VPg of pea enation mosaic enamovirus</article-title>. <source>J. Gen. Virol</source>. <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>2023</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2025</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 9714253?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9714253</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B73">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>R. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A potential nuclear envelope-targeting domain and an arginine-rich RNA binding element identified in the putative movement protein of the GAV strain of Barley yellow dwarf virus</article-title>. <source>Funct. Plant Biol</source>. <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>40</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>50</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/FP07114</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B74">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The complete nucleotide sequence of the barley yellow dwarf GPV isolate from China shows that it is a new member of the genus polerovirus</article-title>. <source>Arch. Virol</source>. <volume>154</volume>, <fpage>1125</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1128</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00705-009-0415-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19551470?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19551470</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B75">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Mfold web server for nucleic acid folding and hybridization prediction</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>3406</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3415</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg595</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12824337?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824337</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
