<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3713025</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-11975</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068441</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Agriculture</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Crops</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cereals</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genetics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Molecular Genetics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Gene Identification and Analysis</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Microbiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Mycology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Fungal Reproduction</subject>
                <subject>Fungi</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plant Microbiology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Plant Science</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plant Pathology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Plant Pathogens</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Functional Roles of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> in Controlling Secondary Metabolism, Sexual Development, and Virulence in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Roles of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Hee-Kyoung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Seunghoon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jo</surname>
            <given-names>Seong-Mi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>McCormick</surname>
            <given-names>Susan P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Butchko</surname>
            <given-names>Robert A. E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Proctor</surname>
            <given-names>Robert H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yun</surname>
            <given-names>Sung-Hwan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Medical Biotechnology, Soonchunhyang University, Asan, Republic of Korea</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Bacterial Foodborne Pathogens and Mycology Research Unit, National Center for Agricultural Utilization Research, Agricultural Research Service, United States Department of Agriculture, Peoria, Illinois, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>Jae-Hyuk</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>University of Wisconsin - Madison, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>sy14@sch.ac.kr</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The corresponding author, Sung-Hwan Yun, is a PLOS ONE Editorial Board member, and this does not alter the authors&#x2019; adherence to all the PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: SHY RHP. Performed the experiments: HKK SL SMJ SPM RAEB. Analyzed the data: HKK SL SPM RAEB RHP SHY. Wrote the paper: SHY SPM.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <elocation-id>e68441</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Kim et al</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p><italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>, the causal agent of Fusarium head blight in cereal crops, produces mycotoxins such as trichothecenes and zearalenone in infected plants. Here, we focused on the function of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, a homolog of <italic>Aspergillus nidulans LaeA</italic> encoding the global regulator for both secondary metabolism and sexual development. Prior to gene analysis, we constructed a novel luciferase reporter system consisting of a transgenic <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strain expressing a firefly luciferase gene under control of the promoter for either <italic>TRI6</italic> or <italic>ZEB2</italic> controlling the biosynthesis of these mycotoxins. Targeted deletion of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> led to a dramatic reduction of luminescence in reporter strains, indicating that <italic>FgLaeA</italic> controls the expression of these transcription factors in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>; reduced toxin accumulation was further confirmed by GC-MS analysis. Overexpression of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> caused the increased production of trichothecenes and additional metabolites. RNA seq-analysis revealed that gene member(s) belonging to &#x223C;70% of total tentative gene clusters, which were previously proposed, were differentially expressed in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain. In addition, &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strains exhibited an earlier induction of sexual fruiting body (perithecia) formation and drastically reduced disease symptoms in wheat, indicating that <italic>FgLaeA</italic> seems to negatively control perithecial induction, but positively control virulence toward the host plant. <italic>FgLaeA</italic> was constitutively expressed under both mycotoxin production and sexual development conditions. Overexpression of a <italic>GFP-FgLaeA</italic> fusion construct in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain restored all phenotypic changes to wild-type levels and led to constitutive expression of GFP in both nuclei and cytoplasm at different developmental stages. A split luciferase assay demonstrated that FgLaeA was able to interact with FgVeA, a homolog of <italic>A. nidulans</italic> veA. Taken together, these results demonstrate that FgLaeA, a member of putative FgVeA complex, controls secondary metabolism, sexual development, and virulence in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, although the specific regulation pattern differs from that of LaeA in <italic>A. nidulans</italic>.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This research was supported by the R&amp;D Convergence Center Support Program, Ministry for Food, Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries, Republic of Korea, and by a grant from the Next-Generation Bio Green21 Program (no. PJ008210), the Rural Development Administration, Republic of Korea. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="15"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> (teleomorph: <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic>), a homothallic ascomycetous fungus, is an important pathogen of major cereal plants that causes diseases such as head blight (scab), stalk rot, and ear rot <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-McMullen1">[1]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Leslie1">[3]</xref>. Previously classified as a single panmictic species, the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> species complex consists of over 16 phylogenetically distinct species or lineages found throughout the world <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Starkey1">[4]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-YliMattila1">[9]</xref>. The ability of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> to produce sexual progeny (ascospores) on overwintering cereal debris is essential for completion of the recurrent cycle of the plant diseases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Trail1">[10]</xref>. In addition to direct yield losses, <italic>F. graminearum</italic> produces mycotoxins such as trichothecenes and zearalenone in host plants, threatening human and animal health <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Desjardins1">[2]</xref>. Trichothecenes, potent inhibitors of eukaryotic protein biosynthesis, are associated with feed refusal, vomiting, diarrhea, dermatitis, and hemorrhages in farm animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Desjardins1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Marasas1">[11]</xref>. Trichothecenes also appear to contribute to the virulence of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> on host plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Proctor1">[12]</xref>. Zearalenone causes estrogenic disorders in laboratory rats, mice, and farm-raised swine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Desjardins1">[2]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Genes involved in the biosynthesis of mycotoxins and other secondary metabolites (e.g., those encoding metabolic enzymes and transporters) usually reside close to one another on a chromosome, forming a gene cluster. Expression of these gene clusters is controlled at multiple levels. A pathway-specific transcription factor located within a gene cluster can regulate the expression of other members of the same cluster (e.g., <italic>TRI6</italic> and <italic>ZEB2</italic> for the regulations of trichothecenes and zearalenone biosynthesis, respectively, in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Hohn1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim1">[14]</xref>. Expression of these pathway-specific transcription factors is affected by environmental conditions such as ambient pH and availability of nitrogen, which are in turn regulated by other types of transcription factors, often located outside of the gene cluster (e.g., AreA and/or PacC regulate the gene clusters for gibberellic acid, fumonisin, and trichothecenes) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Gardiner1">[15]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Min1">[19]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In addition to specific transcription factors, the discovery of global regulators provides new insight into the regulatory hierarchy for fungal secondary metabolites. These master regulators operate in a relatively nonspecific manner by acting at the level of chromatin remodeling. One of the most intensively studied global regulators is LaeA, a nuclear protein containing a methyltransferase domain. It was first identified as a positive regulator of various secondary metabolites in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bok1">[20]</xref>. It has been shown to modulate the function of the so-called velvet (VeA) complex consisting of at least 10 different proteins including VeA, VeA-like, VelB, and VosA. This complex coordinates both secondary metabolism and morphological development in response to light <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram2">[22]</xref>. Under dark conditions, LaeA interacts with the VeA&#x2013;VelB heterodimeric complex in the nucleus, forming the heterotrimeric VeA complex (VelB&#x2013;VeA&#x2013;LaeA), which is responsible for activating secondary metabolism and regulating asexual/sexual development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram2">[22]</xref>. Additionally, LaeA has been shown to control both the protein levels of other VeA members (VosA, VelB, and VeA), as well as physical interactions between them, thereby indirectly regulating fungal development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram2">[22]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The functional roles of LaeA have been demonstrated in several fungal species including <italic>Aspergillus</italic> and <italic>Penicillium</italic> (Eurotiomycetes) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bok1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Amaike1">[23]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Perrin1">[26]</xref>, <italic>Cochliobolus heterostrophus</italic> (Dothideomycetes) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Wu1">[27]</xref>, and <italic>F. fujikuroi</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Wiemann1">[28]</xref>, <italic>F. verticillioides</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Butchko1">[29]</xref>, <italic>F. oxysporum</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-LopezBerges1">[30]</xref>, and <italic>Trichoderma reesei</italic> (Sordariomycetes) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Seiboth1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-KarimiAghcheh1">[32]</xref>. In <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, homologs of three VeA complex members have been identified, two of which, FgVeA and FgVelB, have been shown to regulate mycotoxin production and fungal development, similar to those in <italic>Aspergillus</italic> spp. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Jiang1">[33]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Jiang2">[35]</xref>. However, function of the <italic>F. graminearum LaeA</italic> homolog (designated <italic>FgLaeA</italic>) and the existence of the nuclear heterotrimeric FgVeA complex FgVelB&#x2013;FgVeA&#x2013;FgVelB have yet to be established.</p>
      <p>In this study, we provide a detailed functional characterization of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> using newly developed firefly luciferase reporter systems for toxin production and protein&#x2013;protein interaction, respectively, and other strategies. Targeted gene deletion, complementation, and overexpression demonstrated that <italic>FgLaeA</italic> functions as a positive regulator in the production of various mycotoxins, asexual development (only in the dark), and virulence on host plant as well as in gene expression for the corresponding secondary metabolites, while acting as a negative regulator in sexual development (albeit in a light-independent manner). In addition, <italic>in vivo</italic> protein interaction between FgVeA and FgLaeA was clearly demonstrated. In contrast to other fungal LaeA homologs, the FgLaeA protein was constitutively localized in both the cytoplasm and nucleus under both dark and light conditions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Targeted Deletion, Complementation, and Overexpression of <italic>FgLaeA</italic></title>
        <p>A genome-wide search for homologs of the functionally characterized fungal <italic>LaeA-</italic>like genes, such as <italic>A. nidulans LaeA</italic> (GenBank accession no. AAQ95166.1) and <italic>F. fujikuroi FfLae1</italic> (FN548141), identified two open reading frames (ORFs) as possible LaeA homologs based on sequence homology, both carrying a conserved methyltransferase domain, in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. The first ORF (annotated as FGSG_00657.3 in the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> genome database), encodes for 317 amino acids, interrupted by 6 introns, which was confirmed by reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR), but different from the previous annotation in the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> database. The intron positions are as follows: 25&#x2013;87, 191&#x2013;243, 393&#x2013;445, 503&#x2013;552, 703&#x2013;749, and 1176&#x2013;1222 (nucleotide numbering starts with 1 at the first nucleotide of the <italic>FgLaeA</italic> ORF as annotated in the genome database). Its coding region showed the highest similarity to FfLae1 (with 70% identity over 282 residues), but a lower similarity to LaeA (27.8% over 180 residues). We designated this ORF <italic>FgLaeA</italic>, as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Jiang1">[33]</xref>, due to its highest sequence homology to <italic>FfLae1</italic> from a closely related <italic>Fusarium</italic> species. The second ORF (FGSG_07660, previously designated <italic>FgVIP1</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Jiang1">[33]</xref>) shared 35.8% identity to LaeA, and 30.6% identity to FfLae1 over 296 residues. Targeted deletion of both genes was performed in WT strain Z3643, resulting in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> and &#x394;<italic>FgVIP1</italic> strains, respectively. Integration of gene deletion constructs into the fungal genome via double crossover was verified by Southern blot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g001">Fig. 1</xref>, data not shown for &#x394;<italic>FgVIP1</italic>). Because the &#x394;<italic>FgVIP1</italic> strains showed no dramatic changes in major fungal traits, further gene deletions using the FLTRI6 and FLZEB2 strains (the luciferase reporter strains for biosynthesis of trichothecenes and zearalenone, respectively; for details, see the subheading &#x201C;Development of a firefly luciferase reporter system for mycotoxin production&#x201D; in the result section) were done for only <italic>FgLaeA</italic>, generating the FLTRI6&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> and FLZEB2&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strains, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Genetic complementation of a &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain derived from Z3643 was achieved by introducing an intact copy of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> (including &#x223C;1 kb of its native promoter region) into the genome of the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain, generating the so-called add-back strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). For generating transgenic <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains overexpressing <italic>FgLaeA</italic>, we complemented the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain with an intact copy of the <italic>FgLaeA</italic> ORF fused to a green fluorescence protein gene (<italic>GFP</italic>) under control of a strong promoter from the <italic>Cryphonectria parasitica Crp</italic> gene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kwon1">[36]</xref>, generating the OE::<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>FgLaeA</italic> (OE) strain.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0068441-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068441.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Targeted deletion of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> from the genome of the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> Z3643 (WT), FLTRI6, or FLZEB2 strains.</title>
            <p>(A) Deletion scheme. (B) <italic>Bgl</italic>II-digested genomic DNA gel blot hybridized with probe 1 (upper panel) and probe 2 (lower), respectively; positions are indicated in A. Lanes 1, 2, and 6: the Z3643, FLTRI6, and FLZEB2 strains; lanes 3 and 4: the <italic>FgLaeA</italic>-deletion strains derived from Z3643 (designated &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic>); lanes 5 and 7: the <italic>FgLaeA</italic>-deletion strains derived from FLTRI6 (FLTRI6&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic>); lane 7: the FLZEB2&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain; lanes 9 and 10: the <italic>FgLaeA</italic> add-back strains derived from the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain; lane 11: the <italic>FgLaeA</italic>-overexpression strain derived from the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain. DNA size markers are indicated on the left side of the gel. Note that a &#x223C;7.5-kb nonspecific hybridizing band was observed in all of the strains examined when hybridized with probe 1.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0068441.g001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Hyphal Growth, Pigmentation, Conidiation, and Sexual Development in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> and OE::<italic>FgLaeA</italic> Strains</title>
        <p>Compared to wild-type (WT) progenitors Z3643, FLTRI6, and FLZEB2, all &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strains examined exhibited a slight reduction in radial growth, but a significant reduction in red hyphal pigmentation on potato dextrose agar (PDA; Difco Laboratories, Detroit, MI, USA), CM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Leslie1">[3]</xref>, and carrot agar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). However, this reduction was relatively modest compared with the phenotypes caused by the deletion of <italic>FgVeA</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Jiang1">[33]</xref> or <italic>FgVelB</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee1">[34]</xref>, which showed fewer aerial hyphae with reduced or abolished pigmentation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). The reduced pigmentation phenotype caused by &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> was less robust than a typical albino mutant of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> (e.g., that generated by a deletion of <italic>PKS12</italic>, the gene responsible for biosynthesis of the red pigment aurofusarin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim3">[37]</xref>). Aurofusarin production was still observed in young marginal hyphae of mutant colonies, but older regions of the colony were albino, resulting in ring-shaped pigmentation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). This pigmentation pattern was also seen in the marginal regions between different growing colonies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s001">Fig. S1</xref>). Fewer aerial mycelia, with lower hydrophobicity were observed only on the albino region in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strains; however, the formation of thick aerial hyphae was retained in the pigmented margin areas, similar to those from WT strains. This reduced pigmentation phenotype was restored to WT levels in both the <italic>FgLaeA-</italic>add-back and OE strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). However, this phenotype is dependent upon growth conditions, as the same &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain was completely albino when grown in complete liquid medium (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s001">Fig. S1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0068441-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068441.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Hyphal growth, pigmentation, and conidiation.</title>
            <p>(A) Colony morphology of the WT (Z3643), &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic>, OE (<italic>FgLaeA</italic>-overexpression), add-back, &#x394;<italic>FgVeA</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-KarimiAghcheh1">[32]</xref>, and &#x394;<italic>FgVelB</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Jiang1">[33]</xref> strains on CM plates. Upper and lower panels show the morphology in surface and undersurface of plates, respectively. (B) The number of conidia formed in CMC liquid medium under dark and light conditions. The <italic>y</italic>-axis represents the number of conidia (&#xD7;10<sup>5</sup> or &#xD7;10<sup>6</sup>/mL). Data shown are the mean values obtained from three independent samples. Statistical analysis was performed with ANOVA and Duncan&#x2019;s multiple range test. The same letter above bars represents no significant difference.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0068441.g002"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Conidiation of WT strains grown in carboxymethyl cellulose (CMC) liquid medium was strongly favored (&#x223C;10&#x2013;15-fold increase) under 24-h light condition compared to those maintained in the dark. &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strains showed no dramatic changes under light condition, while showed reduced levels of conidiation under dark condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). No significant changes were detected among the WT, OE, and add-back strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g002">Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
        <p>Sexual development (self-fertility) of &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strains was determined based on perithecia production on carrot agar. The WT Z3643 strain began to produce protoperithecia approximately 72 h after sexual induction on carrot agar under both 24-h light and 12-h dark/light cycle conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). After an additional 3- or 4-day incubation, mature perithecia containing asci, each with eight ascospores formed. In contrast, five independent experiments confirmed that all &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strains derived from the Z3643, FLTRI6, and FLZEB2 strains began producing protoperithecia approximately 24 h earlier than the WT strain under the same culture conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). However, neither the WT nor &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strains produced protoperithecia on carrot agar under 24-h dark conditions (data not shown). This early induction of protoperithecia formation in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strains was restored to WT levels in both the add-back and OE strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). When a conidial suspension of the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain was spermatized for the self-sterile &#x394;<italic>MAT1-2</italic> strain, fertile perithecia successfully formed on carrot agar, indicating that the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain has no defect in male fertility (data not shown).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0068441-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068441.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Protoperithecia formation and the expression of <italic>MAT</italic> genes.</title>
            <p>(A) Protoperithecia formation on carrot agar in the WT (Z3643), &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic>, OE (<italic>FgLaeA</italic>-overexpression), and add-back strains. Time since perithecia induction (i.e., the removal of aerial mycelia, which had previously grown for 7 days in the dark) is indicated above the pictures. Upper and lower panels for each strain show the surface and undersurface, respectively, of carrot agar plates. The size bar indicates 200 &#xB5;m. (B) Relative transcript levels for two <italic>MAT</italic> genes (<italic>x</italic>-axis) accumulated in the fungal strains shown in (A) at each of the growth time points (days, <italic>y</italic>-axis) for total RNA extraction. 3 and 6: days 3 and 6 under vegetative growth, respectively; 8, 9, and 10: days 8, 9, and 10 following perithecial induction, respectively (<italic>i.e.</italic> 24 h, 48 h, and 72 h after perithecia induction, respectively). <italic>GzRPS16</italic> (FGSG_09438.3) was used as an endogenous control for data normalization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim6">[52]</xref>. <italic>MAT1-1-1</italic> and <italic>MAT1-2-1</italic> transcript levels from a 3-day-old vegetative sample of a <italic>F. graminearum</italic> WT strain were used as references. Statistical analysis was performed with ANOVA and Duncan&#x2019;s multiple range test. The same letter above bars represents no significant difference.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0068441.g003"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Mycotoxin Production and Virulence of the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> and OE::<italic>GFP-FgLaeA</italic> Strains</title>
        <p>The effect of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> deletion and overexpression on the production of mycotoxins [trichothecenes (e.g. deoxynivalenol, DON; 15-acetyl DON, 15ADON) and zearalenone (ZEA)] in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> was determined using the luminescence reporter system, chemical analysis, and qRT-PCR. In all tests, the WT strain produced both DON and ZEA with concomitant gene expression levels under appropriate conditions, whereas toxin production in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strains significantly decreased. Luminescence signal intensity from cell lysates extracted from FLTRI6&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strains grown in AG medium for 6 days were at least 10-fold lower than those from the FLTRI6 strain, demonstrating that the <italic>Tri6</italic> transcript level significantly decreased due to &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic>; no significant difference in luminescence was observed between FLTRI6 strains grown under dark and light conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). Similarly, luminescence intensities for <italic>ZEB2</italic> expression in the FLZEB2&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain decreased &#x223C;2-fold compared to FLZEB2 when grown in AG medium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>) and &#x223C;6-fold when grown on a rice substrate for 2 weeks (data not shown). GC-MS analysis using extracts from the fungal rice culture confirmed that 15ADON and ZEA were detected in the Z3643 and add-back strains, whereas no detectable amount of 15ADON or a &#x223C;30-fold-reduced level of ZEA was detected in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain derived from Z3643 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g005">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s008">Table S1</xref>). However, a <italic>FgLaeA-</italic>overexpression strain (OE8) produced &#x223C;11-fold-increased amounts of 15ADON along with additional metabolites, such as butenolide and culmorin, which were not detected in Z3643; no ZEA levels were altered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g005">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s008">Table S1</xref>). The same effect of &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> on the DON and ZEA production was also confirmed using the other wild-type strain (9F1) of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> that produces a significant amount of culmorin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-McCormick1">[38]</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s002">Fig S2</xref>). In addition, qRT-PCR confirmed that the gene transcript levels for theses metabolites, <italic>Tri6</italic> (FGSG_03536) required for 15ADON and <italic>CLM1</italic> (FGSG_10397) for culmorin were drastically reduced in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain, but increased in the OE strain when grown in AG medium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g004">Fig. 4C</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0068441-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068441.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Mycotoxin production determined by luminescence signals and gene transcript levels.</title>
            <p>(A) Luminescence signals in the cell lysates from the Z3643 (Z43), FLTRI6, and two independent FLTRI6&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> (&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA-1</italic> and &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA-2</italic>) strains grown in AG liquid medium for 6 days. (B) Luminescence signals in cell lysates from the FLZEB2 and FLZEB2&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> (&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic>) strains grown in SG liquid medium for 8 days. (C) Relative transcript levels for secondary metabolites accumulated in the WT, &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> (derived from Z3643), <italic>FgLaeA</italic>-overexpression (OE), and add-back strains grown in AG liquid medium for 6 days, as determined by qRT-PCR. The amount of <italic>CLM1</italic> transcript in the WT strain was used as a reference.//: discontinuity. Statistical analysis was performed with ANOVA and Duncan&#x2019;s multiple range test. The same letter above bars represents no significant difference.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0068441.g004"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0068441-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068441.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Reconstructed ion chromatogram of fungal rice culture extracts.</title>
            <p>WT (Z3643), the wild-type Z3643 strain; &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA,</italic> a Z3643&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain derived from Z3643; OE, a <italic>FgLaeA-</italic>overexpression strain derived from the Z3643&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain; add-back, a <italic>FgLaeA</italic>-add-back strain derived from the Z3643&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain. A, 15ADON; B, butenolide; C, culmorin; Z, zearalenone.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0068441.g005"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In plant inoculation tests, the WT, OE, and add-back strains examined caused typical head blight leading to complete bleaching on wheat. The &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strains were able to colonized inoculated spikelets, but rarely spread to the adjacent ones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g006">Fig. 6</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0068441-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068441.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Virulence of the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains on wheat heads.</title>
            <p>The photographs were taken 14 days after inoculation. WT, wild-type strain Z3643; &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic>, the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain derived from Z3643; OE, the <italic>FgLaeA</italic>-overexpression strain derived from Z3643; add-back, the <italic>FgLaeA-</italic>add-back strain derived from the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0068441.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Expression Pattern of <italic>FgLaeA</italic>, <italic>FgVeA</italic> and <italic>FgVelB</italic> in the Fungal Strains</title>
        <p>qRT-PCR analysis revealed that the <italic>FgLaeA</italic> transcript was constitutively but weakly expressed in WT strain Z3643 during vegetative growth, perithecial formation on carrot agar, and trichothecene production in AG medium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). Except during conidiation in CMC medium, and 6 days after perithecia induction on carrot agar, <italic>FgLaeA</italic> transcript levels remained stable across all time points examined, staying within 1.5-fold relative to a reference gene (either <italic>EF1A</italic> or FGSG_09438) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). The constitutive low expression of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> under these conditions was clearly confirmed by RNA-seq analysis (unpublished data). The RPKM (reads per kilobase per million mapped reads) values of the <italic>FgLaeA</italic> transcripts accumulated under conditions for sexual development, trichothecene production, and vegetative hyphal growth were 4.3, 5.5, and 7.6, respectively. However, two other genes, <italic>FgVeA</italic> (FGSG_11955.3) and <italic>FgVelB</italic> (FGSG_01362.3), which may represent a FgVeA complex, showed sexual developmental-specific expression patterns and higher expression levels under all three conditions compared to <italic>FgLaeA</italic>. RPKMs for <italic>FgVeA</italic> and <italic>FgVelB</italic> were 325.9, 100.9, 126.4, and 630.9, 56.8, 33.0, respectively. Note that the <italic>FgVelB</italic> transcript, which significantly accumulated only on carrot agar for sexual development, could be clearly detected in a Northern blot hybridization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee1">[34]</xref>. In contrast, the <italic>FgLaeA</italic> transcript levels in two independent OE strains (OE7 and OE8) dramatically increased (up to &#x223C;1,200-fold) compared to those in Z3643 during the entire growth conditions examined; those in the add-back strains were not significantly different from those in Z3643 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s003">Fig. S3A</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0068441-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068441.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Expression of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> under various culture conditions.</title>
            <p>Relative <italic>FgLaeA</italic> transcript levels in the WT Z3643 strain grown in complete liquid medium for vegetative growth, CMC liquid medium for conidiation, AG liquid medium (AG) for trichothecene production, and on carrot agar for sexual development under dark or dark/light cycle conditions (cycle). Days of incubation following inoculation in each medium is shown in on the <italic>x</italic>-axis. <italic>GzRPS16</italic> (FGSG_09438.3) was used as an endogenous control for data normalization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Sambrook1">[51]</xref>. The amount of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> transcript from a 3-day-old sample in complete liquid medium was used as a reference.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0068441.g007"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Expressions of two genes (<italic>FgVeA</italic> and <italic>FgVelB</italic>) for putative members of the FgVeA complex were dramatically elevated in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain on carrot agar (under the sexual developmental stage); only the <italic>FgVeA</italic> transcript level was increased in CM medium (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s003">Fig. S3B</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Expression of Mating-type (<italic>MAT</italic>) Genes in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> Strain under Sexual Development</title>
        <p>To investigate a possible genetic cause for the early sexual induction in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain, we compared gene expression profiles at the mating-type (<italic>MAT</italic>) locus, the master regulator for sexual development, among the WT, &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA,</italic> OE, and add-back strains. qRT-PCR analysis confirmed that the transcript levels of two <italic>MAT</italic> genes (<italic>MAT1-1-1</italic> and <italic>MAT1-2-1</italic>, both of which are required for early sexual stage development in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim4">[39]</xref>), were elevated &#x223C;2&#x2013;3-fold in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain compared to the WT strain 24 h after perithecial induction on carrot agar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>); no changes were observed in the OE and add-back strains during the same time points for perithecial induction compared to those in WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>). However, the other three <italic>MAT</italic> genes (<italic>MAT1-1-2</italic>, <italic>MAT1-1-3</italic>, and <italic>MAT1-2-3</italic>) showed no dramatic differences in transcript levels among the strains examined (data not shown).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Differentially Expressed Genes (DEGs) in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> Strain under Trichothecene Production Conditions</title>
        <p>To identify genes regulated under control of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> during trichothecene production, we performed RNA-seq analysis using total RNA extracted from mycelia of &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> and Z3643 strains grown in AG liquid medium for 60 h, an early induction stage for trichothecene production. Analysis of transcriptional profiles revealed a total of 799 genes differentially regulated &#x2265;2-fold in the FLTRI6&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain compared to its WT progenitor FLTRI6; 444 and 355 genes were significantly down- and upregulated, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s009">Tables S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s010">S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s011">S4</xref>). Gene ontology (GO) analysis using blast2go (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.blast2go.com">http://www.blast2go.com</ext-link>) revealed enrichment of DEGs associated with catalytic activity among GO molecular functions, and enrichment of DEGs associated with metabolic and cellular processes among GO biological processes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s004">Fig. S4</xref>).</p>
        <p>Searching against the conserved domain database (CDD) revealed that 332 of the DEGs (63.4%) found within the database contained enzymatic domains or were related to enzyme functions, including 72 genes (13.7%) involved in metabolism. In contrast, only 16 genes (3.0%) were identified as those probably involved in development and signal transduction (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s012">Table S5</xref>). In addition, 8 and 17 genes for transcription factors (TFs) were identified as down- and upregulated, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s009">Tables S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s010">S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s011">S4</xref>); however, none of the TFs differentially regulated in the FLTRI6&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain were associated with distinct functions based on gene deletion assays <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Son1">[40]</xref>. Unlike in the <italic>A. nidulans</italic> &#x394;<italic>laeA</italic> strain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram1">[21]</xref>, three major members of a putative FgVeA complex, <italic>FgVeA</italic>, <italic>FgVelB</italic>, and <italic>FgVosA</italic> (FGSG_06774.3), were not significantly differentially regulated in the FLTRI6&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain in AG medium; <italic>FgVeA</italic> and <italic>FgVosA</italic> showed only 1.48- and 1.43-fold increases, respectively, compared to FLTRI6 (note that the transcript levels of both <italic>FgVeA</italic> and <italic>FgVelB</italic> were dramatically increased in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain under sexual development condition, confirmed by qRT-PCR).</p>
        <p>To identify genes for secondary metabolites, we compared the DEGs against members of the 77 tentative functional gene clusters (TFCs) in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, previously identified using five types of functional descriptions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee2">[41]</xref>. Gene member(s) belonging to 37 TFCs and 19 TFCs were identified in downregulated and upregulated genes in the FLTRI6&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s009">Tables S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s010">S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s011">S4</xref>). Moreover, members of nine TFCs were found in both down- and upregulated genes without overlapping.</p>
        <p>Among the downregulated genes, seven genes (<italic>Tri3&#x2013;Tri14</italic>) in the <italic>Tri</italic> gene cluster for trichothecene biosynthesis were identified; <italic>Tri101</italic> (FGSG_07896.3), located outside the gene cluster, was not differentially expressed. Three polyketide synthase (<italic>PKS</italic>) genes including <italic>PKS10,</italic> responsible for biosynthesis of fusarin C, and two <italic>PKS</italic> genes (<italic>PKS2</italic> and <italic>PKS14</italic>) whose chemical products have not yet been identified, a non-ribosomal peptide synthetase gene (<italic>NPS7</italic>), and <italic>CLM1</italic> (FGSG_10397) for culmorin biosynthesis were also identified. However, all of these genes except <italic>PKS10</italic> showed very low RPKM values (&lt;0.5) in the WT FLTRI6 strain; eight members of a putative <italic>PKS10</italic> cluster (FGSG_07798&#x2013;07807) showed higher RPKM values ranging from 5.4 to 90.0 in FLTRI6. In addition to these key enzyme genes, three additional genes in the <italic>PKS</italic> cluster (<italic>PKS5</italic>, <italic>PKS11</italic>, and <italic>PKS12</italic> for aurofusarin), one <italic>NPS</italic> gene (<italic>NPS12</italic>), and one butenolide cluster gene were downregulated. Six genes with contiguous gene numbers (FGSG_10608&#x2013;10614), which were not deduced as a TFC in the previous study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee2">[41]</xref>, were also downregulated (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s009">Tables S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s010">S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s011">S4</xref>). In contrast, no key enzyme genes in any TFCs were identified among the upregulated genes, with the exception of <italic>PKS7</italic> (FGSG_08795.3).</p>
        <p>Mapping of the DEGs onto the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> genome revealed the DEGs to be dispersed throughout the four chromosomes; however, they were not evenly distributed on each chromosome. The genomic positions of some DEGs seemed to be enriched in specific regions such as subtelomeres, or genome-wide locations of histone H3-lysine methylations (H3K7me3 or H3Kme2) (Freitag, personal communication) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s005">Fig. S5</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Comparison of DEGs in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> and &#x394;<italic>FgVelB</italic> Strains</title>
        <p>We compared DEGs in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain under toxin production conditions with those obtained from the &#x394;<italic>FgVelB</italic> strain grown under sexual development conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee1">[34]</xref>. Although growth conditions for the gene deletion strains were different from each other, more than 30% of DEGs in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain overlapped with those from the &#x394;<italic>FgVelB</italic> strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g008">Fig. 8</xref>). Among 444 genes downregulated in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain, 108 (24.3%) and 32 (7.2%) genes were similarly downregulated and upregulated, respectively, in the &#x394;<italic>FgVelB</italic> strain; genes belonging to 16 TFCs were downregulated in both strains. Gene members of five TFCs including the <italic>Tri</italic> gene cluster were differentially expressed between strains, exhibiting downregulation in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain and upregulation in the &#x394;<italic>FgVelB</italic> strain. Similarly, 83 (23.3%) and 32 (9.0%) genes from the sets of down- and upregulated genes in the &#x394;<italic>FgVelB</italic> strain overlapped with those upregulated in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g008">Fig. 8</xref>). Gene members of three TFCs were upregulated in both strains, while six other TFCs also showed differential expression between strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g008">Fig. 8</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0068441-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068441.g008</object-id>
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Number of genes expressed differentially in the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> and &#x394;<italic>FgVelB</italic> strains.</title>
            <p>(A) Downregulated genes; (B) upregulated genes. The numbers of DEGs for each category is indicated in parentheses below the fungal strains. TFC, tentative functional cluster according to Lee (2010) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Son1">[40]</xref>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0068441.g008"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Cellular Localization of FgLaeA</title>
        <p>To determine the cellular localization of the protein product of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> under various developmental stages, we constructed two additional transgenic fungal strains derived from the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain, as well as the OE::<italic>GFP-FgLaeA</italic> strain described above. The &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic>::<italic>nGFP</italic>-<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain was generated by introducing an intact copy of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> fused to <italic>GFP</italic> under its native promoter into the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain. The OE::<italic>RFP-His::GFP-FgLaeA</italic> strain was constructed by introducing the P<italic>crp-GFP-FgLaeA</italic> construct into the genome of a <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strain (H4::RFP) carrying a red fluorescence protein (RFP) fused to a histone gene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee3">[42]</xref>. The red pigmentation and perithecia formation pattern in both &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic>::<italic>nGFP</italic>-<italic>FgLaeA</italic> and H4::RFP-OE::<italic>GFP-FgLaeA</italic> strains were restored to WT levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). However, GFP expression in the former strains was not visualized by fluorescence microscopy.</p>
        <p>In both OE::<italic>GFP-FgLaeA</italic> and H4::RFP-OE::<italic>GFP-FgLaeA</italic> strains, GFP-FgLaeA commonly localized to both the nucleus and cytoplasm in fungal cells grown under all of stages examined, including newly formed conidia, germinating conidia, mature hyphae, and ascospores under both dark and light conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g009">Fig. 9</xref>). Occasionally, nuclear enrichment of GFP signals was not obvious; instead, GFP expression was clearly seen in cellular compartments other than the nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g009">Fig. 9B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0068441-g009" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068441.g009</object-id>
          <label>Figure 9</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Expression of GFP in the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> OE::<italic>GFP-FgLaeA</italic> strain grown on CM plates.</title>
            <p>(A) Vegetative hyphae grown under dark/light cycle conditions; (B) those grown under constant dark conditions; (C) ascospore in ascus; (D) conidia; (E) conidium 3 h after germination; (F) apical tip of the germ tube after 7 h germination. Each picture consists of DIC, H4::RFP, GFP::FgLaeA and a merged picture of the RFP and GFP images, respectively. White arrows indicate the nuclei in each image. Size bar is 10 &#xB5;m.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0068441.g009"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2i">
        <title>Protein Interactions between FgLaeA and FgVeA, FgLaeA and FgVelB, and FgVeA and FgVelB</title>
        <p>To determine if the FgLaeA protein is a member of a possible FgVeA complex (i.e., a direct interaction occurred between FgLaeA and FgVeA), we employed the split luciferase complementation assay, a sensitive and efficient method of monitoring <italic>in vivo</italic> protein&#x2013;protein interactions in filamentous ascomycetes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim5">[43]</xref>. For this assay, we generated plasmid vectors carrying the entire coding region of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> fused to a DNA region encoding an N-terminal fragment of luciferase (FgLaeA&#x2013;nLuc) and the <italic>FgVeA</italic> fused to a C-terminal fragment (cLuc&#x2013;FgVeA), respectively, and introduced either or both of them to the genome of Z3643. All cell lysates from negative controls grown in complete liquid medium, which were transgenic <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains carrying a single empty vector expressing only nLuc or cLuc (pFNLucG or pFCLucH), a single-fused gene (<italic>FNLuc&#x2013;FgLaeA</italic> or <italic>FCLuc&#x2013;FgVeA</italic>), or the single fused gene along with the corresponding singly empty vector, exhibited only background levels of luminescence similar to WT strains (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068441-t001">Table 1</xref>). In contrast, all fungal transformants co-expressing both of the fused proteins, FNLuc&#x2013;FgLaeA and FCLuc&#x2013;FgVeA, exhibited &#x223C;1,000&#x2013;2,300-fold increased luminescence relative to negative controls (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068441-t001">Table 1</xref>). Similarly, we examined whether other <italic>F. graminearum</italic> LaeA-like proteins, including FgVIP1 described above, had the capacity to interact with FgVeA. No significant increase in luminescence intensity was found in the fungal strains co-expressing the FNLuc&#x2013;FgVIP1 and FCLuc&#x2013;FgVeA compared to the negative controls (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068441-t001">Table 1</xref>). In addition, we examined the interactions between FgLaeA and FgVelB as well as between FgVeA and FgVelB. Transgenic <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains co-expressing the <italic>FNLuc-FgVelB</italic> and <italic>FCluc-FgVeA</italic> constructs showed higher levels of luminescence compared to WT strains (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068441-t001">Table 1</xref>), demonstrating the FgVeA-FgVelB interaction. Interestingly, the luminescence levels in the cell lysates from the fungal strains carrying both <italic>FNLuc-VelB</italic> and <italic>FCLuc-FgLaeA</italic> were also higher than those from the WT strains and negative controls although the luminescence levels for the FgLaeA-FgVelB interaction were much lower than those from the other fungal strains showing positive signals (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068441-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0068441-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068441.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Luminescence activity<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">1</xref> in fungal cell lysates.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0068441-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0068441.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interaction</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmids inserted</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RLU<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">2</xref></td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z3643</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15-&#xB1;6</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cLUCnLUC</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLucG &amp; pFCLucH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23&#xB1;13</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GzFNCS-1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBP1-SKP1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLuc-FBP1G &amp;pFCLuc-SKP1H</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,815&#xB1;7,268</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VeALaeA-5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FgLaeA-FgVeA</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLuc-FgLaeAG &amp;pFCLuc-FgVeAH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67,555&#xB1;15,605</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VeALaeA-8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FgLaeA-FgVeA</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLuc-FgLaeAG &amp;pFCLuc-FgVeAH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28,849&#xB1;5,341</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VeAVelB-4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FgVeA-FgVelB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLuc-FgVelBG &amp;pFCLuc-FgVeAH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,596&#xB1;1,790</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VeAVelB-5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FgVeA-FgVelB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLuc-FgVelBG &amp;pFCLuc-FgVeAH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,786&#xB1;1,543</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VelBLaeA-1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FgLaeA-FgVelB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLuc-FgVelBG &amp;pFCLuc-FgLaeAH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249&#xB1;94</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VelBLaeA-4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FgLaeA-FgVelB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLuc-FgVelBG &amp;pFCLuc-FgLaeAH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">505&#xB1;294</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VeAVIP1-6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FgVIP1-FgVeA</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLuc-FgVIP1G &amp;pFCLuc-FgVeAH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29&#xB1;6</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VeAVIP1-9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FgVIP1-FgVeA</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLuc-FgVIP1G &amp;pFCLuc-FgVeAH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#xB1;4</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LaeAN-1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FgLaeA-FN<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">3</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLuc-FgLaeAG &amp; pFCLucH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48&#xB1;2</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LaeAN-3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FgLaeA-FN</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLuc-FgLaeAG &amp; pFCLucH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35&#xB1;4</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LaeAC-1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FC<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">3</xref>-FgLaeA</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLucG &amp; pFCLuc-FgLaeAH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#xB1;3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VeAC-2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FC-FgVeA</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLucG &amp; pFCLuc-FgVeAH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22&#xB1;4</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VeAC-3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FC-FgVeA</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLucG &amp; pFCLuc-FgVeAH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#xB1;8</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VelBC-3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FC-FgVelB</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLucG &amp; pFCLuc-FgVelBH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#xB1;5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VIP1C-2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FgVIP1-FC</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLuc-FgVIP1G &amp; pFCLucH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#xB1;7</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VIP1C-3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FgVIP1-FC</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pFNLuc-FgVIP1G &amp; pFCLucH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#xB1;2</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label>1</label>
              <p>obtained from three replicates.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label>2</label>
              <p>relative light units per microgram of protein per min.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label>3</label>
              <p>FC: a C-terminal fragment of the firefly luciferase, FN: a N-terminal fragment.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2j">
        <title>Development of a Firefly Luciferase Reporter System for Mycotoxin Production</title>
        <p>To circumvent several problems in the chemical analysis of mycotoxin production, we developed a new reporter system for mycotoxin production in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> using firefly luciferase. A DNA construct carrying the firefly <italic>Photinus pyralis</italic> luciferase gene (designated <italic>Fluc</italic>) under control of a putative promoter region (&#x223C;1,000 bp) from either <italic>TRI6</italic> or <italic>ZEB2</italic> (transcription factors controlling the production of trichothecenes and zearalenone, respectively) was inserted into its native genomic region in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strain Z3643 via homologous recombination (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s006">Fig. S6</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s007">S7</xref>). The single crossover integration events, confirmed by Southern hybridizations, resulted in fungal strains designated FLTRI6 and FLZEB2, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s006">Figs. S6</xref>, 7). No differences were seen between strains FLTRI6 and FLZEB2 and their WT progenitor (Z3643) for hyphal growth, pigmentation, conidiation, sexual development, and toxin production (data not shown). Strain FLTRI6 was grown in AG liquid medium, which favors trichothecene production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Gardiner1">[15]</xref>, for 7 days. Luminescence signal intensities from cell lysates peaked at day 6, whereas only basal levels were detected in complete medium (CM; Fig S6C). Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) analysis revealed that the FLTRI6 strain began producing both DON and 15ADON at day 4, and showed maximum levels of toxin production at day 7; no detectable level of trichothecenes were produced in complete liquid medium during the entire incubation periods (data not shown). Similarly, the luminescence signals from the FLZEB2 strain grown in SG liquid medium, which favors zearalenone production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim1">[14]</xref>, increased up to day 8, but showed only basal level when grown in CM (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s007">Fig. S7C</xref>). Higher luminescence signals and toxin accumulations were detected on 2-week-old rice cultures of the FLZEB2 strain, a more favorable condition for the production of both toxins (data not shown). A similar pattern in time-course increases between luminescence signals and toxin accumulations from these strains demonstrated that both the FLTRI6 and FLZEB2 strains could be used as luminescence reporter systems for qualitative and quantitative determination of mycotoxin production in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The results presented here clearly demonstrate that a <italic>LaeA</italic>-like gene (<italic>FgLaeA</italic>) of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> is involved in controlling developmental processes, secondary metabolism, and virulence on host plant. Reduced pigmentation of aerial mycelia in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strains is one of the most common growth-related phenotype in the <italic>LaeA</italic>-deletion strains of the previously characterized filamentous fungi except <italic>C. heterostrophus</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Wu1">[27]</xref>, in which pigmentation was increased, even though the biosynthetic pathways for each polyketide pigment were different (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068441-t002">Table 2</xref>). This phenotypic change could have been attributable to the role of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> in controlling secondary metabolism described below. However, the leaky pigmentation phenotype on agar plates indicates that <italic>PKS12-</italic>mediated aurofusarin production is not tightly regulated by <italic>FgLaeA</italic>, especially when hyphal elongation was physically blocked (e.g., by Petri dish wall or neighbor colonies on agar plates). The relatively minor effect of &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> on light-dependent asexual development (conidiation) under dark condition was also similar to those of <italic>LaeA</italic> homologs in other fungi, in which the conidiation mostly decreased (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068441-t002">Table 2</xref>). However, no disturbance of light-dependent conidiation by either the absence or overproduction of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> implies that <italic>FgLaeA</italic> is not involved in a light-sensing pathway for conidiation in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0068441-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068441.t002</object-id>
        <label>Table 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Comparison of phenotypic changes<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref> caused by the <italic>LaeA</italic>-like gene deletion or overexpression in filamentous fungi.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0068441-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0068441.t002"/>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyphal growth &amp; morphology</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pigmentation</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conidiation</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sexual development</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Secondary metabolism<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">b</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Virulence</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A. nidulans</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">similar to WT</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">loss</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">increased smaller, lowerfertile cleisothecia</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced for ST and PN; <bold>increased for</bold><bold>PN, LOV, &amp; monocolin J</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bok1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram2">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bok2">[25]</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A. fumigatus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">similar to WT; more hyphal mass</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">loss</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced for gliotoxin</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">impaired</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bok1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bok2">[25]</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A. flavus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">similar to WT</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">loss</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced; <bold>increased on</bold><bold>peanut</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no sclerotia; <bold>increased</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced for AF, cyclopiazonic acid, &amp;kojic acid; <bold>increased for AF &amp;</bold><bold>additional metabolites</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kale1">[24]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>P. chrysogenum</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">curly &amp; hyperbranching hyphae</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced, light-dependent</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced for PN</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim5">[43]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>C. heterostrophus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced growth; reducedtolerance to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">increased; <bold>reduced</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">increased under vegetative</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">female-sterile;<bold>female-sterile</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced for T-toxin in the dark;<bold>increased for T-toxin in both</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Wu1">[27]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>T. reesei</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">similar to WT</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">loss</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced; <bold>increased;</bold><bold>light-dependent</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">loss of cellulases; <bold>increased for</bold><bold>cellulases</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Seiboth1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-KarimiAghcheh1">[32]</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>F. fujikuroi</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">similar to WT</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">slightly reduced;<bold>increased</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced for GA; <bold>increased for</bold><bold>bikaverin</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Wiemann1">[28]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>F. verticillioides</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced for bikaverin, fusaric acid,&amp; fusarin C</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Butchko1">[29]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>F. oxysporum</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">increased growth rate; no aerialmycelium; reducedhydrophobicity</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">d</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced for siderophores,beauvericin, &amp; fusaric acidin the dark</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-LopezBerges1">[30]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>F. graminearum</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fewer aerial mycelium; reducedhydrophobicity; <bold>similar to WT</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced or loss;<bold>similar to WT</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced only in the dark;light-dependent;<bold>similar to WT</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">slightly increased;light-dependent<bold>similar to WT</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced for DON, ZEA, CM, &amp;fusarin C; light-independent;<bold>increased for DON,</bold><bold>BT, &amp; CM</bold></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reduced</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">this study</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt104">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>phenotypes caused by <italic>FgLaeA-</italic>overexpression were shown in bold in the same column for each description.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt105">
            <label>b</label>
            <p>abbreviations for metabolites: PN, penicillin; LOV, lovastatin; AF, aflatoxins; GA, gibberellic acids; DON, deoxynivalenol; ZEA, zearalenone; BT, butenolide; CM, culmorin.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt106">
            <label>c</label>
            <p>not applicable;</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt107">
            <label>d</label>
            <p>not determined.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>In contrast to these conserved functions, an earlier induction of perithecia formation in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain (and recovery to WT levels in both add-back and OE strains) provided genetic evidence demonstrating a distinct role of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> during sexual development in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. This phenotype could be comparable to the elevated, constitutive formation of fruiting bodies (cleistothecia) in the <italic>A. nidulans</italic> &#x394;<italic>laeA</italic> strain (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068441-t002">Table 2</xref>), implying a conserved role of <italic>LaeA</italic> as a negative regulator for initiating sexual development in both fungi. However, the effect of gene deletions on completion of sexual development were different between the two species. The <italic>A. nidulans</italic> &#x394;<italic>laeA</italic> strain was not able to form H&#xFC;lle cells, which nurse the young cleistothecia, leading to the production of smaller, less fertile cleistothecia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram2">[22]</xref>; no obvious impairments in maturation of fertile perithecia were observed in <italic>F. graminearum.</italic></p>
      <p>The other striking difference between <italic>F. graminearum LaeA</italic> and <italic>LaeA</italic> from other species is the effect of light on sexual development. In <italic>A. nidulans</italic>, cleistothecia formation occurs preferentially in the dark and is inhibited by light. This responsiveness, required for proper sexual development, is disrupted in &#x394;<italic>laeA</italic> strains, as elevated cleistothecia formation is observed even in the presence of light <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram2">[22]</xref>. In contrast, the light effect on inducing sexual development in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> is completely opposite to that of <italic>A. nidulans</italic>; perithecia formation occurs exclusively under either light or dark/light cycle conditions, and is completely inhibited under dark condition. Even though the absence of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> enhanced sexual development, it did not affect light-dependent perithecia formation, suggesting that <italic>FgLaeA</italic> may play a role in repressing sexual developmental processes, especially during early stages. However, unlike <italic>A. nidulans laeA</italic>, <italic>FgLaeA</italic> is not involved in sensing light signals for initiating sexual development, which is similar to its role in regulating conidiation, as described above. The effect of <italic>LaeA</italic> deletion in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> was opposite that of <italic>C. heterostrophus</italic>, when &#x394;<italic>Chlae1</italic> caused female sterility, suggesting a role in positive regulation of sexual reproduction by <italic>ChLAE</italic> in this species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Wu1">[27]</xref>. Even though this phenotypic change in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain seems relatively subtle, the distinct role of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> in sexual development becomes more readily apparent when compared to phenotypic changes caused by the deletion of other velvet complex member genes in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> (e.g., &#x394;<italic>FgVeA</italic> and &#x394;<italic>FgVelB</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Jiang1">[33]</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Jiang2">[35]</xref>. Loss of <italic>FgVeA</italic> and <italic>FgVelB</italic> completely abolished the capability of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> to form perithecia, which is opposite to effect of &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic>. Downregulation of three <italic>MAT</italic> genes in the &#x394;<italic>FgVelB</italic> strain, confirmed by a microarray analysis, is consistent with <italic>FgVelB</italic> as a positive regulator of <italic>MAT</italic> gene expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee1">[34]</xref>. In contrast, increased <italic>MAT</italic> transcript levels in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain during early stage of perithecia formation, confirmed by qRT-PCR, could be attributable to the enhanced sexual development phenotype, indicating that <italic>FgLaeA</italic> controls <italic>MAT</italic> gene expression in a manner different from that of the other FgVeA complex members (i.e., independently of the FgVeA complex). In addition, upregulation of <italic>FgVeA</italic> and <italic>FgVelB</italic> in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain under perithecial induction stage, but not under toxin production stage also suggests a specific role for FgLaeA (as a negative regulator) in modulating FgVeA complex for sexual development, as proposed in <italic>A. nidulans</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram2">[22]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In contrast to developmental processes, secondary metabolism was significantly affected by &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, consistent with the role of <italic>LaeA</italic> homologs in many filamentous fungi (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068441-t002">Table 2</xref>). Not only reduced production of several mycotoxins and their corresponding gene expression levels in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain, but increased production of these metabolites by <italic>FgLaeA</italic> overexpression clearly confirms <italic>FgLaeA</italic> as a positive regulator of secondary metabolite biosynthesis. In addition, RNA-seq analysis of a &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain (FLTRI6&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic>) grown under conditions favoring trichothecene production supports the role of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> as a global regulator for secondary metabolite production, including these mycotoxins. Among the DEGs in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain were genes for key enzymes (e.g., PKS, NRPS, terpenoid synthase, transporters, and cytochrome P450) and other members <italic>F. graminearum</italic> TFCs for secondary metabolites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee2">[41]</xref>. These genes were identified at a high frequency (56 of 77), indicating that these TFCs may be globally regulated by <italic>FgLaeA</italic>, although in many TFCs, only a small number of genes were found to be differentially expressed. Further RNA-seq analyses using an <italic>FgLaeA</italic>-overexpressing strain, as well as the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain under different conditions favoring other metabolites, would be necessary to confirm a global role for <italic>FgLaeA</italic> in controlling secondary metabolite production in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. Localization of some DEGs in subtelomeric or H3K7 methylation regions of each of the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> chromosomes would support a role for <italic>FgLaeA</italic> in chromatin-based regulation of gene expression for secondary metabolites, as proposed in <italic>Aspergillus</italic> species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Shwab1">[44]</xref>. Taken together, these data provide conclusive evidence that <italic>FgLaeA</italic> has a conserved role in secondary metabolism at the global level in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, as demonstrated in other species of <italic>Fusarium</italic> (<italic>F. fujikuroi</italic>, <italic>F. verticillioides</italic>, and <italic>F. oxysporum</italic>), as well as distantly related species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068441-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
      <p>Fewer symptoms on wheat displayed in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain could be attributed to impaired ability of this strain to produce a secondary metabolite required for disease development, such as trichothecenes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Proctor1">[12]</xref>, which is comparable to the effect of other fungal <italic>LaeA</italic> genes on the production of secondary metabolites required for virulence in <italic>A. fumigatus</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bok2">[25]</xref>, <italic>C. heterostrophus</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Wu1">[27]</xref>, and <italic>F. fujikuroi</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Wiemann1">[28]</xref>. However, more attenuated symptoms caused by &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> than those by the gene disruption for trichothecene biosynthesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Proctor1">[12]</xref> suggests that <italic>FgLaeA</italic> controls additional secondary metabolisms and/or regulatory pathways essential for disease development in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>.</p>
      <p>The next question we wanted to ask was whether the regulatory roles of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> described above are associated with those of other members of the putative FgVeA complex, as in <italic>A. nidulans</italic> and other species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Amaike1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Wu1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Wiemann1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-LopezBerges1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Hoff1">[45]</xref>. To address this question, we would need to demonstrate a direct interaction between FgLaeA and FgVeA in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, similar to that seen in <italic>A. nidulans</italic>, <italic>Penicillium chrysogenum</italic>, and <italic>F. fujikuroi</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Wiemann1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Hoff1">[45]</xref>, in which protein&#x2013;protein interactions were confirmed by either yeast two-hybrid or bimolecular fluorescence complementation (BiFC) analysis. A previous study showed no interaction between FgLaeA and FgVeA using a yeast two-hybrid method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Jiang1">[33]</xref>. Evidence provided in this study directly contradicts this finding; we demonstrated a clear <italic>in vivo</italic> protein&#x2013;protein interaction between FgLaeA and FgVeA in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> using a newly developed split-luciferase complementation assay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim5">[43]</xref>, implying that FgLaeA plays a role as a member of the FgVeA complex. In addition, the interaction between FgVeA and FgVelB, which was also confirmed by split luciferase complementaion, clearly supports the existence of the heterotrimeric FgLaeA&#x2013;FgVeA&#x2013;FgVelB complex in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. Interestingly, positive (but lower) luminescence signals from the interaction between FgLaeA and FgVelB, which has not been intensively investigated in other fungi except <italic>A. nidulans</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram2">[22]</xref>, may suggest a possibility for the direct interaction between these two protein in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. However, it is also possible that FgVeA acts as a bridge to bring the FNLuc-FgVelB and FCLuc-FgLaeA into close proximity, as shown in <italic>A. nidulans</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram2">[22]</xref>, which leads to a partial complementation of split luciferase domains. Furthermore, more than 30% of DEGs in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain overlapped with those in the &#x394;<italic>FgVelB</italic> strain despite the difference in culture conditions for each gene deletion strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g008">Fig. 8</xref>). These overlapping DEGs may be common targets of both FgLaeA and FgVelB, or the FgLaeA&#x2013;FgVeA&#x2013;FgVelB complex. The presence of DEGs displaying opposite gene expression patterns between two strains (i.e., 32 genes downregulated the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain and upregulated in the &#x394;<italic>FgVelB</italic> strain, and 83 genes upregulated in the &#x394;<italic>FglaeA</italic> strain and downregulated the &#x394;<italic>FgVelB</italic> strain) suggests their expression may be differentially controlled by the FgVeA complex, which is growth condition-dependent. For example, the trichothecene gene cluster is positively controlled by the FgVeA complex in agmatine liquid medium, while negatively controlled during the sexual development, as previously suggested <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee1">[34]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In addition to protein&#x2013;protein interactions, constitutive nuclear localization of LaeA homologs would be important evidence regarding the regulatory role of LaeA. Nuclear localization of the OE::<italic>GFP-FgLaeA</italic> product during various developmental stages, such as mature hyphae, conidia, germinating conidia, and ascospores, regardless of light signals, was clearly demonstrated in this study. However, exclusive nuclear enrichment of a LaeA&#x2013;GFP signal in <italic>A. nidulans</italic>, as evidenced based on the nuclear/cytoplasmic GFP signal ratio <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram1">[21]</xref>, was not evident in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068441-g009">Fig. 9</xref>), in which significant levels of GFP expression were visualized in the cytoplasm as well as in the nucleus. This localization could be inferred based on nonspecific accumulation of the excessively producing GFP&#x2013;FgLaeA in the cytoplasm. However, considering that the <italic>LaeA&#x2013;GFP</italic> constructs used in cellular localization analyses in <italic>A. nidulans</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bok1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Bayram1">[21]</xref> and <italic>F. fujikuroi</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Wiemann1">[28]</xref> were expressed under the control of strong promoters such as those for <italic>alcA</italic>, <italic>niiA</italic>, and <italic>gpd</italic> in <italic>A. nidulans</italic>, the cytoplasmic distribution of GFP&#x2013;FgLaeA may be not an artifact, but reflect a distinct function of FgLaeA compared to other fungi.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, <italic>FgLaeA</italic> plays important roles in controlling secondary metabolism, various developmental processes, and virulence in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, not only through functions conserved across several filamentous fungi (e.g., as a member of the FgVeA complex), but also through distinct additional functions (e.g., FgVeA complex-independent), which may reflect the unique life style of <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. Looking beyond <italic>FgLaeA</italic>, the efficiency and usefulness of the firefly luciferase reporter system for mycotoxin production developed here was clearly demonstrated in this study. This system has a potential for application in other investigations, e.g., using a recipient strain for an insertional mutagenesis to identify a novel gene controlling the expression of <italic>Tri6</italic> or <italic>ZEB2</italic>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Fungal Strains and Culture Conditions</title>
        <p>The <italic>F. graminearum</italic> WT strains Z3643, provided by Dr. Robert L. Bowden (USDA-ARS Plant Science and Entomology Research Unit, Manhattan, KS, USA), and 9F1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-McCormick1">[38]</xref> belongs to lineage 7 of the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> species complex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-ODonnell2">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee4">[46]</xref>. T43&#x394;M2-2, acting as a female in an outcross, is a <italic>MAT1-2-1-</italic>deleted strain derived from Z3643 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee5">[47]</xref>. A <italic>F. graminearum</italic> transgenic strain carrying histone H4 fused with RFP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee3">[42]</xref> was used for the nuclear localization of FgLaeA. The WT and transgenic strains derived from Z3643 were stored in 20% glycerol at &#x2013;70&#xB0;C. Conidiation was induced in CMC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Capellini1">[48]</xref> liquid medium. For sexual development, strains were inoculated and incubated on carrot agar as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Leslie1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee5">[47]</xref>. For genomic DNA extraction, each strain was grown in 50 mL CM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Leslie1">[3]</xref> at 25&#xB0;C for 72 h on a rotary shaker (150 rpm). For trichothecene production and total RNA extraction, 1 mL conidial suspension (10<sup>5</sup>/mL) of each strain was inoculated into the AG-amended liquid medium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Gardiner2">[49]</xref>, as previously described. For zearalenone production and total RNA extraction, fungal strains were grown in SG liquid medium or on rice substrate, as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim1">[14]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Nucleic Acid Manipulations and Primers</title>
        <p>Fungal genomic DNA was prepared as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Leslie1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Chi1">[50]</xref>, and total RNA was extracted from mycelia using an Easy-Spin Total RNA Extraction kit (Intron Biotech, Seongnam, Korea) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. Other general procedures for nucleic acid manipulations were performed as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Sambrook1">[51]</xref>. DNA gel blots were hybridized with biotinylated DNA probes prepared using the BioPrime DNA labeling system (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and developed using the BrightStar&#xAE; BioDetect&#x2122; Kit (Ambion, Austin, TX, USA). All PCR primers used in this study (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s012">Table S5</xref>) were synthesized by the Bioneer Corporation (Chungwon, Korea). qRT-PCR was performed with SYBR Green Super Mix (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA) using first-strand cDNA synthesized from total RNA; amplification efficiencies of all genes were determined as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim6">[52]</xref>. Gene expression was measured in three biological replicates from each time point. <italic>GzRPS16</italic> (FGSG_09438.3) and <italic>EF1A</italic> (FGSG_08811.3) were used as endogenous controls for data normalization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim6">[52]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Mycotoxin Analysis, Virulence Test, and Luciferase Assay</title>
        <p><italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains were grown in 20 mL AG liquid medium for 6 days for trichothecene production and extracted as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Seo1">[53]</xref>. For production of both trichothecenes and zearalenone, and other metabolites, fungal strains were grown in triplicate on 40 g of rice substrate inoculated with spores washed from V8 juice plate for 7 days in the dark at 25&#xB0;C. The fungal cultures were extracted on a rotary shaker with 100 ml ethyl acetate, dried on a rotoevaporator, and re-dissolved in 20 ml acetonitrile-water (86&#x2236;14). Five milliliter of this solution was cleaned with a Romer MycoSep225&#xAE; Trich column, dried under a stream of nitrogen, and re-dissolved in 1 ml methanol. GC-MS analysis was performed on a HP 6890 has chromatograph fitted with HP-5MS (30 m&#xD7;0.25 mm film thickness) and a 5973 mass detector. The carrier gas was helium with a 20&#x2236;1 split ratio and a 20 ml/min slot flow. The column was held at 120&#xB0;C at injection, heated to 260&#xB0;C at 25&#xB0;C/min and held at 260&#xB0;C for 14 min. Compounds were identified by comparison of GC retention time and mass spectral fragmentation with those of standard compounds.</p>
        <p>The virulence of fungal strains was determined on wheat heads. Briefly, conidia of each strain were harvested from CMC culture, suspended in sterile water (1&#xD7;10<sup>6</sup> conidia/ml), and injected into a floret in the basal spikelet of the wheat (cv. Eunpamil) head at mid-anthesis. The plants were placed in a greenhouse for two weeks after a 3-day incubation in a humidity chamber.</p>
        <p>Luciferase activity in cell lysates from fungal strains was measured using GloMax&#xAE; 96 Microplate Luminometer (Promega) as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim5">[43]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>RNA-seq Analysis</title>
        <p>PolyA tailed transcript RNA (mRNA) was enriched from total RNAs prescreened for quality using Oligo dT beads (TruSeq RNA Sample Prep. Kit, FC-122-1001,1002; Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA) and fragmented for cDNA synthesis by reverse transcriptase (SuperScript II Reverse Transcriptase, part no. 18064-014; Invitrogen). The synthesized cDNA underwent end-repair and subsequent 3&#x2032; A tailing for adaptor ligation (TruSeq RNA Sample Prep. Kit, FC-122-1001,1002; Illumina). After amplification of cDNA with adaptors, 300&#x2013;400-bp cDNA fragments were finally selected. Paired-end sequencing of the amplified cDNA library was performed using the HiSeq2000 platform [TruSeq SBS Kit v3&#x2013;HS (200 cycles), ILFC-401-3001; Illumina). RNA-seq reads were aligned to the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> genome sequences available from the Broad Institute (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/fusarium_group/MultiDownloads.html">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/fusarium_group/MultiDownloads.html</ext-link>) and normalized to RPKM values for genes by using the CLC Genomics Workbench RNA-seq data analysis pipeline according to the developer&#x2019;s instructions. RPKM values from each strain were used for identification of DEG sets. The RNA-seq data have been deposited in the NCBI Short Read Archive (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra</ext-link>; SRP022085).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Constructions of Vectors and Fusion PCR Products for Fungal Transformation</title>
        <p>The DNA construct for deletion of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> from the genomes of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains Z3643, FLTRI6, and FLZEB2 was created using a split-marker recombination procedure as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim4">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Catlett1">[54]</xref>. The 5&#x2032; and 3&#x2032; flanking regions of the <italic>FgLaeA</italic> ORF were amplified with the primer pairs 657for5/657revtail5 and 657fortail3/657rev3, respectively, fused to the geneticin resistance gene (<italic>gen</italic>) cassette, which was amplified from pII99 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Namiki1">[55]</xref> with the primers Gen-for and Gen-rev, in the second round of PCR, and used as a template to generate split markers with the new nested primer sets, 657nest5/Gen-revN and 657nest3/Gen-forN, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s013">Table S6</xref>).</p>
        <p>DNA plasmids carrying <italic>FgLaeA</italic> fused to <italic>GFP</italic> under control of the <italic>cryparin</italic> gene (<italic>Crp</italic>) promoter from <italic>C. parasitica</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kwon1">[36]</xref> (P<italic>Crp-GFP-FgLaeA</italic>), and the same construct under control of the native promoter region of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> (Pnative-<italic>GFP-FgLaeA</italic>), were generated using a double-joint PCR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Yu1">[56]</xref>. For the P<italic>Crp&#x2013;GFP&#x2013;FgLaeA</italic> construct, three amplicons were amplified from pCHPH1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kwon1">[36]</xref>, pIGPAPA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee5">[47]</xref>, and Z3643 with the primer pairs Pcrp_for/Pcrp-GFP tai/rev, GFP_for/GFP_rev, and LaeA-GFP tail/LaeA rev, respectively, mixed in a 1&#x2236;1:3 molar ratio, and finally fused together using the nested primer set Pcrp_for and LaeA 3rd fusion. For Pnative-<italic>GFP-FgLaeA,</italic> the 1.0-kb native promoter region of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> was amplified from Z3643 with primers pLaeA for and pLaeA rev. The final fusion product was amplified with the nested primer set pLaeA for and LaeA 3rd fusion. Each of these two fusion PCR products was cloned into pGEMT (Promega), creating pP<italic>Crp&#x2013;GFP&#x2013;FgLaeA</italic> and pPnative&#x2013;<italic>GFP&#x2013;FgLaeA</italic>, respectively. The DNA plasmid (pPnative&#x2013;<italic>FgLaeA</italic>) used in generating the add-back strain was constructed by amplification of a 3.2-kb <italic>FgLaeA</italic> region including the <italic>FgLaeA</italic> ORF with its 5&#x2032; (0.9 kb) and 3&#x2032; (1.0 kb) flanking regions with primers LaeA5R and LaeA3F, followed by cloning into pGEMT.</p>
        <p>For insertion of the firefly luciferase gene (<italic>FLuc</italic>) under control of the putative promoter region of <italic>Tri6</italic>, a 1.8-kb fragment upstream of the 5&#x2032; end of <italic>Tri</italic> ORF was fused to the <italic>FLuc</italic> ORF (1.6 kb) using a single-joint PCR method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Yu1">[56]</xref>. The promoter region and <italic>FLuc</italic> were amplified from the genomic DNA of Z3643 and the plasmid DNA pSPluc+NF fusion vector (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) with primer pairs Tri6SPL5/Tri6Luc3 and SPluc5/SPluc3 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s013">Table S6</xref>), respectively. The two amplicons were mixed in a 1&#x2236;1 molar ratio and fused in a second round of PCR, followed by a third round of PCR using the nested primer set SPLuc5nest and TSPluc3nest (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068441.s013">Table S6</xref>). The amplified product was cloned into pGEMT (Promega), creating pPTri6-FLuc. A <italic>Sal</italic>I-digested <italic>hygB</italic> cassette, derived from pBCATPH, was cloned into pPTri6-FLuc, resulting in a 8.9-kb plasmid pPTri6-FLuc-H. Similarly, the plasmid DNA carrying the <italic>FLuc</italic> gene fused to a promoter of <italic>ZEB2</italic> was constructed as described above. The <italic>ZEB2</italic> promoter region (1.8 kb) was amplified from Z3643 with the primers ZEBSPLuc5 and ZEBSPLuc3 for the first round of PCR and fused to the <italic>FLuc</italic> PCR product in the second round, followed by a third round with primers ZSLuc5nest and SPLuc3nest. Using the same cloning procedure described above, the final vector pPZEB2&#x2013;Fluc-H was constructed.</p>
        <p>The amplified fusion products or constructed DNA plasmids were added into the protoplasts of WT <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains for transformation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim4">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Lee6">[57]</xref>; pP<italic>Crp&#x2013;GFP&#x2013;FgLaeA</italic>, pPnative&#x2013;<italic>GFP&#x2013;FgLaeA</italic>, and pPnative&#x2013;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> were added into the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain along with pII99 carrying <italic>gen</italic>, respectively, for co-transformation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4f">
        <title>Split Luciferase Complementation Assay</title>
        <p>For split luciferase complementation, the coding regions of the <italic>FgLaeA</italic> and <italic>FgVIP1</italic> genes, which were amplified from total RNA of Z3643 with the primer pairs LaeAnLuc-for2/LaeA-inrev3 and VIP1-forNT/VIP1-revNT, respectively, were introduced into the <italic>Sal</italic>I site of the DNA plasmid pFNLucG <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim5">[43]</xref> carrying an N-terminal fragment of <italic>FLuc</italic> and <italic>gen</italic> using the In-Fusion&#xAE; HD Cloning Kit (Clontech, Mountain View, CA, USA) as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim5">[43]</xref>, creating pFNLuc-FgLaeAG and pFNLuc-FgVIP1G (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068441-t001">Table 1</xref>), respectively. Similarly, the cDNA of <italic>FgVeA</italic> (FGSG_11956.3) was cloned into pFCLucH <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim5">[43]</xref> carrying a C-terminal fragment of <italic>FLuc</italic> and <italic>hygB</italic>, generating pFCLuc&#x2013;FgVeAH (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068441-t001">Table 1</xref>). The DNA plasmid pFCLuc&#x2013;FgVeAH was added into the protoplasts of Z3643 along with either pFNLuc&#x2013;FgLaeAG or pFNLuc&#x2013;FgVIP1G for selection of fungal transformants carrying both plasmids. Luciferase activity was measured from the cell lysates of the transformants grown in CM liquid medium for 3 days, as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim5">[43]</xref>. As a positive control, we included the transgenic <italic>F. graminearum</italic> GzFNCS-1 strain showing high luciferase activity driven by an <italic>in vivo</italic> protein&#x2013;protein interaction between FBP1 and SKP1, fused to NLuc and CLuc, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0068441-Kim5">[43]</xref>. The experiment was repeated three times.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4g">
        <title>Microscopic Observations</title>
        <p>Microscopic observations were performed using an image analysis system consisting of a microscope (Leica DM 2000) with attached digital camera (Leica DFC 550) and a computer.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068441.s001">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>(A) Pigmentation of the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain in the marginal regions between different growing colonies grown on CM agar plate, and (B) when grown in CM liquid medium. Left and right, WT and &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain, respectively.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0068441.s001.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068441.s002">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Reconstructed ion chromatograms of rice culture extracts from the fungal strains derived from 9F1.</bold> WT (9F1), the wild-type 9F1 strain; &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic>, a 9F1 &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain derived from 9F1; add-back, a 9F1 <italic>FgLaeA</italic>-add-back strain derived from the 9F1&#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain. A, 15ADON; C, culmorin; Z, zearalenone.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0068441.s002.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068441.s003">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Expression of </bold><bold><italic>FgLaeA, FgVeA</italic></bold><bold> and </bold><bold><italic>FgVelB</italic></bold><bold> in various </bold><bold><italic>F. gramineaum</italic></bold><bold> strains.</bold> (A) Relative transcript levels of <italic>FgLaeA</italic> in the <italic>FgLaeA-</italic>overexpression and add-back strains, and (B) those of <italic>FgVeA</italic> and <italic>FgVelB</italic> in the &#x394;<italic>FgLaeA</italic> strain derived from Z3643, which were grown in CM liquid medium for vegetative growth, CMC liquid medium for conidiation, AG liquid medium for trichothecene production, and on carrot agar for sexual development. Days of incubation following inoculation in each medium are shown in on the <italic>x</italic>-axis. cycle, 12 h-dark/12 h-light cycle. The amounts of <italic>FgVeA</italic> and <italic>FgVelB</italic> transcripts from a 6-day-old sample in AG liquid medium were used as references in (A) and (B), respectively.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0068441.s003.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068441.s004">
        <label>Figure S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Gene ontology analysis of DEGs in the &#x394;</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>FgLaeA</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> strain grown in AG liquid medium for 60 h.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0068441.s004.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068441.s005">
        <label>Figure S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Distribution of DEGs in the &#x394;</bold><bold><italic>FgLaeA</italic></bold><bold> strain on each chromosome of the </bold><bold><italic>F. graminearum</italic></bold><bold> PH-1 strain.</bold> The genomic locations of histone 3 lysine methylations (H3K7me3 and H3K4me2) were indicated by thin black and red bars, respectively, below the positions of DEGs.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0068441.s005.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068441.s006">
        <label>Figure S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Generation of a firefly luciferase reporter system for trichothecene production.</bold> (A) Scheme for the insertion of the <italic>FLuc</italic> gene under control of a promoter region of <italic>Tri6</italic> into the genome of the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> Z3643 (WT) strain by homologous recombination. (B) <italic>Sal</italic>I-digested genomic DNA gel blot probed with the entire vector. Lane 1, WT strain; lane 2, the FLTRI6 strain. DNA size markers are indicated on the left side of the gel. (C) Luminescence signals in the cell lysate from FLTRI6 grown in AG and complete liquid media, respectively. Days postinoculation (DPI) are indicated below the days of incubation.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0068441.s006.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068441.s007">
        <label>Figure S7</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Generation of firefly luciferase reporter system for zearalenone production.</bold> (A) Scheme for the insertion of the <italic>FLuc</italic> gene under control of a <italic>ZEB2</italic> promoter into the genome of the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> Z3643 (WT) strain by homologous recombination. (B) <italic>Sal</italic>I-digested genomic DNA gel blot probed with the entire vector. Lane 1, WT strain; lanes 2 and 3, the FLZEB2 strains. DNA size markers are indicated on the left side of the gel. (C) Luminescence signals in the cell lysate from a FLZEB2 strain grown in SG and complete liquid media, respectively. Days postinoculation (DPI) are indicated below the days of incubation. Asterisks above the bars indicate a significant difference between two culture conditions for each DPI according to Tukey&#x2019;s test.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0068441.s007.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068441.s008">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Quantification of 15ADON and ZEA levels in fungal rice culture extracts.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0068441.s008.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068441.s009">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Genes down-regulated in the &#x394;</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>FgLaeA</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> strain grown in agmatine-amended liquid medium for 60 h.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0068441.s009.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068441.s010">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Genes up-regulated in the &#x394;</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>FgLaeA</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> strain grown in agmatine-amended liquid medium.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0068441.s010.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068441.s011">
        <label>Table S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>DEGs belonging to tentative functional gene clusters from the &#x394;</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>FgLaeA</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> strain.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0068441.s011.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068441.s012">
        <label>Table S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Grouping of differentially expressed genes in the &#x394;</bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>FgLaeA</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> strain by functional domains.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0068441.s012.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068441.s013">
        <label>Table S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Primers used in this study.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0068441.s013.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We are grateful to Crystal Probyn for her technical assistance, and Stephanie Folmar and Jennifer Teresi for conducting the virulence test.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-McMullen1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McMullen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gallenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Scab of wheat and barley: a re-emerging disease of devastating impact</article-title>. <source>Plant Dis</source><volume>81</volume>: <fpage>1340</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1348</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Desjardins1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Desjardins AE (2006) Fusarium mycotoxin: chemistry, genetics and biology. St. Paul, MN, U.S.A.: APS Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Leslie1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leslie JF, Summerell BA (2006) The Fusarium lab manual. Ames, IA, U.S.A.: Blackwell.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Starkey1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Starkey</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Global molecular surveillance reveals novel Fusarium head blight species and trichothecene toxin diversity</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1191</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17451976</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Sarver1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sarver</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Broz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Novel Fusarium head blight pathogens from Nepal and Louisiana revealed by multilocus genealogical concordance</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>48</volume>: <fpage>1096</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22004876</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-ODonnell1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aberra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Multilocus genotyping and molecular phylogenetics resolve a novel head blight pathogen within the <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> species complex from Ethiopia</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>45</volume>: <fpage>1514</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18824240</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-ODonnell2">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tacke</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Casper</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Gene genealogies reveal global phylogeographic structure and reproductive isolation among lineages of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>, the fungus causing wheat scab</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>97</volume>: <fpage>7905</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7910</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10869425</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-ODonnell3">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geiser</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Corby Kistler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Genealogical concordance between the mating type locus and seven other nuclear genes supports formal recognition of nine phylogenetically distinct species within the <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> clade</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>600</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15121083</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-YliMattila1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yli-Mattila</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gagkaeva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A novel Asian clade within the <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> species complex includes a newly discovered cereal head blight pathogen from the Russian Far East</article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source><volume>101</volume>: <fpage>841</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19927749</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Trail1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trail</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loranger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gadoury</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Physiological and environmental aspects of ascospore discharge in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic> (anamorph <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source><volume>94</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21156487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Marasas1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marasas WFO, Nelson PE, Toussoun TA (1984) Toxigenic <italic>Fusarium</italic> species: identity and mycotoxicology. University Park: The Pennsylvania State University Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Proctor1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hohn</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Reduced virulence of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic> caused by disruption of a trichothecene toxin biosynthetic gene</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>593</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8589414</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Hohn1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hohn</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Characterization of a transcriptional activator controlling trichothecene toxin biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>26</volume>: <fpage>224</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10361036</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Kim1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Two different polyketide synthase genes are required for synthesis of zearalenone in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>58</volume>: <fpage>1102</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16262793</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Gardiner1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Low pH regulates the production of deoxynivalenol by <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source><volume>155</volume>: <fpage>3149</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19497949</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Tudzynski1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tudzynski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Homann</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marzluf</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Isolation, characterization and disruption of the areA nitrogen regulatory gene of <italic>Gibberella fujikuroi</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source><volume>261</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10071216</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Kim2">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woloshuk</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Role of AREA, a regulator of nitrogen metabolism, during colonization of maize kernels and fumonisin biosynthesis in <italic>Fusarium verticillioides</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>45</volume>: <fpage>947</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>953</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18440841</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Flaherty1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Flaherty</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pirttila</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bluhm</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woloshuk</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title><italic>PAC1</italic>, a pH-regulatory gene from <italic>Fusarium verticillioides</italic></article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>69</volume>: <fpage>5222</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12957906</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Min1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Functional analyses of the nitrogen regulatory gene <italic>areA</italic> in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><volume>334</volume>: <fpage>66</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22702217</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Bok1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bok</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>LaeA, a regulator of secondary metabolism in <italic>Aspergillus</italic> spp</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>527</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15075281</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Bayram1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bayram</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krappmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bok</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Helmstaedt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>VelB/VeA/LaeA complex coordinates light signal with fungal development and secondary metabolism</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>320</volume>: <fpage>1504</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18556559</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Bayram2">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bayram</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bayram</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valerius</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Irniger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>LaeA control of velvet family regulatory proteins for light-dependent development and fungal cell-type specificity</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1001226</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21152013</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Amaike1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Amaike</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Distinct roles for VeA and LaeA in development and pathogenesis of <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic></article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1051</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1060</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19411623</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Kale1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kale</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Milde</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trapp</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frisvad</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Requirement of LaeA for secondary metabolism and sclerotial production in <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>45</volume>: <fpage>1422</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18667168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Bok2">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bok</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balajee</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marr</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>LaeA, a regulator of morphogenetic fungal virulence factor</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1574</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16151250</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Perrin1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fedorova</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bok</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wortman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional regulation of chemical diversity in <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> by LaeA</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e50</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17432932</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Wu1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oide</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turgeon</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>ChLae1 and ChVel1 regulate T-toxin production, virulence, oxidative stress response, and development of the maize pathogen <italic>Cochliobolus heterostrophus</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002542</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22383877</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Wiemann1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wiemann P, Brown DW, Kleigrewe K, Bok JW, Keller NP, <etal>et al</etal>. (2010) FfVel1 and FfLae1, components of a velvet-like complex in <italic>Fusarium fujikuroi</italic>, affect differentiation, secondary metabolism and virulence. Mol Microbiol.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Butchko1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Butchko</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Busman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tudzynski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wiemann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Lae1 regulates expression of multiple secondary metabolite gene clusters in <italic>Fusarium verticillioides</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>49</volume>: <fpage>602</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22713715</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-LopezBerges1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lopez-Berges</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sulyok</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Capilla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The velvet complex governs mycotoxin production and virulence of <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> on plant and mammalian hosts</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>87</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23106229</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Seiboth1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seiboth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phatale</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Linke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The putative protein methyltransferase LAE1 controls cellulase gene expression in <italic>Trichoderma reesei</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>84</volume>: <fpage>1150</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22554051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-KarimiAghcheh1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karimi-Aghcheh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bok</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phatale</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Functional analyses of <italic>Trichoderma reesei</italic> LAE1 reveal conserved and contrasting roles of this regulator</article-title>. <source>G3 (Bethesda)</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23390613</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Jiang1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Involvement of a velvet protein FgVeA in the regulation of asexual development, lipid and secondary metabolisms and virulence in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e28291</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22140571</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Lee1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Myong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>FgVelB globally regulates sexual reproduction, mycotoxin production and pathogenicity in the cereal pathogen <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source><volume>158</volume>: <fpage>1723</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22516221</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Jiang2">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>FgVELB is associated with vegetative differentiation, secondary metabolism and virulence in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>49</volume>: <fpage>653</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>662</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22713714</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Kwon1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Assessment of the core cryparin promoter from <italic>Cryphonectria parasitica</italic> for heterologous expression in filamentous fungi</article-title>. <source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><volume>83</volume>: <fpage>339</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19238380</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Kim3">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Putative polyketide synthase and laccase genes for biosynthesis of aurofusarin in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1701</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15811992</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-McCormick1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>CLM1 of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> encodes a longiborneol synthase required for culmorin production</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>76</volume>: <fpage>136</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19880637</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Kim4">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Functional analyses of individual mating-type transcripts at <italic>MAT</italic> loci in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> and <italic>Fusarium asiaticum</italic></article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><volume>337</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22998651</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Son1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A phenome-based functional analysis of transcription factors in the cereal head blight fungus, <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002310</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22028654</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Lee2">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lee W (2010) Comprehensive discovery of fungal gene clusters: unexpected co-work reflected at the genomic level. M&#xFC;nchen, Germany: Technische Universit&#xE4;t M&#xFC;nchen.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Lee3">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Functional analyses of two acetyl coenzyme A synthetases in the ascomycete <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1043</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21666077</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Kim5">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A split luciferase complementation assay for studying in vivo protein-protein interactions in filamentous ascomycetes</article-title>. <source>Curr Genet</source><volume>58</volume>: <fpage>179</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22531843</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Shwab1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shwab</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bok</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tribus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galehr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Graessle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Histone deacetylase activity regulates chemical diversity in <italic>Aspergillus</italic></article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1656</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17616629</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Hoff1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoff</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kamerewerd</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sigl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mitterbauer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zadra</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Two components of a <italic>velvet</italic>-like complex control hyphal morphogenesis, conidiophore development, and penicillin biosynthesis in <italic>Penicillium chrysogenum</italic></article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source><volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1236</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20543063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Lee4">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Identification of the down-regulated genes in a <italic>mat1&#x2013;2-</italic>deleted strain of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic>, using cDNA subtraction and microarray analysis</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>43</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16504554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Lee5">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turgeon</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Shifting fungal reproductive mode by manipulation of mating type genes: obligatory heterothallism of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>50</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14507370</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Capellini1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Capellini</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>1965</year>) <article-title>Macroconidium formation in submerged cultures by a nonsporulating strain of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source><volume>57</volume>: <fpage>962</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>966</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Gardiner2">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Nutrient profiling reveals potent inducers of trichothecene biosynthesis in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>46</volume>: <fpage>604</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19406250</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Chi1">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A quick and safe method for fungal DNA extraction</article-title>. <source>Plant Pathology J</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>108</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>111</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Sambrook1">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sambrook J, Russell DW (2001) Molecular cloning: a laboratory manual. Plainview, U.S.A.: Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Kim6">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of potential reference genes for quantitative RT-PCR analysis in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> under different culture conditions</article-title>. <source>Plant Pathol J</source><volume>27</volume>: <fpage>301</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>309</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Seo1">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Variation in 8-ketotrichothecenes and zearalenone production by <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> isolates from corn and barley in Korea</article-title>. <source>Mycopathologia</source><volume>134</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20882466</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Catlett1">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Catlett</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turgeon</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Split-marker recombination for efficient targeted deletion of fungal genes</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Newsl</source><volume>50</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Namiki1">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Namiki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsunaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Mutation of an arginine biosynthesis gene causes reduced pathogenicity in <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f. sp. <italic>melonis</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>580</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11310747</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Yu1">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamari</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reyes-Dominguez</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Double-joint PCR: a PCR-based molecular tool for gene manipulations in filamentous fungi</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>973</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15465386</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0068441-Lee6">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Estrogenic compounds compatible with a conditional gene expression system for the phytopathogenic fungus <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Pathol J</source><volume>27</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>353</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
