<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3707864</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-33456</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0069737</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Effects of External Potassium (K) Supply on Drought Tolerances of Two Contrasting Winter Wheat Cultivars</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Effects of K Supply on Drought Tolerance of Wheat</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>Jiguang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Caihong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Yong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>Gaoming</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cheng</surname>
            <given-names>Guanglei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <given-names>Yanhai</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Vegetation and Environmental Change, Institute of Botany, the Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, PR China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Soil Erosion and Dryland Farming on the Loess Plateau, Northwest A&amp;F University, Yangling, Shanxi, PR China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>University of the Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, PR China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff4">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line>Beijing Academy of Agriculture and Forestry Sciences, Beijing, PR China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Pandey</surname>
            <given-names>Girdhar&#xA0;K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>University of Delhi South Campus, India</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>zhengyanhai333@163.com</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: Y-HZ G-MJ. Performed the experiments: J-GW C-HL YL G-LC. Analyzed the data: J-GW. Wrote the manuscript: J-GW Y-HZ. </p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <elocation-id>e69737</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Wei et al</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec sec-type="headed">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Drought is a common stress limiting crops growth and productivities worldwide. Water deficit may increase cellular membrane permeability, resulting in K outflow. Internal K starvation may disorder plant metabolism and limit plant growth. However, it is seldom reported about the effects of external K on drought tolerance of contrasting wheat cultivars.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="headed">
          <title>Methodology/Principal Findings</title>
          <p>A hydroponics experiment was carried out in a non-controlled greenhouse. Seedlings of drought-tolerant SN16 and intolerant JM22 were simultaneously treated by five levels of K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> (0, 2.5, 5, 7.5, 10 mM) and two levels of PEG6000 (0, 20%) for 7 days. External K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> significantly increased shoot K<sup>+</sup> content, water potential, chlorophyll content as well as gas exchange, but decreased electrolyte leakage (EL) and MDA content in both cultivars under PEG6000 stress. Antioxidant enzymes activities were up-regulated by PEG6000 while external K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> reduced those changes. Molecular basis was explained by measuring the expression levels of antioxidant enzymes related genes. Shoot and root biomass were also increased by K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> supply under drought stress. Although adequate K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> application enhanced plant growth for both cultivars under drought stress, SN16 was better than JM22 due to its high drought tolerance.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="headed">
          <title>Conclusions/Significance</title>
          <p>Adequate external K may effectively protect winter wheat from drought injuries. We conclude that drought-tolerant wheat combined with adequate external K supply may be a promising strategy for better growth in arid and semi-arid regions.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This research was jointly supported by Grants from State Key Laboratory of Soil Erosion and Dryland Farming on Loess Plateau (10501-263), the State Key Laboratory of Crop Biology at Shandong Agricultural University (2010KF08), the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31170367) and the Key Laboratory of Crop Water Physiology and Drought-tolerance Germplasm Improvement, Ministry of Agriculture, P. R. China (2012KF03). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Potassium (K) is a key element for crops growth and productivities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Normally, K<sup>+</sup> influx is in balance with K<sup>+</sup> outflow in K<sup>+</sup>-repletion plants, however, plant growth is limited if the K<sup>+</sup> supply is interrupted, such as excessive K<sup>+</sup> outflow caused by increasing of cellular membrane permeability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Stress conditions (salinity, drought, etc.) influence the capacity of unidirectional K<sup>+</sup> influx and net K<sup>+</sup> uptake, while internal K<sup>+</sup> concentration is exerted by both K<sup>+</sup> influx and cell K<sup>+</sup> conservation in the face of adversity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p>
      <p>Drought is a common stress to damage plant cellular membrane integrity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Drought-induced overproduction of reactive oxygen species (ROS) may aggravate lipid peroxidation and increase cellular membrane permeability, resulting in excessive K<sup>+</sup> outflow and limiting plant growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Ions outflow may increase the cytoplasm water potential and decrease plant water absorbance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Internal K starvation may decrease some K<sup>+</sup>-depended enzymes activities and disorder plant physiological metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. In addition, K starvation often activates overlapping cell signaling pathways and cellular responses, such as the reductions of chlorophyll production and photosynthetic capacity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Electrolyte leakage (EL) and MDA content are two parameters to assess cellular membrane permeability and lipid peroxidation, and the increases of both parameters may indicate drought aggravation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Antioxidant enzymes activities are direct indicators for ROS scavenging ability and plant drought tolerance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p>
      <p>Our previous studies show that external K may effectively elevate leaf K<sup>+</sup> concentration of salinity-stressed wheat and protect winter wheat from salinity injuries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. However, little is known about the responses of drought-stressed winter wheat to exogenous K and the differential responses between cultivars with contrasting drought adaptation behaviors. Here, we hypothesize that external K may increase plant drought tolerance of winter wheat by enhancing internal K<sup>+</sup> concentration under drought stress.</p>
      <p>To test the above hypothesis, a hydroponics experiment was conducted to investigate the effects of exogenous K on leaf K<sup>+</sup> content, water potential, chlorophyll content, gas exchange, cellular membrane integrity, antioxidant enzymes activities and shoot/root biomass yield of two winter wheat cultivars differing in drought tolerance. Molecular basis was also explained by measuring the expression levels of antioxidant enzymes related genes. More specifically, the present study addressed the following three questions: (1) Can external K significantly increase plant internal K and protect winter wheat from drought injuries? (2) Are there any differential responses to external K between wheat cultivars differing in drought tolerance? (3) What is the best combination between wheat variety and K application in arid and semi-arid regions?</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2.1">
        <title>Gas exchange</title>
        <p>In well-watered plants, non-significant effects of 2.5 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> concentration on light-saturated net photosynthetic rate (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>) were noted in both cultivars, but significant adverse effects were measured at 5.0, 7.5 and 10.0 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g001">Figure 1A)</xref>. PEG6000 considerably reduced <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> of both cultivars, with the extent being smaller in SN16 than in JM22 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g001">Figure 1B)</xref>. Under PEG6000-stressed condition, no significant increase of <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> was found in SN16 but it did in JM22 by K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> supply.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0069737-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0069737.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of exogenous K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> on light-saturated net photosynthetic rate (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>) and stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) in SN16 and JM22 under different water treatments.</title>
            <p>(<italic>A</italic>, <italic>C</italic>) Plants are in well-watered condition. (<italic>B</italic>, <italic>D</italic>) Plants are in 20% PEG6000-stressed condition. Vertical bars denote SE (<italic>n =6</italic>). Different letters indicate significant at <italic>p</italic> &#x2264;0.05.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0069737.g001"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The variation trends of stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) were similar with <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> in both cultivars in either well-watered condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g001">Figure 1C)</xref> or PEG6000-stressed condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g001">Figure 1D)</xref>. Obviously, both <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> and <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> were always higher in SN16 than in JM22 in each K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> treatment under PEG6000-stressed condition.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2.2">
        <title>K<sup>+</sup> contents in shoot and root</title>
        <p>The K<sup>+</sup> contents in both shoot and root were little higher in SN16 than in JM22 in control (no PEG6000, 0 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>) plants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1)</xref>. External K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> significantly increased internal K<sup>+</sup> contents of both cultivars under well-watered conditions. PEG6000 drastically reduced K<sup>+</sup> contents in both shoot and root of two cultivars. Adequate K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> application increased K<sup>+</sup> content in both shoot and root, with the extent being larger in root than in shoot in both cultivars. The K<sup>+</sup> content in shoot peaked at 7.5 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> in both cultivars, while the maximum values in roots were noted in 10 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> treatment.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of external K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> on shoot/root K<sup>+</sup> content of drought-tolerant SN16 and intolerant JM22 under well-watered and PEG6000-stressed conditions.</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">K<sup>+</sup> content in SN16</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">K<sup>+</sup> content in JM22</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEG-6000 (w/v)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> (mM)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shoot (mg g<sup>-1</sup> DM)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root (mg g<sup>-1</sup> DM)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shoot (mg g<sup>-1</sup> DM)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root (mg g<sup>-1</sup> DM)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.2&#xB1;0.7b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8&#xB1;0.9d</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.7&#xB1;0.8c</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7&#xB1;0.5d</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.1&#xB1;1.1b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8&#xB1;0.7c</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.9&#xB1;0.9b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4&#xB1;0.7c</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.5&#xB1;0.9b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9&#xB1;0.8b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.1&#xB1;1.2a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.8&#xB1;0.8b</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.7&#xB1;0.3a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.8&#xB1;0.6a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5&#xB1;1.3a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6&#xB1;0.9a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.0&#xB1;1.4a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1&#xB1;0.7a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.5&#xB1;1.4a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2&#xB1;0.9a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20%</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.8&#xB1;1.2b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9&#xB1;0.2e</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.9&#xB1;0.7c</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7&#xB1;0.1d</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5&#xB1;2.1a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7&#xB1;0.3d</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5&#xB1;0.8b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2&#xB1;0.2c</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.6&#xB1;1.5a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5&#xB1;0.3c</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0&#xB1;0.6a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0&#xB1;0.2b</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.6&#xB1;1.1a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8&#xB1;0.4b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.8&#xB1;0.5a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2&#xB1;0.4a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0&#xB1;1.7a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7&#xB1;0.3a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0&#xB1;0.6b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7&#xB1;0.6a</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>Significance analyses of data were performed using ANOVA analysis in SPSS package (Ver. 11, SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). Within each column, means followed by different letter are significantly changed at <italic>p</italic> &#x2264;0.05</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2.3">
        <title>Water potential and chlorophyll content</title>
        <p>Under well-watered condition, non-significant effects of 2.5 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> supply on &#x3A8;<sub>l</sub> were measured in both cultivars, while drastic decreases were noted in 7.5-10 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> treatments in SN16 and 5-10 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> treatments in JM22 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g002">Figure 2A)</xref>. PEG6000-induced reduction of &#x3A8;<sub>l</sub> was smaller in SN16 than in JM22. In PEG6000-stressed plants, adequate K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> application significantly increased &#x3A8;<sub>l</sub> of both cultivars, and they peaked at 7.5 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> concentration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g002">Figure 2B)</xref>. The &#x3A8;<sub>l</sub> of SN16 was always higher than that of JM22 in each K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> treatment under PEG6000-stressed condition.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0069737-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0069737.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> application on leaf water potential (<italic>&#x3A8;</italic><sub>l</sub>) and Chlorophyll (Chl) contents in SN16 and JM22 under different water treatments.</title>
            <p>(<italic>A</italic>, <italic>C</italic>) Plants are in well-watered condition. (<italic>B</italic>, <italic>D</italic>) Plants are in 20% PEG6000-stressed condition. Vertical bars denote SE (<italic>n =6</italic>). Different letters indicate significant at <italic>p</italic> &#x2264;0.05.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0069737.g002"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In well-watered plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g002">Figure 2C)</xref>, non-significant differences were determined in chlorophyll (Chl) contents of both cultivars in 2.5-7.5 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> application except 7.5 mM in JM22, however, considerable reductions occurred in 10 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> treatment than control. PEG6000 alone obviously decreased Chl contents, with the extent being smaller in SN16 than in JM22 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g002">Figure 2C and D)</xref>. Adequate external K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> drastically increased Chl contents in both cultivars under PEG6000 stress.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2.4">
        <title>Electrolyte leakage and MDA content</title>
        <p>In well-watered plants, no significant differences were noted in electrolyte leakage (EL) between K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> treatments in both cultivars (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g003">Figure 3A)</xref>. PEG6000 significantly increased EL in both cultivars, with the extent being larger in JM22 than in SN16. Under PEG6000-stressed condition, external K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> supply drastically reduced EL in both cultivars, with the best treatments being 5-7.5 mM for SN16 and 7.5 mM for JM22 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g003">Figure 3B)</xref>. However, higher EL was noted in 10 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> than in 7.5 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> treatment in both cultivars.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0069737-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0069737.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of exogenous K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> on electrolyte leakage (EL) and malondialdehyde (MDA) content in SN16 and JM22 under different water treatments.</title>
            <p>(<italic>A</italic>, <italic>C</italic>) Plants treated with 0% PEG6000. (<italic>B</italic>, <italic>D</italic>) Plants treated with 20% PEG6000. Vertical bars denote SE (<italic>n =6</italic>). Different letters indicate significant at <italic>p</italic> &#x2264;0.05.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0069737.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The responses of MDA content to K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> application in both well-watered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g003">Figure 3C)</xref> and PEG6000-stressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g003">Figure 3D)</xref> conditions were similar to the variation trends of EL in two wheat cultivars. Both EL and MDA content were smaller in SN16 than in JM22 in each K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> treatment under PEG6000-stressed condition.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2.5">
        <title>Antioxidant enzymes activities and expression levels of their related genes</title>
        <p>In well-watered plants, superoxide dismutase (SOD) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g004">Figure 4A)</xref>, peroxidase (POD) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g004">Figure 4C)</xref> and catalase (CAT) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g004">Figure 4E)</xref> activities were significantly enhanced by K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> application (except 2.5 mM) in both cultivars. PEG6000 increased those parameters in both cultivars, with the extents being larger in JM22 than in SN16. In PEG6000-stressed plants, only 7.5 mM external K supply drastically decreased the activities of SOD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g004">Figure 4B)</xref> and CAT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g004">Figure 4F)</xref>, but significant effects of 2.5-7.5 mM K supply were noted on POD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g004">Figure 4D)</xref> activities in both cultivars. Those antioxidant enzymes activities increased in 10 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> than in 7.5 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> treatment.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0069737-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0069737.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of exogenous K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> on superoxide dismutase (SOD), peroxidase (POD) and catalase (CAT) activities in SN16 and JM22 under different water treatments.</title>
            <p>(<italic>A</italic>, <italic>C</italic>, <italic>E</italic>) Plants treated with 0% PEG6000. (<italic>B</italic>, <italic>D</italic>, <italic>F</italic>) Plants treated with 20% PEG6000. Vertical bars denote SE (<italic>n =6</italic>). Different letters indicate significant at <italic>p</italic> &#x2264;0.05.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0069737.g004"/>
        </fig>
        <p>External K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> (+K) supply significantly up-regulated the expression levels of SOD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g005">Figure 5A)</xref> and CAT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g005">Figure 5B)</xref> related genes of both SN16 and JM22 in &#x2013;PEG but down-regulated them in +PEG condition. No-significant increases induced by K application were noted in the expression levels of APX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g005">Figure 5C)</xref> and GPX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g005">Figure 5D)</xref> related genes of two cultivars in &#x2013;PEG but considerable decreases occurred in +PEG condition. Nevertheless, PEG alone (under &#x2013;K condition) drastically up-regulated the expression levels of all antioxidant enzymes related genes in both cultivars.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0069737-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0069737.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The expression levels of antioxidant enzymes related genes (SOD (<italic>A</italic>), CAT (<italic>B</italic>), APX (<italic>C</italic>) and GPX (<italic>D</italic>)) in SN16 and JM22 under different K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> and PEG6000 treatments.</title>
            <p>Data are mean &#xB1; SE (<italic>n</italic> =3).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0069737.g005"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2.6">
        <title>Plant growth and biomass yield</title>
        <p>Plant height and root length peaked at 2.5 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> level in both cultivars in well-watered condition (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table 2)</xref>. Both parameters were decreased by PEG6000 in two cultivars, with the extent being smaller in SN16 than in JM22. Under PEG6000-stressed condition, plant height and root length increased by adequate external K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> and both parameters peaked at 5.0-7.5 mM in two cultivars.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of external K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> on shoot/root dry masses of drought-tolerant SN16 and intolerant JM22 under well-watered and PEG6000-stressed conditions.</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shoot</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cultivar</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEG6000 (w/v)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> (mM)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant height (cm)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry mass (mg)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root length (cm)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry mass (mg)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SN16</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.45&#xB1;0.63b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31&#xB1;0.03b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.33&#xB1;0.43a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11&#xB1;0.00b</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.45&#xB1;0.93a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38&#xB1;0.03a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.02&#xB1;0.92a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15&#xB1;0.02a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.14&#xB1;1.02a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.43&#xB1;0.63a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14&#xB1;0.03a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.02&#xB1;0.82b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32&#xB1;0.02b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.41&#xB1;0.71a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13&#xB1;0.01a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.27&#xB1;0.72c</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27&#xB1;0.02c</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.28&#xB1;0.52a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10&#xB1;0.01b</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20%</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.21&#xB1;0.43b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22&#xB1;0.03b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.92&#xB1;0.53b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09&#xB1;0.00b</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.83&#xB1;0.52b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24&#xB1;0.02b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.21&#xB1;0.72b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11&#xB1;0.01a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.31&#xB1;0.71a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.37&#xB1;0.43a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13&#xB1;0.02a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.01&#xB1;0.93a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31&#xB1;0.03a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.39&#xB1;0.63a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12&#xB1;0.02a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.26&#xB1;1.03a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26&#xB1;0.02b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.77&#xB1;0.32b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10&#xB1;0.01b</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JM22</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.28&#xB1;0.72b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.22&#xB1;0.33b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08&#xB1;0.00b</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.92&#xB1;0.64a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.21&#xB1;0.73a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13&#xB1;0.02a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.79&#xB1;0.83b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.02&#xB1;0.42a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12&#xB1;0.02a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.28&#xB1;1.03b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27&#xB1;0.03a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.59&#xB1;0.62b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11&#xB1;0.01a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.28&#xB1;1.12c</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23&#xB1;0.03b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.29&#xB1;0.93c</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06&#xB1;0.01c</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20%</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.21&#xB1;0.54b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19&#xB1;0.04b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.09&#xB1;0.34b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07&#xB1;0.00b</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.10&#xB1;0.63b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21&#xB1;0.01b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.28&#xB1;0.56b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07&#xB1;0.01b</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.76&#xB1;0.82a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.35&#xB1;0.32a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09&#xB1;0.01a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.15&#xB1;0.55a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26&#xB1;0.05a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.12&#xB1;0.55a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11&#xB1;0.02a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.35&#xB1;0.86c</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23&#xB1;0.06b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.01&#xB1;0.37b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08&#xB1;0.01b</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>Significance analyses of data were performed using ANOVA analysis in SPSS package (Ver. 11, SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). Within each column, means followed by different letter are significantly changed at <italic>p</italic> &#x2264;0.05</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Adequate K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> application (2.5-5.0 mM) significantly increased shoot and root masses in both cultivars under well-watered condition. PEG6000 alone obviously decreased shoot and root dry masses in both cultivars. External K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> significantly increased shoot and root masses of both cultivars under PEG6000-stressed condition, with peaks being noted in 5-7.5 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> treatment. The K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>-induced increases of biomass were larger in root than in shoot in both cultivars.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2.7">
        <title>PEG6000, K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> and their interaction</title>
        <p>Significant (<italic>p</italic> &#x2264;0.05) effects of PEG6000, K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> and PEG6000&#xD7;K <sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> (except root length) were noted on all growth, physiological and biochemical parameters (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab3">Table 3)</xref>. Considerable effects of cultivar and cultivar&#xD7;PEG6000 were also measured in most those parameters. However, no significant effects of cultivar&#xD7;K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> were noted in growth and physiological parameters except plant height. Cultivar&#xD7;K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>&#xD7;PEG6000 significantly affected most biochemical parameters, <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>, plant height and shoot mass, but not for root length and root mass.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tab3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects (P-values) of cultivar, PEG6000, K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> and their interactions on plant physiological and biochemical parameters of winter wheat analyzed using three-way (cultivar, PEG6000 and K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> as the fixed factors) general linear model in SPSS (Ver. 11, SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). </title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cultivars(Cv)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEG6000(P)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>(K)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cv&#xD7;P</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cv&#xD7;K</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P&#xD7;K</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cv&#xD7;P&#xD7;K</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant height</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.001</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.014</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.049</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root length</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.008</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.001</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.914</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.840</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.786</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shoot mass</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.477</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.042</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.964</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.025</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root mass</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.049</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.002</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.038</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.392</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.398</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>A</italic>
                  <sub>sat</sub>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.024</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.263</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.039</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>g</italic>
                  <sub>s</sub>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.356</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.001</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shoot K<sup>+</sup></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.379</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chl</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.009</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.019</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>&#x3A8;</italic>
                  <sub>l</sub>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EL</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDA</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.341</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.522</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOD</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.916</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.020</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">POD</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.001</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.036</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.022</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.033</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAT</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.017</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.000</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>0.009</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p><italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>, light-saturated photosynthetic rate; <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>, stamotal conductance; Chl, chlorophyll; EL, electrolyte leakage; MDA, malondialdehyde; SOD, superoxide dismutase; POD, peroxidase; CAT, catalase. The bold numerals highlight the significance at <italic>p</italic> &#x2264;0.05.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s3.1">
        <title>External K increased shoot/root K<sup>+</sup> content and gas exchange</title>
        <p>Stress-induced K<sup>+</sup> outflow decreases internal K<sup>+</sup> supply and limits plant growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Potassium starvation may cause plant physiological disorder, which lead to tissue dehydration in water-stressed crops [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. In this study, adequate external K significantly increased K<sup>+</sup> contents in both shoot and root of PEG6000-stressed plants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1)</xref>. This might be explained that (1) higher K<sup>+</sup> concentration in plant growing medium offered more opportunity for roots absorbing K<sup>+</sup>; (2) cellular membrane recovery enhanced K<sup>+</sup> conservation in plant tissues.</p>
        <p>Stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) may be decided by the water potential which depends on ions concentration in stoma guard-cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. External K might increase the K<sup>+</sup> concentration in stoma guard-cells, leading to considerable enhancement of <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Generally, significant positive correlation exists between <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> and light-saturated net photosynthetic rate (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Drought-induced K<sup>+</sup> outflow significantly decreased <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> and <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> in both drought-tolerant and intolerant wheat, however, adequate K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> application effectively recovered both parameters by increasing shoot/root K<sup>+</sup> contents under drought stress. Both shoot and root biomasses were enhanced by adequate external K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> supply in PEG6000-stressed condition.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3.2">
        <title>External K protected cellular membrane under drought stress</title>
        <p>Drought-induced overproduction of reactive oxygen species (ROS) may aggravate cellular lipid peroxidation, leading to an increase of cellular membrane permeability, evidenced by increases of electronic leakage (EL) and MDA content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. High ions outflow may induce ions imbalance in plant tissues and lead to a physiological metabolic disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. In this study, adequate external K supply significantly reduced EL and MDA content (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g003">Figure 3)</xref>, which might indicate that it protects cellular membrane of drought-stressed plants. This might be explained that (1) adequate K supply enhances cellular membrane stability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]; (2) adequate external K supply may increase some solutes (such as proline, etc.) production and enhance plant osmotic adjustment ability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]; (3) adequate external K reduces ROS production and its oxidative injuries under drought stress. However, excessive K supply also adversely affects the cellular membrane integrity in both drought-tolerant and intolerant winter wheat cultivars.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3.3">
        <title>Antioxidant enzymes activities and the expression levels of their related genes</title>
        <p>Antioxidant enzymes activities were considered as indicators of scavenging ROS and reducing oxidative stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. For example, SOD may convert superoxide radicals into H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> was further decomposed by CAT and POD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. In this study, PEG6000 significantly increased the antioxidant enzymes activities, with the extent being larger in drought-intolerant than in drought-tolerant wheat cultivar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0069737-g004">Figure 4)</xref>. Adequate external K supply significantly decreased antioxidant enzymes activities in PEG6000-stressed plants might be caused by enhancing plant physiological metabolism and reducing ROS production. However, excessive K supply also aggravated plant oxidative stress.</p>
        <p>The expression levels of antioxidant enzymes related genes are known to be responsible for antioxidant enzymes production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. PEG6000 significantly up-regulated the expression levels of antioxidant enzymes related genes, with the extents being larger in drought-intolerant than in drought-tolerant wheat. Adequate external K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> supply decreased the expression levels of antioxidant enzymes related genes in both cultivars under PEG6000-stressed condition. The results were consistent with the variation trends of antioxidant enzymes activities.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3.4">
        <title>Interaction of cultivar, PEG6000 and K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> to plant growth</title>
        <p>Significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x2264;0.05) effects of cultivar, PEG6000 and K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> were noted in growth, physiological and biochemical parameters (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab3">Table 3)</xref>. The effects of cultivar were significant in plant height, root length and root mass. This might indicate that plant growth characteristics closely correlated with its drought tolerance. Significant effects of cultivar&#xD7;PEG6000 were noted in growth parameters but not of cultivar&#xD7;K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>. These might point out that cultivars differently response to PEG6000 but not to external K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> supply. In addition, significant effects of PEG6000&#xD7;K <sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>&#xD7;cultivar were measured in plant height and shoot mass, which might indicate that significant interactions existed in aboveground plants between cultivar and external K supply under drought stress.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3.5">
        <title>Conclusions and future perspectives</title>
        <p>Adequate external K supply protected winter wheat from drought injuries by reducing ROS production, enhancing K<sup>+</sup> content and cellular membrane integrity, resulting in an increase of plant photosynthetic capacity.</p>
        <p>Similar effects of external K were noted on drought-tolerant and intolerant wheat cultivars, however, the former growth performed better than the later due to its less damage by drought stress. Hence drought-tolerant cultivar combined with adequate external K supply may be a promising strategy for crops better growth and higher productivity in arid and semi-arid regions.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4.1">
        <title>Plant culture</title>
        <p>SN16, a hybrid of high-yield JN13 (female parent) &#xD7; drought-tolerant 635 (male parent), is a typical drought-tolerant wheat cultivar which mainly demonstrated in arid and semi-arid croplands, and JM22, a drought-intolerant wheat cultivar, is a popular high-yield variety grown in adequate water farmlands in Shandong Province, China. Fifteen-day-old seedlings of SN16 and JM22 were equally transplanted and grown in 60 plastic boxes (length &#xD7; width &#xD7; height = 26 &#xD7; 18 &#xD7; 12 cm<sup>3</sup>) containing 1/2 Hoagland nutrient solution (pH =5.5), with 15 SN16 and 15 JM22 being separately planted in each box. Referring to our previous study on salt stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], five levels of K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> (0, 2.5, 5, 7.5 and 10 mM) and two levels of PEG6000 (0, 20%) were simultaneously treated after 3 days adaptation. No K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> and PEG6000 treatment was used as control. Six replications were exposed for each treatment. The pH value of each solution was adjusted to 5.5 with diluted H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. Water lost was replenished daily by weighing method during the experiment. The photosynthetic photon flux density (PPFD) was approximately 800-1200 &#xB5;mol m<sup>-2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> at canopy height. The temperature in the greenhouse fluctuated from 15&#xB0;C (night) to 25&#xB0;C (day), with the relative humidity (RH) being kept in 15-35%. Physiological and biochemical parameters were measured 7 d after K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> and PEG6000 treatments. And the expression patterns of antioxidant enzymes related genes were examined at transcriptional levels by qPCR in -K and +K (5 mM K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>) combined with &#x2013;PEG and +PEG (20% PEG6000) treatments.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4.2">
        <title>Gas exchange</title>
        <p>Gas exchange was measured on the most recently fully expanded leaves (third leaves) using a portable gas exchange system (<italic>LI-6400, LI-COR</italic>, USA). Relative humidity (RH) varied from 15&#x2013;25%, and leaf temperature was set at 25 &#xB0;C in the leaf chamber. The flow rate was set at 500 &#xB5;mol s<sup>-1</sup>. The leaf was illuminated with a PPFD of 1200 &#xB5;mol m<sup>-2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> (saturated light) with an internal light source in the leaf chamber. After the gas exchange conditions were stabilized, the light-saturated net photosynthetic rate (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>) and stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) were simultaneously recorded.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4.3">
        <title>Leaf water potential and chlorophyll content</title>
        <p>Leaf water potential (&#x3A8;<sub>l</sub>) was measured following the method of Jongdee et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. Ten most recently fully expanded leaves were sampled from 10 plants which grown in same box of each treatment, cut into pieces and spread evenly on the bottom of the sample cup to determine &#x3A8;<sub>l</sub> with a Water Potential Meter (<italic>WP4-T</italic>, <italic>Decagon Devices</italic>, Pullman, WA, USA).</p>
        <p>Samples (0.05 g) were incubated in centrifuge tubes containing 10 ml 80% acetone under dark conditions for 36 h and centrifuged at 5000&#xD7;<italic>g</italic> for 10 min. The extracts were decanted and completed to 25 ml. The absorbance of the extracts was recorded at 663 and 645 nm, respectively. Chlorophyll contents were calculated using the following formulas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]:</p>
        <p>Chl (mg g<sup>-1</sup> DM) =(20.2&#xD7;<italic>A</italic><sub>645</sub>+8.02&#xD7;<italic>A</italic><sub>663</sub>) &#xD7;<italic>V</italic>/(<italic>DM</italic> &#xD7; 1000)</p>
        <p>Where <italic>A</italic><sub>663</sub> and <italic>A</italic><sub>645</sub> are the absorbance at 663 and 645 nm, respectively, <italic>V</italic> is the volume of the extract and <italic>DM</italic> is the dry mass of the sample.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4.4">
        <title>K<sup>+</sup> contents</title>
        <p>K<sup>+</sup> contents in shoot and root of winter wheat were assayed following the method described by Zheng et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Dry samples of shoots and roots were finely ground before passing through a 2-mm sieve. Approximately 0.2 g samples were soaked for 12 h in digesting tubes with 8 ml concentrated nitric acid and 2 ml perchloric acid and then digested at 300&#xB0;C for 6 h. The extractions were completed to 50 ml with deionized water. K<sup>+</sup> contents were determined using a sequential plasma spectrometer (<italic>ICPS-7500</italic>, <italic>SHIMADZU</italic>, JAPAN).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4.5">
        <title>Cellular membrane permeability</title>
        <p>Cellular membrane permeability was assessed by measuring electrolyte leakage (EL) following the method described by Tripathy et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. Ten 4-cm length leaf middle sections were soaked in test tubes containing 10 ml deionized water and incubated at 25&#xB0;C for 2 h to measure the initial electrical conductivity (EC<sub>1</sub>). The samples were autoclaved at 100&#xB0;C for 20 min to release electrolytes, and then cooled to 25&#xB0;C to measure the final electrical conductivity (EC<sub>2</sub>). EL was calculated using the following formula:</p>
        <p>EL = 100&#xD7;EC<sub>1</sub>/EC<sub>2</sub></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4.6">
        <title>Lipid peroxidation and antioxidant enzyme activities</title>
        <p>Leaf samples were collected, immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and transferred to an ultra-freezer at -80 &#xB0;C until the time of assay. Samples (about 0.5 g) were crushed into fine powder in an ice-cold mortar with 10 ml 0.05 M KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> (pH 7.8) buffer. The homogenate was centrifuged at 10000&#xD7;<italic>g</italic> for 20 min, with the supernatants being further prepared to measure MDA contents and antioxidant enzyme activities. These processes were performed at 0&#x2013;4 &#xB0;C.</p>
        <p>Lipid peroxidation was assessed by measuring the malondialdehyde (MDA) content according to Draper and Hadley [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. A mixture of 1 ml extract and 2 ml 0.6% thiobarbituric acid (TBA) was boiled for 15 min, cooled and centrifuged for 10 min at 10000&#xD7;<italic>g</italic>. The content of MDA was determined from the absorbance at 600, 532 and 450 nm and then calculated using the following formula:</p>
        <p>MDA (&#x3BC;mol g<sup>-1</sup> FM) = (6.45&#xD7;(<italic>A</italic><sub>532</sub>-<italic>A</italic><sub>600</sub>)-0.56&#xD7;<italic>A</italic><sub>450</sub>) &#xD7;<italic>V</italic><sub>t</sub>/(<italic>V</italic><sub>s</sub>&#xD7;FM)</p>
        <p>where <italic>A</italic><sub>600</sub>, <italic>A</italic><sub>532</sub> and <italic>A</italic><sub>450</sub> are the absorbances at 600, 532 and 450 nm, respectively, <italic>V</italic><sub>t</sub> is the volume of extract, <italic>V</italic><sub>s</sub> is the volume of the test extract and FM is the fresh mass of the sample.</p>
        <p>Superoxide dismutase (SOD) activity was determined following the method described by Zheng et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. One enzyme unit of SOD activity (U) was defined as the amount of crude enzyme extract required for inhibiting the reduction rate of nitro-blue tetrazolium (NBT) by 50%. Peroxidase (POD) was estimated by measuring the oxidation of guaiacol. The guaiacol reagent was composed of 50 ml 0.1 M KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> (pH 6.0) buffer, 28 &#xB5;L guaiacol and 19 &#xB5;L 30% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. A mixture of 20 &#xB5;L crude enzyme extract + 3 ml guaiacol reagent was formed, and the absorbance was continuously recorded five times at 470 nm in 30 s intervals. Variation of absorbance per minute per gram fresh mass (&#x22BF;A470 min-1 g-1 FM) served for POD activity. Activity for CAT was expressed as variation of absorbance per minute per gram fresh mass (&#x22BF;A240 min-1 g-1 FM). All spectrophotometric analyses were conducted on a UV/visible light spectrophotometer (<italic>UV-2450, SHIMADZU</italic>, JAPAN).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4.7">
        <title>Plant growth and biomass yield</title>
        <p>Plants were harvested immediately after the above physiological and biochemical measurements. Twenty plants of individual cultivar which randomly picked from six replicates of each K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> and PEG6000 treatments were cleaned and measured plant height and root length, then separated into shoots and roots and oven-dried at 75&#xB0;C to constant weight. Biomass of shoot and root was then recorded, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4.8">
        <title>Expression patterns of antioxidant enzymes related genes</title>
        <p>Total RNAs were extracted from harvested leaves of wheat with Trizol reagent (Invitrogen). The total RNAs were reversely transcribed into first-strand cDNA with PrimeScript<sup>&#xAE;</sup>&#xA0;RT reagent Kit With gDNA Eraser (Takara Bio), and the cDNAs obtained were used as templates for PCR amplification with specific primers. Gene-specific primers used for RT-qPCR were: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2019;-TTG TAG GTC GCT GGT TTC-3&#x2019;</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2019;-CCA AGT TCA CGG TTC ATA G-3&#x2019;</named-content> for <italic>TaSOD</italic> (U69536.1); <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2019;-AGT TGG ACG GAT GGT ACT GA-3&#x2019;</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2019;-AAG ACG GTG CCT TTG GGT-3&#x2019;</named-content> for <italic>TaCAT</italic> (X94352.1); <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2019;-GAC GGC TGA ATG GTT GAA-3&#x2019;</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2019;-AAT GCC TCC TGG TCC TCT-3&#x2019;</named-content> for <italic>TaAPX</italic> (AF387739.1); <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2019;-AAC TAC CCG CTC TGC TCC T-3&#x2019;</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2019;-GCC TTG GTC CTT GTA CTT CG-3&#x2019;</named-content> for <italic>TaGPX</italic> (AJ010455.1). In addition, <italic>TaActin</italic> (AB181991.1) was used as internal control: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2019;-CTA TCC TTC GTT TGG ACC TT-3&#x2019;</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2019;-AGC GAG CTT CTC CTT TAT GT-3&#x2019;</named-content>. RT-qPCR was performed using StepOne instrument. Each reaction contained 10 &#xB5;l 2&#xD7;SYBR Green Master Mix reagent (Takara Bio), 1.0 &#xB5;l cDNA samples, 1.2 &#xB5;l 10 mM gene-specific primers and 0.4 &#xB5;l 50&#xD7;ROX in a final volume of 20 &#xB5;l. The thermal cycle was used as followings: 95&#xB0;C for 2 min; 40 cycles of 95&#xB0;C for 30s, 55&#xB0;C for 30s, and 72&#xB0;C for 30s. The expression levels of antioxidant enzymes were analyzed by the comparative Ct method.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4.9">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>Significance analyses of data were performed for each cultivar under each condition using ANOVA analysis in SPSS package (Ver. 11, SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). The effects of Cultivar, PEG6000, K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> and their interactions were analyzed using three-way (cultivar, PEG6000 and K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> as the fixed factors) general linear model on each measured dependent variable. The significance was considered at <italic>p</italic> &#x2264;0.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Associate Professor Meizhen Liu of Institute of Botany, the Chinese Academy of Sciences for her help on providing experimental site.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Munns</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Comparative physiology of salt and water stress</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>-<lpage>250</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.0016-8025.2001.00808.x">10.1046/j.0016-8025.2001.00808.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11841667">11841667</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11841667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Armengaud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sulpice</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amtmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Multilevel analysis of primary metabolism provides new insights into the role of potassium nutrition for glycolysis and nitrogen assimilation in Arabidopsis roots</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>150</volume>: <fpage>772</fpage>-<lpage>785</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.108.133629">10.1104/pp.108.133629</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19346439">19346439</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19346439</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tomemori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Interactive effects of sodium and potassium on the growth and photosynthesis of spinach and komatsuna</article-title>. <source>Plant Prod Sci</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>-<lpage>285</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1626/pps.5.281">10.1626/pps.5.281</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cakmak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The role of potassium in alleviating detrimental effects of abiotic stresses in plants</article-title>. <source>J Plant Nutr Soil Sci</source><volume>168</volume>: <fpage>521</fpage>-<lpage>530</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/jpln.200420485">10.1002/jpln.200420485</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Potassium nitrate application alleviates sodium chloride stress in winter wheat cultivars differing in salt tolerance</article-title>. <source>J Plant Physiol</source><volume>165</volume>: <fpage>1455</fpage>-<lpage>1465</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jplph.2008.01.001">10.1016/j.jplph.2008.01.001</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18313170">18313170</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18313170</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mendham</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Screening plants for salt tolerance by measuring K+ flux: a case study for barley</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source><volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1230</fpage>-<lpage>1246</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3040.2005.01364.x">10.1111/j.1365-3040.2005.01364.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alexieva</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sergiev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mapelli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karanov</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The effect of drought and ultraviolet radiation on growth and stress markers in pea and wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source><volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1337</fpage>-<lpage>1344</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-3040.2001.00778.x">10.1046/j.1365-3040.2001.00778.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmidhalter</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Drought and salinity: A comparison of their effects on mineral nutrition of plants</article-title>. <source>J Plant Nutr Soil Sci</source><volume>168</volume>: <fpage>541</fpage>-<lpage>549</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/jpln.200420516">10.1002/jpln.200420516</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Water-induced oxidative stress and antioxidant defenses in rice plants</article-title>. <source>J Plant Physiol</source><volume>155</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>-<lpage>261</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0176-1617(99)80016-9">10.1016/S0176-1617(99)80016-9</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Silicon improves the tolerance to water-deficit stress induced by polyethylene glycol in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) seedlings</article-title>. <source>J Plant Growth Regul</source><volume>29</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>-<lpage>115</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00344-009-9120-9">10.1007/s00344-009-9120-9</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kloepper</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Rhizosphere bacteria help plants tolerate abiotic stress</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tplants.2008.10.004">10.1016/j.tplants.2008.10.004</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19056309">19056309</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19056309</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piper</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Physiological mechanisms of drought-induced tree mortality are far from being resolved</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source><volume>186</volume>: <fpage>274</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>281</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.03167.x">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.03167.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20409184">20409184</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20409184</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Responses of physiological parameters, grain yield, and grain quality to foliar application of potassium nitrate in two contrasting winter wheat cultivars under salinity stress</article-title>. <source>J Plant Nutr Soil Sci</source><volume>173</volume>: <fpage>444</fpage>-<lpage>452</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/jpln.200900313">10.1002/jpln.200900313</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sofo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dichio</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiloyannis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Masia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Antioxidant defences in olive trees during drought stress: changes in activity of some antioxidant enzymes</article-title>. <source>Funct Plant Biol</source><volume>32</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>53</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/FP04003">10.1071/FP04003</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Blokhina</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Virolainen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fagerstedt</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Antioxidants, oxidative damage and oxygen deprivation stress: a review</article-title>. <source>Ann Bot</source><volume>91</volume>: <fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>194</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/aob/mcf118">10.1093/aob/mcf118</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12509339">12509339</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12509339</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Horie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katsuhara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Differential sodium and potassium transport selectivities of the rice OsHKT2;1 and OsHKT2;2 transporters in plant cells</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>152</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>-<lpage>355</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.109.145722">10.1104/pp.109.145722</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19889878">19889878</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19889878</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hayano-Kanashiro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calder&#xF3;n-V&#xE1;zquez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ibarra-Laclette</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herrera-Estrella</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Analysis of gene expression and physiological responses in three Mexican maize landraces under drought stress and recovery irrigation</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>4</volume>(<issue-id>10</issue-id>): <fpage>e7531</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0007531">10.1371/journal.pone.0007531</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19888455">19888455</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19888455</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dionisio-Sese</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tobita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Antioxidant responses of rice seedlings to salinity stress</article-title>. <source>Plant Sci</source><volume>135</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0168-9452(98)00025-9">10.1016/S0168-9452(98)00025-9</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Vendruscolo</surname></name><comment> ECG</comment>, <comment>Schuster I</comment>, <comment>Pileggi M</comment>, <comment>Scapim CA</comment>, <comment>Correa HB (2007) Stress-induced synthesis of proline confers tolerance to water deficit in transgenic wheat. J Plant Physiol 10: 1367-1376. </comment><publisher-name>PubMed</publisher-name><comment>: 17604875</comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Osmotic stress-induced changes in cell wall peroxidase activity and hydrogen peroxide level in roots of rice seedlings</article-title>. <source>Plant Growth Regul</source><volume>37</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>-<lpage>183</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1020523017867">10.1023/A:1020523017867</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Flexas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bota</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galmes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Medrano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ribas-Carbo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Keeping a positive carbon balance under adverse conditions: responses of photosynthesis and respiration to water stress</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>127</volume>: <fpage>343</fpage>-<lpage>352</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1399-3054.2006.00621.x">10.1111/j.1399-3054.2006.00621.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sonobe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inanaga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>An</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Short term stomatal responses to light intensity changes and osmotic stress in sorghum seedlings raised with and without silicon</article-title>. <source>Environ Exp Bot</source><volume>60</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>-<lpage>182</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.envexpbot.2006.10.004">10.1016/j.envexpbot.2006.10.004</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Farooq</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Azam</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The use of cell membrane stability (CMS) technique to screen for salt tolerant wheat varieties</article-title>. <source>J Plant Physiol</source><volume>163</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>-<lpage>637</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jplph.2005.06.006">10.1016/j.jplph.2005.06.006</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16545996">16545996</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16545996</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sanchez-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rubio-Wilhelmi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cervilla</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blasco</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genotypic differences in some physiological parameters symptomatic for oxidative stress under moderate drought in tomato plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Sci</source><volume>178</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.plantsci.2009.10.001">10.1016/j.plantsci.2009.10.001</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Silicon alleviates oxidative damage of wheat plants in pots under drought</article-title>. <source>Plant Sci</source><volume>169</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>-<lpage>321</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.plantsci.2005.02.023">10.1016/j.plantsci.2005.02.023</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Purty</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Transformation of tomato cultivar 'Pusa Ruby' with <italic>bspA</italic> gene from <italic>Populus tremula</italic> for drought tolerance</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult</source><volume>84</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sairam</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Water stress tolerance of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.): variations in hydrogen peroxide accumulation and antioxidant activity in tolerant and susceptible genotypes</article-title>. <source>J Agron Crop Sci</source><volume>186</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1439-037x.2001.00461.x">10.1046/j.1439-037x.2001.00461.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Simova-Stoilova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Demirevska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petrova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsenov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feller</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Antioxidative protection and proteolytic activity in tolerant and sensitive wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) varieties subjected to long-term field drought</article-title>. <source>Plant Growth Regul</source><volume>58</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>117</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10725-008-9356-6">10.1007/s10725-008-9356-6</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fazeli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghorbanli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niknam</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Effect of drought on biomass, protein content, lipid peroxidation and antioxidant enzymes in two sesame cultivars</article-title>. <source>Biol Plant</source><volume>51</volume>: <fpage>98</fpage>-<lpage>103</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10535-007-0020-1">10.1007/s10535-007-0020-1</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wellburn</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The spectral determination of chlorophyll a and b, as well as total carotenoids, using various solvents with spectrophotometers of different resolution</article-title>. <source>J Plant Physiol</source><volume>144</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>-<lpage>313</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0176-1617(11)81192-2">10.1016/S0176-1617(11)81192-2</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Draper</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hadley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Malondialdehyde determination as index of lipid peroxidation</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol</source><volume>186</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>-<lpage>431</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0076-6879(90)86135-I">10.1016/0076-6879(90)86135-I</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2233309">2233309</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2233309</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Spollen</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valliyodan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hejlek</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Spatial distribution of transcript changes in the maize primary root elongation zone at low water potential</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18387193">18387193</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Degenkolbe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zuther</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Repsilber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Expression profiling of rice cultivars differing in their tolerance to long-term drought stress</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source><volume>69</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>-<lpage>153</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11103-008-9412-7">10.1007/s11103-008-9412-7</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18931976">18931976</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18931976</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cuin</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shabala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Compatible solutes reduce ROS-induced potassium efflux in Arabidopsis roots</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source><volume>30</volume>: <fpage>875</fpage>-<lpage>885</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3040.2007.01674.x">10.1111/j.1365-3040.2007.01674.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17547658">17547658</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17547658</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nyamdari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>C-J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The tonoplast-localized sucrose transporter in Populus (PtaSUT4) regulates whole-plant water relations, responses to water stress, and photosynthesis</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>7</volume>(<issue-id>8</issue-id>): <fpage>e44467</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0044467">10.1371/journal.pone.0044467</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22952983">22952983</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22952983</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Redman</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>CJDA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Espino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Increased fitness of rice plants to abiotic stress via habitat adapted symbiosis: A strategy for mitigating impacts of climate change</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>6</volume>(<issue-id>7</issue-id>): <fpage>e14823</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0014823">10.1371/journal.pone.0014823</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21750695">21750695</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21750695</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sunkar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Drought and salt tolerance in plants</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Plant Sci</source><volume>24</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/07352680590910410">10.1080/07352680590910410</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ch&#xE9;rel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Regulation of K<sup>+</sup> channel activities in plants: from physiological to molecular aspects</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source><volume>55</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>-<lpage>351</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jxb/erh028">10.1093/jxb/erh028</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14739260">14739260</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14739260</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of a common wheat gene TaSnRK2.8 enhances tolerance to drought, salt and low temperature in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>5</volume>(<issue-id>12</issue-id>): <fpage>e16041</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0016041">10.1371/journal.pone.0016041</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21209856">21209856</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21209856</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jongdee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fukai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Leaf water potential and osmotic adjustment as physiological traits to improve drought tolerance in rice</article-title>. <source>Field Crops Res</source><volume>76</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>-<lpage>163</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0378-4290(02)00036-9">10.1016/S0378-4290(02)00036-9</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tripathy</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>QTLs for cell-membrane stability mapped in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) under drought stress</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>100</volume>: <fpage>1197</fpage>-<lpage>1202</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s001220051424">10.1007/s001220051424</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
