<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4634908</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">657</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-015-0657-4</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Identification and comprehensive analyses of the <italic>CBL</italic> and <italic>CIPK</italic> gene families in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Tao</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>suntaohust123@163.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Yan</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>wy875643001wy@163.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Meng</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>932915391@qq.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Tingting</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>1532975716@163.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>Yi</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>phyllisyy@126.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Xiatian</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>wangxiatiancwz@163.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>Shuya</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>17380604@qq.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>Guangyuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+86-27-87792271</phone>
            <email>hegy@hust.edu.cn</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Guangxiao</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+86-27-87792273</phone>
            <email>ygx@hust.edu.cn</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1">The Genetic Engineering International Cooperation Base of Chinese Ministry of Science and Technology, The Key Laboratory of Molecular Biophysics of Chinese Ministry of Education, College of Life Science and Technology, Huazhong University of Science &amp; Technology, Wuhan, 430074 China </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <elocation-id>269</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Sun et al. 2015</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Calcineurin B-like (CBL) proteins belong to a unique group of calcium sensors in plant that decode the Ca<sup>2+</sup> signature by interacting with CBL-interacting protein kinases (CIPKs). Although CBL-CIPK complexes have been shown to play important roles in the responses to various stresses in plants, little is known about their functions in wheat.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>A total of seven <italic>TaCBL</italic> and 20 <italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes were amplified from bread wheat, <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> cv. Chinese Spring. Reverse-transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and <italic>in silico</italic> expression analyses showed that <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes were expressed at different levels in different tissues, or maintained at nearly constant expression levels during the whole life cycle of the wheat plant. Some <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes showed up- or down-regulated expressions during seed germination. Preferential interactions between TaCBLs and TaCIPKs were observed in yeast two-hybrid and bimolecular fluorescence complementation experiments. Analyses of a deletion series of TaCIPK proteins with amino acid variations at the C-terminus provided new insights into the specificity of the interactions between TaCIPKs and TaCBLs, and indicated that the TaCBL&#x2013;TaCIPK signaling pathway is very complex in wheat because of its hexaploid genome. The expressions of many <italic>TaCBLs</italic> and <italic>TaCIPKs</italic> were responsive to abiotic stresses (salt, cold, and simulated drought) and abscisic acid treatment. Transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants overexpressing <italic>TaCIPK24</italic> exhibited improved salt tolerance through increased Na<sup>+</sup> efflux and an enhanced reactive oxygen species scavenging capacity.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>These results contribute to our understanding of the functions of CBL-CIPK complexes and provide the basis for selecting appropriate genes for in-depth functional studies of <italic>CBL</italic>&#x2013;<italic>CIPK</italic> in wheat.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
          <p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12870-015-0657-4) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>
          <italic>TaCIPK24</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd><italic>CBL</italic>&#x2013;<italic>CIPK</italic></kwd>
        <kwd>Expression profiles</kwd>
        <kwd>Stress response</kwd>
        <kwd>Preferential interactions</kwd>
        <kwd>Wheat</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2015</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>The calcium ion (Ca<sup>2+</sup>) functions as a ubiquitous second messenger in plants, and participates in signal transduction in response to various environmental and developmental stimuli. The transient Ca<sup>2+</sup> signal in the cytoplasm of plant cells is captured by a variety of Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensors including calmodulins, calmodulin-like proteins (CML), calcium-dependent protein kinases (CDPKs), and calcineurin B-like (CBL) proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. These Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensors transfer the environmental and developmental signals to downstream components, causing a series of physiological and biochemical changes.</p>
      <p>CBLs, which harbor a core region consisting of four conserved EF hands, capture the Ca<sup>2+</sup> signal, and interact with CBL-interacting protein kinases (CIPKs) to phosphorylate their target proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The CIPKs with the NAF motif for interaction with CBL belong to the SnRK3 protein family, whose members have a specific Ser/Thr protein kinase domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Recently, CIPK proteins were shown to phosphorylate their interacting CBL proteins at N-terminal conservative Ser residue (AtCBL1-Ser<sup>201</sup>, AtCBL2-Ser<sup>216</sup>, AtCBL4-Ser<sup>205</sup> and AtCBL10-Ser<sup>237</sup>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] and this proper phosphorylation of CBL was proved to be absolutely required for the <italic>in vivo</italic> activation of the AKT1 K<sup>+</sup> channel by CBL1-CIPK23 and CBL9-CIPK23 complexes in oocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The <italic>CBL</italic> and <italic>CIPK</italic> gene families have been described in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Oryza sativa, Zea mays</italic>, and <italic>Brassica napus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p>
      <p>In previous studies, CBL&#x2013;CIPK complexes were found to play very important roles in responses to external stimuli. The salt overly sensitive (SOS) pathway was the first CBL-CIPK network to be identified, and this CBL-CIPK complex comprised CBL4 (SOS3) and CIPK24 (SOS2). The CBL4 protein was shown to interact with CIPK24 and recruit it to the cytoplasmic membrane, where it activated the H<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> (SOS1) antiporter to enhance salt tolerance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. This result indicated that the CBL-CIPK complex functions in regulating sodium ion homeostasis. Meanwhile, V-ATPase proteins were shown to directly interact with SOS2 to rescue the salt-defective phenotype of <italic>sos2</italic> mutant plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In recent years, many CBLs and CIPKs have been shown to promote stress tolerance by balancing the intracellular ion concentration in plants. The sodium concentration was markedly lower in the <italic>Arabidopsis cbl10</italic> mutant than in control plants, in both normal and salt-stress conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The <italic>CBL10</italic>-overexpressing lines exhibited a K<sup>+</sup>-sensitive phenotype, like that of the <italic>akt1</italic> mutant under low K<sup>+</sup> conditions. The interaction between CBL10 and AKT1 was verified in bimolecular fluorescence complementation (BiFC), yeast two-hybrid (Y2H), and co-immunoprecipitation experiments, and was shown to impair AKT1-mediated inward potassium (K<sup>+</sup>) currents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. AtCIPK23 could directly interact with CBL1 to promote K<sup>+</sup> uptake under low K<sup>+</sup> conditions by phosphorylating and activating the K<sup>+</sup> channel (AKT1) in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. However, a recent study suggested that CBL1/CBL9 might interact with AKT1 independently of CIPK23 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Moreover, in response to low-K<sup>+</sup> conditions, CIPK9 was recruited to the tonoplast by CBL3 to regulate K<sup>+</sup> homeostasis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p>
      <p>Over-expression and mutant analyses of <italic>CBL</italic>s and <italic>CIPK</italic>s have greatly enriched our understanding of their functions. The <italic>cbl2/cbl3</italic> double mutant showed defects in growth and ion homeostasis, possibly as a result of disrupted vacuolar H<sup>+</sup>-ATPase activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In another study, CBL2 and CBL3 were shown to affect seed development and morphology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The ectopic overexpression of <italic>ZmCIPK16</italic> in the <italic>Arabidopsi sos2</italic> mutant enhanced the expression of <italic>SOS1</italic> and improved salt tolerance under saline conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. <italic>AtCIPK3</italic> was induced by abscisic acid (ABA) and stress conditions and established a molecular connection between stress- and ABA-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> signals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. CBL10 and CIPK6 were shown to positively regulate both immunity- and disease-associated programmed cell death in tomato and tobacco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The <italic>oscipk31</italic> insertion mutant was hypersensitive to ABA and stresses (salt, mannitol, and glucose), and showed altered expression levels of several stress-responsive genes when it was exposed to these abiotic stresses during the seed germination and seedling stages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. In a recent study, a few AtCBL members were also found to target to another group of enzymes 5'-methylthioadenosine nucleosidases by yeast two-hybrid system, indicting an additional level of complexity on the CBL-mediated signaling networks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. However, with respect to the larger families of CBLs and CIPKs, few CBL-CIPK complexes have been functionally characterized, especially in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.), which is one of the most important food crops. Bread wheat has an allohexaploid genome with a size of approximately 17&#xA0;GB, making it one of the largest and most complex plant genomes. In recent years, the genome sequencing of <italic>T. aestivum</italic>, <italic>Triticum urartu,</italic> and <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> has promoted research on bread wheat, especially studies on agronomically important gene families related to disease resistance, abiotic stress endurance, and grain quality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p>
      <p>In our previous work, we demonstrated that transgenic tobacco overexpressing wheat <italic>TaCIPK14</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK29</italic> showed increased tolerance to salinity and drought stress, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. In this study, seven <italic>TaCBL</italic> and 20 <italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes in wheat were identified and cloned by a genome-wide analysis combined with expressed sequence tag (EST) assembly. Here, we present the results of analyses of expression profiles, the specific interactions between TaCBLs and TaCIPKs, and the stress tolerance of transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants expressing <italic>TaCIPK24</italic>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Identification of <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> gene families in wheat</title>
        <p>The bread wheat genome is thought to have formed <italic>via</italic> fusion of three ancestral genomes, which are believed to be related to <italic>T. urartu</italic>, <italic>Aegilops speltoides,</italic> and <italic>A. tauschii</italic>. These fusion events are thought to have occurred several hundred thousand years ago [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. We searched the wheat genome and found 24 <italic>CBL</italic> (7, 9, and 8 loci in sub-genomes A, B, and D, respectively) and 79 <italic>CIPK</italic> (21, 34, and 24 loci in sub-genomes A, B, and D, respectively) loci on wheat chromosomes (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The relative positions of these loci on chromosomes were identified on genetic maps (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). The protein and DNA sequences of <italic>T. urartu</italic> and <italic>A. tauschii</italic> (the B sub-genome was not analyzed in this work) were retrieved from NCBI and all the <italic>CBL</italic> and <italic>CIPK</italic> nucleotide sequences from these three species (<italic>T. aestivum</italic>, <italic>T. urartu</italic>, and <italic>A. tauschii</italic>) were clustered against each other (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The closest matching genes were regarded as equivalent partners, as shown in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Ten and nine genes of <italic>T. urartu</italic> and <italic>A. tauschii</italic>, respectively, had no equivalents in <italic>T. aestivum,</italic> implying the existence of potential un-identified <italic>TaCBL</italic>/<italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes. Additionally, <italic>TaCIPK15-A</italic>, <italic>TaCIPK26-A</italic>, <italic>TaCIPK8-D,</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK22-D2</italic> (wheat specific genes) had no equivalents in <italic>T. urartu</italic> and <italic>A. tauschii</italic> (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Considering that the physical maps of current wheat genome do not cover all the chromosome arms, it is difficult to know whether these potential un-identified <italic>TaCBL</italic>/<italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes are resulted from gene retention, duplication and whether these wheat specific genes are the results of the loss of <italic>CBL</italic> and <italic>CIPK</italic> genes after polyploidization. In the future, a more detailed wheat physical map may resolve this question.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Identification of <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> gene families in wheat genome</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Gene <sup>a</sup>
</th><th>Gene names related to Chr.</th><th>Amino Acid</th><th>Exon</th><th>Chr.</th><th>Contigs</th><th colspan="2">Gene Position Start end</th><th><italic>Triticum urartu</italic></th><th><italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic></th><th>GenBank Acc No.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="5"><italic>TaCBL1</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCBL1&#x2013;A1</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>215</td><td>8</td><td>1AL</td><td>3974931</td><td>2941</td><td>6756</td><td>KD278069</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="5">JX2443002</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL1&#x2013;A2</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td/><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD162834</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL1&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1BL</td><td>3900149</td><td>166</td><td>3357</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL1&#x2013;D1</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1DL</td><td>1737972</td><td>560</td><td>1484</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD512543</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL1&#x2013;D2</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1DL</td><td>464815</td><td>15</td><td/><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD578957</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCBL2</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCBL2&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>215</td><td>8</td><td>5AS</td><td>1464783</td><td>5151</td><td>93449</td><td>KD141203</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">JX243003</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL2&#x2013;B</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>245</td><td>7</td><td>5BS</td><td>2281375</td><td>80</td><td>4667</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL2&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>225</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>5DS</td><td>2741958</td><td>5680</td><td>9158</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD544824</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCBL3</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td>TaCIPK3&#x2013;A<sup>P</sup>
</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD241885</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">JX243004</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL3&#x2013;B</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>8</td><td>4BS</td><td>4897686</td><td>4127</td><td>8100</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL3&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>226</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>4DS</td><td>2274776</td><td>2834</td><td>7044</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD515143</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4"><italic>TaCBL4</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCBL4&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1AL</td><td>3951410</td><td>100</td><td>1380</td><td>KD20084</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="4">JX243005</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL4&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>7</td><td>1BL</td><td>3917583</td><td>1507</td><td>2702</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL4&#x2013;D1</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>218</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1DL</td><td>2274485</td><td>1479</td><td>2868</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD597121</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL4&#x2013;D2</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>7</td><td>1DL</td><td>2273437</td><td>4080</td><td>5129</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD604528</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCBL6</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCBL6&#x2013;A</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>218</td><td>5</td><td>5AL</td><td>2189286</td><td>246</td><td>2332</td><td>KD045461</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">JX243006</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL6&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>226</td><td>8</td><td>5BL</td><td>10906286</td><td>5260</td><td>8935</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL6&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>5DL</td><td>4595540</td><td>1995</td><td>5159</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD546381</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCBL7</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCBL7&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1AL</td><td>3887581</td><td>5948</td><td>7521</td><td>KD220101</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">JX243001</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL7&#x2013;B</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>8</td><td>1BL</td><td>3897439</td><td>22549</td><td>24230</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL7&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>213</td><td>8</td><td>1DL</td><td>2195979</td><td>3589</td><td>5243</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD592851</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7"><italic>TaCBL9</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCBL9&#x2013;A1</italic></td><td>296</td><td>8</td><td>3AL</td><td>4339532</td><td>1</td><td>784</td><td>KD258230</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="7">JX243010</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL9&#x2013;D1</italic><sup>P</sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>3D</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD508651</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL9&#x2013;A2</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>5</td><td>3AS</td><td>3303239</td><td>2125</td><td>4252</td><td>KD217616</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL9&#x2013;D2</italic><sup>P</sup></td><td>296</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD546760</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL9&#x2013;B1</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>296</td><td>9</td><td>3B</td><td>10535092</td><td>2016</td><td>4459</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL9&#x2013;B2</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>3B</td><td>10578811</td><td>5421</td><td>7996</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCBL9&#x2013;B3</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>3B</td><td>10423444</td><td>3743</td><td>5534</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK2</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK2&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1</td><td>2AS</td><td>1136699</td><td>1058</td><td>2612</td><td>KD178374</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">KJ561791</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK2&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>452</td><td>1</td><td>2BS</td><td>5209173</td><td>4420</td><td>6031</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK2&#x2013;D</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>452</td><td>1</td><td>2DS</td><td>5352995</td><td>3439</td><td>6170</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD537702</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK3</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK3&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>456</td><td>14</td><td>2AS</td><td>5278308</td><td>778</td><td>4232</td><td>KD224079</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">KJ561800</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK3&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>447</td><td>14</td><td>2BS</td><td>5215259</td><td>1889</td><td>4792</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK3&#x2013;D</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>447</td><td>14</td><td>2DS</td><td>5388639</td><td>6194</td><td>9544</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD551511</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>TaCIPK4</italic></td><td><italic>TaCIPK4&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>448</td><td rowspan="2">2<break/>2</td><td>5BS</td><td>2276618</td><td>1805</td><td>3100</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="2">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK4&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>432</td><td>5DS</td><td>2735985</td><td>15903</td><td>17161</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD505215</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK5</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK5&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>433</td><td>1</td><td>3AS</td><td>3302816</td><td>1652</td><td>3448</td><td>KD141920</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">KJ561802</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK5&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>466</td><td>1</td><td>3B</td><td>10642252</td><td>4923</td><td>6712</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK5&#x2013;D</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>464</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>3DS</td><td>1035659</td><td>1</td><td>1176</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD508285</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>TaCIPK6</italic></td><td><italic>TaCIPK6&#x2013;A</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td/><td/><td>KD207883</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="2">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK6&#x2013;D</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td/><td/><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD557345</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5"><italic>TaCIPK7</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK7&#x2013;A1</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td/><td/><td>KD036546</td><td/><td rowspan="5">KJ561803</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK7&#x2013;A2</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td/><td/><td>KD051070</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK7&#x2013;A3</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td/><td/><td>KD103566</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK7&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1</td><td>5BL</td><td>10732661</td><td>4349</td><td>5764</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK7&#x2013;D</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>431</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td/><td/><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD522041.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>TaCIPK8</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK8&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>3</td><td>3B</td><td>10524427</td><td>1670</td><td>3978</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="2">KJ561804</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK8&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>464</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>3DL</td><td>6956205</td><td>367</td><td>2132</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK9</italic></td><td><italic>TaCIPK9&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>14</td><td>5AL</td><td>1668033</td><td>412</td><td>3585</td><td>KD006963</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">AK332473</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK9&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>446</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>4BL</td><td>6995603</td><td>4780</td><td>8912</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK9&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>15</td><td>4DL</td><td>14472121</td><td/><td/><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD554016</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK10</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK10&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>445</td><td>1</td><td>4AS</td><td>5974107</td><td>2247</td><td>3728</td><td>KD248893</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">KJ561787</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK10&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>384</td><td>1</td><td>4BL</td><td>7036526</td><td>5067</td><td>6516</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK10&#x2013;D</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>439</td><td>1</td><td>4DL</td><td>14429928</td><td/><td/><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD540780</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5"><italic>TaCIPK11</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK11&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>438</td><td>1</td><td>3AL</td><td>2838468</td><td>1233</td><td>3144</td><td>KD051997</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="5">KJ561788</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK11&#x2013;B1</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>507</td><td>1</td><td>3B</td><td>10507835</td><td>1</td><td>1663</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK11&#x2013;B2</italic></td><td>507</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>3B</td><td>10507836</td><td>1</td><td>1544</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK11&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1</td><td>3DL</td><td>6897880</td><td>8953</td><td>10856</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD509836</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK11&#x2013;D2</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>507</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>KD556601</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK12</italic></td><td><italic>TaCIPK12&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>2</td><td>1AL</td><td>3875215</td><td>1</td><td>875</td><td>KD167973</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK12&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1</td><td>1BL</td><td>3828145</td><td>1</td><td>326</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK12&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1</td><td>1DL</td><td>2112699</td><td>1</td><td>418</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD507283</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>TaCIPK13</italic></td><td><italic>TaCIPK13&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1</td><td>3B</td><td>10753103</td><td/><td/><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="2">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK13&#x2013;D</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD502264</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK14</italic></td><td><italic>TaCIPK14&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1</td><td>4AL</td><td>7147326</td><td/><td/><td>KD239100</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">JX879754</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK14&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>449</td><td>1</td><td>4BS</td><td>4951408</td><td>11612</td><td>13239</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK14&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>444</td><td>1</td><td>4DS</td><td>2283949</td><td>3085</td><td>4712</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD546797</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaIPK15</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaIPK15&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>449</td><td>1</td><td>5AL</td><td>1668033</td><td>1866</td><td>3335</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">KJ561789</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK15&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="2">1<break/>&#x2013;</td><td>5BL</td><td>10796477</td><td>2838</td><td>4331</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK15&#x2013;D</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>438</td><td>5DL</td><td>4490016</td><td>1021</td><td>2355</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD560960</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK16</italic></td><td><italic>TaCIPK16&#x2013;A</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD143696</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">AK331419</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK16&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>2</td><td>5BL</td><td>10860020</td><td>4595</td><td>6233</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK16&#x2013;D</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>447</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD721304</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7"><italic>TaCIPK17</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK17&#x2013;A1</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>6</td><td>1AS</td><td>3313233</td><td>19</td><td>2337</td><td>KD250230</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="7">KJ561790</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK17&#x2013;A2</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>11</td><td>1AS</td><td>3259469</td><td>1075</td><td>3521</td><td>KD132920</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK17&#x2013;B1</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>12</td><td>1BS</td><td>1265003</td><td>1916</td><td>5673</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK17&#x2013;B2</italic></td><td>466</td><td>12</td><td>1BS</td><td>3424219</td><td>1678</td><td>5957</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK17&#x2013;D1</italic></td><td>466</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1DS</td><td>1916039</td><td>456</td><td>3542</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD530641</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK17&#x2013;D2</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1DS</td><td>1890755</td><td>1</td><td>3079</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD563756</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK17&#x2013;D3</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>11</td><td>1DS</td><td>271737</td><td>999</td><td>3311</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD589116</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK19</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK19&#x2013;A</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD117636</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">JX234011</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK19&#x2013;B1</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>2</td><td>3B</td><td>10573976</td><td>10157</td><td>13650</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK19&#x2013;B2</italic></td><td>483</td><td>1</td><td>3B</td><td>10753103</td><td>13446</td><td>14093</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK20</italic></td><td><italic>TaCIPK20&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>525</td><td>4</td><td>6AS</td><td>4406549</td><td/><td/><td>KD224235</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK20&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>12</td><td>6BS</td><td>2936057</td><td/><td/><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK20&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>11</td><td>6DS</td><td>2096196</td><td/><td/><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD544165</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK21</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK21&#x2013;A</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>12</td><td>2AS</td><td>5304926</td><td>1845</td><td>6080</td><td>KD277172</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">KJ561792</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK21&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>451</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>2BS</td><td>5197551</td><td>4370</td><td>8637</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK21&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>2DS</td><td>5319123</td><td>2007</td><td>4463</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD511088</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6"><italic>TaCIPK22</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK22&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>2AL</td><td>6383902</td><td>1</td><td>934</td><td>KD203757</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="6">KJ561793</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK22&#x2013;B1</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>2BL</td><td>7988831</td><td>2848</td><td>4399</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK22&#x2013;B2</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>2BL</td><td>8033849</td><td>3684</td><td>4533</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK22&#x2013;B3</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>2BL</td><td>7949729</td><td>3040</td><td>4484</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK22&#x2013;D1</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1</td><td>2DL</td><td>9860188</td><td>4959</td><td>6607</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD500669</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK22&#x2013;D2</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>433</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>2DL</td><td>9908802</td><td>3988</td><td>4888</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK23</italic></td><td><italic>TaCIPK23&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>14</td><td>2AL</td><td>6369709</td><td>442</td><td>4149</td><td>KD007171</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">JX243012</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK23&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>452</td><td>14</td><td>2BL</td><td>7939869</td><td>5925</td><td>8812</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK23&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>462</td><td>14</td><td>2DL</td><td>9894674</td><td>10517</td><td>14199</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD502068</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4"><italic>TaCIPK24</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK24&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>462</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>7AL</td><td>4552082</td><td>7689</td><td>11571</td><td>KD185370</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="4">KJ561794</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK24&#x2013;B1</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>7BL</td><td>6743884</td><td>3133</td><td>8220</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK24&#x2013;B2</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>7BL</td><td>6725100</td><td>299</td><td>1430</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK24&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>14</td><td>7DL</td><td>3369425</td><td>6709</td><td>12113</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD554191</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>TaCIPK25</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK25&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>446</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>7AL</td><td>4557464</td><td>1</td><td>906</td><td>KD203605</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="2">KJ561795</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK25&#x2013;D</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>7DL</td><td>3315123</td><td>3089</td><td>4703</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD578984</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK26</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK26&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1</td><td>6AS</td><td>4399246</td><td>659</td><td>2242</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">KJ561796</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK26&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>481</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>6BS</td><td>1542240</td><td>652</td><td>2262</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK26&#x2013;D</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1</td><td>6DS</td><td>32939</td><td>832</td><td>2285</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD556601</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>TaCIPK27</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK27&#x2013;B1</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>486</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>5BL</td><td>10894042</td><td>2308</td><td>3872</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="2">KJ561797</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK27&#x2013;B2</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1</td><td>5BL</td><td>10894043</td><td>2308</td><td>3872</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK28</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK28&#x2013;A</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>447</td><td>1</td><td>1AL</td><td>2752572</td><td>4061</td><td>5848</td><td>KD259754</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">KJ561798</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK28&#x2013;B</italic></td><td>472</td><td>1</td><td>1BL</td><td>3799843</td><td>6758</td><td>8542</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK28&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>472</td><td>1</td><td>1DL</td><td>2281163</td><td>487</td><td>2269</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD506845</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK29</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK29&#x2013;A</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>472</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td/><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD176996</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">JX243013</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK29&#x2013;B</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1</td><td>2BS</td><td>5246729</td><td>19006</td><td>20606</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK29&#x2013;D</italic><sup><italic>P</italic></sup></td><td>436</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD506473</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK30</italic></td><td><italic>TaCIPK30&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>1</td><td>3AL</td><td>4303945</td><td>2592</td><td>3265</td><td>KD117636</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>AK330597</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK31</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td><italic>TaCIPK31&#x2013;A</italic></td><td>478</td><td>14</td><td>4AS</td><td>5932853</td><td>800</td><td>4412</td><td>KD170661</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">KJ561799</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK31&#x2013;B</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>449</td><td>15</td><td>4BL</td><td>7038614</td><td>5874</td><td>10593</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK31&#x2013;D</italic><sup>P</sup></td><td>449</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD566562</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>TaCIPK32</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td>TaCIPK32&#x2013;A<sup>P</sup>
</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD060684</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td rowspan="3">KJ561801</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK32&#x2013;B</italic><sup>*</sup></td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>14</td><td>4BS</td><td>4875486</td><td>20714</td><td>24433</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>TaCIPK32&#x2013;D</italic></td><td>439</td><td>14</td><td>4DS</td><td>2325367</td><td>3990</td><td>77792</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>KD929083</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>&#x201C;&#x2013;&#x201D; represents no data available. &#x201C;P&#x201D; represents the potential genes were not identified in this work. &#x201C;a&#x201D; represents those genes that were amplified in this study. &#x201C;*&#x201D; represents those amplified genes that were identified as transcripts from indicated chromosomes</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree of CBL <bold>a</bold> and CIPK <bold>b</bold> proteins of <italic>T. aestivum</italic> (Ta), <italic>A. tauschii</italic> (Aet), <italic>T. urartu</italic> (Tu), <italic>A. thaliana</italic> (At) and <italic>O. sativa</italic> (Os). Multiple sequence alignment of CBL and CIPK proteins was performed using ClustalW. The wheat proteins were indicated with &#x201C;rhombus&#x201D; symbol. The genes belonging to A, B and D sub-genomes were marked with letters suffix and genes cloned in this study were colored with red</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2015_657_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
        <p>Among the identified <italic>TaCBL</italic>/<italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes, the cDNAs of seven <italic>TaCBLs</italic> and 20 <italic>TaCIPKs</italic> were successfully PCR amplified from hexaploid bread wheat (<italic>T. aestivum</italic>) using gene-specific primers (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>) from a cDNA mixture prepared from wheat cv. Chinese Spring as the template. The genomic DNA and cDNA of all identified <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> are provided in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>. To explore the evolutionary relationship of the CBL/CIPKs, two phylogenetic trees were generated based on all transcribed CBL/CIPKs from <italic>T. aestivum</italic>, <italic>T. urartu</italic>, <italic>A. tauschii</italic>, <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, and <italic>O. sativa</italic>. As expected, the genes from <italic>T. aestivum</italic>, <italic>T. urartu,</italic> and <italic>A. tauschii</italic> had the closest evolutionary relationships, and these genes had closer phylogenetic relationships with rice (a monocot) than with <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (a dicot). Thus, the names assigned to the identified genes in wheat followed their homology to rice <italic>CBL</italic>s and <italic>CIPK</italic>s (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). To analyze the structural characteristics of <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes, the gene structures including exons and introns were mapped based on the wheat genome sequence (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>). Some genes' structures were partly characterized with exons/intros, because of lack adequate genome sequences. Only the structures covering the ORF were regarded as complete structures and used for further analysis. All the <italic>TaCBL</italic>s were intron-rich, with five to eight introns. Among the <italic>TaCIPKs</italic>, 26 <italic>TaCIPK</italic>s had no introns, and the other 15 <italic>TaCIPK</italic>s had 5&#x2013;14 introns. For most genes, there were no obvious differences in gene structure among genomes A, B, and D (e.g., <italic>TaCIPK3</italic>, <italic>TaCIPK10</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK23</italic>). Some genes (like <italic>TaCIPK31, TaCBL9</italic>) had a different intron length between the structures in different genome locations.</p>
        <p>The CBL proteins containing EF-hand motifs are known as Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding proteins, and show similarities to CML and CaM proteins. Each of the seven TaCBL proteins harbored four EF-hand motifs. Although these motifs in CBLs did not shared high similarity compared with CaM and CML proteins in other species (Arabidopsis, rice, <italic>C.elegans</italic>, yeast, zebrafish, mouse, and human), they were conserved among the CBLs in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, rice, and wheat (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>). As for the TaCIPK proteins, all 20 TaCIPKs (the genes were amplified by PCR) had domain structures similar to that of AtSOS2; that is, these 20 TaCIPKs harbored a protein kinase catalytic domain (PKC) and the NAF/FISL motif. Considering that CIPK proteins belong to the SnRK superfamily, we selected some representative SnRK superfamily proteins for comparisons of their structural features. As shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>, the PKC domains in SnRK family proteins were conserved and had some highly consistent sites, especially in the activation loop, while the NAF/ FISL motif was unique to CIPK proteins.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Identification and validation of TaCBL&#x2013;TaCIPK interactions</title>
        <p>We analyzed the physical interactions between TaCBL and TaCIPK proteins in wheat using the Y2H method. As shown in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>), the interactions between TaCBLs and TaCIPKs showed different strengths and specificities. TaCBL1 strongly interacted with five CIPKs (TaCIPK3, 5, 14, 15, and 25). TaCBL2 strongly interacted with 11 CIPKs (TaCIPK3, 5, 11, 14, 15, 17, 21, 25, 26, 27, and 32). TaCBL3 showed strong interactions with 10 TaCIPKs (TaCIPK3, 8, 11, 14, 15, 17, 21, 26, 27, and 31) out of 19 TaCIPKs. TaCBL4, the ortholog of AtSOS3 (CBL4), strongly interacted with six TaCIPKs (TaCIPK3, 5, 14, 15, 26, and 31). TaCBL6 strongly interacted with five TaCIPKs (TaCIPK5, 11, 15, 21, and 27), and TaCBL7 interacted with seven TaCIPKs (TaCIPK5, 14, 15, 21, 22, 26, and 31). TaCBL9 strongly interacted with only two TaCIPK proteins (TaCIPK11 and TaCIPK31). To view the interactions from a different perspective, we found that TaCIPK7, 10, 19, 22, 24, 28, and 29 did not interact with any of the seven TaCBL proteins assayed, implying that these CIPK proteins might perceive signals from other unidentified CBL proteins in wheat. We selected nine of the interactions (CBL1&#x2013;CIPK15, CBL2&#x2013;CIPK31, CBL3&#x2013;CIPK15, CBL3&#x2013;CIPK27, CBL4&#x2013;CIPK15, CBL4&#x2013;CIPK31, CIPK6&#x2013;CIPK15, CBL7&#x2013;CIPK27, and CBL9&#x2013;CIPK31) detected between CBL and CIPK proteins using the Y2H assay for further analyses <italic>in planta</italic> using the BiFC method (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>). For all of the assayed TaCBL&#x2013;TaCIPK interaction complexes, yellow fluorescence signals were observed when TaCBLs and TaCIPKs were co-expressed in epidermal cells of tobacco leaves. Notably, it seemed that the observed preferential interactions were inconsistent with the close phylogenetic relationships of the TaCIPKs, namely, the closely phylogenetic related CIPK pairs do not display same interaction profile. For example, TaCIPK14 and TaCIPK15, which had 81&#xA0;% similarity, showed similar interactions with five TaCBLs (TaCBL1, 2, 3, 4 and 7) but different interactions with TaCBL6 and 9. Compared with TaCIPK14/15, other TaCIPKs showed lower amino acid sequence similarity and more diverse interaction specificity. Thus, sequence similarity or phylogenetic relationships are not sufficient to predict the result of CBL-CIPK interactions in the Y2H assay.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Interactions of TaCIPKs with TaCBLs in yeast two-hybrid assay</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>TaCBL1-BD</th><th>TaCBL2-BD</th><th>TaCBL3-BD</th><th>TaCBL4-BD</th><th>TaCBL6-BD</th><th>TaCBL7-BD</th><th>TaCBL9-BD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>TaCIPK3-AD</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK5-AD</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK7-AD</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK8-AD</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK10-AD</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK11-AD</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>-</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK14-AD</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK15-AD</td><td>+ *</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+*</td><td>+*</td><td>+</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK17-AD</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK19-AD</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK21-AD</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK22-AD</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK24-AD</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK25-AD</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK26-AD</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK27-AD</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>+*</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>-*</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK28-AD</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK29-AD</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK31-AD</td><td>-</td><td>+*</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>+*</td></tr><tr><td>TaCIPK32-AD</td><td>-</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The interaction analyses of wheat TaCBL and TaCIPK proteins were performed by Y2H method. TaCIPKs and TaCBLs were respectively cloned to PGAD and PGBK Vector, and then co-transformed into Y187 strains. The transformants containing the target plasmid combinations were grown on selection medium (TDO: SD/&#x2013;Trp/&#x2013;Leu/&#x2013;His/+10&#xA0;mM 3AT) and indicated as growth (+, interaction) and no growth (&#x2212;, no interaction). &#x201C;*&#x201D; represents the interactions were verified by BiFC assays</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Previous studies have shown that the NAF/FISL motif located in the <italic>C</italic>-terminal regulatory domain and the kinase activity of the PKC domain in the N-terminal region of CIPKs are necessary and sufficient for mediating interactions with CBLs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The roles of the redundant parts (those other than the NAF/FISL motif) in the <italic>C</italic>-terminal region of CIPKs have not yet been fully studied. Here, the TaCIPK11 protein, which interacted with CBL2, 3, 6, and 9, contained a large <italic>C</italic>-terminal region (amino acids 311&#x2013;507) that was not present in the other CIPKs. This led us to speculate about the role of this large fragment in regulating the specific interactions of this protein. Analyses of a series of <italic>C</italic>-terminal deletion mutants of TaCIPK11 (CIPK11&#x2013;M1, M2, M3, and M4; M1&#x2013;M3 containing the complete NAF/FISL motif, and M4 with a truncated NAF/FISL motif) showed that there were diverse interaction patterns between TaCIPK11 mutants and TaCBLs (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). CBL3, 6, and 9 could not interact with any of the TaCIPK11 deletion mutants, while TaCBL1/TaCBL4 physically interacted with some or all of the mutants. TaCBL2 lost its specific interaction with the minimal mutant (CIPK11&#x2013;M4). TaCBL7 did not interact with TaCIPK11 or any of its mutants. It seems that TaCBL3, 6, and 9 require the last 86 amino acid for interaction with TaCIPK11 and also inhibits the binding of TaCBL1 and TaCBL4. These changes in the patterns of interaction may result from changes in protein structure after the deletions. In terms of this deletion assay, we supposed that the interaction between CBL and CIPK followed a &#x201C;concave&#x2013;convex&#x201D; model as shown in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>, similar to the model for the structures of AtSOS3-AtSOS2 and AtCBL2-AtCIPK14 complexes proposed by S&#xE1;nchez et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. In this model, the spatial structures of CBLs/CIPKs have an important role for their interactions, and a consummate physical interaction depends on whether the NAF/FISL motif properly reach the CBL cavity. It is believed that the diversified spatial structures resulted from divergent <italic>C</italic>-terminal region of CIPKs explain the molecular basis of the selectivity of certain CBLs towards particular CIPKs. This led to another intriguing question; that is, do the nonsynonymous sequence variations of alleles from different wheat sub-genomes result in aberrant spatial structures that affect the patterns of interaction? To answer this question, we amplified <italic>TaCIPK17</italic>-<italic>A</italic>, which encodes a protein with many amino acid variations in the <italic>C</italic>-terminal regulatory region compared with the homologous TaCIPK17-B protein (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). Interestingly, TaCIPK17-A not only interacted with TaCBL2 and TaCBL3, but also with TaCBL6 in Y2H experiments (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). Despite two mutant sites (G<sup>23</sup> to A<sup>23</sup>, G<sup>48</sup> to D<sup>48</sup>) were observed at PKC domain, it is possible that several amino acid variations in the <italic>C</italic>-terminal regulatory region would confer different patterns of interaction. Such changes in interactions may render CIPKs capable of perceiving signals from other CBLs. These results indicate that the TaCBL-TaCIPK signaling pathway in wheat is very complex because of its allohexaploid genome.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Deletions or mutations in <italic>C</italic>-terminal ends of TaCIPKs dramatically changes its ability to interact with TaCBLs. <bold>a</bold> series deletions in <italic>C</italic>-terminal ends of TaCIPK11 leads to changing interacting patterns with TaCBLs. The boxes indicate the PKC and NAF domains, and numbers beside the lines represent the beginning and the ending positions of TaCIPK11 protein fragments. <bold>b</bold>, <italic>C</italic>-terminal ends alignment between TaCIPK17-A and TaCIPK17-B. Residues with grey background indicates mutant amino acid sites. <bold>c</bold>, interactions of TaCIPK17-A and TaCIPK17-B with TaCBLs. Yeast was monitored on the selection medium and indicated as growth (+) and no growth (&#x2212;). <bold>d</bold>, Schematic representation of the &#x201C;concave-convex&#x201D; model</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2015_657_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Expression patterns of <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes at different developmental stages in wheat</title>
        <p>To investigate the spatial expression patterns of <italic>TaCBL</italic>s and <italic>TaCIPK</italic>s in wheat, we detected their transcriptional levels using RT-PCR in 10 representative tissues, i.e., coleoptile, root (seedling and flowering stage), stem (seedling and flowering stage), leaf (seedling and flowering stage), flag leaf (flowering stage), pistil, and stamen (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). The results showed that the majority of <italic>TaCBL</italic>s and <italic>TaCIPK</italic>s were expressed at different levels in all tissues tested. Most <italic>TaCBL</italic> genes were constitutively expressed in all organs and at all developmental stages, although the transcript levels of certain genes were very low in some tissues. Some <italic>CIPK</italic> genes were expressed abundantly in certain tissues. For example, <italic>TaCIPK22</italic> was specifically expressed in the root at the seedling stage, indicating that it may play an important role in this organ. Moreover, the gene transcript levels differed between vegetative (seedling) and flowering stages. There were higher transcript levels of <italic>TaCBL3</italic> in seedlings than in plants at the flowering stage (roots, stems, and leaves). The flag leaf, as the last leaf of wheat, delivers the largest proportion of photosynthate to fill wheat grains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Among the genes expressed in the flag leaf, <italic>TaCBL7</italic> showed lower transcript levels in leaves of seedlings and plants at the flowering stage, and higher transcript levels in the flag leaf, implying that it might play roles in regulating photosynthesis and/or metabolism in the flag leaf. To study the transcription levels of <italic>TaCBL</italic>s and <italic>TaCIPK</italic>s during the whole life cycle of wheat, we analyzed microarray data that were obtained from tissues at various developmental stages; these data were obtained from publically accessible databases. The genes formed two groups according to their expression patterns (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>). Group I consisted of the genes with high transcript abundance in nearly all tissues (<italic>TaCBL1</italic>, <italic>2</italic>, and <italic>6</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK2</italic>, <italic>8</italic>, <italic>9</italic>, <italic>15</italic>, <italic>16</italic>, <italic>23</italic>, <italic>25</italic>, and <italic>27</italic>). Group II genes consisted of 4 <italic>TaCBLs</italic> and 15 <italic>TaCIPKs</italic> that showed different expression patterns in different tissues and stages. Some of them showed low transcript levels in all tissues. For most of the <italic>TaCBL</italic>s/<italic>TaCIPK</italic>s, their expression profiles in the microarray data matched to the RT-PCR results, but a few genes showed inconsistencies. For example, high transcript levels of <italic>TaCBL4</italic> were detected in the stamen in RT-PCR analyses, but low expression levels in anthers (before anthesis) were indicated in the microarray data. This inconsistency may have resulted from differences in the growth stages of plants between experiments, or from the different methods used.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Expression profile analyses of <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> in wheat tissues with microarray data <bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold> and <bold>c</bold>) and RT-PCR (<bold>d</bold> and <bold>e</bold>). <bold>a</bold> gene expression analyses in wheat whole life cycle using public microarray data. <bold>b</bold>, gene expression analyses during seeds germination process after immersed with water. <bold>c</bold>, comparative transcriptomic analyses between dormant and after-ripened seeds in both imbibed and ABA application states. The value (<bold>b</bold> and <bold>c</bold>) represents relative transcript levels compared to control (before immersion; 0&#xA0;h). The up panels in <bold>a b</bold> and <bold>c</bold> represent log2 transformed values. <bold>d</bold>, gene expression analyses during wheat development using RT-PCR method. &#x201C;S&#x201D; and &#x201C;F&#x201D; represent seedlings and flowering stages, respectively. <bold>e</bold>, the induced genes in seeds germination (<bold>b</bold>) were confirmed by RT-PCR</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2015_657_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
        <p>To further clarify the detailed roles of <italic>TaCIPK</italic> and <italic>TaCBL</italic> in seed germination, we analyzed public microarray data representing the transcription patterns during seed germination. As shown in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>, <italic>TaCIPK6</italic>, <italic>12</italic>, <italic>14</italic>, <italic>15</italic>, <italic>16</italic>, <italic>23</italic>, <italic>25,</italic> and <italic>27,</italic> and <italic>TaCBL2</italic> were up-regulated (log&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;1, <italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05) after 12&#xA0;h of imbibition, and then down-regulated (log&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;1, <italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05). <italic>TaCIPK12</italic>, <italic>TaCIPK31</italic>, <italic>TaCIPK32</italic>, and <italic>TaCBL3</italic> were down-regulated during imbibition (log&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;1, <italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05). Semi-quantitative RT-PCR analyses were conducted to confirm the <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> transcription patterns at five stages of germination (0, 12, 24, 36, and 48&#xA0;h). All of the selected up-regulated genes were induced during seed germination (the EST of <italic>TaCIPK12</italic> was unavailable, and the probe sequence of CIPK12 was not amplified), but the timing of induction differed (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3e</xref>). <italic>TaCIPK16</italic>, <italic>TaCIPK25,</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK27</italic> showed peak transcript levels after 12&#xA0;h of imbibition, while <italic>TaCIPK14</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK23</italic> showed peak transcript levels at 48&#xA0;h and lower transcript levels at other time points. These transcriptional patterns indicated that the genes played roles at different stages of germination. High transcript levels of <italic>TaCIPK15</italic> were detected only at 36&#xA0;h, when the radicle of seeds emerged and the coleoptile became visible. There were high transcript levels of <italic>TaCIPK16</italic> at the initial stage of germination (12&#xA0;h). For down-regulated genes (<italic>TaCBL3</italic>, <italic>TaCIPK31</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK32</italic>) (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>), our data showed that these genes were actually up-regulated or showed no significantly changes in transcription. Moreover, despite some up-regulated genes were all validated in RT-PCR and microarray data, they displayed peak transcript levels at different time point. For example, <italic>TaCIPK23</italic> reached peak levels at 48&#xA0;h in RT-PCR analysis, while it was up-regulated at 12&#xA0;h followed with decreasing transcript levels in microarray analysis. The inconsistencies in the expression levels of genes may have been because the data were obtained using different methods, from different sub-species, or from seeds at slightly different stages of germination. We analyzed microarray data from another experiment, which focused on seed dormancy and after-ripening in bread wheat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], and found that four genes (<italic>TaCIPK7</italic>, <italic>10</italic>, <italic>17,</italic> and <italic>21</italic>) corresponded to germination and that <italic>TaCIPK31</italic> was up-regulated gene during germination (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>). Interestingly, <italic>TaCIPK32</italic> was down-regulated in dormant seeds, but up-regulated in after-ripened seeds. These data provided the preliminary information about the roles of TaCBL&#x2013;TaCIPK in seed germination.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Expression profiles of <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> in response to abscisic acid and abiotic stresses</title>
        <p>There is considerable evidence that <italic>CBL</italic> and <italic>CIPK</italic> genes play important roles in the responses to phytohormones and abiotic stresses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Among the stress hormones, ABA is a well-known signaling molecule in biotic or abiotic stress responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Cold, drought, and salinity are crucial factors affecting wheat growth and crop yields, and these stresses often cause oxidative stress.</p>
        <p>To investigate the expression profiles of <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes under stress conditions, we conducted real-time quantitative RT-PCR analyses. We analyzed the transcript levels of two <italic>TaCBL</italic>s and five <italic>TaCIPK</italic>s in wheat seedling roots and leaves under salt (NaCl), H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, drought (PEG), and cold (4&#xA0;&#xB0;C) stress treatments, and in response to ABA application (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The transcript levels of all tested <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes changed in response to many of the treatments. The genes that did not show significant changes in transcript levels (significant criterion: log&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;2, up-regulated; log&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.5, down-regulated) were <italic>TaCBL9</italic> in the leaf (ABA/PEG treatments) and in the root (cold treatment), <italic>TaCBL7</italic> in the root (NaCl treatment), <italic>TaCIPK15</italic> in the root (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment), and <italic>TaCIPK31</italic> in the leaf (ABA treatment). Among the analyzed genes, <italic>TaCIPK31</italic> exhibited remarkable ABA-induced up-regulation in roots (350-fold increase compared with that in the control at 3&#xA0;h), but not in the leaves. Under salt stress, <italic>TaCIPK24</italic> was up-regulated in roots and leaves. Therefore, it was selected for further functional characterization. The expression patterns of the analyzed <italic>TaCBL</italic>s and <italic>TaCIPK</italic>s were not completely consistent between seedling roots and leaves. For example, <italic>TaCBL4</italic> was up-regulated in roots and down-regulated in leaves in response to ABA application. Several genes responded to the same stress; for example, <italic>TaCBL9</italic>, <italic>TCIPK7</italic>, <italic>15</italic>, <italic>24</italic>, and <italic>32</italic> were induced by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Among the five treatments, cold treatment resulted in the largest number of up-regulated genes, and none of the assayed genes were down-regulated by cold in roots or leaves. In brief, the expression patterns of the assayed genes differed among different treatments and tissues, indicating that various <italic>TaCBLs</italic> or <italic>TaCIPK</italic>s may participate in the signaling response to the same stress, and that a single <italic>TaCBL</italic> or <italic>TaCIPK</italic> might function in multiple stress responses.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Expression analyses of <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> in leaves and roots responding to various treatments, including ABA (10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M), NaCl (200&#xA0;mM), H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>(10&#xA0;mM), PEG (20&#xA0;%) and cold (4&#xA0;&#xB0;C). Five time points (0&#xA0;h, 1&#xA0;h, 3&#xA0;h, 6&#xA0;h, 9&#xA0;h, 12&#xA0;h and 24&#xA0;h) were used to detect the gene expressions. The vertical axis represents gene relative expression levels. Data is the mean of three biological replicates&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;S.E</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2015_657_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
        <p>In previous studies, monocot and dicot species were shown to have divergent gene expression patterns in response to abiotic stresses or ABA application [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Thus, we conducted a comparative expression analysis of <italic>CBLs</italic>/<italic>CIPKs</italic> among wheat and two other important monocot crops (rice and maize). Microarray datasets of rice <italic>CBL</italic>/<italic>CIPK</italic> expression patterns in response to abiotic stresses were collected by Zhang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], and a dataset of maize <italic>CIPK</italic> expression patterns was obtained by semi-quantitative-PCR by Chen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The comparative analyses showed that several orthologous genes had similar transcription patterns. For example, the transcript level of <italic>CIPK32</italic> increased in leaves and decreased in roots under salinity treatment in wheat and maize. However, some orthologous genes exhibited divergent expression patterns. For example, <italic>TaCBL4</italic> showed increased transcript levels in roots and leaves under cold stress, while the transcript levels of <italic>OsCBL4</italic> decreased under cold stress. Thus, there are both conserved and divergent expression models for orthologous genes among wheat, maize, and rice.</p>
        <p>Next, we focused on stress-responsive <italic>cis</italic>-elements to decode the <italic>CBL</italic>/<italic>CIPK</italic> expression models. These elements included the ABA responsive element (ABRE), the dehydration-responsive element (DRE)/C-repeat, and the low-temperature-responsive element (LTRE) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Sequence analyses of 1-kbp sequences upstream from the start codon of the stress-inducible genes (<italic>TaCBL4</italic>, <italic>TaCBL9</italic>, <italic>TaCIPK7</italic>, <italic>TaCIPK15</italic>, and <italic>TaCIPK24</italic>) revealed that these genes contained putative ABRE, DRE, and LTRE elements (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>). These elements at least partly explained the stress-inducible expression patterns of these genes. However, even though <italic>TaCIPK31</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK32</italic> were induced by ABA, PEG, and cold, they contained only the ABRE element in their promoter regions (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>). This result is not so surprising, since we only searched for three <italic>cis</italic>-elements in this study, and there may be other unidentified elements that are important for stress-responsive gene expression. Generally, the putative stress-responsive <italic>cis</italic>-elements in promoter regions are crucial for stress-responsive expression, and activation of the <italic>cis</italic>-elements depends on the tissue, the development stage, and/or the genetic background. Therefore, there are many explanations for the diversified expression patterns of orthologous genes among different species.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Over-expression of <italic>TaCIPK24</italic> improves salt tolerance in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></title>
        <p>Previous studies showed that AtCIPK24 (SOS2) and BnaCIPK24 (homolog of TaCIPK24) participated in the salt stress response in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. In our expression analysis, <italic>TaCIPK24</italic> was induced in roots and leaves under salt stress (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Therefore, we generated transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants over-expressing <italic>TaCIPK24</italic> (or harboring pBI121 as the empty-vector control). In total, 28 transgenic lines were obtained. Three independent T3 homozygous lines (designated as OE-2, OE-7, and OE-9) were selected for further analyses. The transcript levels of <italic>TaCIPK24</italic> were detected by RT-PCR (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). In plants grown on Murashige and Skoog (MS) medium, root growth did not differ significantly among the transformants, the empty-vector control, and wild type (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b and d</xref>). However, the <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>TaCIPK24</italic> transgenic plants showed greater root growth than those of controls after treatment with 150&#xA0;mM NaCl (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c and e</xref>; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05). There were no significant differences in the phenotypes of aerial parts between transgenic lines and controls at the seedling stage under normal and salt-stress conditions. Therefore, our data indicated that TaCIPK24 promoted root elongation in transgenic plants under salt stress.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Overexpression of <italic>TaCIPK24</italic> in Arabidopsis. <bold>a</bold>
<italic>TaCIPK24</italic> expression levels in selected transgenic lines, vector control and wild type. <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold> the plants grown on control (MS medium) and stress condition (MS&#x2009;+&#x2009;150&#xA0;mM NaCl). <bold>d</bold>, <bold>e</bold> statistical analysis of the changing root length between MS control and salt stress condition (<italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2015_657_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
        <p>To further confirm the salt tolerance of <italic>TaCIPK24</italic>, seedlings of 10-day-old, soil-grown, wild-type and transgenic lines were irrigated with 200&#xA0;mM NaCl for 25 d. As shown in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>, the transgenic lines grew better than did the control plants. Furthermore, Na<sup>+</sup> accumulated to lower levels in leaves of transgenic lines than in leaves of the empty-vector control and wild type. The K<sup>+</sup> contents were not significantly different between transgenic lines and the empty-vector control/wild type (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>), indicating that the improved salt tolerance may involve Na<sup>+</sup> efflux. In addition, excess Na<sup>+</sup> would generate reactive oxygen species (ROS), such as peroxide, superoxide, and hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>), causing oxidative stress in plants. The accumulation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> was reduced in transgenic lines compared with that in the control plants (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6c</xref>). This result indicated that decreased Na<sup>+</sup> contents led to lower ROS production (at least H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) and thus, the plants were able to grow well under salt stress conditions. Antioxidant enzymes are crucial for ROS scavenging and play roles in the salt stress response in plants. Therefore, we measured the activities of three important antioxidant enzymes (catalase, CAT; peroxidase, POD; and superoxide dismutase, SOD) in transgenic plants and controls under salt stress and normal conditions. The activities of CAT, POD, and SOD were higher in transgenic lines than in wild-type and empty-vector controls (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6c</xref>). These results showed that the ectopic expression of <italic>TaCIPK24</italic> enhanced salt tolerance through facilitating Na<sup>+</sup> efflux and ROS scavenging.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Phenotype of <italic>TaCIPK24</italic> over-expression lines in Arabidopsis. <bold>a</bold> phenotypic comparison of transgenic (OE-4, OE-7, and OE-9) and control (WT) plants under 200&#xA0;mM salt stress and water control. <bold>b</bold> Na<sup>+</sup>/K<sup>+</sup> concentration in seedlings under stress conditions. <bold>c</bold> contents of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, oxidants malondialdehyde (MDA), enzymatic activities of peroxidase (POD), catalase (CAT) and superoxide dismutase (SOD) in control and transgenic plants</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2015_657_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec8" sec-type="conclusion">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>CBL and CIPK proteins play important roles in the Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling pathway and affect plant development, as well as participating in biotic and abiotic stress responses. <italic>CBL</italic>s and <italic>CIPK</italic>s have been identified and functionally characterized in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, rice, maize, and canola [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], but less is known about the <italic>CBL</italic>s and <italic>CIPK</italic>s in wheat. In this study, we identified seven <italic>TaCBL</italic> and 29 <italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes from wheat, and cloned cDNAs of seven <italic>TaCBL</italic>s and 20 <italic>TaCIPK</italic>s. Analyses of <italic>TaCBL</italic>&#x2013;<italic>TaCIPK</italic> identified 24 <italic>TaCBL</italic> and 79 <italic>TaCIPK</italic> loci in the wheat genome, indicating that there were large numbers of these gene loci in the hexaploid wheat. Blast analyses suggested that four <italic>TaCBL</italic> and 55 <italic>TaCIPK</italic> loci were derived from the <italic>T. urartu</italic> and <italic>A. tauschii</italic> genomes. We studied the preferential interactions between TaCBL and TaCIPK proteins and found 44 CBL&#x2013;CIPK interaction complexes. The proteins TaCIPK7, 10, 19, 22, 24, 28, and 29 did not interact with any of the seven TaCBL proteins assayed in these experiments. Expression analyses revealed that the majority of <italic>TaCBL</italic>s and <italic>TaCIPK</italic>s were expressed at varying levels in all tested tissues, although the transcript levels of some of these genes were very low in some tissues. We conducted RT-PCR analyses to monitor the transcript levels of seven <italic>TaCB</italic>L and 17 <italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes under abiotic stress and hormone treatments. Most were distinctly regulated by at least one treatment. Among them, <italic>TaCIPK24</italic>, the ortholog of <italic>Arabidopsis SOS2</italic>, was up-regulated by salt stress in root and leaf tissues. We generated transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> lines over-expressing <italic>TaCIPK24</italic>, and all of them showed enhanced salt tolerance. Overall, this study lays a solid foundation for further exploration of the roles of TaCBL and TaCIPK proteins in abiotic stress responses, and enhances our understanding the functions of the wheat <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> gene families. These results also provide information that will be useful for the genetic manipulation of wheat to improve stress tolerance.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec9" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title>Identification of <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes</title>
        <p>The reported CBL and CIPK protein sequences from rice and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> were used to search the NCBI UniGene database. All the selected EST sequences were collected to form a local database and were assembled into longer cDNA sequences. To further validate the integrity of <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> gene sequences, these sequences were used to search the <italic>T. aestivum</italic> cv. Chinese Spring draft genome using the BLASTn method at Gramene (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gramene.org/">http://www.gramene.org/</ext-link>) and IWGSC (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wheatgenome.org/">http://www.wheatgenome.org/</ext-link>). Rigorous criteria (E&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup>, identity&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;90&#xA0;%) were used to ensure the reliability of the nucleotide sequences.</p>
        <p>The gene-specific primers used for gene cloning were designed using Primer Premier 6 software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.premierbiosoft.com/">http://www.premierbiosoft.com/</ext-link>). <italic>TaCBLs</italic> and <italic>TaCIPKs</italic> were amplified by RT-PCR from cDNA mixtures of prepared from wheat (cv. Chinese Spring) that included cDNAs from the coleoptile, root, stem, leaf, flag, leaf, pistil, anthers, and from seedlings treated with polyethylene glycol, NaCl, cold, and ABA.</p>
        <p>The structures of <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes were illustrated using the Gene Structure Display Server (GSDS, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gsds.cbi.pku.edu.cn/">http://gsds.cbi.pku.edu.cn/</ext-link>). Briefly, the cDNA sequences of <italic>T. aestivum, T. urartu,</italic> and <italic>A. tauschii</italic> were used to search the related genomic DNA sequences of <italic>T. aestivum</italic> following the instruction of GSDS. Multiple sequence alignments were executed using Clustal W (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clustal.org/">http://www.clustal.org</ext-link>) with default parameters. An un-rooted neighbor-joining phylogenetic tree was constructed using MEGA 5.2.2 software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.megasoftware.net/">http://www.megasoftware.net</ext-link>). Genome-based sequences were used to confirm the affiliations of genes in all 21 chromosomes. Chromosomal locations were identified on genetic maps with Genome Zipper V5 at IWGSC and visualized by MapDraw. To analyze putative <italic>cis</italic>-elements in the promoters of <italic>TaCBL</italic>/<italic>TaCIPK</italic> genes, 1-kbp regions upstream of the CDS were extracted from wheat genomic sequences and subjected to a <italic>cis</italic>-element search using PLACE (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dna.affrc.go.jp/PLACE/signalup.html">http://www.dna.affrc.go.jp/PLACE/signalup.html</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>Gene expression analyses</title>
        <p>Wheat (<italic>T. aestivum</italic> L. cv. Chinese Spring) seeds were surface sterilized and then germinated in distilled water in a greenhouse at 25&#xA0;&#xB0;C. The germinated seeds were collected at five different time points (0&#xA0;h, 12&#xA0;h, 24&#xA0;h, 36&#xA0;h, and 48&#xA0;h) to analyze gene expression during seed germination. After 2&#xA0;weeks, young seedlings were subjected to ABA (10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M), H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (10&#xA0;mM), cold (4&#xA0;&#xB0;C), NaCl (200&#xA0;mM), and PEG (20&#xA0;%&#xA0;v/v) treatments for 24&#xA0;h. Samples were collected at 0&#xA0;h, 1&#xA0;h, 3&#xA0;h, 6&#xA0;h, 9&#xA0;h, 12&#xA0;h, and 24&#xA0;h after the stress treatments for analyses. Leaf samples for analyses of CAT, POD, and SOD activities were collected at 25 d after the stress treatments. All the samples were harvested, frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at &#x2212;80&#xA0;&#xB0;C until use. Total RNA was isolated from frozen tissue using a Plant total RNA Extraction kit (ZOMANBIO, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.zomanbio.com/">http://www.zomanbio.com</ext-link>). The reverse-transcription reactions were performed using a FastQuant RT kit (TIANGEN, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tiangen.com/">http://www.tiangen.com/</ext-link>).</p>
        <p>The primers used for expression analyses are listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>. The microarray datasets were processed using R 3.0.1 with the &#x201C;Affy&#x201D; package. Expression intensities were first normalized using the arithmetic RMA normalization method and then used for expression analyses. <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> DNA sequences were used to probe the Affymetrix microarray datasets with blastn in PLEXdb (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plexdb.org/index.php">http://www.plexdb.org/index.php</ext-link>). The microarray expression data and gene probes used for these analyses are listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM10" ref-type="media">10</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>Yeast two-hybrid (Y2H) and bimolecular fluorescence complementation (BiFC) assays</title>
        <p>The Y2H assays were conducted using the MatchMaker yeast two-hybrid system (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clontech.com/">www.clontech.com</ext-link>). The ORF regions of <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> were respectively sub-cloned into pGBKT7 and pGADT7 vectors and co-transformed into the Y187 yeast strain. The transformants were grown on double-dropout medium (DDO: SD/-Trp/-Leu) and selected on triple-dropout medium (TDO: SD/-Trp/-Leu/-His) containing 10&#xA0;mM 3-amino-1, 2, 4-triazole (3-AT). For BiFC assays, the ORF regions of <italic>TaCBL</italic> and <italic>TaCIPK</italic> were sub-cloned into 35S-SPYCE and 35S-SPYNE vectors, respectively. After confirmation by sequencing, these constructs were separately transformed into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> GV3101, then into tobacco leaves by <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> infiltration<italic>.</italic> Freshly transformed <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> cell cultures were re-suspended in suspension medium (10&#xA0;mM MES-KOH (pH&#xA0;5.6), 10&#xA0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 0.1&#xA0;mM acetosyringone), adjusted to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.5-0.8, and left at room temperature for 3&#xA0;h before infiltration into tobacco leaves. Infiltrated leaf discs were collected 3&#x2013;5 d later for observation under a confocal microscope. The <italic>TaCBLs</italic> and <italic>TaCIPKs</italic> primers used for vector construction are listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec13">
        <title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> transformation and treatments</title>
        <p>The full-length coding sequence of <italic>TaCIPK24</italic> was inserted into the pBI121 overexpression vector. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants were transformed using the floral-dip method with <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> strain EHA105 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The assayed plants (transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> lines and wild type) were grown on MS medium until they reached the four-leaf stage, then transferred onto MS medium containing NaCl (150&#xA0;mM) for salt stress analysis. The seedling root lengths were measured 7&#xA0;days later. For salt tolerance analysis, 10-day-old soil-grown plants were irrigated with 200&#xA0;mM NaCl at 5 d intervals for 25 d.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec14">
        <title>Ion accumulation, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> content, and enzyme activity measurements</title>
        <p>To determine ion contents, samples were analyzed by atomic absorption spectrometry. Briefly, leaves were dried at 80&#xA0;&#xB0;C for 3 d, mixed with 30&#xA0;% (v/v) H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, heated for 15&#xA0;min at 180&#xA0;&#xB0;C, and then digested with concentrated HNO<sub>3</sub> overnight. The samples were then analyzed using an atomic absorption spectrometer (AA-6300, Shimadzu Corporation). The H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> content and activities of CAT, POD, and SOD were measured by spectrophotometric methods using commercial detection kits (A064, A007, A084, and A001, Nanjing Jiancheng, China).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec15">
      <title>Availability of supporting data</title>
      <p>All the supporting data are included as additional files.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <app-group>
      <app id="App1">
        <sec id="Sec16">
          <title>Additional files</title>
          <p>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2015_657_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM1">
              <label>Additional file 1:</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>Chromosomal distribution of wheat </bold><bold><italic>TaCBL</italic></bold><bold>and</bold><bold><italic>TaCIPK</italic></bold><bold>genes identified in this study.</bold> The chromosome number is indicated on the top of each chromosome. (PDF 788&#xA0;kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2015_657_MOESM2_ESM.doc" id="MOESM2">
              <label>Additional file 2:</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>Forward and reverse primers used in gene cloning, expression and vector constructions.</bold> (DOC 72&#xA0;kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2015_657_MOESM3_ESM.doc" id="MOESM3">
              <label>Additional file 3:</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>The genome DNA, cDNA and protein sequences of all identified</bold><bold><italic>CBL</italic></bold><bold>and</bold><bold><italic>CIPK</italic></bold><bold>of</bold><bold><italic>T. aestivum</italic></bold>, <bold><italic>T. urartu</italic></bold><bold>and</bold><bold><italic>A. tauschii.</italic></bold> (DOC 1296&#xA0;kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2015_657_MOESM4_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM4">
              <label>Additional file 4:</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>Exon-intron analysis of</bold><bold><italic>TaCBLs</italic></bold><bold>and</bold><bold><italic>TaCIPKs</italic></bold><bold>in wheat.</bold> (PDF 1435&#xA0;kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2015_657_MOESM5_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM5">
              <label>Additional file 5:</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>Analysis of EF-hand motifs in calcium binding proteins of representative species.</bold> (PDF 147&#xA0;kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2015_657_MOESM6_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM6">
              <label>Additional file 6:</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>Analysis of SnRK proteins of representative species.</bold> (PDF 420&#xA0;kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2015_657_MOESM7_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM7">
              <label>Additional file 7:</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>The interaction analysis of wheat TaCBL and TaCIPK proteins were performed by Y2H method.</bold> (PDF 191&#xA0;kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2015_657_MOESM8_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM8">
              <label>Additional file 8:</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>The bimolecular fluorescence complementation experiments.</bold> (PDF 310&#xA0;kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2015_657_MOESM9_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM9">
              <label>Additional file 9:</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>Putative ABRE, DRE and LTRE core sequences in the 1-kb promoter regions of the stress-inducible genes.</bold> (PDF 114&#xA0;kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2015_657_MOESM10_ESM.xls" id="MOESM10">
              <label>Additional file 10:</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>Probes and selected microarray data in expression analysis.</bold> (XLS 66&#xA0;kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
          </p>
        </sec>
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>ABA</term>
          <def>
            <p>Abscisic acid</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>ABRE</term>
          <def>
            <p>ABA responsive element</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>BiFC</term>
          <def>
            <p>bimolecular fluorescence complementation</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CBL</term>
          <def>
            <p>Calcineurin B-like protein</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CDPK</term>
          <def>
            <p>calcium-dependent protein kinase</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CIPK</term>
          <def>
            <p>CBL interacting protein kinase</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CML</term>
          <def>
            <p>calmodulins, calmodulin-like protein</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>DDO</term>
          <def>
            <p>double-dropout medium</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>DRE</term>
          <def>
            <p>dehydration-responsive element</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>EST</term>
          <def>
            <p>expressed sequence tag</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></term>
          <def>
            <p>hydrogen peroxide</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>LTRE</term>
          <def>
            <p>low-temperature-responsive element</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>MS</term>
          <def>
            <p>Murashige and Skoog medium</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>POD</term>
          <def>
            <p>peroxidase</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>qRT-PCR</term>
          <def>
            <p>quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>ROS</term>
          <def>
            <p>reactive oxygen species</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>SOD</term>
          <def>
            <p>superoxide dismutase</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>SOS</term>
          <def>
            <p>salt overly sensitive</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>TDO</term>
          <def>
            <p>triple-dropout medium</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>VC</term>
          <def>
            <p>vector control</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>Y2H</term>
          <def>
            <p>yeast two-hybrid</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>Tao Sun and Yan Wang contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>GYH, GXY&#xA0;and&#xA0;TS&#xA0;conceived and designed the experiments. TS and YW participated in all experiments, analyzed the data. MW, TTL, XTW, SYW and YZ performed the gene cloning, RT-PCR, Y2H analyses, genetic transformation and physiological assays. TS, GYH and&#xA0;GXY wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>This work was supported by International S &amp; T Cooperation Key Projects of MoST (grant No. 2009DFB30340); National Genetically Modified New Varieties of Major Projects of China (2015ZX08002-004, 2015ZX08010-004); Research Fund for the Doctoral Program of Higher Education of China (Grant no. 2012014211075). We thank Prof. J&#xF6;rg Kudla (Universit&#xE4;t M&#xFC;nster, Germany) for providing the BiFC vectors.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sheen</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent protein kinases and stress signal transduction in plants</article-title>
          <source>SCIENCE</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>274</volume>
          <issue>5294</issue>
          <fpage>1900</fpage>
          <lpage>1902</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.274.5294.1900</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 8943201?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8943201</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Snedden</surname>
              <given-names>WA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fromm</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Calmodulin, calmodulin-related proteins and plant responses to the environment</article-title>
          <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>299</fpage>
          <lpage>304</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1360-1385(98)01284-9</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Albrecht</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weinl</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blazevic</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D'Angelo</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Batistic</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kolukisaoglu</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The calcium sensor CBL1 integrates plant responses to abiotic stresses</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>457</fpage>
          <lpage>470</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2003.01892.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 14617077?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14617077</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shi</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>KN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ritz</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Albrecht</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harter</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Novel protein kinases associated with calcineurin B-like calcium sensors in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>2393</fpage>
          <lpage>2405</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.11.12.2393</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 10590166?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10590166</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Albrecht</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ritz</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Linder</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harter</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kudla</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The NAF domain defines a novel protein-protein interaction module conserved in Ca<sup>2+</sup>-regulated kinases</article-title>
          <source>EMBO J</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>1051</fpage>
          <lpage>1063</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/20.5.1051</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 11230129?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11230129</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hashimoto</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eckert</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anschutz</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scholz</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Held</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waadt</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phosphorylation of calcineurin B-like (CBL) calcium sensor proteins by their CBL-interacting protein kinases (CIPKs) is required for full activity of CBL-CIPK complexes toward their target proteins</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>287</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>7956</fpage>
          <lpage>7968</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111.279331</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22253446?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22253446</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quan</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mendoza</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Du</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phosphorylation of SOS3-like calcium binding protein8 by SOS2 protein kinase stabilizes their protein complex and regulates salt tolerance in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>1607</fpage>
          <lpage>1619</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.066217</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19448033?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19448033</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Du</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fuglsang</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phosphorylation of SOS3-like calcium-binding proteins by their interacting SOS2-like protein kinases is a common regulatory mechanism in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>156</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>2235</fpage>
          <lpage>2243</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.173377</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21685179?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21685179</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kudla</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harter</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gruissem</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genes for calcineurin B-like proteins in Arabidopsis are differentially regulated by stress signals</article-title>
          <source>P NATL ACAD SCI USA</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>96</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>4718</fpage>
          <lpage>4723</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.8.4718</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gu</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xin</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hao</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification and characterization of putative CIPK genes in maize</article-title>
          <source>J Genet Genomics</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>77</fpage>
          <lpage>87</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcg.2011.01.005</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21356527?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21356527</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>WZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification and characterization of CBL and CIPK gene families in canola (Brassica napus L)</article-title>
          <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>8</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-14-8</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24397480?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24397480</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zheng</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huai</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cloning and characterization of a novel CBL-interacting protein kinase from maize</article-title>
          <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>661</fpage>
          <lpage>674</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-008-9445-y</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19105030?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19105030</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Qiu</surname>
              <given-names>QS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dietrich</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schumaker</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of SOS1, a plasma membrane Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> exchanger in Arabidopsis thaliana, by SOS2 and SOS3</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>8436</fpage>
          <lpage>8441</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.122224699</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12034882?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12034882</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Batelli</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verslues</surname>
              <given-names>PE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Agius</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qiu</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujii</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>SOS2 promotes salt tolerance in part by interacting with the vacuolar H<sup>+</sup>-ATPase and upregulating its transport activity</article-title>
          <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>22</issue>
          <fpage>7781</fpage>
          <lpage>7790</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.00430-07</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17875927?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17875927</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>BG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waadt</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheong</surname>
              <given-names>YH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pandey</surname>
              <given-names>GK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dominguez-Solis</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schultke</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The calcium sensor CBL10 mediates salt tolerance by regulating ion homeostasis in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>473</fpage>
          <lpage>484</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03249.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17825054?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17825054</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ren</surname>
              <given-names>XL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qi</surname>
              <given-names>GN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feng</surname>
              <given-names>HQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Calcineurin B-like protein CBL10 directly interacts with AKT1 and modulates K<sup>+</sup> homeostasis in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>258</fpage>
          <lpage>266</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12123</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23331977?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23331977</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>HD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>LQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>LL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A protein kinase, interacting with two calcineurin B-like proteins, regulates K<sup>+</sup> transporter AKT1 in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>125</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>1347</fpage>
          <lpage>1360</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2006.06.011</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16814720?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16814720</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Long</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qi</surname>
              <given-names>GN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>ZJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Os-AKT1 channel is critical for K+ uptake in rice roots and is modulated by the rice CBL1-CIPK23 complex</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>3387</fpage>
          <lpage>3402</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.114.123455</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25096783?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25096783</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grefen</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blatt</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Do calcineurin B-like proteins interact independently of the serine threonine kinase CIPK23 with the K<sup>+</sup> channel AKT1? Lessons learned from a menage a trois</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>159</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>915</fpage>
          <lpage>919</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.198051</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22548784?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22548784</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>LL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ren</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>LQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A protein kinase, calcineurin B-like protein-interacting protein Kinase 9, interacts with calcium sensor calcineurin B-like Protein3 and regulates potassium homeostasis under low-potassium stress in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>161</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>266</fpage>
          <lpage>277</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.206896</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23109687?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23109687</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gao</surname>
              <given-names>XS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garcia</surname>
              <given-names>VJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tonoplast calcium sensors CBL2 and CBL3 control plant growth and ion homeostasis through regulating V-ATPase activity in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Cell Res</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>1650</fpage>
          <lpage>1665</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2012.161</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23184060?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23184060</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eckert</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Offenborn</surname>
              <given-names>JN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heinz</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Armarego-Marriott</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schultke</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The vacuolar calcium sensors CBL2 and CBL3 affect seed size and embryonic development in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>146</fpage>
          <lpage>156</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12456</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24479654?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24479654</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>KN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheong</surname>
              <given-names>YH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grant</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pandey</surname>
              <given-names>GK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>CIPK3, a calcium sensor-associated protein kinase that regulates abscisic acid and cold signal transduction in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>411</fpage>
          <lpage>423</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.006858</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12566581?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12566581</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>de la Torre</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gutierrez-Beltran</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pareja-Jaime</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chakravarthy</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Del</surname>
              <given-names>PO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The tomato calcium sensor Cbl10 and its interacting protein kinase Cipk6 define a signaling pathway in plant immunity</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>2748</fpage>
          <lpage>2764</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.113.113530</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23903322?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23903322</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Piao</surname>
              <given-names>HL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xuan</surname>
              <given-names>YH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Je</surname>
              <given-names>BI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>OsCIPK31, a CBL-interacting protein kinase is involved in germination and seedling growth under abiotic stress conditions in rice plants</article-title>
          <source>Mol Cells</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>19</fpage>
          <lpage>27</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10059-010-0084-1</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20652492?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20652492</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ok</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cho</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oh</surname>
              <given-names>SI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shin</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Calcineurin B-like 3 calcium sensor associates with and inhibits 5'-methylthioadenosine nucleosidase 2 in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Plant Sci</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>238</volume>
          <fpage>228</fpage>
          <lpage>240</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2015.06.016</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26259190?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26259190</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jia</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kong</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Aegilops tauschii draft genome sequence reveals a gene repertoire for wheat adaptation</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>496</volume>
          <issue>7443</issue>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <lpage>95</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12028</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23535592?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23535592</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ling</surname>
              <given-names>HQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Draft genome of the wheat A-genome progenitor <italic>Triticum urartu</italic></article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>496</volume>
          <issue>7443</issue>
          <fpage>87</fpage>
          <lpage>90</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11997</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23535596?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23535596</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brenchley</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spannagl</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pfeifer</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barker</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D'Amore</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allen</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysis of the bread wheat genome using whole-genome shotgun sequencing</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>491</volume>
          <issue>7426</issue>
          <fpage>705</fpage>
          <lpage>710</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11650</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23192148?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23192148</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Deng</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wei</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>TaCIPK29, a CBL-interacting protein kinase gene from wheat, confers salt stress tolerance in transgenic tobacco</article-title>
          <source>Plos One</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0069881</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23922838?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23922838</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Deng</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feng</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ectopic expression of wheat TaCIPK14, encoding a calcineurin B-like protein-interacting protein kinase, confers salinity and cold tolerance in tobacco</article-title>
          <source>Physiol Plant</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>149</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>367</fpage>
          <lpage>377</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 23534344?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23534344</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Petersen</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seberg</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yde</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berthelsen</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships of <italic>Triticum</italic> and <italic>Aegilops</italic> and evidence for the origin of the A, B, and D genomes of common wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>)</article-title>
          <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>70</fpage>
          <lpage>82</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2006.01.023</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16504543?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16504543</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Halfter</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishitani</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular characterization of functional domains in the protein kinase SOS2 tha is required for plant salt tolerance</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>1383</fpage>
          <lpage>1400</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.13.6.1383</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 11402167?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402167</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sanchez-Barrena</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martinez-Ripoll</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Albert</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Structural Biology of a Major Signaling Network that Regulates Plant Abiotic Stress: The CBL-CIPK Mediated Pathway</article-title>
          <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>5734</fpage>
          <lpage>5749</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms14035734</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23481636?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23481636</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Borrill</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fahy</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uauy</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wheat grain filling is limited by grain filling capacity rather than the duration of flag leaf photosynthesis: a case study using NAM RNAi plants</article-title>
          <source>Plos One</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134947</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gao</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kanno</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jordan</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamiya</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of wheat seed dormancy by after-ripening is mediated by specific transcriptional switches that induce changes in seed hormone metabolism and signaling</article-title>
          <source>Plos One</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056570</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23437172?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23437172</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>An</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The CBL-CIPK network mediates different signaling pathways in plants</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell Rep</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <lpage>214</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-013-1507-1</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24097244?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24097244</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xiong</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schumaker</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cell signaling during cold, drought, and salt stress</article-title>
          <source>PLANT CELL</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>Suppl</issue>
          <fpage>S165</fpage>
          <lpage>S183</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 12045276?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12045276</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohashi-Ito</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bergmann</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Orthologs of Arabidopsis thaliana stomatal bHLH genes and regulation of stomatal development in grasses</article-title>
          <source>Development</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>136</volume>
          <issue>13</issue>
          <fpage>2265</fpage>
          <lpage>2276</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.032938</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19502487?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19502487</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shinozaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Organization of cis-acting regulatory elements in osmotic- and cold-stress-responsive promoters</article-title>
          <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>88</fpage>
          <lpage>94</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2004.12.012</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 15708346?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15708346</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shinwari</surname>
              <given-names>ZK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakashima</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miura</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kasuga</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seki</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An Arabidopsis gene family encoding DRE/CRT binding proteins involved in low-temperature-responsive gene expression</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Bioph Res Co</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>250</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>161</fpage>
          <lpage>170</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.1998.9267</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Simpson</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakashima</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Narusaka</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seki</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shinozaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Two different novel cis-acting elements of erd1, a clpA homologous Arabidopsis gene function in induction by dehydration stress and dark-induced senescence</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>259</fpage>
          <lpage>270</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2003.01624.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12535340?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12535340</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xue</surname>
              <given-names>GP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterisation of the DNA-binding profile of barley HvCBF1 using an enzymatic method for rapid, quantitative and high-throughput analysis of the DNA-binding activity</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <issue>15</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gnf076</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12140339?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12140339</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishitani</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Halfter</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Arabidopsis thaliana SOS2 gene encodes a protein kinase that is required for salt tolerance</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>3730</fpage>
          <lpage>3734</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.7.3730</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 10725382?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10725382</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liu WZ, Deng M, Li L, Yang B, Li H, Deng H, et al. Rapeseed calcineurin B-like protein CBL4, interacting with CBL-interacting protein kinase CIPK24, modulates salt tolerance in plants. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2015.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kolukisaoglu</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weinl</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blazevic</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Batistic</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kudla</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Calcium sensors and their interacting protein kinases: genomics of the Arabidopsis and rice CBL-CIPK signaling networks</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>134</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          <lpage>58</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.033068</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 14730064?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14730064</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xiang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xiong</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization of stress-responsive CIPK genes in rice for stress tolerance improvement</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>144</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>1416</fpage>
          <lpage>1428</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.107.101295</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17535819?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17535819</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Clough</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bent</surname>
              <given-names>AF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Floral dip: a simplified method for Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>735</fpage>
          <lpage>743</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.1998.00343.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 10069079?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10069079</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
