<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4658102</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0142864</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-32250</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Evolutionary Quantitative Genomics of <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic></article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Evolutionary Quantitative Genomics</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Porth</surname>
            <given-names>Ilga</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kl&#xE1;p&#x161;t&#x11B;</surname>
            <given-names>Jaroslav</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>McKown</surname>
            <given-names>Athena D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>La Mantia</surname>
            <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Guy</surname>
            <given-names>Robert D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ingvarsson</surname>
            <given-names>P&#xE4;r K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hamelin</surname>
            <given-names>Richard</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mansfield</surname>
            <given-names>Shawn D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff006">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ehlting</surname>
            <given-names>J&#xFC;rgen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff007">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Douglas</surname>
            <given-names>Carl J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff008">
            <sup>8</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>El-Kassaby</surname>
            <given-names>Yousry A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff001">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Forest and Conservation Sciences, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC V6T 1Z4, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff002">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>D&#xE9;partement des Sciences du Bois et de la For&#xEA;t, Facult&#xE9; de Foresterie, de G&#xE9;ographie et de G&#xE9;omatique, Universit&#xE9; Laval, Qu&#xE9;bec, QC, G1V 0A6 Canada</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff003">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Genetics and Physiology of Forest Trees, Czech University of Life Sciences, Prague, 165 21, Czech Republic</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff004">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line>Corn, Soybean and Wheat Quality Research Unit, United States Department of Agriculture, Wooster, Ohio, 44691 United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff005">
        <label>5</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Ecology and Environmental Science, Ume&#xE5; University, Ume&#xE5;, SE-901 87, Sweden</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff006">
        <label>6</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Wood Science, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC V6T 1Z4, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff007">
        <label>7</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Biology and Centre for Forest Biology, University of Victoria, Victoria, BC V8W 3N5, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff008">
        <label>8</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Botany, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC V6T 1Z4, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Hamberger</surname>
            <given-names>Bj&#xF6;rn</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>University of Copenhagen, DENMARK</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: YE-K RDG RCH JE SDM CJD. Performed the experiments: IP ADM JL. Analyzed the data: JK IP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: PI. Wrote the paper: IP JK YE-K.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>y.el-kassaby@ubc.ca</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>11</issue>
      <elocation-id>e0142864</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Porth et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0142864.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Forest trees generally show high levels of local adaptation and efforts focusing on understanding adaptation to climate will be crucial for species survival and management. Here, we address fundamental questions regarding the molecular basis of adaptation in undomesticated forest tree populations to past climatic environments by employing an integrative quantitative genetics and landscape genomics approach. Using this comprehensive approach, we studied the molecular basis of climate adaptation in 433 <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic> (black cottonwood) genotypes originating across western North America. Variation in 74 field-assessed traits (growth, ecophysiology, phenology, leaf stomata, wood, and disease resistance) was investigated for signatures of selection (comparing <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> -<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>) using clustering of individuals by climate of origin (temperature and precipitation). 29,354 SNPs were investigated employing three different outlier detection methods and marker-inferred relatedness was estimated to obtain the <italic>narrow-sense</italic> estimate of population differentiation in wild populations. In addition, we compared our results with previously assessed selection of candidate SNPs using the 25 topographical units (drainages) across the <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> sampling range as population groupings. <italic>Narrow-sense Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> for 53% of distinct field traits was significantly divergent from expectations of neutrality (indicating <italic>adaptive</italic> trait variation); 2,855 SNPs showed signals of diversifying selection and of these, 118 SNPs (within 81 genes) were associated with adaptive traits (based on significant <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>). Many SNPs were putatively pleiotropic for functionally uncorrelated adaptive traits, such as autumn phenology, height, and disease resistance. Evolutionary quantitative genomics in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> provides an enhanced understanding regarding the molecular basis of climate-driven selection in forest trees and we highlight that important loci underlying <italic>adaptive</italic> trait variation also show relationship to climate of origin. We consider our approach the most comprehensive, as it uncovers the molecular mechanisms of adaptation using multiple methods and tests. We also provide a detailed outline of the required analyses for studying adaptation to the environment in a population genomics context to better understand the species&#x2019; potential adaptive capacity to future climatic scenarios.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by Genome British Columbia Applied Genomics Innovation Program (Project 103BIO) and Genome Canada Large-Scale Applied Research Project (Project 168BIO), funds to RDG, RCH, JE, SDM, CJD, and YE-K.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="6"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <page-count count="25"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta id="data-availability">
          <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
          <meta-value>All relevant data are available within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability</title>
      <p>All relevant data are available within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Knowledge about the genetic basis of <italic>adaptive</italic> quantitative traits in forest trees and genetic differentiation in response to selection facilitates the prediction of long-term responses to climate, but the genetic basis of adaptation is not comprehensively understood [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. High levels of local adaptation due to consistent natural selection in a given environment resulted in local populations that have their highest fitness at their original provenance, and consequently, are differentiated from non-local populations. Within population diversity is fundamental to species survival in unpredictable environments, and therefore also relevant for conservation and forest management ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]). Recent studies within forest trees have investigated the association of local climate and geography with either randomly identified loci (<italic>Pinus taeda</italic>: [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]; <italic>Cryptomeria japonica</italic>: [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], or candidate functional genes (<italic>Picea abies</italic>: bud set candidate genes, [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]; <italic>Populus balsamifera</italic>: flowering time candidate genes, [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]) to uncover genes underlying local adaptation. The genetic architecture underlying adaptive phenotypes of forest trees is generally highly complex (<italic>e</italic>.<italic>g</italic>. [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]). Therefore, untangling the relationships between adaptive loci and the role of climate in selection vs. neutral evolutionary processes is inherently difficult.</p>
      <p>Evidence for potential adaptive significance of a genetic marker is often interpreted from &#x2018;<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier&#x2019; analyses where genetic loci significantly differ in their allelic frequencies among populations. These &#x2018;outliers&#x2019; can be efficiently detected using multilocus scans comparing patterns of nucleotide diversity and genetic differentiation to the simulated genome-wide neutral genetic background ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]). For instance, this methodology has led to the detection of SNPs implicated in local climate adaptation in <italic>Picea</italic> ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]). In order to obtain a detailed understanding of how populations have diverged in response to climate variation, such <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outliers can be tested for associations with an adaptive trait and an environmental variable to substantiate the evidence for their involvement in local adaptation ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]). Integrating quantitative and population genomics is therefore essential to determine the degree to which genetic and phenotypic variation are driven by selection as opposed to neutral processes (<italic>e</italic>.<italic>g</italic>. genetic drift). Specifically, this allows for comprehensive information from genome-wide association studies (GWAS), <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> quantitative genetics analysis (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. &#x2018;top-down&#x2019; approaches, [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]) and landscape population <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier analysis (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. &#x2018;bottom-up&#x2019; approaches, [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]) be merged.</p>
      <p>The existence of interaction effects among different loci within co-adapted gene complexes has long been recognized [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Yeaman (2013) suggested that ecological selection might even promote the physical clustering of locally adaptive loci through genomic rearrangements [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Landscape population genomics can identify genome regions significantly associated with spatial and temporal environmental gradients [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. For instance, the study using natural <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genotypes spanning the species&#x2019; range revealed that local adaptation might be maintained by independent target loci enriched for molecular processes that exhibit their major genetic effects within distinct local environments but are neutral in others [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The geographic variation in the degree to which a genetic region under selection responds is termed &#x201C;conditional neutrality&#x201D; [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and suggests a given species has not uniformly responded to an environmental pressure or that the pressure is not equally active across a species range. Importantly, the assessment of local adaptation in this work on <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> involves the study of fitness traits such as fecundity and survival (viability) ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]). In addition, there also exist traits that increase fitness in one environment, but reduce it in another. Ecological genetics can more easily explore the genetic changes over time in annuals (due to their short generation times) involving multiple generations studied under a changing environment ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]). This is less feasible for long-lived forest trees. However, the estimation of quantitative genetic parameters using SNP marker-inferred relatedness estimation to obtain <italic>narrow-sense</italic> estimates of heritability and <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> in wild populations [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] can allow monitoring adaptive genetic responses along an ecological time-scale [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p>
      <p>In this study, we integrated an extensive body of results on the genetics of wild <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic> Torr. &amp; A. Gray (black cottonwood) to understand adaptation to climate. All poplars, aspens, and cottonwoods (genus <italic>Populus</italic>) play important roles in natural ecosystems as pioneer species ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]) and are economically important for various industrial products with an increasing role as bioenergy crops ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]). <italic>Populus</italic> species are still largely undomesticated with very low population differentiation indicative of extensive long-distance intraspecific gene flow [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In western North America, <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> has an extensive cordilleran range (31&#x2013;62&#xB0;N), yet with no clear north-south differentiation in genetic diversity (and no decreasing genetic diversity with latitude), consistent with the species&#x2019; colonization history from multiple potential glacial refugia [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Several studies have indicated subtle sub-structure in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]) relating to isolation-by-distance (IBD; <italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. the decrease of genetic similarity among populations with increasing geographical distance between these populations reflected in <italic>continuous</italic> patterns of genetic differentiation and allele frequency variation in the species [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] as opposed to natural barriers causing discrete local genetic clusters), introgression and adaptation [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. We explored the extensive body of data on the genetics of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic>, including genome-wide coverage of SNPs [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], and comprehensive GWAS results from wood characteristics [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], leaf rust fungus (<italic>Melampsora</italic> x<italic>columbiana</italic>) resistance [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], biomass, ecophysiology, leaf stomata and phenology traits [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. We studied the divergence patterns of phenotypic variation and SNPs among distinct climate clusters in 433 unrelated <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> genotypes originally collected throughout the northern two-thirds of the species&#x2019; latitudinal range (excluding the highly diverged Californian population Tahoe: [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]). We tested whether phenotypic variation in traits was diverged among the climatic regions (based on non-neutral <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>), as would be expected of adaptive variation. We then predicted that SNPs that are most diverged among different climatic regions would be associated with mapped genes that underlie <italic>adaptive</italic> phenotypic variation [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p>
      <p>In brief, we used an integrative analysis of quantitative traits and genetic markers to investigate climate adaptation in wild <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> populations, we developed an integrative approach through merging genomic-based datasets and results. (1) The effects of individual loci were first separated from confounding population effects using spatial PCA (sPCA) to investigate the presence of local and global genetic structures. Following this assessment of population structure using genetic markers showing evidence of only one single genetic structure, distinct population clusters were generated based on climatic factors and this sub-population clustering was used in subsequent analyses (<xref rid="pone.0142864.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). (2) The genetic differentiation in quantitative traits (narrow-sense <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>) among populations defined by climate clusters was calculated involving the estimation of relatedness based on genetic markers. (3) In parallel, the divergence of genetic markers (<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier analysis) among populations defined by climate clusters was assessed. (4) The significance of quantitative trait divergence among populations, as defined by climate clusters, was assessed by comparing the observed <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values with the simulated distribution of <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>-<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> for a neutral trait. If the null hypothesis was rejected, the trait was considered adaptive. (5) GWAS results identifying the SNP variants underlying adaptive traits were incorporated. If these SNP variants also corresponded to loci under selection (employing four different outlier detection methods), then, the SNP variants were considered adaptive. This comprehensive analysis of genomic and phenotypic information underscores the necessity of merging multiple datasets to more fully understand evolutionary genomics of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic>.</p>
      <fig id="pone.0142864.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0142864.g001</object-id>
        <label>Fig 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Geographical origins of 433 <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> genotypes collected across 140 unique locations within the Pacific Northwest (British Columbia, Canada; Oregon, USA) and grouped into four distinct climate clusters using local temperature and precipitation records for location of origin.</title>
          <p>The climate regions were identified based on K-medoids clustering using the mean annual temperature (&#xB0;C) between yrs 1971&#x2013;2002 (MAT_1971&#x2013;2002), the number of frost-free days (NFFD_1971&#x2013;2002), and the mean annual precipitation (mm), observed between yrs 1971&#x2013;2002 (MAP_1971&#x2013;2002). Color coding is as follows: (a) population averages for MAT_1971&#x2013;2002; NFFD_1971_2002: dark red (9.5&#xB0;C; 287.1d); red (8.1&#xB0;C; 267.2d); orange (6.4&#xB0;C; 215.2d); yellow (4.2&#xB0;C; 175.4d); (b) population average for MAP_1971&#x2013;2002: dark blue (2805.9mm); blue (1571.8mm); light blue (1517.0mm); green (744.2mm). We note here that canonical correlations between geography and ecology were high (r = 0.9 for the first canonical variable component).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.g001"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="sec002">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="sec003">
        <title>Population structure assessment</title>
        <p>Negative eigenvalues from sPCA were negligible (<xref rid="pone.0142864.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>), suggesting no local genetic clusters. By comparison, the presence of IBD was verified by large positive eigenvalues (<xref rid="pone.0142864.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). These results were further confirmed by the local and global tests within the &#x201C;adegenet&#x201D; program (see <xref rid="sec012" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>). While, again, we did not detect local genetic structure in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> (local test <italic>P</italic> = 0.937), we did identify global genetic structure attributed to IBD (global test <italic>P</italic> = 0.001) that was observed across the entire population involving the 140 unique geographical locations represented by one randomly chosen genotype.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0142864.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0142864.g002</object-id>
          <label>Fig 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Identification of isolation-by-distance (IBD) among 433 <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> genotypes based on spatial PCA.</title>
            <p>Large positive eigenvalues were indicative of IBD.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.g002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec004">
        <title>Divergence of quantitative characters (<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>) among climate clusters</title>
        <p>We calculated <italic>narrow-sense Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values for 74 distinct field-assessed traits for the study population. Assessments included 16 wood, 12 biomass, 14 phenology, 18 ecophysiological, 13 leaf stomata, and one rust resistance phenotype (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). Observed <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values for each trait were compared to the simulated distribution of <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub><italic>-F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values for a neutral trait (simulating a range of possible demographic scenarios, see <xref rid="sec012" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>). Among all traits, 53% (39/74 traits) had <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values significantly different from zero and therefore were classified as <italic>adaptive</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0142864.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The highest number of significant <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values was observed among biomass traits (76%), phenology traits (70%), ecophysiology traits (64%) and leaf rust resistance (100%). By comparison, only 25% of wood-based traits had significant <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values. <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values for traits that significantly diverged among the four climate clusters ranged from 0.03 (&#x3B4;15N, <italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. stable nitrogen isotope ratio) to 0.26 (bole biomass). Among all tested traits, the climatic clusters best explained the phenotypic variation in phenology based on the <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values, ranging from 17% (100% leaf yellowing) to 24% (bud set). Among wood characteristics, two cell wall sugar traits (% galactose and % arabinose in dry wood) and two wood ultrastructure attributes (fiber length and microfibril angle) showed significant <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values. The climatic clusters explained 13 and 12% of the arabinose and galactose content, respectively.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0142864.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0142864.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>h</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>, and <italic>h</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> corrected <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> of adaptive traits (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</title>
            <p>Summary of 39 distinct <italic>adaptive</italic> traits of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> that diverged among different climate clusters (displayed are 59 tests for adaptation including tests for traits replicated in time, comprehensive results shown in <xref rid="pone.0142864.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>).</p>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0142864.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0142864.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">#</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trait</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>narrow-sense h</italic>
                    <sup>
                      <italic>2</italic>
                    </sup>
                  </th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S.E.</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>narrow-sense Q</italic>
                    <sub>
                      <italic>ST</italic>
                    </sub>
                  </th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S.E.</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variance explained by partitions<xref rid="t001fn009" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>&#x2551;</sup></xref></th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S.E.</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bole density_2012<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4040</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0402</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0482</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0522</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0397</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0429</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0017</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bole mass_2012<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1758</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0430</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2584</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1788</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1109</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0877</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Branches_2009<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4898</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0245</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1567</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1151</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1541</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1131</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H:D2+_2011<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3753</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0254</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0321</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0352</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0243</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0268</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0178</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Height _2008<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4540</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0260</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1133</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0905</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1040</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0835</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Height _2009<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6543</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0200</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1132</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0893</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1432</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1088</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Height _2010<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7378</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0165</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0900</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0743</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1274</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1006</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Height _2011<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7092</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0178</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0792</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0673</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1087</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0892</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Height gain _2009<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7504</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0163</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0952</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0777</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1364</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1061</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Height gain _2010<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6217</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0212</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0477</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0455</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0586</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0551</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0019</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Height gain _2011<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3372</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0250</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0490</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0483</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0337</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0335</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0016</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole tree mass_2012<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2279</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0434</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2323</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1634</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1225</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0953</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Volume _2009<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3663</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0256</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1159</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0925</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0877</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0718</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Volume _2010<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4519</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0253</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0945</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0783</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0862</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0718</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Volume _2011<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5091</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0243</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0900</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0751</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0915</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0760</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Volume gain _2010<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4441</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0254</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0913</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0763</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0820</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0689</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Volume gain _2011<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4396</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0253</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0923</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0771</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0822</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0691</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amax/mass_2009<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1349</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0264</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1822</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1396</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0579</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0493</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amax_2009<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1916</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0261</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0596</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0604</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0240</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0248</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0007</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlsummer _2009<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2692</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0292</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1160</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0968</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0663</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0577</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlsummer _2011<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3078</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0288</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1438</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1135</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0939</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0777</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C:N_2009<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1631</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0270</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1423</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1156</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0518</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0454</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d15N_2009<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0882</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0232</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0257</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0395</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0047</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0072</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0446</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dleaf_2009<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4872</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0272</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0269</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0299</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0263</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0291</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0371</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gs_2009<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4243</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0279</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0402</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0401</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0344</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0343</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0055</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaves per bud _2011<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3307</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0310</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0767</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0695</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0523</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0482</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaves per bud _2012<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4786</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0297</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0910</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0765</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0875</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0735</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>LMAsummer _2010<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2360</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0281</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0628</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0644</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0307</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0322</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Narea_2009<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1907</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0278</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0479</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0525</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0189</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0211</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0028</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nmass_2009<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1592</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0271</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1409</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1150</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0500</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0441</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WUE_2009<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2457</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0274</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0731</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0667</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0373</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0350</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUDPC-2009<xref rid="t001fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5322</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0245</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0490</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0470</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0521</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0495</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0017</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUDPC-2010<xref rid="t001fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3937</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0260</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0723</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0646</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0579</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0523</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0002</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUDPC-2011<xref rid="t001fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3132</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0251</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0848</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0740</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0551</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0492</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Active growth rate _2009<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6094</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0222</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0390</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0393</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0471</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0469</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0083</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Bud set _2008<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5970</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0224</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1390</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1051</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1617</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1186</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Bud set _2009<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7390</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0165</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1790</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1262</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2438</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1580</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Bud set _2010<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6483</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0200</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1708</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1224</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2108</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1434</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bud set186_2009<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5247</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0234</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1988</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1368</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2067</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1403</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bud set186_2010<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4041</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0268</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2125</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1444</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1792</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1261</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Height growth cessation _2009<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7114</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0178</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1434</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1072</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1923</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1354</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Leaf drop _2008<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5175</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0244</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1533</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1137</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1579</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1160</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Leaf drop _2009<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5168</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0237</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2335</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1525</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2396</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1547</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Leaf drop _2010<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5965</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0214</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1453</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1088</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1687</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1225</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Leaf lifespan_2010<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6278</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0208</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0432</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0419</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0537</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0514</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0039</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canopy duration _2009<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2409</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0253</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0944</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0809</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0480</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0428</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Canopy duration _2010<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8119</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0126</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0462</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0438</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0729</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0671</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0024</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth period _2009<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3176</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0255</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1046</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0862</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0693</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0589</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Growth period _2010<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7095</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0176</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1365</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1032</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1833</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1308</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Post-bud set period _2009<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4222</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0260</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0332</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0352</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0282</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0299</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0187</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>Post-bud set period _2010<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5230</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0237</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1432</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1075</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1489</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1106</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>100% Yellowing _2010<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5886</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0220</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1498</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1113</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1718</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1240</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="t001fn008" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>75% Yellowing _2010<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5640</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0227</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0638</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0571</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0714</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0632</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0002</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arabinose<xref rid="t001fn006" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8786</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2227</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0749</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0707</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1276</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1079</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0002</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fiber<xref rid="t001fn006" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3027</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2423</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0825</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1135</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0446</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0515</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Galactose<xref rid="t001fn006" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9327</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2089</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0663</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0621</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1167</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1002</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MFA1<xref rid="t001fn006" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4074</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2383</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0403</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0539</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0355</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0419</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0054</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ad_StomataNUM1<xref rid="t001fn007" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3165</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0266</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1229</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0984</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.d.</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.d.</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0129</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ad_STM_distribution<xref rid="t001fn007" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1779</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0351</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1050</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1041</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.d.</td>
                  <td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.d.</td>
                  <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0357</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t001fn001">
              <p>Note: <italic>P</italic>-value obtained by comparison of the observed <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub><italic>&#x2014;F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> to the quantile of the simulated <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub><italic>&#x2014;F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> distribution for a neutral trait [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>].</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn002">
              <p><sup>a</sup>biomass trait [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn003">
              <p><sup>b</sup>ecophysiology trait [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn004">
              <p><sup>c</sup>leaf rust resistance trait [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn005">
              <p><sup>d</sup>phenology trait [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn006">
              <p><sup>e</sup>wood trait [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn007">
              <p><sup>f</sup>leaf stomata traits [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn008">
              <p>*spatially adjusted trait [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn009">
              <p><sup>&#x2551;</sup>the variance explained by climate clusters compared to the total variance was estimated as h<sup>2</sup> corrected P<sub>ST</sub></p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn010">
              <p>S.E. refers to standard errors</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn011">
              <p>Active growth rate (cm day <sup>-1</sup>)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn012">
              <p>Ad_StomataNUM1: Adaxial stomata numbers</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn013">
              <p>Ad_STM_distribution: Adaxial stomata distribution</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn014">
              <p>Amax/mass = photosynthetic rate per unit dry mass (&#x3BC;mol CO<sub>2</sub> mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn015">
              <p>Arabinose in dry wood (%)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn016">
              <p>AUDPC = (calculated) area under the disease curve, based on <italic>M</italic>. x<italic>columbiana</italic> infection rating</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn017">
              <p>Bole density (kg/m<sup>3</sup>)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn018">
              <p>Bole mass (kg)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn019">
              <p>Branch #</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn020">
              <p>Bud set (day)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn021">
              <p>Bud set<sup>&#x1C2;</sup> (day): bud set dates considered only after summer solstice</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn022">
              <p>C:N = carbon:nitrogen (mg mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn023">
              <p>Canopy duration (days)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn024">
              <p>Chlsummer = chlorophyll content index (CCI)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn025">
              <p>D15N = stable nitrogen isotope ratio (&#x2030;)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn026">
              <p>Dleaf = net discrimination (&#x2030;)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn027">
              <p>Fiber: fiber length Lw (mm)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn028">
              <p>Galactose in dry wood (%)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn029">
              <p>Growth period (days)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn030">
              <p>gs = stomatal conductance (mol H<sub>2</sub>O m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn031">
              <p>H:D = height to diameter (cm:cm)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn032">
              <p>Height (cm)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn033">
              <p>Height gain (cm)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn034">
              <p>Height growth cessation (day)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn035">
              <p>Leaf drop (day)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn036">
              <p>Leaf lifespan (days)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn037">
              <p>Leaves per bud (#)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn038">
              <p>LMA = leaf mass per unit area (mg mm<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn039">
              <p>MFA1: microfibril angle at most recent growth ring (&#xB0;)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn040">
              <p>Narea = nitrogen (mg mm<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn041">
              <p>Nmass = nitrogen (mg mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn042">
              <p>Post-bud set period (days)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn043">
              <p>Volume (cm<sup>3</sup>)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn044">
              <p>Volume gain (cm<sup>3</sup>)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn045">
              <p>Whole tree mass (kg)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn046">
              <p>WUE = instantaneous water-use efficiency (&#x3BC;mol CO<sub>2</sub> mmol<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> H<sub>2</sub>O)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn047">
              <p>Yellowing, 100% (day)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t001fn048">
              <p>Yellowing, 75% (day)</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec005">
        <title>Identification of SNPs under selection</title>
        <p>Using both unsupervised and climate-based SPA, a total of 1,468 SNPs were identified being under selection at a 5% cutoff for each method (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). We also performed <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier analysis on climate clusters. While the mean <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> value for the complete dataset (29,354 SNPs) was 0.0108, we obtained a mean neutral <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> value (0.0078) after removing loci identified to be potentially under selection [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In the final analysis, all loci were tested against this neutral mean to identify a set of potential <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outliers relating to climate. Using 200k simulations in Fdist2, we identified 121 SNPs outside the 99% limits of the neutral distribution (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>) as potential candidates subjected to diversifying (positive) selection related to the four climate clusters. Among these, 88% of these climate-related &#x2018;outliers&#x2019; were confirmed by allelic frequency correlation analysis with averages for climate variables within subpopulation (using multiple univariate logit regression models in SAM (&#x3B1; = 0.05, <xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>)), 77 of these loci persisted across different selection scan scenarios employed (unsupervised SPA, climate-based SPA, and <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> analysis based on population subdivision [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]), and 48 SNPs were retrieved using association genetics (see below) (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). A comparison between Fdist and SPA testing gene dispersal and employing Moran&#x2019;s test for spatial autocorrelation (<xref rid="pone.0142864.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>) indicates, in general, the higher effectiveness of SPA to identify genetic selection signals under patterns of IBD.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0142864.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0142864.g003</object-id>
          <label>Fig 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparison of two outlier detection methods (<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>, SPA) for their efficiency to identify genetic selection signals under isolation-by-distance (IBD).</title>
            <p>Gene dispersal was tested employing Moran&#x2019;s test for spatial autocorrelation using 200km lags.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>A significant accumulation of <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outliers was identified on chromosome 15 (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). The extent of linkage disequilibrium (LD) between all 121 outlier loci is presented in <xref rid="pone.0142864.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>. In general, we found that LD was not substantial between SNPs from different genes. Incomplete LD can be caused by the possibility that SNPs are close to but not in complete LD with the causal variants (here probably due to &#x2018;tag SNP&#x2019; design of the SNP chip array [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]) explaining why the observed LD between diverged loci is generally low [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] One notable exception is two neighboring poplar genes (Potri.009G008600 and Potri.009G008500) initially annotated based on sequence homology to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes as nitrate transporter types <italic>ATNRT2</italic>:<italic>1</italic> and <italic>ATNRT2</italic>:<italic>4</italic>, respectively. The allele frequencies of three SNPs and one SNP, respectively, in poplar orthologs of <italic>ATNRT2</italic>:<italic>1</italic> and <italic>ATNRT2</italic>:4, respectively, are strongly correlated to temperature (R<sup>2</sup>&gt;0.9; <italic>P</italic> = 0.05), while the remaining SNPs in both genes did not follow such a strong pattern (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec006">
        <title>SNPs under diversifying selection and associated with quantitative traits</title>
        <p>To corroborate findings of candidate loci putatively under diversifying selection based on climate, we compared these results with SNPs uncovered by associations with adaptive traits (showing non-neutral <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>). Among four GWAS studies in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic>, a total of 619 SNPs had been identified with significant trait associations (at &#x3B1; = 0.05): 410 with biomass, ecophysiology and phenology [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], 141 with wood property traits [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], 40 with <italic>Melampsora</italic> x<italic>columbiana</italic> resistance [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], and 28 SNPs related to leaf stomata variation [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].</p>
        <p>We compared four different outlier analyses to identify selection signals in 29,354 SNPs. Most trait-associated SNPs for which we detected selection signals were associated with adaptive traits (89%, <xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). The highest percentage of trait-associated SNPs in outlier analyses was found for climate-based <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier analysis (40% of the total number of outliers identified by the method; 48 SNPs), followed by geography-based <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier analysis (8%; 75 SNPs that were reported in [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], unsupervised SPA (5%; 75 SNPs), and SPA with climate as a covariate (3%; 37 SNPs). In total, selection signals were detected for 151 trait-associated SNPs with 44% overlap among evaluation methods. Interestingly, there was a lack of genome-wide correlation between selection and association signal (<xref rid="pone.0142864.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>) and thus only dispersed association signals were detected among SPA selection signals (<xref rid="pone.0142864.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). This result is probably a consequence of the structure correction methods employed in GWAS.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0142864.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0142864.g004</object-id>
          <label>Fig 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Genome-wide correlations between selection outliers and association signals based on 29k SNPs.</title>
            <p>Correlation of -log (<italic>P</italic>) versus spa was plotted against the trait&#x2019;s <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.g004"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone.0142864.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0142864.g005</object-id>
          <label>Fig 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Individual SNPs under diversifying selection within genes mapping to quantitative trait variation.</title>
            <p>5% cutoff: dashed and yellow lines; 1% cutoff: solid and red lines; ecology (biomass, ecophysiology, phenology, stomata)&#x2014;green dots; wood properties (orange); rust resistance (blue).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.g005"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We retrieved a number of unique but also shared SNPs among the different analyses (<xref rid="pone.0142864.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>). Shared SNPs were highest for climate <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> (75%) and geography-based <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> (72%). Unsupervised SPA had the highest number of unique SNPs among the four methods (51%). We found 118 SNPs associated with adaptive traits (significant <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>) including 59 SNPs under diversifying selection shared among at least two outlier detection methods and 59 unique SNPs detected by climate <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>, climate SPA and unsupervised SPA, respectively (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>). A large number of SNPs (40%) that we identified as <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outliers using climate clustering were candidate SNPs from association studies (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). The high number of trait-associated SNPs reflects both the polygenic nature of phenotypic traits (<italic>e</italic>.<italic>g</italic>., c.200 for bud set, [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]) and linkage disequilibrium (LD) to a lesser extent. The highest number of climate-based <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outliers associated with adaptive traits was found on chromosome 15 (12 SNPs), identifying a genomic region where SNPs putatively under selection to local climate generally may be clustered (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0142864.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0142864.g006</object-id>
          <label>Fig 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Venn diagram showing the numbers of unique and shared SNPs (totaling 151 trait-associated SNPs) among four different outlier detection approaches.</title>
            <p><italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> using climate clusters, <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> using geographical grouping, SPA analyses&#x2014;with climate-based PCs incorporated as covariates and unsupervised, respectively. A subset of this information (118 SNPs) related to genetic polymorphisms associated solely with <italic>adaptive</italic> trait variation is provided in <xref rid="pone.0142864.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.g006"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We found that SNPs under potential climate selection matching putative causal variants from association studies consistently mapped to non-neutral <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>, <italic>adaptive</italic> traits (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref> Tables). Only one SNP associated with wood traits (within Potri.009G006500 annotated as <italic>FRA8</italic> associated with fiber length, [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]) was among the <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier loci. Comparatively, phenology traits were the most complex <italic>adaptive</italic> traits from the high match between the total number of associated SNPs and the proportion of SNPs with allele frequencies significantly diverged among climate clusters (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). In total, 118 SNPs were outliers under diversifying selection, associated with <italic>adaptive</italic> traits (significant <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>), and with many SNPs putatively pleiotropic for functionally uncorrelated adaptive traits, such as autumn phenology, height, and disease resistance (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>). The 78 annotated poplar genes were largely derived from major gene functional group such as (1) transcription factors of several categories and (2) carbohydrate-related genes, but also transporters. Among these transporters, two poplar genes (Potri.009G008600 and Potri.009G008500) annotated based on sequence homology to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes as nitrate transporter types <italic>ATNRT2</italic>:<italic>1</italic> and <italic>ATNRT2</italic>:<italic>4</italic>, respectively, were highly pleiotropic for several adaptive traits (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec007">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="sec008">
        <title>Evolutionary quantitative genomics</title>
        <p>The main focus of our work involved identifying adaptive traits and their genetic basis in forest trees by employing both a quantitative genetics approach (<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> analysis) and population genomics [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] to uncover SNPs under strong selection (among c.29k tested genetic polymorphisms). Our analyses revealed that 53% of these traits produced significant <italic>narrow-sense Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>) underscoring that such quantitative traits are very likely related to adaption to local climatic conditions [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</p>
        <p>This study uses SNP marker-inferred relatedness estimation (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. the &#x2018;animal model&#x2019;) to obtain <italic>narrow-sense</italic> estimates of heritability and <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> in wild populations [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The quality of genetic estimates using the &#x2018;animal model&#x2019; approach largely depends on the accuracy of relationship coefficient estimates and are affected by: 1) number and quality of markers [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], 2) variance in actual relatedness [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], and 3) how well the relationship estimates reflect the segregation of causal variants [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] Our present study is based on extensive, genome-wide SNPs [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] which can provide high accuracy for both the relationship coefficients and the estimated genetic parameters. However, samples from natural tree populations are subject to intensive gene flow (outcrossing) and generally show low levels of relatedness which can negatively affect heritability and <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> analyses.</p>
        <p>Heritability is usually dependent on the population sampled (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. the observed allele frequency differences) and thus, can differ for smaller sampling sizes and/or specific sampling areas (<italic>e</italic>.<italic>g</italic>., central vs. marginal regions of species distribution). Heritability estimates taken across a greater coverage of the species distribution are more likely to reflect evolutionary history of the traits (stabilizing vs. diversifying selection) rather than the effects of population subsampling. Sufficient variance in the actual relatedness is also required to reveal heritability in wild populations [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], although heritability, and indirectly, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> estimates, can suffer from the inability to separate the pure additive genetics from environmental effects, specifically when relatedness is lacking. Thus, the presence of LD between markers and causal variants (QTLs) is crucial to recover the genetic parameters with sufficient precision. In the case of traits under diversifying selection, the additive genetic variance estimates (such as <italic>narrow-sense</italic> heritability) may also include a substantial QTL covariance component, in addition to the pure genic variance. This is especially the case when many QTLs follow the same cline, and can further extend the additive genetic variance when the QTLs interact (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>., epistasis) [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] unless the epistasis is accounted for in the model [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Thus, heritability estimates for traits under diversifying selection (<xref rid="pone.0142864.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) may be upwardly biased (see below).</p>
        <p>Heritability estimates are often interpreted as the capacity for adaptive evolution. In addition, epistatic interactions, specifically, the directional epistasis, have major effects through altering the genetic background (both, the additive genetic variances and the covariances, <italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. the allelic frequencies but also their effects) [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Hemani <italic>et al</italic>. (2013) outlined that for traits under selection, high levels of genetic variation are maintained and the traits evolve more slowly than expected, yet this could be attributed to high epistasis in traits under strong diversifying selection [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec009">
        <title>Selectively non-neutral genetic variants underlying traits adaptive to climate</title>
        <p>Overall, the number of <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier SNPs underlying an adaptive trait correlated well with the total number of candidate SNPs associated with that trait (r = 0.625, P = 0.0005). Yet, the majority of trait associated SNPs were not <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outliers (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>) and appeared to be unresponsive to selection for different climatic conditions, especially for phenology traits such as bud set, leaf drop or growth period. A previous simulation study suggested that differentiation in candidate loci is limited for complex traits in forest trees (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>., their <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values are similar to neutral values), despite their strong adaptive divergence among local populations (high <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>), due to large population sizes and high levels of gene flow [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Thus, highly polygenic adaptation (as observed in complex genetic traits) will not show sufficient allele frequency differentiation such that climatic clines in SNPs of candidate genes can be exhaustively detected.</p>
        <p>We modelled the spatial structure of genetic variation using SPA (addressing gene flow under IBD), and SNPs identified via SPA were compared against GWAS-identified SNPs, climate-related <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outliers and geography-informed <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outliers. The majority of SNPs with steep allele frequency clines (based on unsupervised SPA) uncovered allele frequency correlations with the north-south cline (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). We noted that enrichment for particular genes, such as circadian rhythm/clock genes, was found in PC1 (a north-south population structure) [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] and that SNPs of these genes were among the highest ranked in SPA. Nonetheless, associations of circadian rhythm clock genes with strong correlations to environment were largely missing among the identified genetic associations for phenology traits (discussed in McKown et al. [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]). The interplay of IBD and natural selection was lost by the necessary structure correction in GWAS, however, evidence from gene expression or gene regulation that is also highly correlated with the trait under question might be possible to retrieve such SNPs of putative importance (Anonymous, [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]).</p>
        <p>The presence of IBD in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> underscores the larger issue for investigating wild populations with quantitative genetics and population genomics approaches as IBD can confound population structure, association mapping, and outlier analyses. The power to detect local selection depends on several factors, including selection strength, the presence of distinct types of microenvironment heterogeneity, and the distance of gene dispersal compared to the overall spatial scale [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. In our case, as the observed gene dispersal is ~500 km (<xref rid="pone.0142864.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>) and sampling is also discontinuous (<xref rid="pone.0142864.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>), this does not allow us to perform <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> analysis on arbitrarily defined local populations because it will be more difficult to separate the stochastic noise (drift, migration) from the selection signal in smaller scale population subsampling leading to an excess of false positives [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Yet, selection pressures can differ along environmental clines. Thus, <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outliers should be investigated on the largest scale possible following the spatial distribution of the environment in order to identify spatial genetic structure. Nevertheless, IBD in wild populations will create some compromised statistical power in detecting local adaptation using specific pairs of populations that is unavoidable (<xref rid="pone.0142864.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec010">
        <title>Polygenic and pleiotropic adaptation relating to climate</title>
        <p>Our climate clustering partitioned the study population into four large, evenly-sized groups of individuals lending robustness to SNP detection even for lower frequency (recent) variants. In our study, the top two SNPs among climate related <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outliers showed strongest associations to climate partitions according to SAM analysis [Potri.010G250600 (<italic>MSR2/ MANNAN SYNTHESIS RELATED 2</italic> implicated in carbohydrate metabolism) and Potri.010G254400 (transporter <italic>ATGCN4</italic>) (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>)]. In addition, six genes that harboured climate-related <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier SNPs have been identified as candidates for bud set in previous studies ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]), yet these loci were not associated with bud set in our GWAS study ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]; <xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>), possibly through implementing the conservative population structure correction term in GWAS. Nevertheless, these genes may represent additional candidates for bud set, including Potri.003G218900 (<italic>ACD1-LIKE</italic>), Potri.009G015100 (senescence-associated family protein), Potri.014G170400 (<italic>XERICO</italic>), Potri.015G012500 (<italic>IQ-domain 21</italic>), Potri.018G015100 (chloroplast nucleoid DNA-binding protein), and Potri.019G078400 (leucine-rich repeat transmembrane protein kinase) (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>).</p>
        <p>Evidence is emerging that for perennial trees to effectively sense short day signals, <italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. critical day length in autumn phenology [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], a temperature optimum is required and genetically pre-determined by the local climate of the individual&#x2019;s origin [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Allele frequencies for most of the SNPs that both associated with bud set and diverged among the climate clusters showed strong regression on the mean temperature variation of the climatic clusters (R<sup>2</sup> up to 0.94; <xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). A critical role for temperature, rather than precipitation, on bud set has also been found in <italic>Picea</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. For autumn phenology, elevated temperatures can either accelerate or delay growth cessation depending on species or ecotype ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]), but under climate warming, the overall effects on phenological timing in forest trees is unknown.</p>
        <p>SNP allelic frequencies within both nitrate transporter genes <italic>ATNRT2</italic>:<italic>4</italic> and <italic>ATNRT2</italic>:1 were strongly aligned with temperature variation (R<sup>2</sup>~90%) in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic>. Moreover, these SNPs were pleiotropic for multiple autumn phenology traits, height, and leaf rust resistance (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>). Nitrate transporters are generally important in plants, as nitrate is the main nitrogen source required for synthesis of nucleic and amino acids. Therefore, a regulation of nitrate distribution is crucial to modulate growth (biomass acquisition) in response to temperature or light conditions ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]). Interestingly, there are only two poplar representatives within a phylogenetic sub-clade of NRT2 that is populated by as many as five Arabidopsis sequences (<italic>ATNRT2</italic>.<italic>1</italic>/<italic>2</italic>.<italic>2</italic>/<italic>2</italic>.<italic>3/2</italic>.<italic>4</italic>/<italic>2</italic>.<italic>6</italic>). This implies that a deletion event occurred in this clade whose functional significance remains elusive to date [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Phylogenetic reconstruction coupled with gene expression analysis point at neo/subfunctionalisation of the two poplar nitrate transporters for long distance nitrate transport from roots, wood to leaves [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. This acquisition of novel expression pattern and loss of the ancestral expression pattern demonstrates the signature of adaptive evolution in functional diversification in paralogous gene pairs [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>].</p>
        <p>In addition, our results revealed that adaptive genetic variants within both poplar nitrate transporters were also associated with leaf rust resistance ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]; <xref rid="pone.0142864.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>). In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, loss of function of <italic>ATNRT2</italic>.<italic>1</italic> primes salicylic acid signaling and <italic>PR1</italic> up-regulation [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. In poplar leaf rust inoculations, both PT<italic>NRT2</italic>.<italic>4</italic> and PT<italic>NRT2</italic>.<italic>1</italic> are strongly down-regulated in incompatible interactions, while no expression change is apparent in compatible interactions (J. La Mantia, personal observation). The identified nitrogen transporters might be important in nitrogen storage and nitrogen remobilization to recycle nutrients during the progression of leaf senescence [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. They may also function in down-regulation of nitrogen assimilation during seasonal remodeling of tree phenology related to growth cessation induced by short photoperiods ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]) and/or temperature [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. The effect of temperature on rust aggressiveness is noted [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>] and the climatic conditions which form a conducive environment for rust infection and disease duration likely provide a strong adaptive selection toward resistance.</p>
        <p>Pectin esterase gene Potri.012G014500 (SNP scaffold_12_1811250) represents another example for which significant associations with climate (here: temperature) and several adaptive traits were found (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0142864.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref> Tables). In fact, the allelic effects of this SNP related to hypostomaty also related to less rust infection ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]). This is an illustrative example regarding the tradeoff between carbon gain and pest resistance under favourable climatic conditions relating to pathogen pressure ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec011">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>The high adaptive potential of tree populations is considered the result of positive effects of long-distance gene flow based on its interactions with divergent selection across the contrasting environments [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>], while local adaptation in forest trees with regards to climate-related traits is polygenic and recent [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. For instance, interactions between temperature and photoperiodic cues were shown to influence bud set for short-term acclimation in poplar [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. By combining quantitative genetics and population genomics analyses, our study contributes to an enhanced understanding of the molecular basis of adaptation to different local climate in an undomesticated perennial species (<italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic>). The key findings provided SNPs whose allelic frequencies were most diverged among populations from different climate clusters and these SNPs tended to be associated with mapped genes underlying phenotypic variation. This phenotypic variation itself diverged among the different climate clusters. Our study dissected the influence of climate (specifically, temperature and precipitation), yet much of the variation in phenology is also attributed to photoperiod ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]). The tight photoperiodic control of traits such as bud set, height growth cessation, and leaf senescence ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]) is crucial both for resistance to cold temperatures and maximization of the growing season, particularly in trees originating from high-latitude and/or high elevation provenances ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]). While we tested the influence of climate on the variation of other traits in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic>, such as wood and biomass, we consider other local factors, such as soil condition (pH and minerals), soil/root microbial diversity, groundwater, and other ecological interactions also of potential importance. Reciprocal transplants will be necessary to elucidate the effects of gene &#xD7; environment plasticity on the expression of traits with spatially heterogeneous selection [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], but can focus on specific genes identified through a combined quantitative genomics analysis, such as the one proposed here. Forthcoming research can also scale trait-to-performance mapping in known pedigrees for the assessment of SNP effects on fitness [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. These findings will have important implications for the future management of natural forests, acting to guide efforts in facilitated adaptation to climate change via measure such as assisted gene flow [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec012">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="sec013">
        <title>Collection, genotyping, and phenotyping of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic></title>
        <p>The germplasm used in this study was propagated under permission from the British Columbia Ministry of Forests, Lands &amp; Natural Resource Operations. No endangered or protected species were used in this study. Plant material was collected from a population of 433 <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> Torr. &amp; A. Gray genotypes growing in a common garden. These genotypes came from 140 unique geographic locations spanning two thirds of the species&#x2019; range (44&#x2013;60&#xB0;N, 121&#x2013;138&#xB0;W) ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>], <xref rid="pone.0142864.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). Originally collected by the BC Ministry of Forests, Lands and Natural Resource Operations, individual genotypes were grown in two common gardens, Surrey, BC and Totem Field, University of British Columbia, BC. Genotypes were replicated across the two field gardens and the Totem Field individuals (established in 2008 [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]) were clonal propagations from Surrey site individuals (established in 2000 [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]).</p>
        <p>Trees were genotyped using an Illumina iSelect array with 34,131 SNPs from 3,543 candidate genes designed for <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The characteristics of the poplar genome and array development are outlined in [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]). Briefly, the SNP array was designed to include genes of known importance (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. candidate genes) or genes based on expression analyses. Because of the rate of linkage disequilibrium (LD) decay in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic>, between 67&#x2013;134k SNPs would be required to include all common variants throughout the genome at LD = 0.2 (assuming a 403 Mb assembled genome length and an average of 3&#x2013;6 kb for r<sup>2</sup> between common variants to drop to 0.2). Therefore, some SNPs were selected as representative SNPs to &#x201C;tag&#x201D; genes and genetic regions with high LD, and thus represent a group of SNPs (the haplotype). For this study, we further filtered array SNPs for: i) minor allele frequency (MAF) &lt;0.05, ii) &gt;10% missing data, and iii) Illumina&#x2019;s GenTrain score &lt;0.5, thereby reducing SNP numbers to 29,354. This filtering is not biased towards higher frequency SNPs (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. older variants established at much higher frequencies within the population over time) as a wide distribution of allele frequencies (MAF&gt;0.05) was considered for the analysis.</p>
        <p>Phenotyping of genotype accessions within the common gardens and climate of origin data were obtained from previously published work (for full phenotyping details, see [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]). In brief, phenology, ecophysiology, biomass [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], leaf stomatal anatomy [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] and leaf rust (<italic>Melampsora</italic> x<italic>columbiana</italic>) resistance traits [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] were repeatedly measured from accessions planted at the University of British Columbia&#x2019;s research field through replication in space (clonal ramets) and in time (measurements across years). Wood chemistry and ultrastructure traits were measured from wood cores of the nine-year-old ortets representing the same genotypes and growing in Surrey [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec014">
        <title>Assessment of population structure</title>
        <p>Since forest tree species usually have extensive geographic ranges, exhibit extensive gene flow and have low levels of population stratification [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>], we investigated whether the genetic variability due to non-random mating in our population was caused solely by isolation-by-distance (IBD), reflecting the large geographical distribution of our sample (cf. [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]), or also by natural barriers causing local genetic clusters. We performed spatial principal component analysis (sPCA) by using the &#x201C;spca&#x201D; function implemented in the R package &#x201C;adegenet&#x201D; [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>] which is a spatially explicit multivariate analysis accounting for spatial autocorrelation processes and patterns of genetic variation. A K-nearest neighbours method with K = 10 was used as connection network. Positional information for each genotype were transformed into Universal Transverse Mercator (UTM) coordinates using &#x201C;convUL&#x201D; in the R package &#x201C;PBSmapping&#x201D; [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Due to the occurrence of multiple genotypes with identical geographical coordinates (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. trees collected at the same latitude/longitude), we randomly selected a single genotype representing a geographical region (out of the total 140 locations). Eigenvalues for principal components from sPCA provided a cumulative picture about contributing factors, including the genetic variance and the spatial autocorrelation (through Moran&#x2019;s I, see below). Large positive eigenvalues reflect the importance of the proportion of the genetic variance along with a strong positive autocorrelation in the global pattern (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. IBD), while large negative eigenvalues indicate the importance of the proportion of the genetic variance along with negative autocorrelation indicating the existence of discrete local genetic clusters.</p>
        <p>We used the "global.test" and "local.test" functions in the "adegenet" package to infer the statistical significance of each type of genetic structure. These functions are based on a spectral decomposition of the connection matrix into Moran's eigenvector map and test for association of those eigenvectors from Moran's eigenvector map with Moran's I [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. To investigate gene dispersal, we employed a Moran I test for spatial autocorrelation ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]). Moran&#x2019;s I coefficients were investigated in 200 km spatial lags and the analysis was performed using &#x201C;moran.test&#x201D; in the &#x201C;spdep&#x201D; R package [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Moran&#x2019;s I coefficients were estimated as follows:<disp-formula id="pone.0142864.e001"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e001.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e001g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#xAF;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#xAF;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#xAF;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>
where <italic>n</italic> is the number of populations (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. unique geographical locations), <italic>w</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub> is weight set at 0 or 1 depending on whether populations are considered neighbours in each 200 km lag test, <italic>x</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the allele frequency in the i<sup>th</sup> population, and <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e002"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e002.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e002g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the allele frequency across all populations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec015">
        <title>Climatic zone clustering of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic></title>
        <p>Since our initial investigation of population structure with sPCA indicated the presence of only one global structure consisting of IBD and lack of local discrete clusters, any marker-based inference about genetic clusters might be highly unreliable [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Therefore, we established population differentiation on the basis of climate envelopes ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]). Clusters of individual genotypes were defined using climate of origin measures (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. independently of the genetic data). Climate variables were obtained using ClimateWNA [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>] and included mean annual temperature (MAT; &#xB0;C), number of frost-free days (NFFD), and mean annual precipitation (MAP; mm). Climate data were based on positional information (latitude, longitude, elevation) and 1971&#x2013;2002 Canadian Climate Normals [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Using K-medoids clustering and the Calinski-Harabasz criterion [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>], we split the study population into four groups with relatively balanced sample sizes of 87, 103, 142, and 101 representing climate classes #1&#x2013;4, respectively. Clusters generally followed the western North American coastline inwards (<xref rid="pone.0142864.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1<italic>a</italic> &amp; 1<italic>b</italic></xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec016">
        <title>Genetic differentiation in quantitative characters among populations defined by climate clustering</title>
        <p>We tested phenotypic characteristics in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> for their adaptive potential (<xref rid="pone.0142864.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). For <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>&#x2212;<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> comparisons, <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values among the identified climate-related population groups were first estimated for each trait following [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>] and [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], respectively.</p>
        <p>The <italic>narrow-sense Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> was estimated by computing the variance components using the &#x2018;animal model approach&#x2019; [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>] following:
<disp-formula id="pone.0142864.e003"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e003.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e003g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>&#x3B2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>
where <italic>&#x3B2;</italic> is a vector of fixed effects (intercept), <italic>p</italic> and <italic>a</italic> are vectors of random climate cluster and individual tree additive genetic effects, <bold>X</bold> and <bold>Z</bold> are incidence matrices assigning fixed and random effects to measurements in vector y, the cluster effects are following p~N(0,<inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e004"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e004.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e004g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M4"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>) where <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e005"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e005.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e005g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M5"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the cluster variance, individual tree additive effects are following a~N(0,<inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e006"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e006.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e006g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M6"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">G</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>) where <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e007"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e007.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e007g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M7"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the additive genetic variance and <bold>G</bold> is the realized relationship matrix [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>], using 29,354 SNPs estimated in R package &#x201C;synbreed&#x201D; [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>] as follows:
<disp-formula id="pone.0142864.e008"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e008.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e008g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">Z</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">Z</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2032;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>
where <bold>Z</bold> is <bold>M</bold>-P, with M the marker matrix with genotypes recoded into 0, 1 and 2 for the reference homozygote allele, the heterozygote and the alternative homozygote allele, respectively, and with P the vector of doubled allele frequency; e is the vector of random residual effects following e~N(0,<inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e009"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e009.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e009g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M9"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">I</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>) where <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e010"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e010.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e010g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M10"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the residual variance and <bold>I</bold> is the identity matrix. The <italic>narrow sense Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> was estimated as follows:
<disp-formula id="pone.0142864.e011"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e011.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e011g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>Q</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ST</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>=</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e012"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e012.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e012g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M12"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e013"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e013.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e013g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M13"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> are the estimates of cluster and additive genetic variance representing among- and within-group trait variances attributable to additive effects.</p>
        <p>The measurements of all ecology and disease traits using clonal ramets (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. replication) enable estimating <italic>broad-sense Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> directly without the use of any relationship matrix, while <italic>narrow-sense Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> estimation was based on variance components estimated in the mixed linear model considering the realized relationship matrix [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>] as in <xref rid="pone.0142864.e003" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 2</xref>. The model is identical to <xref rid="pone.0142864.e003" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 2</xref> where the variance components for <italic>broad-sense Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> were estimated in the model considering <italic>a</italic> as the vector of clonal genotypic values following a~N(0,<inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e014"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e014.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e014g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M14"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">I</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>) where <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e015"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e015.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e015g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M15"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the total genetic variance (including both additive and non-additive component) and <italic>e</italic> as the vector of ramet within clone effects following e~N(0,<inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e016"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e016.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e016g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M16"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">I</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>). Then, the computed <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values for each trait were compared to the average population differentiation estimate (<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>) strictly based on neutral markers (see below) allowing inferences about trait evolution based on selection or genetic drift (neutral trait), [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>].</p>
        <p><italic>Narrow-sense</italic> heritability (<italic>h</italic><sup>2</sup>) was based on variance components estimated in the mixed model as follows:
<disp-formula id="pone.0142864.e017"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e017.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e017g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M17"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>&#x3B2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(5)</label></disp-formula>
where <italic>&#x3B2;</italic> is the vector of fixed effects (intercept and cluster) and <italic>a</italic> is the random vector of additive genetic effects following the description of <xref rid="pone.0142864.e003" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 2</xref>. The <italic>narrow-sense</italic> heritability was estimated as follows:
<disp-formula id="pone.0142864.e018"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e018.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e018g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e019"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e019.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e019g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M19"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e020"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e020.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e020g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M20"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> are estimates of additive genetic and residual variance, respectively. The phenotypic <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>) ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]) was estimated as follows:
<disp-formula id="pone.0142864.e021"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e021.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e021g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M21"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>P</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ST</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mo>&#x3C3;</mml:mo><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mo>&#x3C3;</mml:mo><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mo>&#x3C3;</mml:mo><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(7)</label></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e022"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e022.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e022g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M22"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e023"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e023.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e023g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M23"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> are estimates of cluster and residual variance representing among- and within-population variances, respectively, and <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e024"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e024.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e024g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M24"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the heritability estimated according to [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The variance components were estimated in ASReml software [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>] using the mixed linear model following:
<disp-formula id="pone.0142864.e025"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e025.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e025g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M25"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>&#x3B2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(8)</label></disp-formula>
where <italic>&#x3B2;</italic> is the vector of fixed effects (intercept) and <italic>p</italic> is the vector of random cluster effects, the effect of individuals within cluster is found within the error variance.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec017">
        <title>Identification of non-neutral SNPs and quantitative traits divergent among climate clusters</title>
        <p>To identify SNPs putatively under selection and also associated with adaptive traits ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]), we performed: 1) <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier analysis (using Fdist2) employing the same climate clusters as for <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> analysis, 2) unsupervised spatial ancestral analysis (SPA), and 3) SPA with climate as a covariate. Additionally, we compared our results with <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier analysis (using Fdist2 and BayeScan) that were reported in [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] using 25 topographic units separated by watershed barriers within the geographic area from Central Oregon, USA (44.3&#xB0;N) to northern BC, Canada (59.6&#xB0;N)).</p>
        <p><italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values for SNPs were calculated among the four climate clusters (for definition and calculation, see above). We implemented the Fdist2 program within the LOSITAN project [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] for SNP <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier detection. Fdist2 compares the distribution of <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values of sampled loci to the modeled neutral expectation of <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> distribution using coalescent simulations [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. We employed the infinite alleles mutation model (as we investigated SNPs), a subsample size of 50, and ran 200k simulations. <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values conditioned on heterozygosity and outside the 99% confidence interval were considered candidate outliers.</p>
        <p>Since <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> populations have known structure related to IBD ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and this study), we applied spatial ancestral analysis (SPA), a logistic regression-based approach [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>], to detect SNPs with sharp allelic frequency changes across geographical space (implying candidates under selection). The unsupervised learning approach (using only genomic data) was employed to obtain SPA statistics. In addition, we tested SPA including the first two principal components (PCs) based on climate variables (explaining 91% of the variance) as covariates to determine individuals&#x2019; location based on allele frequencies related to MAT, NFFD, and MAP climate components.</p>
        <p>We investigated correlations between the outlier SNPs (based on climate clusters) and the environmental variables that defined the established climatic clusters (<xref rid="pone.0142864.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). Subpopulation averages for MAT, NFFD, and MAP were tested for correlations with SNP allele frequencies employing multiple univariate logistic regression models with the spatial analysis method (SAM; [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]). The significance of correlations was assessed using three independent statistical tests (likelihood ratio and two Wald tests) implemented in SAM and applying an initial 95% confidence interval for the statistical tests. We used the Bonferroni correction method (&#x3B1; = 0.05) for multiple testing resulting in <italic>p</italic>&lt;6.887052*10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup> for 726 tested models (242 alleles, three variables). Only those correlations that remained significant after Bonferroni correction for each of the three test statistics (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. the likelihood ratio and the two Wald tests) were retained.</p>
        <p>Finally, we compared observed <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values with the simulated distribution of <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>-<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values for a neutral trait using previously provided R scripts [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. In brief, a range of possible demographic scenarios was tested simulating the distribution of <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values based on mean <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> for neutral markers and mean <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> for neutral traits ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]). For a neutral trait, the expected <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> was estimated based on <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e026"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e026.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e026g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M26"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>., measured within-population variance; see above) and <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e027"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e027.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e027g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M27"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>., expected between-population variance) given in <xref rid="pone.0142864.e011" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 4</xref>. The distribution of <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e028"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e028.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e028g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M28"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> values was based on <inline-formula id="pone.0142864.e029"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0142864.e029.jpg" id="pone.0142864.e029g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M29"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and the observed <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values of 29,233 SNPs present (total number reduced by removing outliers) within the simulated <italic>neutral</italic> envelope of <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values (<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier analysis) with <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> replaced by the <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> in <xref rid="pone.0142864.e011" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq 4</xref>. <italic>P</italic>-values were obtained by testing whether the null hypothesis that the estimated <italic>narrow-sense Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> for each tested trait is statistically equal to the expected <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> for a neutral trait [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec018">
        <title>Marker-trait association mapping</title>
        <p>In previous analyses of marker-trait associations in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic>, confounding effects of population stratification were adjusted using principal component analysis ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] and a <bold>Q</bold> matrix population structure correction [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Phenological mismatch within the common garden can confound trait values [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], thus, association analyses included &#x201C;area under the disease curve&#x201D; resistance measures with adjustment for bud set [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and all ecophysiological traits that were measured prior to bud set [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The Unified Mixed Model (a modification of the generalized linear model) was employed for marker-trait association mapping and is fully described ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]). While necessary, the adjustment for confounding, cryptic genetic structure in the association analyses may have reduced the statistical power to detect associations. This is particularly problematic in species whose distribution is mainly along a one-dimensional cline or for which differentiation in ecological traits covaries with the species demographic history ([<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]). Furthermore, the GWAS results may be biased towards common variants or variants with the greatest effects. This is related to the size of the SNP discovery panel (34k) [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref099" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>] and the power to detect significant associations given the tested population sizes (334&#x2013;448 individuals). As whole genome sequencing and phenotyping of thousands of genotypes would be required to comprehensively uncover the genetic architecture of complex traits, we consider the GWAS results informative but not exhaustive.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec019">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0142864.s001">
        <label>S1 Fig</label>
        <caption>
          <title><italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier loci detection in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> and distribution of outliers along the poplar chromosomes.</title>
          <p>(a) <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier loci detection and distribution of empirical <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> estimates conditioned on expected heterozygosity (H<sub>E</sub>). The envelope of values corresponding to neutral expectations at 99% CI level (with mean <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> = 0.0078), solid line, was constructed with the infinite allele model according to [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. (b) Distribution of the empirical <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> estimates along the 19 poplar chromosomes and additional scaffolds (abbrev: scaff); the 121 identified outlier loci are indicated by red circles above their <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> value bars. A goodness-of-fit test assuming a uniform distribution was performed to test whether the observed frequencies of &#x2018;outlier loci&#x2019; along the 19 poplar chromosomes differed significantly from the expected value. Following the rejection of the null hypothesis (chi-square = 81.98 df = 18, <italic>P</italic>-value = 3.85e-10), we declared &#x2018;outlier loci hotspots&#x2019; if the number of outliers at a given chromosome was equal or above the maximum value (<italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>., 20) for assessed outlier clusters from a randomly generated data set using the 118 outliers found across the 19 chromosomes, and running 1,000 replicates, which identified significant clustering of outliers on chromosome 15.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0142864.s001.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0142864.s002">
        <label>S2 Fig</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Linkage disequilibrium between 121 identified <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier loci and relationship between <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> outlier allele frequencies and climate variables in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic>.</title>
          <p>Simple linear regression (R<sup>2</sup>) of allelic frequencies (following arcsine transformation) on temperature and precipitation, respectively (mean annual temperature in &#xB0;C: MAT_1971&#x2013;2002; number of frost-free days: NFFD_1971&#x2013;2002 and mean annual precipitation in mm: MAP_1971&#x2013;2002, observed between yrs 1971&#x2013;2002) calculated among the four distinct climate clusters (<xref rid="pone.0142864.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>); Note: POPTR_0143s00200 was recently re-annotated to Potri.009G008500 and both genes are now assembled on chromosome 9 within 50kb of each other (new poplar genome assembly Phytozyme v3). Both sequences are now described as tandem gene pair <italic>PTNRT2</italic>.<italic>4A</italic> (alias Potri.009G008600) and <italic>PTNRT2</italic>.<italic>4B</italic> (alias Potri.009G008500) with 97% DNA sequence similarity [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>].</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0142864.s002.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0142864.s003">
        <label>S1 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Comprehensive population differentiation estimates and <italic>h</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> corrected <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> for <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic>: <italic>broad-sense</italic> and <italic>narrow-sense Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> for 58 distinct field traits; <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub><italic>1</italic> and <italic>narrow-sense Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> (<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub><italic>2</italic>) estimates for 16 wood traits.</title>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0142864.s003.xls">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0142864.s004">
        <label>S2 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Comprehensive summary table of all SNP detection results from GWAS [ecology [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]; rust [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]; stomata [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]; wood [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]] and outlier analysis (geographic <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], this study: climate <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>, unsupervised SPA, climate SPA) for the black cottonwood population (presented in <xref rid="pone.0142864.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>) and using the 34k SNP chip [<xref rid="pone.0142864.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]; adaptive traits (significant <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>) are in bold.</title>
          <p>In red and dark blue are 1% cutoffs (spa = 2.78025 and spa = 1.50795), in orange and light blue are 5% cutoffs (spa = 2.12467 and spa = 1.08868) in unsupervised SPA and climate SPA analyses, respectively.</p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0142864.s004.xlsx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0142864.s005">
        <label>S3 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>List of 118 SNPs associated with <italic>adaptive</italic> traits (significant <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> for at least one associated trait) including 59 SNPs under diversifying selection shared among at least two outlier detection methods and 59 unique SNPs detected by climate <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>, climate SPA and unsupervised SPA, respectively.</title>
          <p>Comprehensive results are provided in <xref rid="pone.0142864.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0142864.s005.xls">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors thank Dr. Julien Prunier for help with &#x2018;Spatial analysis method&#x2019; software.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref001">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lascoux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Merila</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ecological genomics of local adaptation</article-title>. <source>Nature Review Genetics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>807</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref002">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yeaman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holliday</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Curtis-McLane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Adaptation, migration or extirpation: climate change outcomes for tree populations</article-title>. <source>Evolutionary Applications</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>95</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>111</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1752-4571.2007.00013.x">10.1111/j.1752-4571.2007.00013.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 25567494?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25567494</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref003">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Allendorf</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hohenlohe</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luikart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genomics and the future of conservation genetics</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>697</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>709</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrg2844">10.1038/nrg2844</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 20847747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20847747</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref004">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bower</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonzalez-Martinez</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wegrzyn</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coop</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Back to nature: ecological genomics of loblolly pine (Pinus taeda, Pinaceae)</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>3789</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>805</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2010.04698.x">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2010.04698.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 20723060?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20723060</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref005">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tsumura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Uchiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moriguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ihara-Ujino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genome scanning for detecting adaptive genes along environmental gradients in the Japanese conifer, Cryptomeria japonica</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>349</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/hdy.2012.50">10.1038/hdy.2012.50</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22929151?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22929151</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref006">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kallman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gyllenstrand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zaina</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morgante</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Disentangling the Roles of History and Local Selection in Shaping Clinal Variation of Allele Frequencies and Gene Expression in Norway Spruce (Picea abies)</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>191</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>865</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>81</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1534/genetics.112.140749">10.1534/genetics.112.140749</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22542968?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22542968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref007">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levsen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tiffin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Local Adaptation in the Flowering-Time Gene Network of Balsam Poplar, Populus balsamifera L</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>3143</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 22513286?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22513286</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref008">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holliday</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>White</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Global monitoring of autumn gene expression within and among phenotypically divergent populations of Sitka spruce (Picea sitchensis)</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>178</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>103</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.02346.x">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.02346.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18194148?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18194148</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref009">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beaumont</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluating loci for use in the genetic analysis of population structure</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B-Biological Sciences</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>263</volume>(<issue>1377</issue>):<fpage>1619</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref010">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eveno</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guevara</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leger</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Contrasting patterns of selection at Pinus pinaster Ait. drought stress candidate genes as revealed by genetic differentiation analyses</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>417</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 18065486?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18065486</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref011">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Namroud</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beaulieu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Juge</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laroche</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bousquet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Scanning the genome for gene single nucleotide polymorphisms involved in adaptive population differentiation in white spruce</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>3599</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>613</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2008.03840.x">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2008.03840.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18662225?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18662225</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref012">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Prunier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laroche</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beaulieu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bousquet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Scanning the genome for gene SNPs related to climate adaptation and estimating selection at the molecular level in boreal black spruce</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1702</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2011.05045.x">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2011.05045.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21375634?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21375634</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref013">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holliday</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suren</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Divergent selection and heterogeneous migration rates across the range of Sitka spruce (Picea sitchensis)</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B-Biological Sciences</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>279</volume>(<issue>1734</issue>):<fpage>1675</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>83</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref014">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luikart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>England</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tallmon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taberlet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>The power and promise of population genomics: From genotyping to genome typing</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>981</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>94</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 14631358?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14631358</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref015">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>MWG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Monitoring adaptive genetic responses to environmental change</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1311</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>29</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2011.05463.x">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2011.05463.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22269082?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22269082</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref016">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sork</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Legendre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Putting the landscape into the genomics of trees: approaches for understanding local adaptation and population responses to changing climate</article-title>. <source>Tree Genetics &amp; Genomes</source>. <year>2013</year>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref017">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stinchcombe</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoekstra</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Combining population genomics and quantitative genetics: finding the genes underlying ecologically important traits</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>158</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17314923?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17314923</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref018">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Endler</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Geographic variation, speciation, and clines</article-title>. <source>Monographs in population biology</source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>246</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 409931?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">409931</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref019">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yeaman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genomic rearrangements and the evolution of clusters of locally adaptive loci</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>E1743</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>51</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref020">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fournier-Level</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Korte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nordborg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilczek</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>. <article-title>A Map of Local Adaptation in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>334</volume>(<issue>6052</issue>):<fpage>86</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1209271">10.1126/science.1209271</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21980109?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21980109</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref021">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schnee</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Conditional neutrality of polygene effects</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>42</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref022">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brachi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jarymowycz</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sperone</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Adaptation to Climate Across the Arabidopsis thaliana Genome</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>334</volume>(<issue>6052</issue>):<fpage>83</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1209244">10.1126/science.1209244</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21980108?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21980108</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref023">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mitchell-Olds</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolutionary genetics of plant adaptation</article-title>. <source>Trends in Genetics</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>258</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>66</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tig.2011.04.001">10.1016/j.tig.2011.04.001</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21550682?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21550682</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref024">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>RIC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pannell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Are Q(ST)-F(ST) comparisons for natural populations meaningful?</article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>4782</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2008.03958.x">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2008.03958.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 19140971?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19140971</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref025">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Eckenwalder</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>. <source>Systematics and evolution of Populus</source>. <name><surname>Stettler</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>B</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heilman</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hinckley</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, editor. <publisher-loc>National Research Council of Canada Ottawa, ON, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NRC Research Press</publisher-name>; <year>1996</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref026">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cronk</surname><given-names>QCB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Plant eco-devo: the potential of poplar as a model organism</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>39</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>48</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15760349?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15760349</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref027">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cellulosic Biofuels</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>82</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.arplant.043008.092125">10.1146/annurev.arplant.043008.092125</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 19014348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19014348</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref028">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sannigrahi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ragauskas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tuskan</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Poplar as a feedstock for biofuels: A review of compositional characteristics</article-title>. <source>Biofuels Bioproducts &amp; Biorefining-Biofpr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>209</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref029">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Stanton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <chapter-title><italic>Populus</italic> breeding: from the classical to the genomic approach</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Jansson S</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Groover</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, editor. <source><italic>Genetics and Genomics of Populus</italic></source>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year> p. <fpage>309</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref030">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Porth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>El-Kassaby</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Using Populus as a lignocellulosic feedstock for bioethanol</article-title>. <source>Biotechnology Journal</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>510</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/biot.201400194">10.1002/biot.201400194</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 25676392?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25676392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref031">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slavov</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhelev</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Salient Biological Features, Systematics, and Genetic Variation of Populus</article-title>. <source>Genetics and Genomics of Populus</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref032">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lexer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stoelting</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Whole genome sequencing (WGS) meets biogeography and shows that genomic selection in forest trees is feasible</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>196</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>652</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2012.04362.x">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2012.04362.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23043586?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23043586</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref033">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slavov</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DiFazio</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Population substructure in continuous and fragmented stands of Populus trichocarpa</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>348</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>57</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/hdy.2010.73">10.1038/hdy.2010.73</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 20531447?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20531447</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref034">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slavov</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DiFazio</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schackwitz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muchero</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodgers-Melnick</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Genome resequencing reveals multiscale geographic structure and extensive linkage disequilibrium in the forest tree Populus trichocarpa</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>196</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>713</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2012.04258.x">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2012.04258.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22861491?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22861491</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref035">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Geraldes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Difazio</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slavov</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ranjan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muchero</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hannemann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A 34K SNP genotyping array for Populus trichocarpa: Design, application to the study of natural populations and transferability to other Populus species</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Resources</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>306</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/1755-0998.12056">10.1111/1755-0998.12056</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23311503?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23311503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref036">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Geraldes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Farzaneh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grassa</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKown</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mansfield</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Landscape genomics of Populus trichocarpa: the role of hybridization, limited gene flow, and natural selection in shaping patterns of population structure</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3260</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/evo.12497">10.1111/evo.12497</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 25065449?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25065449</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref037">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Porth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kl&#xE1;p&#x161;t&#x11B;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skyba</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geraldes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muchero</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Populus trichocarpa cell wall chemistry and ultrastructure trait variation, genetic control and genetic correlations</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>197</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>777</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/nph.12014">10.1111/nph.12014</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23278123?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23278123</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref038">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>La Mantia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klapste</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>El-Kassaby</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Azam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Association Analysis Identifies Melampsora xcolumbiana Poplar Leaf Rust Resistance SNPs</article-title>. <source>PloS One</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e78423</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0078423">10.1371/journal.pone.0078423</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 24236018?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24236018</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref039">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McKown</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kl&#xE1;p&#x161;t&#x11B;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geraldes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Porth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hannemann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Genome-wide association implicates numerous genes underlying ecological trait variation in natural populations of Populus trichocarpa</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>203</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>535</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/nph.12815">10.1111/nph.12815</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 24750093?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24750093</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref040">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slavov</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodgers-Melnick</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ranjan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muchero</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Population genomics of Populus trichocarpa identifies signatures of selection and adaptive trait associations</article-title>. <source>Nature genetics</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1089</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng.3075">10.1038/ng.3075</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 25151358?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25151358</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref041">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Antao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beja-Pereira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luikart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>LOSITAN: A workbench to detect molecular adaptation based on a F(st)-outlier method</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-9-323">10.1186/1471-2105-9-323</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18662398?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18662398</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref042">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hemani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Knott</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>An Evolutionary Perspective on Epistasis and the Missing Heritability</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genetics</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e1003295</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003295">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003295</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23509438?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23509438</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref043">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Porth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klap&#x161;te</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skyba</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hannemann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKown</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Genome-wide association mapping for wood characteristics in Populus identifies an array of candidate single nucleotide polymorphisms</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>200</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>710</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>26</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/nph.12422">10.1111/nph.12422</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23889164?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23889164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref044">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McKown</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quamme</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kl&#xE1;p&#x161;t&#x11B;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>La Mantia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Constabel</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Association genetics, geography and ecophysiology link stomatal patterning in Populus trichocarpa with carbon gain and disease resistance trade-offs</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>5771</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/mec.12969">10.1111/mec.12969</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 25319679?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25319679</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref045">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McKown</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kl&#xE1;p&#x161;t&#x11B;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geraldes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Friedmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cronk</surname><given-names>QCB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Geographical and environmental gradients shape phenotypic trait variation and genetic structure in Populus trichocarpa</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>201</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1263</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/nph.12601">10.1111/nph.12601</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 24491114?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24491114</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref046">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Frentiu</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clegg</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chittock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blows</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>IPF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Pedigree-free animal models: the relatedness matrix reloaded</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B-Biological Sciences</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>275</volume>(<issue>1635</issue>):<fpage>639</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref047">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ritland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ritland</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Inferences about quantitative inheritance based on natural population structure in the yellow monkeyflower, Mimulus guttatus</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1074</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref048">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lippert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kadie</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Listgarten</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heckerman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>The benefits of selecting phenotype-specific variants for applications of mixed models in genomics</article-title>. <source>Scientific Reports</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>1815</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/srep01815">10.1038/srep01815</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23657357?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23657357</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref049">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <source>Genetics and Analysis of Quantitative Traits</source>. <edition>first ed.</edition><publisher-loc>Sunderland, MA, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sinauer Associates</publisher-name>; <year>1998</year><fpage>980</fpage> p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref050">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identifying quantitative trait locus by genetic background interactions in association studies</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>176</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>553</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17179077?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17179077</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref051">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>AJR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hermisson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role of epistatic gene interactions in the response to selection and the evolution of evolvability</article-title>. <source>Theoretical Population Biology</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16122771?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16122771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref052">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Le Corre</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>. <article-title>Decoupling of differentiation between traits and their underlying genes in response to divergent selection</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>375</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/hdy.2011.81">10.1038/hdy.2011.81</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21915150?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21915150</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref053">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Anonymous</collab>. <article-title>On beyond GWAS</article-title>. <source>Nature Genetics</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>551</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng0710-551">10.1038/ng0710-551</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 20581872?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20581872</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref054">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Epperson</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>. <source><italic>Geographical Genetics</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey</publisher-loc>; <year>2003</year><fpage>376</fpage> p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref055">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ruttink</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arend</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morreel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Storme</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rombauts</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fromm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A molecular timetable for apical bud formation and dormancy induction in poplar</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2370</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17693531?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17693531</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref056">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fabbrini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaudet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bastien</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zaina</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harfouche</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beritognolo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Phenotypic plasticity, QTL mapping and genomic characterization of bud set in black poplar</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-12-47">10.1186/1471-2229-12-47</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22471289?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22471289</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref057">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Petterle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karlberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bhalerao</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Daylength mediated control of seasonal growth patterns in perennial trees</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>301</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pbi.2013.02.006">10.1016/j.pbi.2013.02.006</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23473967?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23473967</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref058">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bastien</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boerjan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Temperature signals contribute to the timing of photoperiodic growth cessation and bud set in poplar</article-title>. <source>Tree Physiology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>472</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>82</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/treephys/tpr038">10.1093/treephys/tpr038</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21636689?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21636689</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref059">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kalcsits</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Warm temperature accelerates short photoperiod-induced growth cessation and dormancy induction in hybrid poplar (Populus x spp.)</article-title>. <source>Trees-Structure and Function</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>971</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref060">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hanninen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Tree seasonality in a warming climate</article-title>. <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>412</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tplants.2011.05.001">10.1016/j.tplants.2011.05.001</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21640632?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21640632</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref061">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsay</surname><given-names>Y-F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Arabidopsis Nitrate Transporter NRT1.9 Is Important in Phloem Nitrate Transport</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1945</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>57</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.111.083618">10.1105/tpc.111.083618</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21571952?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21571952</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref062">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Euring</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Volmer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Janz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Polle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Nitrate Transporter (NRT) Gene Family in Poplar</article-title>. <source>PloS One</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e72126</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0072126">10.1371/journal.pone.0072126</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23977227?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23977227</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref063">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leebens-Mack</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Expression pattern shifts following duplication indicative of subfunctionalization and neofunctionalization in regulatory genes of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>469</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>78</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16280546?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16280546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref064">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Camanes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pastor</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cerezo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garcia-Andrade</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vicedo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garcia-Agustin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A Deletion in NRT2.1 Attenuates Pseudomonas syringae-Induced Hormonal Perturbation, Resulting in Primed Plant Defenses</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>158</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1054</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>66</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.111.184424">10.1104/pp.111.184424</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22158760?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22158760</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref065">
        <label>65</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Himelblau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nutrients mobilized from leaves of Arabidopsis thaliana during leaf senescence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Plant Physiology</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>158</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1317</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref066">
        <label>66</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fuchigami</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Partitioning of nitrate assimilation among leaves, stems and roots of poplar</article-title>. <source>Tree Physiology</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>717</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12091153?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12091153</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref067">
        <label>67</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Larisch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wildhagen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lautner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fromm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Polle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Poplar Wood Rays Are Involved in Seasonal Remodeling of Tree Physiology</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>160</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1515</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>29</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.112.202291">10.1104/pp.112.202291</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22992511?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22992511</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref068">
        <label>68</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chandrashekar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heather</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Temperature sensitivity of reactions of populus spp to races of Melampsora-larici-populina</article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>421</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref069">
        <label>69</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ronce</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robledo-Arnuncio</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guillaume</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bohrer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Long-distance gene flow and adaptation of forest trees to rapid climate change</article-title>. <source>Ecology Letters</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>378</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>92</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1461-0248.2012.01746.x">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2012.01746.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22372546?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22372546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref070">
        <label>70</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Le Corre</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The genetic differentiation at quantitative trait loci under local adaptation</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1548</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>66</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05479.x">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05479.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22332667?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22332667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref071">
        <label>71</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Adaptive gradients and isolation-by-distance with postglacial migration in Picea sitchensis</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>224</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17487214?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17487214</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref072">
        <label>72</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Soolanayakanahally</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silim</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Timing of photoperiodic competency causes phenological mismatch in balsam poplar (Populus balsamifera L.)</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell and Environment</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>116</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref073">
        <label>73</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luquez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Albrectsen</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ingvarsson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Natural phenological variation in aspen (Populus tremula): the SwAsp collection</article-title>. <source>Tree Genetics &amp; Genomes</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>279</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref074">
        <label>74</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fracheboud</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luquez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bjorken</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sjodin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tuominen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Control of Autumn Senescence in European Aspen</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>149</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1982</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.108.133249">10.1104/pp.108.133249</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 19201914?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19201914</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref075">
        <label>75</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furnier</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klevorn</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Photoperiodic responses of a northern and southern ecotype of black cottonwood</article-title>. <source>Physiologia Plantarum</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>695</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>708</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref076">
        <label>76</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Whitlock</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolutionary inference from Q(ST)</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1885</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2008.03712.x">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2008.03712.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18363667?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18363667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref077">
        <label>77</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lef&#xE8;vre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bontemps</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Courbet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durand-Gillmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Considering evolutionary processes in adaptive forestry</article-title>. <source>Annals of Forest Science</source>. <year>2013</year>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref078">
        <label>78</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whitlock</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assisted Gene Flow to Facilitate Local Adaptation to Climate Change</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Ecology, Evolution, and Systematics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>367</fpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref079">
        <label>79</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanchuk</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holowachuk</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ecotypic mode of regional differentiation caused by restricted gene migration: a case in black cottonwood (Populus trichocarpa) along the Pacific Northwest coast</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Forest Research</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>519</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref080">
        <label>80</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McKown</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Azam</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drewes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quamme</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Seasonality and phenology alter functional leaf traits</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>172</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>653</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>65</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00442-012-2531-5">10.1007/s00442-012-2531-5</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23212534?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23212534</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref081">
        <label>81</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Porth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>El-Kassaby</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assessment of the Genetic Diversity in Forest Tree Populations Using Molecular Markers</article-title>. <source>Diversity</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>283</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref082">
        <label>82</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jombart</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>adegenet: a R package for the multivariate analysis of genetic markers</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1403</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btn129">10.1093/bioinformatics/btn129</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18397895?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18397895</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref083">
        <label>83</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schnute</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boers</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haigh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>PBS mapping 2: User's guide&#x2014;Introduction</article-title>. <source>Canadian Technical Report of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>2549</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>V</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref084">
        <label>84</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>PAP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Notes on continuous stochastic phenomena</article-title>. <source>Biometrika</source>. <year>1950</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>1&#x2013;2</issue>):<fpage>17</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15420245?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15420245</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref085">
        <label>85</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bivand R. Spdep: spatial dependence: weighting schemes, statistics and models. R package version 0.5&#x2013;77, Available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cran.r-project.org/src/constrib/Descriptions/spdep.html">http://cran.r-project.org/src/constrib/Descriptions/spdep.html</ext-link>. 2014.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref086">
        <label>86</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Novembre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eskin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Halperin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>A model-based approach for analysis of spatial structure in genetic data</article-title>. <source>Nature Genetics</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>725</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng.2285">10.1038/ng.2285</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22610118?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22610118</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref087">
        <label>87</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spittlehouse</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murdock</surname><given-names>TQ</given-names></name>. <article-title>ClimateWNA-High-Resolution Spatial Climate Data for Western North America</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Meteorology and Climatology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>16</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref088">
        <label>88</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Di Giuseppe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jona Lasinio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pasqui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Functional clustering for Italian climate zones identification</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Climatology</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>1&#x2013;2</issue>):<fpage>39</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref089">
        <label>89</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saether</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fiske</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kalas</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuresoo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luigujoe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piertney</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Inferring local adaptation from Q(ST)-F-ST comparisons: neutral genetic and quantitative trait variation in European populations of great snipe</article-title>. <source>Journal of Evolutionary Biology</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1563</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17584249?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17584249</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref090">
        <label>90</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>. <source>Applications of Linear Models in Animal Breeding</source>. <publisher-loc>Guelph, ON</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Guelph</publisher-name>; <year>1984</year><fpage>423</fpage> p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref091">
        <label>91</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>VanRaden</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Efficient Methods to Compute Genomic Predictions</article-title>. <source>Journal of Dairy Science</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>4414</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3168/jds.2007-0980">10.3168/jds.2007-0980</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18946147?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18946147</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref092">
        <label>92</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wimmer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Auinger</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#xF6;n</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>. <article-title>synbreed: a framework for the analysis of genomic prediction data using R</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>2086</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bts335">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts335</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22689388?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22689388</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref093">
        <label>93</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Latta</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Adaptive population divergence: markers, QTL and traits</article-title>. <source>Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>285</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref094">
        <label>94</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Gilmour</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gogel</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cullis</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Welham</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <source>ASReml User Guide Release 1.0</source>. <publisher-loc>Hemel Hempstead</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>VSN International Ltd</publisher-name>; <year>2002</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref095">
        <label>95</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Joost</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bonin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bruford</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Despres</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Conord</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Erhardt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A spatial analysis method (SAM) to detect candidate loci for selection: towards a landscape genomics approach to adaptation</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>3955</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>69</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17850556?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17850556</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref096">
        <label>96</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lind</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ingvarsson</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gene flow and selection on phenotypic plasticity in an island system of rana temporaria</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>684</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01122.x">10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01122.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 20825480?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20825480</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref097">
        <label>97</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewontin</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krakauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Distribution of gene frequency as a test of theory of selective neutrality of polymorphisms</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>1973</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>175</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>95</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 4711903?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4711903</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref098">
        <label>98</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Whitlock</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guillaume</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Testing for Spatially Divergent Selection: Comparing Q(ST) to F-ST</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>183</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1055</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>63</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1534/genetics.108.099812">10.1534/genetics.108.099812</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 19687138?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19687138</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0142864.ref099">
        <label>99</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Geraldes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thiessen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cezard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>SNP discovery in black cottonwood (Populus trichocarpa) by population transcriptome resequencing</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Resources</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>92</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1755-0998.2010.02960.x">10.1111/j.1755-0998.2010.02960.x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 21429165?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21429165</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
