<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4860416</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.00612</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Plant Science</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Original Research</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Heterologous Overexpression of Poplar <italic>SnRK2</italic> Genes Enhanced Salt Stress Tolerance in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Song</surname>
            <given-names>Xueqing</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>Xiang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hori</surname>
            <given-names>Chiaki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/328477/overview"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Demura</surname>
            <given-names>Taku</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/36066/overview"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ohtani</surname>
            <given-names>Misato</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
          <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/212883/overview"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhuge</surname>
            <given-names>Qiang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
          <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/326943/overview"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <sup>1</sup>
        <institution>Key Laboratory of Forest Genetics and Biotechnology, Co-Innovation Center for Sustainable Forestry in Southern China, Ministry of Education, Nanjing Forestry University</institution>
        <country>Nanjing, China</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <sup>2</sup>
        <institution>Biomass Engineering Program Cooperation Division, RIKEN Center for Sustainable Resource Science</institution>
        <country>Yokohama, Japan</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <sup>3</sup>
        <institution>Graduate School of Biological Sciences, Nara Institute of Science and Technology</institution>
        <country>Ikoma, Japan</country>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Edited by: Heribert Hirt, Center for Desert Agriculture, Saudi Arabia</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Reviewed by: Lei Wang, Institute of Botany-The Chinese Academy of Sciences, China; Jinpeng Gao, Washiton State University, USA</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Misato Ohtani <email xlink:type="simple">misato@bs.naist.jp</email>;</corresp>
        <corresp id="fn002">Qiang Zhuge <email xlink:type="simple">qzhuge@njfu.edu.cn</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn003">
          <p>This article was submitted to Plant Physiology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <elocation-id>612</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2016 Song, Yu, Hori, Demura, Ohtani and Zhuge.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Song, Yu, Hori, Demura, Ohtani and Zhuge</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Subfamily 2 of SNF1-related protein kinase (SnRK2) plays important roles in plant abiotic stress responses as a global positive regulator of abscisic acid signaling. In the genome of the model tree <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic>, 12 <italic>SnRK2</italic> genes have been identified, and some are upregulated by abiotic stresses. In this study, we heterologously overexpressed the <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and found that overexpression of <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> genes enhanced stress tolerance. In the <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressors, chlorophyll content, and root elongation were maintained under salt stress conditions, leading to higher survival rates under salt stress compared with those in the wild type. Transcriptomic analysis revealed that <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpression affected stress-related metabolic genes, including lipid metabolism and flavonoid metabolism, even under normal growth conditions. However, the stress response genes reported to be upregulated in Arabidopsis <italic>SRK2C/SnRK2.6</italic> and wheat <italic>SnRK2.8</italic> overexpressors were not changed by <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpression. Furthermore, <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpression widely and largely influenced the transcriptome in response to salt stress; genes related to transport activity, including anion transport-related genes, were characteristically upregulated, and a variety of metabolic genes were specifically downregulated. We also found that the salt stress response genes were greatly upregulated in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor. Taken together, poplar subclass 2 <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes can modulate salt stress tolerance in Arabidopsis, through the activation of cellular signaling pathways in a different manner from that by herbal subclass 2 <italic>SnRK2</italic> genes.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>
          <italic>SnRK2</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>overexpression</kwd>
        <kwd>salt stress</kwd>
        <kwd>transport</kwd>
        <kwd>metabolism</kwd>
        <kwd>salt tolerance</kwd>
        <kwd>poplar</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="5"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <equation-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="50"/>
        <page-count count="11"/>
        <word-count count="7119"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Plants face various environmental stresses including drought, high salinity, and extreme temperatures. Such adverse circumstances can often lead to severe agricultural and industrial losses, so it is important to understand the molecular and physiological mechanisms that plants use to cope with abiotic stresses for further stable production of crops and biomass feedstock. Many studies have indicated that regulatory factors of protein phosphorylation play essential roles in response to environmental stimuli (Sopory and Munshi, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Umezawa et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). One of the well-characterized protein kinases involved in stress responses is the group of sucrose non-fermenting 1 (SNF1)-related protein kinases (SnRKs; Halford and Hey, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). SnRKs are grouped into three subfamilies, SnRK1, SnRK2, and SnRK3 (Halford and Hey, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), and recent studies have indicated pivotal roles of plant-specific subgroups of SnRK2 and SnRK3 in the link between abiotic stress and abscisic acid (ABA) signaling to regulate metabolic pathways (Hrabak et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Halford and Hey, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Increasing evidence shows that SnRK2 proteins function as positive regulators of ABA signaling for stress responses, as well as development, in plants (Umezawa et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (Arabidopsis) and rice, the SnRK2 family includes 10 members, such as SRK2A-SRK2J or SnRK2.1&#x2013;2.10 in Arabidopsis and SAPK1-10 in rice (Yoshida et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Hrabak et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Kobayashi et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>), and they are further classified into three subclasses based on their domain structures (Kobayashi et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Most SnRK2 proteins are activated by abiotic stresses, while the members of subclasses 2 and 3 are also activated by ABA (Boudsocq et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Kobayashi et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). In the current model, ABA-induced activation is largely explained by the interaction between SnRK2s and protein phosphatase type 2C (PP2C) proteins in the ABA signaling pathway (Leung et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>; Meyer et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; Saez et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Nishimura et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Umezawa et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Cutler et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Ng et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In the absence of ABA, group A PP2Cs physically bind to SnRK2s to dephosphorylate SnRK2s, resulting in the inhibition of ABA signal transduction, while in the presence of ABA, SnRK2 will be released from such inhibitory regulation by PP2C, because the soluble ABA receptor PYR/PYL/RCAR inhibits PP2C activity (Umezawa et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Vlad et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p>
      <p>In Arabidopsis, detailed analyses of subclass 2 (SRK2F/SnRK2.7 and SRK2C/SnRK2.8) and subclass 3 (SRK2D/SnRK2.2, SRK2I/SnRK2.3, and SRK2E/SnRK2.6) have revealed their redundant functions in ABA signaling for abiotic stress responses and developmental controls (Yoshida et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Fujii et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Fujii and Zhu, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Fujita et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Nakashima et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Mizoguchi et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Importantly, overexpression of <italic>SnRK2</italic> genes resulted in enhanced abiotic stress tolerance in Arabidopsis (AtSRK2C/SnRK2.8, Umezawa et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; TaSnRK2.3, TaSnRK2.4, TaSnRK2.7, and TaSnRK2.8, Mao et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Tian et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) and in rice (SAPK4; Di&#xE9;dhiou et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Overexpression of <italic>SnRK2</italic> genes in Arabidopsis induced the upregulation of several important stress responsive genes, including RD29A and DREB1A/CBF3, and ABA biosynthetic genes, such as ABA1, under normal conditions (Umezawa et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), suggesting that early and quick stress responses supported by the expression of such key genes may enhance stress tolerance in Arabidopsis. The rice <italic>SAPK4</italic> overexpressor showed increased salt tolerance, and major aspects of its tolerance were explained by changes in the expression of genes related to ion homeostasis and oxidative stress responses (Di&#xE9;dhiou et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). In the cases of SnRK2 overexpressors, the results clearly indicated that SnRK2 can function in abiotic stress responses in plant cells, through the modulation of stress response-related gene expression.</p>
      <p>Comparative genomics studies have demonstrated that the core components of ABA signaling, PYR/PYL/RCAR, SnRK2, and PP2C, are well-conserved in land plant species (Umezawa et al., <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), suggesting the evolutionary conservation of a molecular system involving these proteins in land plants. Indeed, the conserved molecular characteristics of SnRK2, such as transcriptional induction by abiotic stresses and activation by stress and/or ABA, have been reported for SnRK2 genes not only in Arabidopsis and rice, but also in other crop plants: maize (Huai et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Vilela et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) and wheat (Holappa and Walker-Simmons, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>; G&#xF3;mez-Cadenas et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Mao et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Tian et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Additionally, we recently confirmed the physical interaction between SnRK2 and PP2C in a model tree <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic> (poplar), and proposed the possibility that a similar molecular module containing SnRK2 and PP2C is involved in the ABA signaling pathway in trees (Song et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). However, information about the molecular functions of the poplar SnRK2 proteins is still limited. Recently, we evaluated the transcriptional regulation of <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes and found that some of them are upregulated by abiotic stresses in organ-specific manners, suggesting the involvement of PtSnRK2 in ABA-dependent and/or ABA-independent regulation of stress responses (Yu et al., unpublished data.).</p>
      <p>In this study, to obtain further clues as to the molecular functions of PtSnRK2 proteins, we heterologously overexpressed the <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes in Arabidopsis. Our data indicated that poplar subclass II <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes can enhance the salt stress tolerance of Arabidopsis, and that poplar <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> overexpression would activate cellular signaling and stress response pathways in Arabidopsis in a different manner than that by the herbal subclass II <italic>SnRK2</italic> genes.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Plant materials and growth conditions</title>
        <p>Young shoots of black cottonwood, <italic>P. trichocarpa</italic> Torr. &amp; A. Gray (poplar), grown in 15-cm-high plant pots, were used for the cloning of <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> cDNA. For the overexpression analysis, <italic>A. thaliana</italic> (Arabidopsis) plants (Columbia strain) were used. The growth conditions were described in Ohtani et al. (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) for poplar and in Ohtani et al. (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) for Arabidopsis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Plasmid construction and transformation</title>
        <p>The coding sequences of <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes were cloned into the Gateway entry vector pENTR/D-TOPO or pCR8/GW/TOPO (Invitrogen), as described by Song et al. (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>), and were transferred to the destination vector pH35GS (Kubo et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) by the LR reaction using LR clonase II (Invitrogen). In the resulting plasmids, the <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> cDNA was expressed under the control of the cauliflower mosaic virus (CaMV) 35S promoter. The plasmids were electroporated into the <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain GV3101 (pMP90). A simplified version of the floral dip method was used for the transformation of Arabidopsis plants (Clough and Bent, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Establishment of transgenic lines</title>
        <p>For the screening of transgenic lines carrying the empty vector (vector controls) and <italic>35S::PtSnRK2</italic> (<italic>PtSnRK2</italic> overexpressors), T<sub>1</sub> seedlings were grown in germination Murashige and Skoog (MS) medium containing 50 &#x3BC;g mL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> hygromycin for 2 weeks, and the positive plants were transferred to soil for further growth. Although we failed to generate overexpressors of <italic>PtSnRK2.2, PtSnRK2.6</italic>, and <italic>PtSnRK2.8</italic>, more than 16 independent T<sub>2</sub> lines were established for every other <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes.</p>
        <p>To evaluate the expression levels of the introduced <italic>PtSnRK2</italic>, total RNAs were prepared from 7-day-old seedlings of the wild type, vector controls, and <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> overexpressors at the T<sub>2</sub> generation using the RNeasy Mini kit (Qiagen). The first-strand cDNAs were synthesized using SuperScript III (Invitrogen) and subjected to RT-PCR analysis. The RT reaction was performed on a 20-&#x3BC;L scale, with 1 &#x3BC;L first-strand cDNA as a template for PCR, along with 0.5 &#x3BC;M of each gene-specific primer (see Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">S2</xref>) and Ex Taq polymerase (TaKaRa). The PCR conditions were as follows: for the internal control gene <italic>Ubp10</italic>, 95&#xB0;C for 5 min, followed by 35 cycles of 94&#xB0;C for 20 s, 60&#xB0;C for 30 s, and 72&#xB0;C for 15 s, followed by 72&#xB0;C for 7 min; for <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes (target genes), 95&#xB0;C for 5 min, followed by 35 cycles of 94&#xB0;C for 20 s, 60&#xB0;C for 30 s, and 72&#xB0;C for 1 min 15 s, and followed by 72&#xB0;C for 7 min. The amplified PCR products were electrophoresed in 3 and 2% (w/v) agarose gels for the <italic>Ubp10</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes, respectively, and gel images were analyzed using the AE-9020 E-shot II (ATTO; Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>). Information about the primer sets is provided in Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM13">S11</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Salt stress treatment</title>
        <p>It is generally known that the expression level of <italic>35S</italic> promoter-driven genes would be decreased in T<sub>3</sub> homozygous lines, so we decided to use T<sub>2</sub> lines that were confirmed to show high expression levels of inserted <italic>PtSnRK</italic> genes as described above, for the salt stress treatment. Wild-type and transgenic T<sub>2</sub> plants were grown at 22&#xB0;C under LD conditions (16 h light/8 h dark) on 1/2-strength MS medium, after incubation at 4&#xB0;C for 3 days. Then, 7-day-old plants were transferred to 1/2-MS medium plates with or without NaCl. For the survival rates and chlorophyll contents, 200 mM NaCl was included in the medium, and for the root growth phenotype, 100 mM NaCl was used. After an additional 4-day incubation, the numbers of surviving seedlings were counted to obtain survival rates (<italic>n</italic> = 20), and chlorophyll contents were measured as described below (<italic>n</italic> = 10). The primary root length was measured before and after a 5-day incubation on the NaCl plate, to calculate primary root elongation during salt stress treatment (<italic>n</italic> = 10). The treatments were repeated three times for survival rates and root length and six times for chlorophyll contents.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Chlorophyll quantitation</title>
        <p>Ten seedlings treated with 200 mM NaCl for 4 days were sampled in 3 mL (<italic>N,N</italic>-dimethylformamide, DMF). After incubation in DMF overnight at 4&#xB0;C in the dark, A<sub>646.8</sub>, A<sub>663.8</sub>, and A<sub>750</sub> were measured using the iMark Microplate Absorbance Reader (Bio-Rad). The chlorophyll quantitation was calculated by the formula:</p>
        <p>[8.05 &#xD7; (A<sub>663.8</sub>-A<sub>750</sub>) + 19.43 &#xD7; (A<sub>646.8</sub>-A<sub>750</sub>) (&#x3BC;M) / the quantity of seedlings (mg)] (&#x3BC;M/mg) (Porra et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title><italic>In silico</italic> prediction of the three-dimensional structures of PtSnRK2 proteins</title>
        <p>The amino acid sequences of PtSnRK2.5, PtSnRK2.7, and PtSnRK2.9 were submitted to the web-based SWISS-MODEL service (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://swissmodel.expasy.org/workspace/">http://swissmodel.expasy.org/workspace/</ext-link>; Arnold et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>), to build protein structure homology models using information on the crystal structure of the recombinant AtSnRK2.6 protein as a template (Ng et al., <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Microarray analysis</title>
        <p>Seedlings of the wild-type and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor line 20 treated with or without 200 mM NaCl for 2 days were sampled for total RNA extraction. Microarray analysis was performed using ATH1 GeneChips (Affymetrix) according to the manufacturer's instructions on three independent biological replicates. Subsequent procedures of quality control, statistical analysis, and filtering were carried out using GeneSpring GX software (ver. 13.1; Agilent Technologies). Then, <italic>p</italic>-values were calculated for each probe using Welch's <italic>t</italic>-test (n = 3) for differences between the treated seedlings and the control seedlings, as well as between the wild-type and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor incubated without salt treatment. We used the Benjamin-Hochberg FDR method to control for false positives. A <italic>p</italic>-value cut-off of 0.01 was used to select genes whose expression changed with salt treatment. Fold-change values were also computed using GeneSpring GX, and we targeted those probes in which the change was upregulated or downregulated by more than 3-fold. Microarray data presented in this study were submitted to NCBI GEO (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>) and can be retrieved via accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="GSE79997">GSE79997</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Gene ontology (GO) term analysis</title>
        <p>Gene ontology (GO) term analysis was performed using the PANTHER classification system (Overrepresentation Test, release 20150430; Mi et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Quantitative RT-PCR analysis</title>
        <p>To evaluate the enhanced upregulation of salt stress response genes in <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressors, quantitative RT-PCR analysis was performed. Total RNAs were isolated from the seedlings treated with or without 200 mM NaCl for 2 days using Plant RNA Isolation Reagent (Invitrogen) and then purified using the RNeasy Mini Kit (QIAGEN). The first-strand cDNAs were synthesized as described above, and aliquots of the cDNA solution (0.5 &#x3BC;L for each gene) were used as templates for subsequent PCR amplification. The quantitative PCR analysis was performed using the LightCycler 480 System II (Roche) and LightCycler 480 SYBR Green I Master reagents (Roche). As an internal control, the <italic>Ubc9</italic> gene was used. Information on the primer sets is provided in Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM13">S11</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Overexpression of <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> improved salt stress tolerance in Arabidopsis</title>
        <p>In the genome of <italic>P. trichocarpa</italic> (poplar), 12 PtSnRK2 genes have been identified (Song et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). For molecular functional analysis of PtSnRK2, we generated transgenic plants of <italic>A. thaliana</italic> (Arabidopsis) carrying the chimeric gene <italic>35S::PtSnRK2</italic>, in which the cDNA regions of <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes were regulated by the CaMV 35S promoter sequence, to overexpress poplar <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes in Arabidopsis. Unfortunately we could not obtain transgenic plants for <italic>PtSnRK2.2, PtSnRK2.6</italic>, and <italic>PtSnRK2.8</italic> overexpression; however, overexpressors of the other nine <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes were established successfully. It has been reported that overexpression of SnRK2 genes enhances abiotic stress tolerance (Umezawa et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Di&#xE9;dhiou et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Mao et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Tian et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Thus, we examined salt stress tolerance in the <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> overexpressors.</p>
        <p>First, 7-day-old seedlings from 16 independent T<sub>2</sub> lines for each <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> overexpressor were transferred to medium containing 200 mM NaCl, and incubated for 4 days. The <italic>prr9-11 prr7-10 prr5-10</italic> triple mutant (d975) plant, which showed high salinity tolerance because of high expression of salt stress response genes (Nakamichi et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), was used as a positive control (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). The survival rates of seedlings after salt treatment demonstrated that the overexpressors of <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> showed relatively high survival rates among the <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> overexpressors. These two genes encode the subclass 2 PtSnRK2 proteins (Song et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). We further performed a detailed analysis of salt stress tolerance in the <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressors, using the wild-type and vector control plants as negative controls (<bold>Figures 2</bold>, <bold>3</bold>). For the <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressors, three independent lines were selected based on the expression levels of the introduced <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>). In the case of the negative controls, the seedling survival rates after 200 mM NaCl treatment were less than 20%, and the living seedlings exhibited yellowed leaves (<bold>Figure 2</bold>). In contrast, the <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> transgenic seedlings showed significantly higher survival rates (~55%) than those of the controls (<bold>Figure 2</bold>). All three independent <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> lines showed increased survival rates, whereas the <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> line 6 did not show a significantly enhanced survival rate (<bold>Figure 2B</bold>).</p>
        <p>Next, the chlorophyll contents of 10 seedlings treated with salt stress were analyzed. The salt treatment greatly decreased chlorophyll contents in all plants; however, the chlorophyll contents of <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> lines 16 and 20, and all of the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> lines were significantly higher than those of the wild-type and vector control (<bold>Figure 2C</bold>), in accordance with the survival rates. These results suggested that salt stress tolerance was more stable in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressors. Moreover, it was notable that although the chlorophyll contents in the absence of salt stress were at almost the same levels among the wild-type, vector control, and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> lines, but the <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> lines 16 and 20 showed lower amounts of chlorophyll under normal growth conditions (<bold>Figure 2C</bold>). Thus, <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> overexpression may have affected chlorophyll biosynthesis continuously.</p>
        <p>In addition to the increased survival rates and chlorophyll contents, the living seedlings of the <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> transgenic lines seemed to be larger than those of the negative controls under salt stress conditions (<bold>Figure 2A</bold>). To clarify the effects of <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> overexpression on seedling growth, we checked the growth of primary roots after salt treatment. Because the 200 mM NaCl treatment almost completely inhibited primary root elongation in both the overexpressors and negative controls, we used 100 mM NaCl conditions to observe primary root elongation. Our data demonstrated no difference in primary root elongation in the mock-treated seedlings (<bold>Figure 3</bold>), indicating that these two <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes are not involved in root elongation regulation, unlike the Arabidopsis subclass II <italic>AtSRK2C/SnRK2.8</italic> gene, overexpression of which was reported to enhance seedling root growth (Shin et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). However, after a 5-day incubation with 100 mM NaCl, the primary roots of <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> line 20 and all of the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> lines elongated significantly more than did those of the negative controls; the negative controls showed elongation of less than 20 mm, whereas the elongated lengths of <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> line 20 and all of the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> lines were ~25 mm (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, <italic>t</italic>-test). These observations indicated that overexpression of <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic>, and possibly also <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic>, can suppress the inhibition of root elongation by high salinity stress.</p>
        <p>Our data on the <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> transgenic lines demonstrated different phenotypic characteristics between the <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> lines. Thus, it was suspected that the molecular basis for the enhancement of salt stress tolerance would be different between the <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> transgenic lines. In particular, the <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> lines showed unstable salt stress tolerance (<bold>Figures 2</bold>, <bold>3</bold>) and defects in chlorophyll content even under normal growth condition (<bold>Figure 2C</bold>). The subclass 2 PtSnRK2 proteins have highly similar amino acid sequences (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>), and the amino acid sequences of PtSnRK2.5 (unstable, but significantly enhanced salinity tolerance), PtSnRK2.7 (stable and high tolerance), and PtSnRK2.9 (no obviously increased tolerance) did not show major differences between them (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). <italic>In silico</italic> modeling of the three-dimensional structures of these proteins, based on the crystal structure of AtSnRK2.6 (Ng et al., <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), revealed that some of the differences in amino acid sequences among these PtSnRK2 proteins could correspond to the molecular surface regions of these proteins (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>), possibly leading to changes in the molecular activities of the SnRK2 proteins. The different SnRK2 protein activities due to subtle substitutions of amino acids could result in the different strengths of salt stress tolerance among the overexpressors.</p>
        <fig id="F1" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>SnRK2 proteins of <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic> (poplar, Pt), and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (Arabidopsis, At)</bold>. <bold>(A)</bold> Amino acid sequence alignment of subclass 2 PtSnRK2 proteins with AtSnRK2.8. The residues putatively corresponding to the &#x3B1;-helix, &#x3B2;-sheet, PP2C-interaction residues, and the entire ABA box are marked by bars, arrows, asterisks, and the box, respectively. <bold>(B)</bold><italic>In silico</italic> modeling of the three-dimensional structures of PtSnRK2.5, PtSnRK2.7, and PtSnRK2.9 proteins. Homology modeling was performed based on the crystal structure of AtSnRK2.6 using the web-based SWISS-MODEL service (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://swissmodel.expasy.org/workspace/">http://swissmodel.expasy.org/workspace/</ext-link>; Arnold et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Thick and narrow arrows indicate regions presumed to differ in their three-dimensional architecture among the PtSnRK2 proteins because of differences in amino acid sequences.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-00612-g0001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title><italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpression widely and largely influenced the transcriptome in response to salt stress</title>
        <p>We next performed transcriptomic analyses of the wild-type and overexpressors during salt stress treatment. Based on the data described above (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), we selected <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> line 20, which showed stable and strong salt stress tolerance among the transgenic lines, for the gene chip analysis. Then, 7-day-old seedlings of the wild-type and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> line 20 were treated with or without 200 mM NaCl for 2 days and then sampled to extract total RNA. The extracted total RNA samples were subjected to microarray analysis using Affymetrix ATH1 GeneChips (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). First, we compared transcriptomic data between the wild-type and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor, which were mock-treated, to examine the effects of <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpression on gene expression under normal growth conditions. Thirty and 79 genes were shown to be upregulated and downregulated in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor, respectively (FC &gt; 2, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S1</xref>). It has been reported that in AtSRK2C/SnRK2.6 and TaSnRK2.8 overexpressors, stress response-related genes including RD29A and DREB1A/CBF3, and ABA biosynthetic genes are upregulated continuously (Umezawa et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). However, these genes were not changed by <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpression (Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S1</xref>). The gene ontology (GO) term analysis revealed that stress-related metabolic genes, including lipid metabolism and flavonoid metabolism, were significantly downregulated in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). These results suggest that <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpression could continuously affect specific ranges of gene expression regulation, which do not overlap with the primary targets of AtSRK2C/SnRK2.6 and TaSnRK2.8 in Arabidopsis.</p>
        <fig id="F2" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>High salinity tolerance phenotype of transgenic Arabidopsis overexpressing <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK7</italic></bold>. <bold>(A)</bold> Seedlings of the wild-type, vector control, and overexpressors of <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> treated with 200 mM NaCl for 4 days. <bold>(B)</bold> Survival rates determined by observations after a 4-day salt stress treatment. The green seedlings were counted as living seedlings, and the percentages of live seedlings were calculated using 20 seedlings for each line. <bold>(C)</bold> Chlorophyll contents determined from 20 seedlings after a 4-day salt stress treatment. Results are means &#xB1; SE (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences between transgenic and wild-type plants (Student's <italic>t</italic>-test; <sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; <sup>**</sup><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-00612-g0002"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F3" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Primary root elongation of transgenic Arabidopsis overexpressing <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> during salt treatment</bold>. <bold>(A)</bold> Seedlings of the wild-type, vector control, and overexpressors of <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> treated with 100 mM NaCl for 5 days. The positions of the edges of the root tips before salt treatment are indicated by the white dotted lines. Bar = 20 mm. <bold>(B)</bold> Increase in root length after salt stress treatment. Results are means &#xB1; SE (<italic>n</italic> = 15). Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences between transgenic plants and the wild-type (Student's <italic>t</italic>-test; <sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; <sup>**</sup><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-00612-g0003"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F4" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Microarray analysis of the wild-type and PtSnRK2.7 overexpressor line 20</bold>. <bold>(A)</bold> Overview of sample preparation for microarray analysis. <bold>(B)</bold> Venn diagram of upregulated and downregulated genes after salt stress treatment in the wild-type and PtSnRK2.7 overexpressor.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-00612-g0004"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>GO term analysis of the differentially expressed genes between the wild-type and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor grown in the absence of salt stress treatment</bold>.</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>GO biological process complete</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Fold Enrichment</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold><italic>p</italic>-value</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthocyanin-containing compound biosynthetic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.44</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.52E-03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthocyanin-containing compound metabolic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.00</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.29E-03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular response to phosphate starvation</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12E-09</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Galactolipid biosynthetic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.61E-07</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Galactolipid metabolic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.61E-07</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycolipid biosynthetic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.57</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06E-06</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavonoid biosynthetic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.09</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69E-04</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavonoid metabolic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.00</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.11E-04</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liposaccharide metabolic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.53</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.26E-06</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycolipid metabolic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.53</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.26E-06</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Membrane lipid biosynthetic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.22</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.69E-06</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to UV-B</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.83</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.49E-03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular response to starvation</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.18</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.92E-09</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular response to nutrient levels</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.65</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.89E-09</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Membrane lipid metabolic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.39</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.15E-05</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to starvation</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.39</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08E-08</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular response to extracellular stimulus</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.88</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88E-09</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular response to external stimulus</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.67</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26E-09</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to nutrient levels</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.67</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82E-08</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to extracellular stimulus</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.05</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73E-09</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pigment biosynthetic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.73</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65E-03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pigment metabolic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.94</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.65E-03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative regulation of transcription, DNA-templated</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.43</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85E-02</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative regulation of RNA biosynthetic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.43</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.94E-02</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative regulation of nucleic acid-templated transcription</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.43</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.94E-02</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative regulation of RNA metabolic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.43</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.03E-02</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular response to stress</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.62</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09E-04</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to external stimulus</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.65</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57E-03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single-organism biosynthetic process</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.83E-03</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>To examine the impact of <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpression on the salt stress response, the genes upregulated or downregulated by salt treatment were compared between the wild-type and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor. In the wild-type, 337 and 120 genes were upregulated and downregulated by salt treatment, respectively (FC &gt; 3, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref> and Tables <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">S3</xref>). Notably, the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor showed greater numbers of genes whose expression was changed by salt treatment compared with the wild-type; 631 and 698 genes were upregulated and downregulated in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor, respectively (FC &gt; 3, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref> and Tables <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">S4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM7">S5</xref>), suggesting that <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpression affected the expression of a wide range of genes during salt stress responses in Arabidopsis. The GO analysis indicated that the genes functioning in stress responses, including the signaling pathway of stress-related phytohormones (ABA, ethylene, jasmonic acid, and salicylic acid) and in signal transduction by protein phosphorylation, were commonly upregulated between the wild-type and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref> and Tables <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM8">S6</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM10">S8</xref>). Additionally, developmental process-related genes were commonly downregulated in the wild-type and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM12">S10</xref>).</p>
        <p>We also found that some GO terms were enriched in the upregulated genes in genotype-dependent manners, such as &#x201C;respiratory burst&#x201D; and &#x201C;ethylene biosynthetic process&#x201D; found only in the wild-type (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM8">S6</xref>) and &#x201C;purine nucleoside transmembrane transport,&#x201D; &#x201C;amino acid transport,&#x201D; &#x201C;anion transmembrane transport,&#x201D; and &#x201C;nucleic acid metabolic process&#x201D; found only in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM9">S7</xref>). The overrepresentation of the GO terms related to &#x201C;anion transmembrane transport&#x201D; in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor would suggest the enhancement of ion homeostasis activity as a result of <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpression, possibly leading to higher salt stress tolerance. Our results also showed wild-type-specific enrichment of the term &#x201C;ethylene biosynthetic process&#x201D; in upregulated genes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM8">S6</xref>). It has been reported that crosstalk between ABA and ethylene is a critical factor in determining salt stress tolerance in Arabidopsis (Dong et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>); thus, <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpression may influence the phytohormonal modulating system of abiotic stress responses. Moreover, in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor, more than 5-fold more genes were downregulated by salt treatment than those in the wild type. These downregulated genes are involved in a wide range of molecular functions, including metabolic regulation and responses to stimuli (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM11">S9</xref>), indicating that the reason for the high salt stress tolerance in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor may be, at least partially, attributed to its significant impact on metabolic regulation.</p>
        <p>Comparison of transcriptomic data also suggested that the altered expression levels of upregulated genes were greater in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor than in the wild-type (Tables <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">S4</xref>). To confirm this, we selected six genes from the functional categories of stress response (<italic>COR15A</italic>, Artus et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>), phytohormonal signaling (<italic>GASA3</italic>, Herzog et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>), cell wall-related proteins (<italic>AT1G52690</italic> and <italic>AtCWINV5</italic>, Sherson et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>), and lipid metabolism (<italic>AT4G33550</italic>), based on the transcriptomic data, and subjected them to quantitative RT-PCR analysis. <italic>AT4G18280</italic>, which was upregulated only in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor, was also tested to evaluate the consistency of the results between the gene chip analysis and quantitative RT-PCR analysis. Indeed, <italic>AT4G18280</italic> expression was not induced by salt stress in the wild-type or vector control, whereas it was highly upregulated in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> line 20 in accordance to the results of gene chip analysis (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">S4</xref>). The results showed that the tested genes were actively upregulated by salt treatment in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressors compared with the wild-type and vector control (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Our data also demonstrated that <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> overexpression had similar effects on the expression of these genes. Thus, it is supposed that <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> overexpression affected the transcriptome in a similar fashion to <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpression.</p>
        <fig id="F5" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Quantitative RT-PCR analysis of transcript levels of COR15A, GASA3, At4G33550, AtCWINV5, <italic>At1G52690</italic>, and <italic>At4G18280</italic> in the wild-type, vector control, and overexpressors of <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic></bold>. Seedlings treated with or without 200 mM NaCl for 2 days were analyzed. Results are means &#xB1; SE (<italic>n</italic> = 3).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-00612-g0005"/>
        </fig>
        <p>It has been reported that the overexpression of Arabidopsis <italic>AtSnRK2.8</italic> enhanced the stress tolerance of Arabidopsis, probably through the continuous upregulation of key genes for stress responses, such as <italic>RD29A, COR15A, AtGolS3, DREB1A</italic>, and <italic>PKS18</italic> (Umezawa et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). However, our results showed that overexpression of poplar <italic>SnRK2</italic> genes did not constitutively induce these well-known stress responsive genes. Rather, the high salt stress tolerance of the <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> overexpressors may be explained by changes in transcriptomic regulation for a wide range of metabolic regulatory genes (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> and Tables <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S1</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM12">S10</xref>). It is notable that the genes related to anion transport activity were upregulated in the <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic> overexpressor specifically, because similar effects on ion homeostasis-related genes were reported in the case of overexpression of rice <italic>SAPK4</italic> (Di&#xE9;dhiou et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Moreover, a comparative transcriptomic analysis using salt-tolerant and non-tolerant species of poplar indicated that prominent factors for high salt tolerance were not overexpression of the stress responsive pathway, but rather enhanced activities for osmotic adjustment, ion compartmentalization, and detoxification of reactive oxygen species in poplar (Chen and Polle, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Thus, our results may reflect differences in the regulatory targets of SnRK2 proteins between AtSnRK2 and PtSnRK2, which could be related to diversified molecular strategies of stress adaption in each plant species, as suggested by Zhang et al. (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Future comparative analyses on the mode of actions of SnRK2 proteins derived from different plant species may provide important information on novel strategies to improve stress tolerance of crops and other useful plants.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Author contributions</title>
      <p>XS designed and performed the experiments, and drafted the manuscript. MO designed the experiments, analyzed the data, and wrote the manuscript. XY and CH contributed to the data analysis. QZ and TD drafted the manuscript. All authors contributed to and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      <sec>
        <title>Conflict of interest statement</title>
        <p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Ms. Ayumi Ihara, Ms. Arika Takebayashi and Ms. Rokyo Hiroyama (RIKEN) for their technical assistance. This work was supported by the International Science &amp; Technology Cooperation Program of China (2014DFG32440), the National Science Foundation of China (No.31570650), the Priority Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions, the Program for Innovative Research Team in University of Educational Department and Jiangsu Province, China, and the Biomass Engineering Program Cooperation Division, RIKEN Center for Sustainable Resource Science, Japan.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supplementary material</title>
      <p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fpls.2016.00612">http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fpls.2016.00612</ext-link></p>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>RT-PCR analysis of seedlings of the wild-type, vector control, and overexpressors of <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic> and <italic>PtSnRK2.7</italic></bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="Image1.PDF">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Primary screening of transgenic Arabidopsis overexpressing PtSnRK2 genes for the salt tolerance</bold>. Seedlings of the d975 (positive control), vector control, and overexpressors of <italic>PtSnRK2</italic> genes were treated with 200 mM NaCl, and checked their survival rates after 3, 4, and 5 days of NaCl treatment. A part of results for the transgenic lines of <italic>PtSnRK2.5</italic>
<bold>(A)</bold> and <italic>PtSnRK2.9</italic>
<bold>(B)</bold> treated with 200 mM NaCl for 4 days were shown.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="Image2.PDF">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Differentially expressed genes between the wild type and PtSnRK2.7 overexpressor (FC&gt;2, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05)</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="Table1.XLSX">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Upregulated 337 genes in the wild type by the salt treatment (FC&gt;3, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01)</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="Table2.XLSX">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM5">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Downregulated 120 genes in the wild type by the salt treatment (FC&gt;3, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01)</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="Table3.XLSX">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM6">
        <label>Table S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Upregulated 631 genes in the PtSnRK2.7 overexpressor by the salt treatment (FC&gt;3, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01)</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="Table4.XLSX">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM7">
        <label>Table S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Downregulated 698 genes in the PtSnRK2.7 overexpressor by the salt treatment (FC&gt;3, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01)</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="Table5.XLSX">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM8">
        <label>Table S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>GO term analysis on wild-type-specific upregulated genes by salt treatment</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="Table6.XLSX">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM9">
        <label>Table S7</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>GO term analysis on PrSnRK2.7 overexpressor-specific upregulated genes by salt treatment</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="Table7.XLSX">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM10">
        <label>Table S8</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>GO term analysis on commonly upregulated genes between the wild type and PtSnRK2.7 overexpressor by salt treatment</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="Table8.XLSX">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM11">
        <label>Table S9</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>GO term analysis on PrSnRK2.7 overexpressor-specific downregulated genes by salt treatment</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="Table9.XLSX">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM12">
        <label>Table S10</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>GO term analysis on commonly downregulated genes between the wild type and PtSnRK2.7 overexpressor by salt treatment</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="Table10.XLSX">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM13">
        <label>Table S11</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Oligonucleotides used in this paper</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="Table11.XLSX">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bordoli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwede</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The SWISS-MODEL Workspace: a web-based environment for protein structure homology modelling</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>195</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>201</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti770</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16301204?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16301204</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Artus</surname><given-names>N. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steponkus</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilmour</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomashow</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Constitutive expression of the cold-regulated <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> COR15a gene affects both chloroplast and protoplast freezing tolerance</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>93</volume>, <fpage>13404</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>13409</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.93.23.13404</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11038526?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11038526</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boudsocq</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbier-Brygoo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauri&#xE8;re</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Identification of nine sucrose nonfermenting 1-related protein kinases 2 activated by hyperosmotic and saline stesses in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>279</volume>, <fpage>41758</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>41766</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M405259200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15292193?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15292193</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boudsocq</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Droillard</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbier-Brygoo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauri&#xE8;re</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Different phosphorylation mechanisms are involved in the activation of sucrose non-fermenting 1 related protein kinases 2 by osmotic stresses and abscisic acid</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>63</volume>, <fpage>491</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>503</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-006-9103-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17103012?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17103012</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Polle</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Salinity tolerance of <italic>Populus</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Biol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>317</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>333</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1438-8677.2009.00301.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20398238?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20398238</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Floral dip: a simplified method for <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>735</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>743</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.1998.00343.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10069079?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10069079</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Finkelstein</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Abscisic acid: emergence of a core signaling network</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>651</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>679</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042809-112122</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20192755?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20192755</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di&#xE9;dhiou</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Popova</surname><given-names>O. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Golldack</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The SNF1-type serine-threonine protein kinase <italic>SAPK4</italic> regulates stress-responsive gene expression in rice</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-8-49</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18442365?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18442365</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Loss of <italic>ACS7</italic> confers abiotic stress tolerance by modulating ABA sensitivity and accumulation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>4875</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4887</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err143</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21765163?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21765163</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verslues</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Identification of two protein kinases required for abscisic acid regulation of seed germination, root growth, and gene expression in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>485</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>494</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.106.048538</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17307925?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17307925</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Arabidopsis mutant deficient in 3 abscisic acid-activated protein kinases reveals critical roles in growth, reproduction, and stress</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>8380</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8385</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0903144106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19420218?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19420218</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidokoro</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanamori</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Three SnRK2 protein kinases are the main positive regulators of abscisic acid signaling in response to water stress in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><volume>50</volume>, <fpage>2123</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2132</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcp147</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19880399?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19880399</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#xF3;mez-Cadenas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhey</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holappa</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>T. -H. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker-Simmons</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>An abscisic acid-induced protein kinase, PKABA1, mediates abscisic acid-suppressed gene expression in barley aleurone layers</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>96</volume>, <fpage>1767</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1772</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.4.1767</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9990099?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9990099</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halford</surname><given-names>N. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hey</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Snf1-related protein kinases (SnRKs) act within an intricate network that links metabolic and stress signalling in plants</article-title>. <source>Biochem. J.</source>
<volume>419</volume>, <fpage>247</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>259</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20082408</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19309312?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19309312</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorne</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grellet</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>GASA, a gibberellin-regulated gene family from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> related to the tomato GAST1 gene</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>743</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>752</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00020227</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7727751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7727751</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holappa</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker-Simmons</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The wheat abscisic acid-responsive protein kinase mRNA, PKABA1, is up-regulated by dehydration, cold temperature, and osmotic stress</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>1203</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1210</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12228537?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228537</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hrabak</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>C. W. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gribskov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halford</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The Arabidopsis CDPK-SnRK superfamily of protein kinases</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source><volume>132</volume>, <fpage>666</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>680</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.102.011999</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12805596?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12805596</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huai</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Cloning and characterization of the SnRK2 gene family from <italic>Zea mays</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Rep.</source><volume>27</volume>, <fpage>1861</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1868</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-008-0608-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18797872?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18797872</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Minami</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagaya</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Differential activation of the rice sucrose nonfermenting1&#x2013;related protein kinase2 family by hyperosmotic stress and abscisic acid</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>1163</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1177</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.019943</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15084714?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15084714</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Udagawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishikubo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horiguchi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Transcription switches for protoxylem and metaxylem vessel formation</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source><volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1855</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1860</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1331305</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16103214?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16103214</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouvier-Durand</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrier</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chefdor</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giraudat</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Arabidopsis ABA response gene ABI1: features of a calcium-modulated protein phosphatase</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>264</volume>, <fpage>1448</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1452</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.7910981</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7910981?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7910981</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merlot</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giraudat</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The Arabidopsis ABSCISIC ACID-INSENSITIVE 2 (ABI2) and ABI1 genes encode homologous protein phosphatases 2C involved in abscisic acid signal transduction</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>759</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>771</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.9.5.759</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9165752?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9165752</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>TaSnRK2.4, an SNF1-type serine/threonine protein kinase of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.), confers enhanced multistress tolerance in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>683</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>696</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erp331</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20022921?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20022921</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leube</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grill</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>A protein phosphatase 2C involved in ABA signal transduction in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>264</volume>, <fpage>1452</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1455</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.8197457</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8197457?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8197457</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muruganujan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casagrande</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Large-scale gene function analysis with the PANTHER classification system</article-title>. <source>Nat. Protoc.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1551</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1566</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2013.092</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23868073?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23868073</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Umezawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidokoro</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takasaki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Two closely related subclass II SnRK2 protein kinases cooperatively regulate drought-inducible gene expression</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><volume>51</volume>, <fpage>842</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>847</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcq041</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20375108?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20375108</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamichi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukushima</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashino</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Transcript profiling of an Arabidopsis <italic>PSEUDO RESPONSE REGULATOR</italic> arrhythmic triple mutant reveals a role for the circadian clock in cold stress response</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><volume>50</volume>, <fpage>447</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>462</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcp004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19131357?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19131357</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanamori</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Umezawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidokoro</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Three Arabidopsis SnRK2 protein kinases, SRK2D/SnRK2.2, SRK2E/SnRK2.6/OST1 and SRK2I/SnRK2.3, involved in ABA signaling are essential for the control of seed development and dormancy</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><volume>50</volume>, <fpage>1345</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1363</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcp083</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19541597?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19541597</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Melcher</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teh</surname><given-names>B. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Abscisic acid perception and signaling: structural mechanisms and applications</article-title>. <source>Acta Pharmacol. Sin.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>567</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>584</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/aps.2014.5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24786231?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24786231</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soon</surname><given-names>F. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovach</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suino-Powell</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Structural basis for basal activity and autoactivation of abscisic acid (ABA) signaling SnRK2 kinases</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source><volume>108</volume>, <fpage>21259</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>21264</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1118651109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22160701?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22160701</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitahata</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asami</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirayama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title><italic>ABA-Hypersensitive Germination1</italic> encodes a protein phosphatase 2C, an essential component of abscisic acid signaling in Arabidopsis seed</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>935</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>949</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03107.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17461784?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17461784</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohtani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Demura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ROOT INITIATION DEFECTIVE1, a DEAH-Box RNA helicase involved in pre-mRNA splicing, is essential for plant development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>2056</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2069</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.113.111922</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23771891?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23771891</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohtani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishikubo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsuda</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gou&#xE9;</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A NAC domain protein family contributing to the regulation of wood formation in poplar</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source><volume>67</volume>, <fpage>499</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>512</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04614.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21649762?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21649762</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porra</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriedemann</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Determination of accurate extinction coefficients and simultaneous equations for assaying chlorophylls a and b extracted with four different solvents: verification of the concentration of chlorophyll standards by atomic absorption spectroscopy</article-title>. <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta Bioenerget.</source>
<volume>975</volume>, <fpage>384</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>394</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0005-2728(89)80347-0</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Apostolova</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Guzman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Garcia</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Gain-of-function and loss-of-function phenotypes of the protein phosphatase 2C <italic>HAB1</italic> reveal its role as a negative regulator of abscisic acid signalling</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source><volume>37</volume>, <fpage>354</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>369</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2003.01966.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14731256?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14731256</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherson</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alford</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Roles of cell-wall invertases and monosaccharide transporters in the growth and development of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>525</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>531</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erg055</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12508063?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12508063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burch</surname><given-names>A. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jez</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schachtman</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Phosphoproteomic identification of targets of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> sucrose nonfermenting-like kinase SnRK2. 8 reveals a connection to metabolic processes</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>104</volume>, <fpage>6460</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6465</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0610208104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17404219?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17404219</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohtani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takebayasi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiroyama</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rejab</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Physical interaction between SnRK2 and PP2C is conserved in <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>337</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>341</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5511/plantbiotechnology.15.0813b</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sopory</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Munshi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Protein kinases and phosphatases and their role in cellular signaling in plants</article-title>. <source>Crit. Rev. Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>245</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>318</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07352689891304230</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Cloning and characterization of <italic>TaSnRK2.3</italic>, a novel SnRK2 gene in common wheat</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><volume>64</volume>, <fpage>2063</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2080</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ert072</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23630328?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23630328</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umezawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyakawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuromori</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanokura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Molecular basis of the core regulatory network in ABA responses: sensing, signaling and tranport</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><volume>51</volume>, <fpage>1821</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1839</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcq156</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20980270?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20980270</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umezawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myouga</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Type 2C protein phosphatases directly regulate abscisic acid-activated protein kinases in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source><volume>106</volume>, <fpage>17588</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>17593</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0907095106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19805022?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19805022</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umezawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishihama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Genetics and phosphoproteomics reveal a protein phosphorylation network in the abscisic acid signaling pathway in <italic>Arabdiopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Sci. Signal</source><volume>6</volume>:<fpage>rs8</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scisignal.2003509</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23572148?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23572148</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umezawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>SRK2C, a SNF1-related protein kinase 2, improves drought tolerance by controlling stress-responsive gene expression in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>17306</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>17311</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0407758101</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15561775?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15561775</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B45">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vilela</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Capellades</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pag&#xE8;s</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lumbreras</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>ZmSnRK2.8 responds to ABA through the SnRK2-PP2C complex</article-title>. <source>Maydica</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B46">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vlad</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirichandra</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Protein phosphatases 2C regulate the activation of the Snf1-related kinase OST1 by abscisic acid in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>21</volume>, <fpage>3170</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3184</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.069179</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19855047?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19855047</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B47">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichimura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aronso</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>ABA-activated SnRK2 protein kinase is required for dehydration stress signaling in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><volume>43</volume>, <fpage>1473</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1483</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcf188</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12514244?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12514244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B48">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Characterization of a common wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) <italic>TaSnRK2.7</italic> gene involved in abiotic stress reponses</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>975</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>988</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erq328</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21030389?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21030389</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B49">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Overexpression of a common wheat gene <italic>TaSnRK2.8</italic> enhances tolerance to drought, salt and low temperature</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e16041</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0016041</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21209856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21209856</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B50">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Transcriptome differences between two sister desert poplar species under salt stress</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>15</volume>:<fpage>337</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-337</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24886148?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24886148</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <glossary>
      <def-list>
        <title>Abbreviations</title>
        <def-item>
          <term>SnRK2</term>
          <def>
            <p>SNF1-related protein kinases 2</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>ABA</term>
          <def>
            <p>abscisic acid.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
  </back>
</article>
