<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4588574</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep14476</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep14476</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Transcriptome analysis of hormone-induced gene expression in <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kakei</surname>
            <given-names>Yusuke</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mochida</surname>
            <given-names>Keiichi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sakurai</surname>
            <given-names>Tetsuya</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yoshida</surname>
            <given-names>Takuhiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shinozaki</surname>
            <given-names>Kazuo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shimada</surname>
            <given-names>Yukihisa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Kihara Institute for Biological Research, Yokohama City University</institution>, Kanagawa, <country>JAPAN</country></aff>
        <aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Cellulose Production Research Team, Biomass Engineering Program Cooperation Division, RIKEN Center for Sustainable Resource Science</institution>, Kanagawa, <country>JAPAN</country></aff>
        <aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Integrated Genome Informatics Research Unit, RIKEN Center for Sustainable Resource Science</institution>, Kanagawa, <country>JAPAN</country></aff>
        <aff id="a4"><label>4</label><institution>Gene Discovery Research Group, RIKEN Center for Sustainable Resource Science</institution>, Kanagawa, <country>JAPAN</country></aff>
        <aff id="a5"><label>5</label><institution>Biomass Research Platform Team, Biomass Engineering Research Division, RIKEN Center for Sustainable Resource Science</institution>, Kanagawa, <country>JAPAN</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1">
          <label>a</label>
          <email>yshimada@yokohama-cu.ac.jp</email>
        </corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>09</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>5</volume>
      <elocation-id>14476</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>02</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>09</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2015, Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-holder>
        <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <!--author-paid-->
          <license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x2019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p><italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> is a new model plant closely related to wheat and other cereals. In this study, we performed a comprehensive analysis of hormone-regulated genes in <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> using RNA sequencing technology. <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> seedlings were treated with eight phytohormones (auxin, cytokinine, brassinosteroid, gibberelline, abscisic acid, ethylene, jasmonate and salicylic acid) and two inhibitors, Brz220 (brassinosteroid biosynthesis inhibitor) and prohexadione (gibberelline biosynthesis inhibitor). The expressions of 1807 genes were regulated in a phytohormone-dependent manner. We compared the data with the phytohormone responses that have reported in rice. Transcriptional responses to hormones are conserved between <italic>Bracypodium</italic> and rice. Transcriptional regulation by brassinosteroid, gibberellin and ethylene was relatively weaker than those by other hormones. This is consistent with the data obtained from comprehensive analysis of hormone responses reported in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> also shared some common transcriptional responses to phytohormones. Alternatively, unique transcriptional responses to phytohormones were observed in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>. For example, the expressions of ACC synthase genes were up-regulated by auxin treatment in rice and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, but no orthologous ACC synthase gene was up-regulated in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>. Our results provide information useful to understand the diversity and similarity of hormone-regulated transcriptional responses between eudicots and monocots.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Human diets greatly depend on grasses, which have applications as energy crops and sustainable energy sources. Rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) and maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) are commonly used as model plants for monocots, as their genome sequence and extensive genetic resources are available<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>. Draper <italic>et al.</italic> proposed <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (<italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>) as a novel model plant in 2001 because it has advantages such as a small genome size, short life cycle, small plant size, and the ability to self-pollinate<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>. Furthermore, <italic>Brachypodium</italic> is more closely related to wheat [<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>] and rye [<italic>Secale cereale</italic>] than rice and maize are, which makes it convenient for analysis of different grass groups using model systems<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>. The whole genome sequence of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> inbred line Bd21 was released in 2010 as the first genome sequence available for the Pooideae subfamily<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. Recently, a comprehensive collection of full-length cDNAs was reported by Mochida <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. Therefore, fundamental resources for <italic>Brachypodium</italic> molecular biology are being rapidly developed. Recently, Priest <italic>et al.</italic> reported an analysis of global gene expression in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> in response to abiotic stress<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>. Large-scale gene expression data are essential resources for model systems. For <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, The Arabidopsis Information Resource (TAIR: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org">http://www.arabidopsis.org</ext-link>) and Arabidopsis e-FP browser<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref> integrate the public transcriptome data with other information to provide information useful for analysis of gene functions. Many tools for biological data mining, such as co-expression analysis (e.g., ATTED-II<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>), transcriptome network analysis (AtCAST<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>), and prediction of transcriptome dynamics in natural conditions<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>, depend on the availability of large-scale transcriptome data.</p>
    <p>Plant growth and development depend on phytohormone-mediated regulation of gene expression. Auxins, cytokinins (CKs), gibberellins (GAs) and brassinosteroids (BRs) generally promote plant growth and greatly influence plant stature and organ size. In contrast, ethylene, abscisic acid (ABA), salicylic acid (SA) and jasmonate (JA) regulate stress-related responses and/or growth retardation. The comprehensive response to a hormone was first reported in the eudicot model plant <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> by the AtGenExpress project (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://atpbsmd.yokohama-cu.ac.jp">http://atpbsmd.yokohama-cu.ac.jp</ext-link>)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>. Hundreds of genes have been identified as being regulated by phytohormones. These comprehensive transcriptome data have been utilized in hundreds of studies of large-scale or gene-specific regulation of transcripts. Therefore, analyses of phytohormone-regulated transcriptomes in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> are essential for transcriptomic and genetic studies of this plant. <italic>Brachypodium</italic> shares about 80% of its genes with rice as homologs<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>, and is more closely related to rice than to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and other model plants. Analyses of phytohormone-regulated transcriptomes were performed in rice for auxin, CK, SA, ABA, JA, and ethylene<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref> and for auxin, CK, GA, BR, ABA, and JA<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>. Comparisons of the responses in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and these other model plants will reveal both responses common to all plants and those specific to Pooideae.</p>
    <p>GA and BR treatment generates almost no change in gene expression in wild-type <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>; indeed, the endogenous GA and BR levels are too high (i.e., saturated) for exogenous hormones to induce gene expression. Therefore, BR- and GA-regulated genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> have been identified using the BR- and GA-deficient mutants <italic>det2</italic> and <italic>ga-1</italic>, respectively, and treatment with brassinolide (BL; BR), GA<sub>3</sub>, or GA<sub>4</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>. In this study, we found that the transcriptional regulation of BR-regulated genes in BR-treated <italic>det2</italic> plants was negatively correlated with BR-biosynthesis inhibitor treatment using the AtCAST database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://atpbsmd.yokohama-cu.ac.jp/atcast/html/genelist/A0036_A0081.html">http://atpbsmd.yokohama-cu.ac.jp/atcast/html/genelist/A0036_A0081.html</ext-link>)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>. These findings suggest that the application of hormone biosynthesis inhibitors (Brz220 for BR and Phx for GA) to generate hormone-deficient conditions is a practical means of identifying BR- or GA-regulated genes in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>.</p>
    <p>In this study, we performed a comprehensive RNA-seq analysis of the transcriptional responses in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> to eight phytohormones; auxin, BR, CK, GA, SA, ABA, JA, and ethylene. The compounds assayed included indole-3-acetic acid (IAA; auxin), trans-zeatin (tZ; CK), BL, Brz220 (Brz; inhibitor of BR synthesis), GA<sub>4</sub>, prohexadione-calcium (Phx: inhibitor of GA synthesis), SA, ABA, methyl jasmonate (MJ; JA) and 1-amino-cyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC; ethylene precursor). In addition, we applied combination treatments of BL and Brz220 (a BR-biosynthesis inhibitor) and GA4 and Phx (GA-biosynthesis inhibitor) to <italic>Brachypodium</italic>. Transcriptional regulation of genes in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> was compared to that in Rice and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>.</p>
    <sec disp-level="1" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Determination of hormone treatment conditions and identification of hormone-regulated genes</title>
        <p>We selected phytohormone-responsive marker genes in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> using the following procedure. Twenty-eight phytohormone-responsive genes from rice<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref> and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref> were selected and their sequences were subjected to a BLAST search for the most similar sequences in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>. Top-hit <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes were used to examine transcriptional responses in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). We checked the transcriptional responses with RT-PCR. In total, 19 of 28 genes showed reproducible gene expression responses to one of the phytohormones or the inhibitors in more than two independent experiments. These 19 genes were selected as phytohormone-responsive marker genes in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). Next, hormone treatment conditions in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> were determined using these marker genes. We used 1, 3, and 10&#x2009;&#x3BC;M for IAA, tZ and GA; 10, 30, and 100&#x2009;&#x3BC;M for Phx, ABA, MJ, ACC, Brz220 and SA; and 1, 10, 100, and 1000&#x2009;&#x3BC;M for BL. The concentrations of phytohormones and inhibitors used in the comprehensive transcriptome analysis were determined accordingly. The optimum concentration of each phytohormone (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>) was determined as that at which the marker gene showed the greatest change in response to treatment compared to mock treatment. After the determination of treatment conditions, the hormone treatment and sampling were repeated twice independently and the hormonal responses were confirmed against the transcriptional responses of the marker genes. Total RNAs extracted in two independent experiments were mixed and used in RNA-seq analysis.</p>
        <p>About 90% of obtained reads from the RNA-seq analysis were successfully mapped to the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genome (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>). Differentially expressed genes (DEGs) in response to each treatment (FDR&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05) were analyzed using edgeR<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref> in a comparison with all other treatments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>). Hundreds of genes were differentially expressed in response to ABA and MJ. Dozens of DEGs were detected for the IAA, tZ and SA treatments. We designated these analyses as being high stringency; the hormone-responsive genes are listed in Data <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">S1&#x2013;S8</xref>. In contrast, only four genes were differentially expressed in the Brz220 treatment. No DEG was detected in the mock 1-h, mock 3-h, Phx, Phx+GA, Brz220+BL and ethylene treatments, indicating that the gene expression responses to GA, BR and ethylene were weaker than those to the other hormones. Therefore, we conducted additional statistical analyses to identify the genes responsive to these hormones. For these analyses, DEGs were compared between the hormone treatment vs. two control treatments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t5">Table 5</xref>). Two hundred and twenty-four DEGs were detected in response to GA, 474 DEGs in response to BR, and 52 DEGs in response to ethylene. We designated these analyses as low stringency; the DEGs are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>, Data <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">S9&#x2013;S16</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Comparison with rice and Arabidopsis</title>
        <p>First, we compared the phytohormone-regulated genes in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> with those in rice. A comparison of our experimental conditions with those used in previous rice studies is presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S1</xref>. Garg <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref> reported the responses of rice seedlings to six hormones: auxin, CK, SA, ethylene, ABA, and JA. We made a list of predicted orthologs of the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> DEGs in rice and evaluated whether they are regulated in the same manner (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t6">Table 6</xref>). Since Garg <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref> reported phytohormone-regulated DEGs in rice without statistical information for each hormone treatment, we simply checked whether the orthologous genes from <italic>Brachypodium</italic> were included in the list of Garg <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref> or not. We predicted 408 orthologs to the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> DEGs in rice. In total, 326 orthologous genes (80%) were regulated by phytohormones in the same manner. The transcriptional response to CK and ABA in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> was consistent with that in rice: 100% of the orthologs of the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> DEGs that were regulated by CK (tZ) were also regulated in rice by CK (BAP), and 98% of the orthologous genes were regulated by ABA in rice. <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and rice shared many auxin- and JA-responsive orthologous genes: 67% of the orthologs were also regulated by IAA in rice. Garg <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref> reported that <italic>Aux/IAA</italic> and <italic>GH3</italic> are IAA-responsive gene families. Consistent with this report, many genes in the <italic>Aux/IAA</italic> family (<italic>Bradi1g55370</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g04910</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g34030</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g16850</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g46420</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g31820</italic>, <italic>Bradi3g55410</italic>, <italic>Bradi4g35960</italic>, <italic>Bradi3g54610</italic>, and <italic>Bradi2g11120</italic>) and <italic>GH3</italic> family (<italic>Bradi2g50840</italic>, <italic>Bradi1g22830</italic>, and <italic>Bradi2g52000</italic>) were found to be auxin-responsive in <italic>Brachypodium.</italic> In total, 42% of the orthologous genes were JA-responsive in rice. <italic>JAZ1-like</italic> genes in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (<italic>Bradi5g24410</italic>), <italic>OsJAZ1</italic>, a <italic>MYC2-like</italic> gene in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (<italic>Bradi3g34200</italic>), and <italic>OsMYC2</italic> were regulated in both plants. Transcriptional responses to SA and ethylene were less conserved. Only 26% and 31% of the orthologous genes were regulated by SA and ethylene in rice. A transcription factor gene, <italic>OsWRKY45</italic>, which acts in SA-mediated pathogen resistance<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>, and its orthologous gene in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (<italic>Bradi2g44270</italic>), were found to be regulated by SA in both plants. <italic>Ethylene receptor-like</italic> genes (<italic>Bradi5g00700</italic> and <italic>LOC_Os04g08740</italic>) were found to be regulated in both plants. Sato <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref> performed a transcriptional analysis using auxin, CK, GA, BR, ABA, and JA and presented a coexpression database. Since they did not show phytohormone-regulated genes, we did not directly compare our hormone-induced gene expression results with those of Sato <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>.</p>
        <p>A gene ontology (GO) term enrichment (GOE) analysis was performed to evaluate the DEGs for <italic>Brachypodium</italic>. In this study, the GO terms for <italic>Brachypodium</italic> were redefined using the latest GO annotation for <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (see the Methods for details) because the GO terms inferred from InterProScan (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://geneontology.org/page/go-annotation-standard-operating-procedures">http://geneontology.org/page/go-annotation-standard-operating-procedures</ext-link>) lack useful GO terms for the study of phytohormone responses (e.g., the &#x201C;Response to cytokinin stimulus&#x201D;; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S2</xref>). Therefore in the following sections, a detailed analysis was performed with the help of GO terms predicted from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t7">Tables 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="t8">8</xref>). In this study, we analyzed the GOE for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> using the latest GO terms (R package ath1121501cdf version 2.14.0) and microarray data provided by Goda <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S3</xref>) to compare the results of GOE analyses with those in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Auxin response</title>
        <p>One hundred and twenty-five genes were identified as auxin-responsive genes in the high-stringency analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Data S1</xref>). The genes with the term &#x201C;response to auxin stimulus&#x201D; were found to be enriched in the GOE analysis of auxin-responsive genes in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t7">Table 7</xref>). As we described in the comparison with rice, many genes in the <italic>Aux/IAA</italic> family and <italic>GH3</italic> family were detected as auxin-responsive genes in <italic>Brachypodium.</italic> These results are also consistent with the auxin response in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S1</xref>). In contrast to the auxin response in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes related to ethylene functions were not regulated in the same manner (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S2</xref>), although their expression levels were not low (present at sufficiently high levels for analysis) (log<sub>2</sub> cpm (number of counts per million reads) &gt;1).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>CK response</title>
        <p>Twenty-three genes were identified as cytokinin-responsive genes in the high-stringency analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Data S2</xref>). The genes with the term &#x201C;response to cytokinin stimulus&#x201D; were enriched in the GOE analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t7">Table 7</xref>). Genes in the type A <italic>ARR</italic> family (<italic>Bradi2g61000</italic>, <italic>Bradi4g43090</italic>, <italic>Bradi5g25860</italic>, <italic>Bradi3g45930</italic> and <italic>Bradi5g11350</italic>) were detected as cytokinin-responsive genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>). In contrast, members of the type B <italic>ARR</italic> gene family were not detected as cytokinin-responsive genes. These results are consistent with the cytokinin response in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>SA response</title>
        <p>Eighty-one genes were identified as SA-responsive genes in the high-stringency analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Data S3</xref>). Genes with the term &#x201C;defense response to fungus&#x201D; were enriched in GOE analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t7">Table 7</xref>). A homolog of the <italic>PR-1</italic> gene (<italic>Bradi1g57590</italic>) was up-regulated by SA treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>ABA response</title>
        <p>Four hundred and forty-five genes were identified as ABA-responsive genes in the high-stringency analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Data S4</xref>). Genes with the term &#x201C;response to abscisic acid stimulus&#x201D; were enriched in the GOE analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t7">Table 7</xref>). Genes homologous to those encoding transcription factors involved in transcriptional regulation in response to ABA (i.e., <italic>ABF</italic>, <italic>NAC</italic>, <italic>Myb</italic>, <italic>bHLH</italic>) were detected as DEGs (<italic>Bradi3g00730</italic>, <italic>Bradi1g59982</italic>, <italic>Bradi3g50220</italic>, <italic>Bradi4g32090</italic>, <italic>Bradi5g17170</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g22660</italic>, <italic>Bradi3g57960</italic>, <italic>Bradi3g19010</italic>, <italic>Bradi3g38200</italic>, <italic>Bradi4g29380</italic>, <italic>Bradi1g22180</italic>, <italic>Bradi1g11800</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g41530</italic>, <italic>Bradi1g20360</italic>, <italic>Bradi4g35910</italic>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>JA response</title>
        <p>Three hundred and eighty-three genes were identified as JA-responsive genes in the high-stringency analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Data S5</xref>). Genes with the term &#x201C;response to wounding&#x201D; were enriched in the GOE analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t7">Table 7</xref>). Genes involved in the biosynthesis of jasmonic acid (<italic>LOX3</italic> homolog (<italic>Bradi5g11590</italic>), <italic>LOX4</italic> homolog (<italic>Bradi1g72690</italic>), <italic>AOS</italic> homolog (<italic>Bradi3g08160</italic>, <italic>Bradi1g07480</italic>, <italic>Bradi1g69330</italic>), <italic>AOC3</italic> homolog (<italic>Bradi1g15840</italic>), <italic>OPR3</italic> homolog (<italic>Bradi3g37650</italic>) and <italic>OPCL1</italic> homolog (<italic>Bradi1g76280</italic>) were up-regulated by MJ treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4</xref>). The <italic>JAZ</italic> genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> encode JA receptors<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>. Two members of the <italic>JAZ</italic> family (<italic>Bradi3g23190</italic>, <italic>Bradi1g58490</italic>) were also up-regulated in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>GA response</title>
        <p>No gene was detected as a DEG in the high-stringency analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Data S6</xref>). This indicates that the GA-inducible gene expression response is relatively weaker than those to other hormones, which is consistent with the GA response in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>. When the effects on gene expression of the GA biosysthesis inhibitor Phx treatment were compared to those of the mock 3-h and Phx+GA treatments (low-stringency analysis), 224 genes were detected as DEGs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Data S14</xref>). Of these genes, those with the term &#x201C;response to nitrate&#x201D; were the most enriched in the GOE analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t8">Table 8</xref>). In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, many GA-biosynthesis genes are also GA-responsive, since there is a negative feedback regulation in the expression of GA-biosynthesis genes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>. The read counts of many genes involved in gibberellin biosynthesis (homologs of <italic>GA2oxs</italic>, <italic>GA3oxs</italic> and <italic>GA20oxs</italic>; i.e., <italic>Bradi1g56200</italic>, <italic>Bradi1g56210</italic>, <italic>Bradi1g56220</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g16727</italic>, <italic>Bradi4g23540</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g16750</italic>, <italic>Bradi3g49390</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g32577</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g24980</italic>, <italic>Bradi5g16040</italic>, <italic>Bradi1g59570</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g06670</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g57027</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g34837</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g19900</italic>, <italic>Bradi2g50280</italic>) were low, and none were detected as DEGs (log<sub>2</sub> cpm &lt;1, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S4</xref>). Genes of <italic>Xyloglucan endotransglucosylase/hydrolases TCH4</italic> (<italic>Bradi3g18690</italic>) and <italic>XTH12</italic> (<italic>Bradi3g10310</italic>) were significantly up-regulated. Many genes in <italic>Peroxidase superfamily</italic> (<italic>Bradi1g17860, Bradi1g17877, Bradi5g27160, Bradi2g38690, Bradi2g38700, Bradi1g44790, Bradi1g59520, Bradi2g20830, Bradi2g38670, Bradi3g33780, Bradi1g61550, Bradi2g11320, Bradi3g10470, Bradi5g10070, Bradi2g38685, Bradi1g61530, Bradi2g12180, Bradi2g20850, Bradi1g20020, Bradi2g20840, Bradi2g09660, Bradi1g33730, Bradi1g44800, Bradi2g38680, Bradi3g54010</italic>) were also up-regulated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>BR response</title>
        <p>Only four genes were detected as DEGs in the Brz220 treatment compared with all other treatments (high-stringency analysis, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Data S7</xref>). This indicates that the BR-inducible gene expression response is relatively weak compared with those to other hormones, which is consistent with the BR response in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>. When the effects on gene expression of the Brz220 treatment were compared with those of the mock 3-h and Brz220+BL treatments (low-stringency analysis), 474 genes were detected as DEGs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Data S15</xref>). Of these genes, those with the term &#x201C;RNA elongation&#x201D; were enriched in the GOE analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t8">Table 8</xref>). Genes with the term &#x201C;photosynthesis&#x201D; were also enriched in the GOE analysis. P450 genes involved in the biosynthesis of brassinosteroids (<italic>Bradi1g15030</italic>, homolog of <italic>BR6ox2</italic> and <italic>Bradi5g12990</italic>, homolog of <italic>DWF4</italic>) were up-regulated by Brz220 compared to the mock 3-h and Brz220+BL treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref>), although the fold change of <italic>Bradi5g12990</italic> was less than twice. This is consistent with the BR response in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>; <italic>BR6ox2</italic> and <italic>DWF4</italic> were up-regulated in the <italic>det2</italic> mutant of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> compared to the wild-type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Ethylene response</title>
        <p>No gene was detected as a DEG in response to ethylene in the high-stringency analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Data S8</xref>). To confirm response of seedlings to ACC treatment under our experimental conditions, plants were treated with ACC for a further week. Seedlings showed growth inhibition when grown in the presence of 10&#x2009;&#x3BC;M ACC (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S3</xref>), indicating that plants respond to exogenous ACC. Therefore, gene expression in response to ACC treatment was compared to that in response to the mock 1-h and mock 3-h treatments (low-stringency analysis). Fifty-two genes were detected as DEGs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Data S16</xref>). Of these DEGs, those with the term &#x201C;RNA elongation&#x201D; were enriched in GOE analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t8">Table 8</xref>). A gene homologous to <italic>EIN4</italic>, which is involved in sensing ethylene (<italic>Bradi5g00700</italic>) was up-regulated, and a gene homologous to <italic>ACS6</italic>, which is a member of the ethylene synthesis gene family, (<italic>Bradi5g19100</italic>) was down-regulated by ethylene treatment compared to the mock 1-h and mock 3-h treatments.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="1" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The comprehensive transcriptional response of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> to phytohormones was analyzed in this study. To obtain clear responses from <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, we optimized the experimental design using the expressions of selected <italic>Brachypodium</italic> marker genes to validate hormone response. The concentrations of phytohormones used in this study were similar (1&#x2013;10-fold) to those used in the analysis of the response to hormones in rice and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S1</xref>), with the exception of the concentration of BL (100-fold compared to that used for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>). We successfully identified BR- and GA-regulated genes (e.g., <italic>Bradi1g15030</italic>, homolog of <italic>BR6ox2</italic> as a BR-responsive gene and <italic>Bradi3g18690,</italic> homolog of <italic>TCH4</italic> as a GA-responsive gene).</p>
      <p>In rice, 80% of the orthologs of the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> DEGs were also regulated by CK, ABA, auxin, JA, SA, and ethylene. These data show that major transcriptional responses to these phytohormones are shared in monocots, although fewer orthologous genes were commonly regulated by SA and ethylene. It was reported that the SA level in rice was the highest among the tested plants<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. This may be one reason for the different responses to SA at similar concentrations. The difference in ethylene-regulated genes between rice and <italic>Brachypodium</italic> was also reported by Pacheco-Villalobos <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>. Sato <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref> also reported the responses of rice seedlings to six hormones: auxin, CK, GA, BR, ABA, and JA. However, it was difficult to compare our data with theirs because they reported their data as part of a large transcriptome dataset and no analysis of hormone-responsive gene expression was performed using the data.</p>
      <p>The transcriptional responses to phytohormones and the mechanisms involved in transcriptional regulation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> are well characterized. In addition, manually curated GO terms for Arabidopsis is very helpful to analyze large transcriptome dataset. Therefore, we compared the transcriptional response to phytohormones in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> to that in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> in detail. A comprehensive analysis of phytohormone-regulated genes of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> revealed common transcriptional responses between <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. To compare the accumulation of GO terms in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, we assigned new GO terms to the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes using the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GO terms. Some results of the GOE analyses in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and <italic>Brachypodium</italic> were common following treatment with the same phytohormones. The GO terms &#x201C;response to auxin stimulus&#x201D; had the lowest p-values in auxin-regulated DEGs. Similarly, &#x201C;cellular response to cytokinin stimulus&#x201D; in CK-regulated DEGs, &#x201C;defense response to fungus&#x201D; in SA-regulated DEGs, &#x201C;response to abscisic acid stimulus&#x201D; in ABA-regulated DEGs and &#x201C;response to wounding&#x201D; in JA-regulated DEGs had the lowest p-values in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t7">Tables 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="t8">8</xref>). These GO terms were also enriched in the hormone-responsive genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S3</xref>). The GO term &#x201C;response to nitrate&#x201D; was enriched in DEGs in the Phx treatment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t7">Table 7</xref>), which was consistent with the enriched GO of the GA-biosynthesis mutant <italic>ga1-5</italic> when compared to the wild type (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S5</xref>). The GO term &#x201C;photosynthesis&#x201D; was enriched in DEGs of Brz-treated <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t7">Table 7</xref>), which was consistent with the enriched GO terms of the BR-biosynthesis mutant <italic>det2</italic> when compared to wild-type <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Consistent with the findings in BR-treated <italic>Arabidopsis det2</italic>, genes involved in BR-synthesis were detected as DEGs in Brz-treated <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref>). Fewer were detected as DEGs in response to ACC than to other hormones (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Tables 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="t5">5</xref>). This was also consistent with transcriptional regulation in ethylene-treated <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>. These results suggest that many molecular mechanisms characteristic of the responses to phytohormones in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> are also present in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>.</p>
      <p>In contrast, there were some differences in the hormone responses of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, genes involved in ethylene synthesis and signaling, <italic>ACO1</italic>, <italic>ACO3</italic>, <italic>ACO4/EFE</italic>, <italic>ACS4</italic>, <italic>ACS8</italic>, and <italic>ERF1</italic>, are responsive to auxin treatment. Only one gene from the <italic>ACO</italic> gene family (<italic>Bradi2g41840</italic>) was detected as a DEG in auxin-treated <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S2</xref>). Genes involved in ethylene signaling, such as <italic>ERF2</italic>, <italic>8</italic>, <italic>11</italic>, <italic>ERS1</italic>, <italic>EBF2</italic>, <italic>ETR2</italic>, <italic>CTR1</italic> and <italic>EIN2</italic>, are regulated by ACC treatment in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>. However, in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, only one gene homologous to <italic>EIN4</italic> (<italic>Bradi5g00700</italic>) was detected as a DEG. These differences in auxin- and ethylene-responsive genes suggest divergent auxin-ethylene relationships between eudicots and monocots. Pacheco-Villalobos <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref> reported that the cross-talk between ethylene and auxin in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> differs from that in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Further analysis of these differentially expressed genes will improve our understanding of the different functions of these hormones and the related genes in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</p>
      <p>We encountered some difficulties in the analysis of RNA-seq data. We prepared 13&#x2013;30 million reads because Liu <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref> reported that the increase in number of DEGs drops after 10&#x2013;15 million reads. However, the transcriptional responses of some genes might not have been detected because of their low read counts. For example, none of the genes involved in GA-biosynthesis was detected as Phx- or GA-responsive in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>. However, it was reported that the expressions of the GA-biosynthetic genes <italic>AtGA2ox1</italic>, <italic>AtGA2ox2</italic>, <italic>GA3ox1</italic> and <italic>GA20ox1</italic> changed in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GA-deficient mutants following endogenous GA treatment<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. The read counts of these GA-biosynthetic genes in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> were low (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S4</xref>). In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and rice, few genes respond to ethylene<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>. In this study, no gene in the expansin family was detected as ethylene-responsive in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, while <italic>AtEXP8</italic> and <italic>AtEXP18</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref> and <italic>OsEXP1, OsEXP2</italic> in rice<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref> are responsive. The expression levels of 27 expansin genes were low (cpm &lt;1, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S6</xref>). The growth of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> was reduced by ACC treatment (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S3</xref>); therefore, some expansin genes may be regulated by ethylene to control cell elongation. To examine the transcriptional regulation of these poorly expressed genes, further analysis using additional RNA-seq reads with different tissues or different growth stages, and/or complementary methods (such as microarray or quantitative PCR) are required.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="1" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Plant materials</title>
        <p>Seedlings of <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> Bd21 were grown on 1/2 MS medium<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref> supplemented with 1% sucrose and 0.8% agar 4 days after breaking dormancy at 4&#x2009;&#xB0;C in the dark. The plants were grown on agar plates for 4 days and transplanted to 1/2 MS liquid culture with 1% sucrose. The plants were pre-incubated for 24&#x2009;h in liquid culture with shaking (70&#x2013;80&#x2009;rpm) and then treated with phytohormones (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). The phytohormones were dissolved in DMSO before addition to the liquid cultures. DMSO (0.1% (v/v)) was used for mock treatments. For the &#x201C;Inhibitor and GA&#x201D; and &#x201C;Inhibitor and BR&#x201D; treatments, GA and BL were added to liquid cultures 2&#x2009;h after treatment with the GA inhibitor, prohexadione-calcium (Wako), or BR-inhibitor, brassinazole220<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>, respectively. All growth and treatment processes were performed at 22&#x2009;&#xB0;C under continuous light. Phytohormone treatments were conducted twice independently as biological replicates, and the hormone responses were confirmed using the transcriptional responses of marker genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). Transcriptional responses of marker genes were checked with RT-PCR using gene specific primers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S7</xref>) prior to the RNA-seq analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>RNA extraction</title>
        <p>RNA was extracted from each sample using the RNeasy Mini Kit (QIAGEN). The concentration and quality of the RNA samples were determined using a Nanodrop 2000 instrument (Thermo Scientific). RNA extracted from two biological replicates was mixed and used for the RNA-seq analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Strand-specific RNA-seq analysis</title>
        <p>Strand-specific RNA libraries were prepared using the TruSeq Small RNA Sample Prep Kit (Illumina) and TruSeq RNA sample Preparation Kit v2 (Illumina) following the instructions in the Directional mRNA-seq Library Prep. (Pre-Release Protocol Rev.A (Illumina)). Fragmented Poly(A)-RNA was treated with T4 polynucleotide kinase (TAKARA) for phosphorylation of the 5&#x2032; end. An RNA 3&#x2032; adopter was ligated to the 3&#x2032; end using T4 RNA ligase 2, truncated (NEB), then an RNA 5&#x2032; adopter was ligated to the 5&#x2032; end using T4 RNA ligase 1 (NEB). Single-strand cDNA was synthesized with a primer for the RNA 3&#x2032; adaptor. Amplified cDNA was size-selected using 6% polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis, then used as the sequencing library. The quality of all libraries was assessed using a Bioanalyzer 2100 (Agilent). Sequencing was performed using a HiSeq2000 sequencer (Illumina) to sequence 100 bp. The sequencing was performed with the single-read method. The sequence data have been submitted to the DDBJ Sequence Read Archive under accession number PRJDB2997.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Mapping of RNA-Seq reads, transcript assembly and abundance estimation</title>
        <p>The sequences were aligned to the Phytozome 9.0 <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> reference genome Bdistachyon_192 (Bdistachyon_192_hardmasked.fa.gz) using TopHat v2.0.11<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>, which is integrated with Bowtie v2.2.1<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. The Bowtie index was generated from Bdistachyon_192 and counting of the mapped reads was performed using Cufflinks v2.2.1<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref> and genome annotation reference PASA_updates.phytozome.gff3<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. Read counts were generated using Cuffdiff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>. Differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were identified with edgeR<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>, as follows. Parameters and function usages in edgeR were determined to maximize the specificity for detecting hormone marker genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>) as DEGs. Read counts were normalized with the function &#x201C;calcNormFactors&#x201D;. The TMM normalization method in edgeR can normalize different amounts of RNA-Seq data without increasing the false-positive rate of detecting DEGs<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref>. Dispersions among genes and among replications were estimated by the functions &#x201C;estimateGLMCommonDisp&#x201D;, &#x201C;estimateGLMTrendedDisp&#x201D; and &#x201C;estimateGLMTagwiseDisp&#x201D; and p-values were calculated using the likelihood-ratio test with the generalized linear models. Calculated p-values were adjusted using the false discovery rate (FDR) of Benjamini and Hochberg&#x2019;s approach<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>. DEGs were defined as FDR &lt;0.05 and up- or down-regulated genes were identified in the DEGs as those having a log<sub>2</sub> ratio of cpm &gt;1 or that of cpm &lt;&#x2212;1, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Phytohormone-regulated genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></title>
        <p>Microarray data from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> treated with phytohormones were retrieved from the AtGenExpress project<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>. Signals in the microarray data were calculated using R package affy (1.42.3) with the MAS5 method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>. DEGs were identified as p-value&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.1 by Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic>-test and up- and down-regulated genes were defined in the DEGs as log<sub>2</sub> ratios of signals &gt;1 and &lt;&#x2212;1, respectively. GOE analyses were performed with the DEGs.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Determination of orthologous/homologous genes and generation of the phylogenetic tree</title>
        <p>To obtain orthologous gene pairs, <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> protein sequences (TAIR10) and rice protein sequences (RGAP 7) were applied to BLAST (blastp) to search for homologous sequences in the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> protein sequence (Bdistachyon_192_peptide.fa from Phytozome 9.0). <italic>Brachypodium</italic> sequences with top hit were collected and applied to BLAST again to search for the most similar sequences in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and rice. If the results of the second BLAST returned the former Arabidopsis or rice sequence, the corresponding gene pairs were selected as orthologous gene pairs. To obtain genes from each gene family in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, protein sequences of members of each family in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> were applied to BLAST (blastp with default settings) to search for similar sequences in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (Bdistachyon_192_peptide.fa). <italic>Brachypodium</italic> sequences with E-values less than thresholds were collected and the corresponding <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes were selected as family members (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Figs S1</xref>,<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">S2</xref>). To obtain superfamily or functionally related subfamily, optimal E-value for each gene family was selected. For the <italic>Aux/IAA</italic> gene family, 19 protein sequences of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Aux/IAA1-19 with a threshold E-value&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;10<sup>&#x2212;10</sup> were used. For the <italic>ARR</italic> family, 17 protein sequences of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ARR1-17 with a threshold E-value&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup> were used. For the <italic>GH3</italic> gene family, sequences of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S1</xref> with a threshold E-value&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.1 were used. For the <italic>ACS</italic> and <italic>ACO</italic> gene families, 11 protein sequences (ACS1-11) and 4 proteins (ACO1-4) with a threshold E-value&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;10<sup>&#x2212;10</sup> were used. To obtain homologous BR-biosynthetic <italic>P450</italic> genes from <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, the protein sequences of BAS1, Chibi2, BR6ox2, BR6ox1, DWF4, CPD, ROT3 and CYP90D1/At3g13730 were applied to BLAST (blastp) to search for similar sequences in the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> protein sequence. <italic>Brachypodium</italic> sequences with an E-value&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;10<sup>&#x2212;100</sup> were collected and the corresponding <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes were selected as BR-biosynthetic genes. To identify SA-responsive genes homologous to <italic>PR1</italic> in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, the protein sequence of PR1 and its <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> homologous proteins (BLAST E-value&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;10<sup>&#x2212;10</sup>) were applied to BLAST (blastp) to search for similar sequences in the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> protein sequence. <italic>Brachypodium</italic> sequences with an E-value&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;10<sup>&#x2212;10</sup> were collected and the corresponding <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes were selected as <italic>PR1-like</italic> genes. Similarly, to identify genes homologous to <italic>ERF1</italic>, the ERF1 protein sequence was applied to BLAST and those with an E-value&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;10<sup>&#x2212;10</sup> were selected as <italic>ERF1-like</italic> genes. To identify genes homologous to JA-biosynthetic genes in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, the protein sequences of AtLOX2-4, AOS, AOC3, OPR3, OPCL1, ACX1, ACX5, AIM1, KAT2, JMT and JAR were applied to BLAST (blastp) to search for homologous sequences in the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> protein sequence. <italic>Brachypodium</italic> sequences with an E-value&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;10<sup>&#x2212;10</sup> were collected and applied to BLAST again to search for the most similar sequences in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. If the results of the second BLAST returned AtLOX2-4, AOS, AOC3, OPR3, OPCL1, ACX1, ACX5, AIM1, KAT2, JMT or JAR, the corresponding <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes were selected as being homologous JA-biosynthetic genes. To create the phylogenetic tree of orthologous genes in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, translated amino acid sequences were aligned with MAFFT<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref> using the &#x201C;auto&#x201D; settings. The neighbor-joining tree<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref> of the aligned sequences was then generated using percent identity and visualized as a Rectangular Cladogram in Dendroscope<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Gene ontology term enrichment (GOE) analysis</title>
        <p>GOE analysis was carried out using the following procedure. First, <italic>Brachypodium</italic> protein sequences were applied to BLAST (tblastn) to search for the most similar gene in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. GO terms of the top hits in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> were copied as the customized annotations of corresponding <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes. GOE analysis was performed using AgriGO<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref> with customized annotations as the query, customized annotated reference and with default settings for statistical analysis (p-value was calculated with Fisher&#x2019;s exact test and &#x201C;FDR with Yekutieli&#x201D;).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="1">
      <title>Additional Information</title>
      <p><bold>How to cite this article</bold>: Kakei, Y. <italic>et al.</italic> Transcriptome analysis of hormone-induced gene expression in <italic>Brachypodium distachyon.</italic><italic>Sci. Rep.</italic>
<bold>5</bold>, 14476; doi: 10.1038/srep14476 (2015).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e24" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Information</title>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep14476-s1.pdf"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e27" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Dataset</title>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep14476-s2.xls"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We are grateful to Ms. Yuka Mitani, Ms. Ayaka Saito and Dr. Ayako Nakamura for their help in growing plants and examining the expression of marker genes. This paper is contribution No. 1019 from the Kihara Institute for Biological Research, Yokohama City University. This work was supported by JSPS KAKENHI Grant Number 26506016.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="b1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brkljacic</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Brachypodium as a Model for the Grasses: Today and the Future</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source><volume>157</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>13</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21771916</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Draper</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Brachypodium distachyon. A New Model System for Functional Genomics in Grasses</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source><volume>127</volume>, <fpage>1539</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1555</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11743099</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">International Brachypodium Initiative. <article-title>Genome sequencing and analysis of the model grass Brachypodium distachyon</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>463</volume>, <fpage>763</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>768</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20148030</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mochida</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Large-Scale Collection and Analysis of Full-Length cDNAs from Brachypodium distachyon and Integration with Pooideae Sequence Resources</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e75265</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24130698</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Priest</surname><given-names>H. D.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Analysis of Global Gene Expression in Brachypodium distachyon Reveals Extensive Network Plasticity in Response to Abiotic Stress</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e87499</fpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24489928</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>An &#x2018;Electronic Fluorescent Pictograph&#x2019; Browser for Exploring and Analyzing Large-Scale Biological Data Sets</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>2</volume>, <fpage>e718</fpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17684564</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Obayashi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kasahara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>ATTED-II Updates: Condition-Specific Gene Coexpression to Extend Coexpression Analyses and Applications to a Broad Range of Flowering Plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>213</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>219</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21217125</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Asami</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>AtCAST, a Tool for Exploring Gene Expression Similarities among DNA Microarray Experiments Using Networks</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>169</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>180</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21113043</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kakei</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>AtCAST3.0 Update: A Web-Based Tool for Analysis of Transcriptome Data by Searching Similarities in Gene Expression Profiles</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source>
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>e7</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>e7</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25505006</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Deciphering and Prediction of Transcriptome Dynamics under Fluctuating Field Conditions</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>151</volume>, <fpage>1358</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1369</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23217716</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>The AtGenExpress hormone and chemical treatment data set: experimental design, data evaluation, model data analysis and data access</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source><volume>55</volume>, <fpage>526</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>542</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18419781</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Structural characterization of Brachypodium genome and its syntenic relationship with rice and wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><volume>70</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>61</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19184460</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Microarray analysis reveals overlapping and specific transcriptional responses to different plant hormones in rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Signal Behav</source>. <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>951</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>956</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22827941</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>RiceXPro Version 3.0: expanding the informatics resource for rice transcriptome</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>41</volume>, <fpage>D1206</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>D1213</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23180765</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nemhauser</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Different Plant Hormones Regulate Similar Processes through Largely Nonoverlapping Transcriptional Responses</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>126</volume>, <fpage>467</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>475</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16901781</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Differential expression analysis of multifactor RNA-Seq experiments with respect to biological variation</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>4288</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4297</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22287627</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shimono</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Rice WRKY45 Plays a Crucial Role in Benzothiadiazole-Inducible Blast Resistance</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>19</volume>, <fpage>2064</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2076</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17601827</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>To</surname><given-names>J. P. C.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Cytokinin Regulates Type-A Arabidopsis Response Regulator Activity and Protein Stability via Two-Component Phosphorelay</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>19</volume>, <fpage>3901</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3914</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18065689</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sheard</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Jasmonate perception by inositol phosphate-potentiated COI1-JAZ co-receptor</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>468</volume>, <fpage>400</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>405</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20927106</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Salicylic Acid in Rice (Biosynthesis, Conjugation, and Possible Role)</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source><volume>108</volume>, <fpage>633</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>639</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228500</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pacheco-Villalobos</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sankar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Hardtke</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Disturbed Local Auxin Homeostasis Enhances Cellular Anisotropy and Reveals Alternative Wiring of Auxin-ethylene Crosstalk in Brachypodium distachyon Seminal Roots</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e1003564</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23840182</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>White</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>RNA-seq differential expression studies: more sequence or more replication?</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>301</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>304</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24319002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Isolation of the Arabidopsis GA4 locus</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Online</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>195</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>201</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Isolation and Expression of Three Gibberellin 20-Oxidase cDNA Clones from Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source><volume>108</volume>, <fpage>1049</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1057</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7630935</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.-L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gage</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Zeevaart</surname><given-names>J. A. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Feedback Regulation of GA5 Expression and Metabolic Engineering of Gibberellin Levels in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Online</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>927</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>935</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Hedden</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Molecular cloning and functional expression of gibberellin 2- oxidases, multifunctional enzymes involved in gibberellin deactivation</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</source>. <volume>96</volume>, <fpage>4698</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4703</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10200325</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>H.-T.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Regulation of Root Hair Initiation and Expansin Gene Expression in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Online</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>3237</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3253</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Murashige</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Skoog</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Revised Medium for Rapid Growth and Bio Assays with Tobacco Tissue Cultures</article-title>. <source>Physiol. Plant.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>473</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>497</lpage> (<year>1962</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sekimata</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>A Specific and Potent Inhibitor of Brassinosteroid Biosynthesis Possessing a Dioxolane Ring</article-title>. <source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>50</volume>, <fpage>3486</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3490</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12033815</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>TopHat2: accurate alignment of transcriptomes in the presence of insertions, deletions and gene fusions</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>R36</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23618408</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>357</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>359</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Differential analysis of gene regulation at transcript resolution with RNA-seq</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><volume>31</volume>, <fpage>46</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>53</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23222703</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dillies</surname><given-names>M.-A.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>A comprehensive evaluation of normalization methods for Illumina high-throughput RNA sequencing data analysis</article-title>. <source>Brief. Bioinform.</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>671</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>683</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22988256</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Controlling the False Discovery Rate: A Practical and Powerful Approach to Multiple Testing</article-title>. <source>J. R. Stat. Soc. Ser. B Methodol</source>. <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>300</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name> &amp; others. <article-title>Model-based analysis of oligonucleotide arrays: model validation, design issues and standard error application</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Toh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Parallelization of the MAFFT multiple sequence alignment program</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>1899</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1900</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20427515</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saitou</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The neighbor-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>406</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>425</lpage> (<year>1987</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3447015</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huson</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Scornavacca</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Dendroscope 3: An Interactive Tool for Rooted Phylogenetic Trees and Networks</article-title>. <source>Syst. Biol. sys062</source> (<year>2012</year>), <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/sys062.</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<article-title>agriGO: a GO analysis toolkit for the agricultural community</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>W64</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>70</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20435677</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p><bold>Author Contributions</bold> Y.K., K.M., K.S. and Y.S. designed the study. Y.K. performed experiments and drafted the manuscript. Y.K., T.S., and T.Y. performed the statistical analysis of data. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f1">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Phylogenic tree of <italic>Aux/IAA</italic> genes and their transcriptional responses to auxin in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</title>
        <p><italic>Brachypodium Aux/IAA</italic> family members were retrieved using the BLAST software. Protein sequences were aligned with MAFFT and similarities (percentage identity) are shown as a phylogenetic tree. <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes are shown in red and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes in black. log<sub>2</sub> ratio represents the gene expression ratio between the read count in IAA treatment divided by the average read count from all other treatments. Stat represents the p-value of the microarray experiment of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> treated with IAA<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref> or the FDR of RNA-seq data when the count of IAA treatment was compared with all other treatments. log<sub>2</sub> ratio is hatched in red if genes are up-regulated. cpm represents the average of log<sub>2</sub>-scaled read counts per million reads in all experiments.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep14476-f1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f2">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Phylogenic tree of <italic>ARR</italic> genes and their transcriptional responses to CK in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</title>
        <p><italic>Brachypodium ARR</italic> family members were retrieved using the BLAST software. Similarities in protein sequences (percentage identity) are shown as a phylogenetic tree. <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes are shown in red and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes in black. log<sub>2</sub> ratio represents the gene expression ratio between the read count in tZ treatments divided by the average read count from all other treatments. Stat represents the p-value of the microarray experiment in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> treated with t-zeatin for 1&#x2009;h<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref> or FDR of RNA-seq data when the count from tZ treatment was compared with all other treatments. log<sub>2</sub> ratio is hatched in red if genes are up-regulated. cpm represents the average of log<sub>2</sub>-scaled read counts per million reads from all experiments.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep14476-f2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f3">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Phylogenic tree of <italic>PR1</italic>, its orthologs and transcriptional responses to SA treatment in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</title>
        <p><italic>Brachypodium PR1-</italic>like genes were retrieved using the BLAST software. Similarities in protein sequences (percentage identity) are shown as a phylogenetic tree. <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes are shown in red and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes in black. log<sub>2</sub> ratio represents the gene expression ratio between read counts from SA treatment divided by the average read counts from all other treatments. Stat represents the p-value of the microarray experiment. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> treated with SA for 3&#x2009;h<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref> for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes or FDR of RNA-seq data when the counts from SA treatment were compared with all other treatments for <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes. log<sub>2</sub> ratio is hatched in red if genes are up-regulated and in blue if down-regulated. cpm represents the log<sub>2</sub>-scaled read count per million reads of RNA-seq data from all treatments.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep14476-f3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f4">
      <label>Figure 4</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Biosynthesis pathway of JA and transcriptional responses in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</title>
        <p>Homologs of jasmonate biosynthetic genes in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> were retrieved using the BLAST software. <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes are shown in red and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes in black. Stat represents the p-value of the microarray experiment. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> treated by MJ for 3&#x2009;hours<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref> and FDR of RNA-seq data when the count of MJ treatment was compared with all other treatments. log<sub>2</sub> ratio represents the gene expression ratio between read counts from the MJ treatment divided by the average read counts from all other treatments. log<sub>2</sub> ratio is hatched in red if genes are up-regulated. cpm represents log<sub>2</sub> scaled read count per million reads of RNA-seq data from all treatments.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep14476-f4"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f5">
      <label>Figure 5</label>
      <caption>
        <title><italic>P450</italic> genes involved in BR biosynthesis and transcriptional responses to Brz in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</title>
        <p><italic>Brachypodium</italic> BR biosynthetic genes were retrieved using the BLAST software. Similarities in protein sequences (percentage identity) are shown as a phylogenetic tree. <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes are shown in red and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes in black. log<sub>2</sub> ratio represents the gene expression ratio between read counts from the Brz treatment divided by the average read counts from mock 1-h and Brz+BL treatments. Stat represents the p-value of the microarray experiment, <italic>Arabidopsis det2</italic> compared with wild-type<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref> for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes or FDR of RNA-seq data when the counts from the Brz treatment were compared with mock 1-h and Brz+BL treatments for <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes. log<sub>2</sub> ratio is hatched in red if genes are up-regulated and in blue if down-regulated. cpm represents log<sub>2</sub> scaled read counts per million reads of RNA-seq data from mock 1-h, Brz and Brz+BL treatments.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep14476-f5"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="t1">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Selection of marker genes.</title>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
        <colgroup>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
        </colgroup>
        <thead valign="bottom">
          <tr>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Hormone</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Arabidopsis (Rice) gene</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold><italic>Brachypodium</italic> gene</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold><italic>Brachypodium</italic> qPCR</bold>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Auxin</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Aux/IAA16</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi4g02600.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">No response</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Auxin</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Aux/IAA9</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi2g31820.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Auxin</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Aux/IAA18</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi2g33417.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Auxin</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>(LOC_Os02g57250)</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi3g55410.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CK</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>AtARR1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi1g69480.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">No response</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CK</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>AtARR9</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi2g61000.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CK</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>(OsRR10)</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi4g43090.2</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BR</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>BR6ox2</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi1g15030.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BR</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>dwf4</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi1g69040.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BR</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>CPD</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi4g43110.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">No response</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>GAI</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi1g11090.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>SCL3</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi2g60750.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">No response</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>AtEXP1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi2g22290.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ABA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>AT1G79520</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi2g02050.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">No response</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ABA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>HsfA6B</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi3g26920.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ABA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>GLTP</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi1g11280.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ABA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>(LOC_Os09g21120)</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi4g29360.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Ethylene</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>ERS2</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi3g55730.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">No response</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Ethylene</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>EFE,ACO4</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi3g57620.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">No response</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Ethylene</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>DL4170C</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi2g27140.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">No response</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Ethylene</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>(OsETR2)</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi5g00700.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Ethylene</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>(LOC_Os01g73200)</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi4g27680.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">JA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>JMT</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi2g47550.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">No response</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">JA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>OPR3</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi3g37650.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">JA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>(OsMYC2)</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi3g34200.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>PR-1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi1g57590.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>WRKY70</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi2g44270.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>AtMES1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <italic>Bradi2g52110.1</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Responded</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="t2">
      <label>Table 2</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Hormone treatment conditions in <italic>Brachypodium.</italic></title>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
        <colgroup>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
        </colgroup>
        <thead valign="bottom">
          <tr>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Hormone treatment</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Chemicals</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Concentration</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Time</bold>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Mock</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x2014;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x2014;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3&#x2009;h</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Auxin</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">IAA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10&#x2009;&#x3BC;M</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3&#x2009;h</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Cytokinin</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">tZ</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1&#x2009;&#x3BC;M</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3&#x2009;h</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Gibberellin inhibitor</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Phx</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100&#x2009;&#x3BC;M</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5&#x2009;h</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Inhibitor and Gibberellin</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Phx+GA4</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100&#x2009;&#x3BC;M+3&#x2009;&#x3BC;M</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x2009;+&#x2009;3&#x2009;h</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Brassinosteroid inhibitor</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Brz220</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100&#x2009;&#x3BC;M</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5&#x2009;h</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Inhibitor and Brassinosteroid</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Brz220+BL</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100&#x2009;&#x3BC;M&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#x2009;&#x3BC;M</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2&#x2009;+&#x2009;3&#x2009;h</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Salicylic acid</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">SA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100&#x2009;&#x3BC;M</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3&#x2009;h</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Mock</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x2014;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x2014;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1&#x2009;h</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Abscisic acid</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">ABA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10&#x2009;&#x3BC;M</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1&#x2009;h</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Jasmonate</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">MJ</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">30&#x2009;&#x3BC;M</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1&#x2009;h</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Ethylene</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">ACC</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100&#x2009;&#x3BC;M</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1&#x2009;h</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="t3">
      <label>Table 3</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Mapped sequence reads from RNA-seq analysis.</title>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
        <colgroup>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="char" char="."/>
        </colgroup>
        <thead valign="bottom">
          <tr>
            <th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Treatment</bold>
            </th>
            <th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>No. of reads</bold>
            </th>
            <th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>TopHat2</bold>
              <hr/>
            </th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>No. of mapped reads</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">
              <bold>% of mapped reads</bold>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Mock 3&#x2009;h</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">14,564,558</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">12,987,675</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.89</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">IAA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13,305,739</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">12,020,000</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.90</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">tZ</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13,370,016</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">11,832,703</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.89</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Phx</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">14,504,534</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13,124,973</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.90</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Phx+GA4</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13,140,608</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10,548,366</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.80</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Brz220</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13,651,634</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">11,005,887</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.81</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Brz220+BL</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">14,590,592</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">12,002,938</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.82</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">14,877,403</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">12,247,895</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.82</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Mock 1&#x2009;h</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">27,388,326</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">25,423,449</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.93</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ABA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">26,462,899</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">24,717,631</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.93</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">MJ</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">29,605,491</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">27,494,719</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.93</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ACC</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">28,057,412</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">26,336,415</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.94</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="t4">
      <label>Table 4</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Number of DEGs detected in comparison with all other experiments (high stringency).</title>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
        <colgroup>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
        </colgroup>
        <thead valign="bottom">
          <tr>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Treatment</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>DEGs</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Treatment</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>DEGs</bold>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Mock 3&#x2009;h</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Mock 1&#x2009;h</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">IAA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">125</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">ABA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">445</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">tZ</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">23</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">MJ</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">383</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Phx</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">ACC</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Phx+GA4</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Brz220</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Brz220+BL</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">81</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="t5">
      <label>Table 5</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Number of DEGs detected in comparison with two control experiments (low stringency).</title>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
        <colgroup>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
        </colgroup>
        <thead valign="bottom">
          <tr>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Treatment</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Control 1</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Control 2</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>DEGs</bold>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Phx</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Mock 3&#x2009;h</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Prohexadion+GA3</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">224</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Brz220</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Mock 3&#x2009;h</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Brz220+BL</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">474</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ACC</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Mock 1&#x2009;h</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Mock 3&#x2009;h</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">52</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Others</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Mock 1&#x2009;h</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Mock 3&#x2009;h</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x2013;</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="t6">
      <label>Table 6</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Comparison of transcriptional response using orthologous genes of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and rice.</title>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
        <colgroup>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="center"/>
        </colgroup>
        <thead valign="bottom">
          <tr>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Hormone treatment</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>DEGs conserved in rice (%)</bold>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CK</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ABA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">98</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">IAA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">67</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">JA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">42</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">SA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">26</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Ethylene</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">31</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Total</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">80</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="t7">
      <label>Table 7</label>
      <caption>
        <title>GOE analysis of DEGs obtained under high-stringency conditions.</title>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
        <colgroup>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
        </colgroup>
        <thead valign="bottom">
          <tr>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>GOE in Auxin</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Term</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>P-value</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>FDR</bold>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0009733</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Response to auxin stimulus</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.00E-19</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.00E-16</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0010311</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Lateral root formation</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9.90E-16</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5.10E-13</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0010102</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Lateral root morphogenesis</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.20E-13</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3.10E-11</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0010101</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Post-embryonic root morphogenesis</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.20E-13</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3.10E-11</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0009741</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Response to brassinosteroid stimulus</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.80E-12</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4.90E-10</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GOE in CK</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0071368</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Cellular response to cytokinin stimulus</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">8.60E-07</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.00015</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0009736</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Cytokinin-mediated signaling pathway</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">8.10E-07</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.00015</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0009735</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Response to cytokinin stimulus</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4.40E-07</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.00015</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0048511</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Rhythmic process</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5.90E-05</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0062</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0007623</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Circadian rhythm</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5.90E-05</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0062</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GOE in SA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0050832</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Defense response to fungus</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0075</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.86</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0002252</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Immune effector process</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.007</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.86</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0006952</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Defense response</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0066</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.86</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0006950</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Response to stress</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.006</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.86</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0010200</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Response to chitin</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.006</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.86</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GOE in ABA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0009737</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Response to abscisic acid stimulus</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4.00E-16</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.00E-12</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0009414</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Response to water deprivation</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7.50E-13</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7.90E-10</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0009415</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Response to water</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">9.20E-13</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7.90E-10</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0009725</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Response to hormone stimulus</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.50E-08</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.00E-05</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0042538</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Hyperosmotic salinity response</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.10E-07</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.00011</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GOE in JA</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0009611</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Response to wounding</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7.70E-31</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.50E-27</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0009695</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Jasmonic acid biosynthetic process</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4.20E-23</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6.70E-20</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0031408</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Oxylipin biosynthetic process</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6.20E-23</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6.70E-20</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0009694</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Jasmonic acid metabolic process</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3.00E-22</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.40E-19</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0031407</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Oxylipin metabolic process</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4.20E-22</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.70E-19</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="t8">
      <label>Table 8</label>
      <caption>
        <title>GOE analysis of DEGs obtained under low-stringency conditions.</title>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
        <colgroup>
          <col align="left"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
          <col align="center"/>
        </colgroup>
        <thead valign="bottom">
          <tr>
            <th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>GOE in Phx</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>Term</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>P-value</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">
              <bold>FDR</bold>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0010167</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Response to nitrate</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3.70E-15</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6.20E-12</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0015706</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Nitrate transport</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.20E-14</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.00E-11</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0015698</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Inorganic anion transport</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5.10E-13</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.80E-10</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0010106</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Cellular response to iron ion starvation</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.30E-12</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5.30E-10</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0006826</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Iron ion transport</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3.30E-11</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.10E-08</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GOE in Brz</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0006354</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">RNA elongation</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.50E-46</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">4.90E-43</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0015979</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Photosynthesis</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.10E-23</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.80E-20</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0006091</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Generation of precursor metabolites and energy</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.00E-17</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.10E-14</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0019684</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Photosynthesis, light reaction</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">8.90E-13</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">7.20E-10</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0009145</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Purine nucleoside triphosphate biosynthetic process</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">6.10E-11</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">3.90E-08</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GOE in Ethylene</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#xA0;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0032774</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">RNA biosynthetic process</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0011</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.066</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0023034</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Intracellular signaling pathway</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.00077</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.066</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0006350</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Transcription</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0011</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.066</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0006351</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Transcription, DNA-dependent</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0011</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.066</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">GO:0048523</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Negative regulation of cellular process</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.00062</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.066</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
