<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4575152</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26381651</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138235</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-09705</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Derepression of Mineral Phosphate Solubilization Phenotype by Insertional Inactivation of <italic>iclR</italic> in <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic></article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Derepression of MPS Phenotype by <italic>iclR</italic> Inactivation in <italic>K. pneumonia</italic></alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Rajput</surname>
            <given-names>Mahendrapal Singh</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Iyer</surname>
            <given-names>Bhagya</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pandya</surname>
            <given-names>Maharshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="econtrib001">
            <sup>&#x2021;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jog</surname>
            <given-names>Rahul</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="econtrib001">
            <sup>&#x2021;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>G</surname>
            <given-names>Naresh Kumar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="econtrib001">
            <sup>&#x2021;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rajkumar</surname>
            <given-names>Shalini</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff001">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Institute of Science, Nirma University, Ahmedabad, Gujarat, India</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff002">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Environmental Molecular Biology Laboratory, Division of Biosphere, Faculty of Environmental Earth Science, Hokkaido University, Sapporo, Hokkaido, Japan</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff003">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Molecular Microbial Biochemistry Laboratory, Department of Biochemistry, Faculty of Science, Maharaja Sayajirao University of Baroda, Vadodara, Gujarat, India</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Berg</surname>
            <given-names>Ivan</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>University of Freiburg, GERMANY</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MSR SR NKG. Performed the experiments: MSR BI MP RJ. Analyzed the data: SR MSR NKG. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SR NKG. Wrote the paper: SR MSR BI.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="econtrib001">
          <p>&#x2021; These authors also contributed equally to this work.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>shalini.rjk@nirmauni.ac.in</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>9</issue>
      <elocation-id>e0138235</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2015 Rajput et al</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Rajput et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0138235.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>The mode of succinate mediated repression of mineral phosphate solubilization and the role of repressor in suppressing phosphate solubilization phenotype of two free-living nitrogen fixing <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> strains was studied. Organic acid mediated mineral phosphate solubilization phenotype of oxalic acid producing <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> SM6 and SM11 were transcriptionally repressed by IclR in presence of succinate as carbon source. Oxalic acid production and expression of genes of the glyoxylate shunt (<italic>aceBAK</italic>) was found only in glucose but not in succinate- and glucose+succinate-grown cells. IclR, repressor of <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon, was inactivated using an allelic exchange system resulting in derepressed mineral phosphate solubilization phenotype through constitutive expression of the glyoxylate shunt. Insertional inactivation of <italic>iclR</italic> resulted in increased activity of the glyoxylate shunt enzymes even in succinate-grown cells. An augmented phosphate solubilization up to 54 and 59% soluble phosphate release was attained in glucose+succinate-grown SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; strains respectively, compared to glucose-grown cells, whereas phosphate solubilization was absent or negligible in wildtype cells grown in glucose+succinate. Both wildtype and <italic>iclR</italic> deletion strains showed similar indole-3-acetic acid production. Wheat seeds inoculated with wildtype SM6 and SM11 improved both root and shoot length by 1.2 fold. However, <italic>iclR</italic> deletion SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; strains increased root and shoot length by 1.5 and 1.4 folds, respectively, compared to uninoculated controls. The repressor inactivated phosphate solubilizers better served the purpose of constitutive phosphate solubilization in pot experiments, where presence of other carbon sources (e.g., succinate) might repress mineral phosphate solubilization phenotype of wildtype strains.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>Dr. SR received the financial grant from the Department of Science and Technology (Ministry of Science, India) (Project Sanction number SERB/F/1433/1014-15). The authors would like to acknowledge the Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR), Government of India, for providing senior research fellowship to Mahendrapal Singh Rajput (Ack No. 113827/2K12/1) and the Department of Science and Technology (DST), Government of India for providing INSPIRE fellowship to Bhagya Iyer (IF130895). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="6"/>
        <table-count count="3"/>
        <page-count count="15"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta id="data-availability">
          <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
          <meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability</title>
      <p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Mineral phosphate solubilization (MPS) is one of the most desirable traits of plant growth promoting rhizobacteria (PGPR). <italic>Klebsiella</italic> is known for plant growth promoting (PGP) activities like phosphate (P) solubilization, indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) production, siderophore production and HCN production [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The existence of <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> associated to nitrogen fixation in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum L</italic>.<italic>)</italic> has been reported [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], while <italic>Klebsiella</italic> strains endophytic to rice, maize, sugarcane and banana have also been reported [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p>
      <p>The principal mode of MPS is organic acid secretion by rhizospheric microorganisms [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Among organic acids responsible for MPS phenotype, gluconic acid, 2-ketogluconic acid, oxalic acid, acetic acid, citric acid, succinic acid and glyoxylic acid are the major ones [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Organic acid production by bacteria depends on the carbon source utilized, as the organic acids produced are intermediates of the central carbon metabolism.</p>
      <p>The central metabolic pathways in bacteria are controlled by a set of global and local regulators depending on the carbon sources available and the culture conditions [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Carbon catabolite repression (CCR) controls the uptake and metabolism of a preferred carbon source when bacteria are exposed to more than one carbon sources. CCR has been extensively studied in the <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> and <italic>Firmicutes</italic> where it is mediated by components of the phosphoenolpyruvate (PEP): carbohydrate phosphotransferase system (PTS), but the mechanisms are different in these groups [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>, the preferential utilization of glucose over other carbon sources is controlled by catabolite repression protein (CRP) and PTS [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p>
      <p>In our previous report, we have shown that <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> SM6 and SM11 solubilized mineral phosphate by production of oxalic acid when grown in glucose as sole carbon source [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. However, acid production and MPS phenotype of both these strains were repressed in the presence of succinate [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Oxalic acid was produced in these bacteria from glyoxylate by the action of glyoxylate oxidase (GO) [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Genes of the glyoxylate shunt in the <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> family are clustered in the <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon under the control of an isocitrate lyase repressor (IclR) [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138235.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon codes for malate synthase (<italic>aceB</italic>), isocitrate lyase (<italic>aceA</italic>) and isocitrate dehydrogenase kinase/phosphatase (<italic>aceK</italic>) [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138235.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Isocitrate lyase (ICL) cleaves isocitrate into glyoxylate and succinate, malate synthase (MS) catalyzes the condensation of acetyl-CoA and glyoxylate to form malate, while isocitrate dehydrogenase kinase/phosphatase inactivates/activates isocitrate dehydrogenase [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138235.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p>
      <p>The IclR class of transcriptional regulators was first reported in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138235.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Regulators of the IclR family have been shown to control diverse cell functions like carbon metabolism in the <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], catabolism of aromatic compounds in soil bacteria [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], quorum-sensing signals in <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and plant virulence in certain enterobacteria [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. IclR (glyoxylate shunt repressor) is the best-characterized member of the IclR family in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>, which regulates the <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon encoding proteins for acetate utilization [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138235.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p>
      <p>In the present study, we investigated the role of <italic>iclR</italic> in catabolite repression of oxalic acid production in P solubilizing <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> SM6 and SM11. To understand the molecular mechanism of succinate mediated repression of oxalic acid linked MPS phenotype, <italic>&#x394;iclR</italic> mutants <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; were generated and assessed for relieved repression of MPS phenotype. Although both strains are genetically similar and produce oxalic acid, they vary considerably in quantity of oxalic acid produced and activities of ICL and GO, as described previously [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Hence, both strains were considered for further studies. Based on expression profile, enzyme activities and physiological studies, we have identified <italic>iclR</italic> as putative repressor of oxalic acid linked MPS phenotype in our isolates. <italic>iclR</italic> inactivation showed derepression of the glyoxylate shunt enzymes and enhanced the MPS phenotype in presence of succinate and glucose. To check the effect of wildtype and <italic>&#x394;iclR</italic> strains on plant growth, pot experiments were conducted under controlled conditions. Indeed, the deletion of <italic>iclR</italic> improved plant growth, compared to the wildtype.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="sec003">
        <title>Bacterial strains, plasmids and growth conditions</title>
        <p>The bacterial strains and plasmids used in this study are listed in <xref rid="pone.0138235.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> DH5&#x3B1;, <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6, <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM11 <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6&#x394; and <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM11&#x394; were grown aerobically on LB medium (Himedia Laboratories, India) at 30&#xB0;C. <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6 and <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM11 were deposited at Microbial Culture Collection (MCC), Pune with accession numbers MCC2730 and MCC2716, respectively. For plate cultures, 1.5% agar was added to LB medium before autoclaving. Temperature sensitive mutants and temperature sensitive plasmid-carrying strains were grown at 28&#xB0;C. Antibiotics ampicillin, erythromycin and kanamycin were added to the medium at a concentration of 50 &#x3BC;g ml<sup>-1</sup>, as and when required. Culture stocks were preserved in 50% (v/v) glycerol and stored at -20&#xB0;C. Antibiotics, salts, reagents and carbon sources were acquired from Merck-Millipore, Germany.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0138235.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138235.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Bacterial strains and plasmids used in the study.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0138235.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0138235.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strains</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relevant Characteristics</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source or Reference</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> DH5&#x3B1;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Host, <italic>&#x394;lacU169 (&#x3D5;80lacZ&#x394;M15) recA1</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P solubilizing, free-living N<sub>2</sub> fixer, Host, Wildtype (GenBank accession number JX139003)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P solubilizing, free-living N<sub>2</sub> fixer, Host, Wildtype (GenBank accession number JX139004)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6&#x394;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x394;iclR</italic>, P solubilizing, free-living N<sub>2</sub> fixer, Host</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM11&#x394;</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x394;iclR</italic>, P solubilizing, free-living N<sub>2</sub> fixer, Host</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Plasmids</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pUC18</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amp<sup>R</sup>, <italic>LacZ&#x3B1;</italic>, pBR322 origin, cloning vector</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pcDNA3.1 (+)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kan<sup>R</sup>, Amp<sup>R</sup>, T7 promoter, CMV promoter, Mammalian expression vector</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Invitrogen, USA</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGRG36</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amp<sup>R</sup>, Tn7 insertion vector, pSC101 origin of replication <italic>oriTS</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pRV85</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ery<sup>R</sup>, <italic>gfp</italic><sub>uv</sub>, <italic>pldh</italic>L promoter</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pSMB1a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386 bp SM6 <italic>iclR</italic>-N&#x2019; fragment at PstI:XbaI site of pUC18, Amp<sup>R</sup>, pBR322 origin</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pSMB2a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">363 bp SM6 <italic>iclR</italic>-C&#x2019; fragment at SmaI:SacI site of pSMB1a, Amp<sup>R</sup>, pBR322 origin</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pSMB3a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">890 bp <italic>kanR</italic> gene at BamHI site of pSMB2a, Amp<sup>R</sup> pBR322 origin,</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pSMB4a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pSC101 temperature sensitive origin of replication, cloned in NdeI:PciI digested pSMB3a, <italic>oriTS</italic>, <italic>iclR</italic>-N&#x2019;, <italic>iclR</italic>-C&#x2019;, Kan<sup>R</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pSMB5a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pldhL</italic>:<italic>gfp</italic><sub><italic>uv</italic></sub> fragment from pRV85 digested with EcoRI, cloned at EcoRI site of pSMB4a, pSC101 <italic>oriTS</italic>, <italic>iclR</italic>-N&#x2019;, <italic>iclR</italic>-C&#x2019;, Kan<sup>R</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pSMB1b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386 bp SM11 <italic>iclR</italic>-N&#x2019; fragment at PstI:XbaI site of pUC18, Amp<sup>R</sup>, pBR322 origin</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pSMB2b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">363 bp SM11 <italic>iclR</italic>-C&#x2019; fragment at SmaI:SacI site of pSMB1b, Amp<sup>R</sup>, pBR322 origin</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pSMB3b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">890 bp <italic>kanR</italic> gene at BamHI site of pSMB2b, Amp<sup>R</sup> pBR322 origin,</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pSMB4b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pSC101 temperature sensitive origin of replication, cloned in NdeI:PciI digested pSMB3b, <italic>oriTS</italic>, <italic>iclR</italic>-N&#x2019;, <italic>iclR</italic>-C&#x2019;, Kan<sup>R</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pSMB5b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pldhL</italic>:<italic>gfp</italic><sub><italic>uv</italic></sub> fragment from pRV85 digested with EcoRI, cloned at EcoRI site of pSMB4b, pSC101 <italic>oriTS</italic>, <italic>iclR</italic>-N&#x2019;, <italic>iclR</italic>-C&#x2019;, Kan<sup>R</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t001fn001">
              <p>Amp<sup>R</sup> ampicillin resistance, Kan<sup>R</sup> kanamycin resistance, Ery<sup>R</sup> erythromycin resistance, <italic>oriTS</italic> temperature sensitive origin of replication, <italic>pldhL Lactobacillus</italic> lactate dehydrogenase promoter, <italic>gfp</italic><sub><italic>uv</italic></sub> UV excitable green fluorescent protein.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec004">
        <title>Growth studies and enzyme assays</title>
        <p>Effect of carbon source on growth of wildtype and mutant strains was studied as described previously [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. To study mono- and diauxic growth of the cultures, they were grown in M9 minimal medium with 20 mM glucose, 20 mM succinate and 10 mM glucose+succinate as carbon source. Glucose utilization in liquid media was quantified by Glucose-SLR Reagent (Lab-Care Diagnostics, India) [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Activities of ICL and GO were determined in cell extracts of glucose-, succinate- and glucose+succinate-grown cells as described previously by Dixon and Kornberg [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and Akamatsu and Shimada [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], respectively, with some modifications [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Cell extract was prepared as described by Buch et al. [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], with mid-log phase cells, harvested by centrifugation at 12,000 rpm for 5 min at 4&#xB0;C. The cell pellet was washed with 80 mM phosphate buffer (pH 7.5) and resuspended in small volume of same buffer with 20% glycerol and 1 mM DTT. The cell suspension was sonicated using Ultrasonic homogenizer JY92-IIDN (Syclon, China) for 2 min at a pulse rate of 30 at 500 Hz on ice. Cell debris were removed by centrifugation at 12,000 rpm at 4&#xB0;C for 30 min and the supernatant was used for enzyme assays.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec005">
        <title>Determination of MPS phenotype</title>
        <p>Qualitative and quantitative estimation of phosphate solubilization was carried out to assess if <italic>iclR</italic> inactivation relieved succinate-mediated repression of MPS phenotype in SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; strains. Qualitative estimation of MPS phenotype of wildtype and mutant strains was performed on Pikovskaya agar [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] and Tris rock phosphate (TRP) agar, as described previously [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. TRP agar contained 100 mM glucose, 100 mM succinate or equimolar mixture of glucose and succinate (50 mM each; repression medium) as carbon sources; Pikovskaya agar contained glucose (10 g L<sup>-1</sup>) or equimolar mixture of glucose and succinate (5 g L<sup>-1</sup> each; repression medium) as carbon sources; Pikovskaya broth contained glucose (10 g L<sup>-1</sup>) or equimolar mixture of glucose and succinate (5 g L<sup>-1</sup> each; repression medium) as carbon sources. Quantitative estimation of P solubilization was carried out in Pikovskaya broth, as described by Rajput et al [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], and phosphate released was quantified as described by Ames [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In this method, soluble phosphate reacts with ammonium molybdate to give phosphomolybdate, which is further reduced by ascorbic acid to give a blue colored complex that can be quantified at 820 nm [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec006">
        <title>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and product purification</title>
        <p>PCR amplifications were carried out for expression studies and vector construction. Primers used for DNA amplification are listed in <xref rid="pone.0138235.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Primers for <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6, SM11, SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; were designed using nucleotide sequences of closely related <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> strains available at NCBI. Genomic DNA was isolated from overnight grown cultures using GeneJET genomic DNA purification kit (Thermo Scientific, USA) following the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. Plasmid isolation from cells grown in LB medium with ampicillin, erythromycin and kanamycin was performed using a GeneJET plasmid miniprep kit (Thermo Scientific, USA). pcDNA3.1 was used as PCR template for amplification of kanamycin resistance gene, pGRG36 for pSC101 <italic>oriTS</italic>, and genomic DNA of <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6 and SM11 for <italic>iclR</italic>-N&#x2019; and <italic>iclR</italic>-C&#x2019; fragments. All PCR amplifications were carried out in a Nexus Gradient Mastercycler (Eppendorf, Germany). The reaction mixture for PCR amplification was as follows: 200 ng template DNA, 200 &#x3BC;M of each of the four dNTPs, 20 pmol of each forward and reverse primer, 2 U Maxima Hot Start <italic>Taq</italic> DNA polymerase (Thermo Scientific, USA) and 1X Maxima Hot Start <italic>Taq</italic> Buffer (Thermo Scientific, USA), in final volume of 20 &#x3BC;l. The PCR parameters were as follows: 4 min initial denaturation at 95&#xB0;C, 35 X (1 min denaturation at 95&#xB0;C, 1 min primer annealing at 50&#x2013;60&#xB0;C (depending on the Tm and G+C content of the primers, see <xref rid="pone.0138235.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), 0.5&#x2013;2.5 min primer extension at 72&#xB0;C (see <xref rid="pone.0138235.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>)) and a final extension of 10 min at 72&#xB0;C. PCR products were analysed on 1% agarose gel. PCR products used for cloning were purified using GeneJET gel extraction and DNA cleanup micro kit (Thermo Scientific, USA). Primers were procured from Integrated DNA Technologies, Inc. (Coralville, USA)</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0138235.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138235.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Primers used in the study.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0138235.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0138235.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primers</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relevant Characteristics (5&#x2019;&#x2192;3&#x2019;)</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annealing Temperature</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer Extension time</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IclRN&#x2019;-F</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAT<underline>CTGCAG</underline>TTCGCGATGGCCACTAC, with PstI underlined site, located 58 bp downstream of <italic>iclR</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IclRN&#x2019;-R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCG<underline>TCTAGA</underline>GAGCACCGCCAGATTCA, with XbaI underlined site, located 445 bp downstream of <italic>iclR</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IclRC&#x2019;-F</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAT<underline>CCCGGG</underline>GACCACCAGGCGATCATTA, with SmaI underlined site, located 454 bp downstream of <italic>iclR</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IclRC&#x2019;-R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACG<underline>GAGCTC</underline>CATCGGTCATACGCGAGAT, with SacI underlined site, located 818 bp downstream of <italic>iclR</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KanR-F</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCC<underline>GGATCC</underline>CCGGGAGCTTGTATATCCATTT, with BamHI underlined site, located 60bp upstream of <italic>kanR</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KanR-R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCC<underline>GGATCC</underline>TCGCTTGGTCGGTCATTTC, with BamHI underlined site, located 17 bp downstream of <italic>kanR</italic> stop codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OriTS-F</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCC<underline>ACATGT</underline>CCCTGTAGCGGCGCATTAAG, with PciI underlined site, located 973 bp upstream of pSC101 <italic>oriTS</italic>.</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OriTS-R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAA<underline>CATATG</underline>TGGTGAACAGCTTTAAATGCACC, with NdeI underlined site, located 1098 bp downstream of pSC101 <italic>oriTS</italic>.</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AceB-F</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACCGATGAACTGGCCTTTA, binds 21 bp downstream of <italic>aceB</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AceB-R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GATTGGGCTGCAACTGATAGA, binds 478 bp downstream of <italic>aceB</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AceA-F</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCGCGCTTTATCGACTACTT, binds 433 bp downstream of <italic>aceA</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AceA-R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGATCCGGTTTCGACGTTTC binds 865 bp downstream of <italic>aceA</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AceK-F</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTAAACGCCTTATCCGGTCTAC, binds 35 bp downstream of <italic>aceK</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AceK-R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGTGATGCGGTAGAAGAGTATG, binds 462 bp downstream of <italic>aceK</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IclR-F</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCATCGGTCATACGCGAGAT binds 77 bp downstream of <italic>iclR</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IclR-R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGCCTGCTGATGGAAGATT binds 480 bp downstream of <italic>iclR</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GyrA-F</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGAAATCAGGGCCAGGAATATG, binds 1983 bp downstream of gyrA start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GyrA-R</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGTTGGTGACGTAATCGGTAAA, binds 2407 bp downstream of <italic>gyrA</italic> start codon</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54&#xB0;C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 min</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t002fn001">
              <p>Restriction sites added at the 5&#x2019; end of primer are underlined.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec007">
        <title>Expression studies</title>
        <p>Total RNA was isolated from glucose-, succinate- and glucose+succinate-grown <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6, SM11, SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; cells using GeneJET RNA purification kit (Thermo Scientific, USA) following manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions, except that the cells were washed twice with sterile NaCl solution (0.8%) and resuspended in the same solution before RNA purification. Purified RNA was quantified by measuring absorbance at 260 nm, and the quality and purity was confirmed by electrophoresis on 1.5% agarose gel containing 1.9% (v/v) formaldehyde. cDNA was synthesized from isolated RNA using First Strand cDNA synthesis kit (Thermo Scientific, USA) following manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. cDNA was used as template for analysing expression of <italic>aceB</italic>, <italic>aceA</italic>, <italic>aceK</italic>, <italic>iclR</italic> and <italic>gyrA</italic> genes in glucose-, succinate- and glucose+succinate-grown cells. DNA Gyrase A (<italic>gyrA</italic>) was used as internal control to standardize expression and mRNA levels.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec008">
        <title>Construction of <italic>iclR</italic> mutants by insertion of a kanamycin cassette</title>
        <p>The <italic>iclR</italic> gene was inactivated employing an allelic exchange system in SM6 and SM11 strains to generate SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; strains, respectively. To achieve this, pSMB5a and pSMB5b vectors were constructed with 386 bp and 363 bp <italic>iclR</italic> N&#x2019; and C&#x2019; gene fragments (of SM6 and SM11, respectively) flanking kanamycin resistance gene, <italic>pldhL</italic>:<italic>gfp</italic><sub><italic>uv</italic></sub>, and pSC101 temperature controlled origin of replication to direct the integration and excision of vector. <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> DH5&#x3B1; was used routinely as a host strain for cloning experiments. DNA was introduced into <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> using Bacterial TransformAid kit (Thermo Scientific, USA). 386 bp <italic>iclR</italic>-N&#x2019; PstI-XbaI fragment was amplified from genomic DNA of <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6 and SM11 using primers IclRN&#x2019;-F and IclRN&#x2019;-R. The amplicon was cloned in pUC18 digested with PstI-XbaI to generate pSMB1a and pSMB1b, respectively. 363 bp <italic>iclR-</italic>C&#x2019; SmaI-SacI fragment was amplified with IclRC&#x2019;-F and IclRC&#x2019;-R primers and cloned in SmaI-SacI digested pSMB1a and pSMB1b, generating pSMB2a and pSMB2b, respectively. Kanamycin resistance gene from pcDNA3.1(+) was amplified using KanR-F and KanR-R primers with BamHI sites. 890 bp <italic>kanR</italic> gene was ligated at <italic>Bam</italic>HI site of pSMB2a and pSMB2b between <italic>iclR-N&#x2019;</italic> and <italic>iclR-C&#x2019;</italic> fragments creating pSMB3a and pSMB3b, respectively. Successful insertion was confirmed by kanamycin resistant colonies on LB agar plate with kanamycin (50 &#x3BC;g ml<sup>-1</sup>), restriction digestion of isolated plasmids and amplification of kanamycin resistance gene from pSMB3a and pSMB3b. 2297 bp <italic>oriTS</italic> was amplified from pGRG36 using oriTS-F and oriTS-R primers with PciI and NdeI flanking sites. pSMB3a and pSMB3b were then digested with PciI and NdeI, and resultant 2288 bp fragment was ligated with 2297 bp PciI and NdeI digested <italic>oriTS</italic>. Thus, ampicillin resistance gene with pBR322 origin of replication in pSMB3a and pSMB3b was replaced by pSC101 temperature sensitive origin of replication to give pSMB4a and pSMB4b. pRV85 was digested with EcoRI to release <italic>pldhL</italic>:<italic>gfp</italic><sub><italic>uv</italic></sub> fragment and was cloned at EcoRI site of pSMB4a and pSMB4b. Restriction enzymes were acquired from New England Biolabs (Ipswich, Mass.). <xref rid="pone.0138235.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref> shows diagrammatic representation of pSMB5a and pSMB5b construction. pSMB5a-transformed SM6 and pSMB5b-transformed SM11 cells were grow on LB medium with kanamycin and checked for fluorescence under UV light at 28&#xB0;C (permissive temperature for replication of <italic>oriTS</italic>) and at 40&#xB0;C (non-permissive temperature) for integration into genome. The <italic>&#x394;iclR</italic> strains were selected for kanamycin resistance and absence of green fluorescence. The integration of pSMB5a and pSMB5b in the genome of SM6 and SM11 strains, respectively, was verified by PCR, loss of green fluorescence and expression of <italic>iclR</italic>. For PCR verification, chromosomal DNA of transformants was amplified using specific forward primer annealing to regions upstream of <italic>iclR</italic> and reverse primer of kanamycin resistance gene (data not shown). The loss of green fluorescence was due to curing of pSMB5a and pSMB5b. <italic>iclR</italic> inactivation and resultant expression of <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon genes were also confirmed by expression studies.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec009">
        <title>Indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) production</title>
        <p><italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> wildtype and <italic>&#x394;iclR</italic> strains were screened for IAA production in the LB medium containing tryptophan (1 mg ml<sup>-1</sup>). The medium was inoculated with 100 &#x3BC;l of overnight-grown bacterial culture and incubated on orbital shaker at 150 rpm for 48 h at 28&#xB0;C. Quantitative estimation of IAA production was performed, as described by Gordon and Weber [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], using Salkowski reagent containing 10 g L<sup>-1</sup> (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>MoO<sub>4</sub>, 10 ml L<sup>-1</sup> H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> and 5 g L<sup>-1</sup> FeSO<sub>4</sub>.7H<sub>2</sub>O. Uninoculated medium was taken as control.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec010">
        <title>Pot experiments</title>
        <p>Pot experiments were carried out with Wheat (var. Lokwan) (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>), as described by Sachdev et al [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Soil samples were collected, air dried, sieved (2 mm mesh) and sterilized by repeated cycles of autoclaving. pH and total P content of the soil was determined by AES-ICP (Model: 330RL, Perkin-Elmer). Soil used for pot experiments was brown, sandy and loamy, with pH 7.3 and total P content 0.12 g L<sup>-1</sup>. Approximately 1 kg of sterile soil was distributed per pot, and sterile seeds were inoculated with SM6, SM11, SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; strains (10<sup>6</sup>&#x2212;10<sup>7</sup> cfu ml<sup>-1</sup>) while seeds treated with sterile medium served as control. All pots were maintained in a greenhouse under natural sunlight (10 h day and 14 h night cycle), temperature (average 25&#xB0;C) and supplied with 150&#x2013;200 ml autoclaved water per pot per day. Plants were gently uprooted on 31<sup>st</sup> day and scored for root length (cm), shoot length (cm), root: shoot ratio and dry mass (g).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec011">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>All the experiments were performed in triplicates, and the values in results are mean &#xB1; standard deviation, averaged for data analysis. The plant experiment data were expressed as mean &#xB1; standard deviation and an analysis of variance (ANOVA) to test the significance of differences was performed with the statistical program Prism&#xAE; (GraphPad 5.0, USA). The differences between the parameters were evaluated using Tukey&#x2019;s test (Prism&#xAE; software). P values &#x2264; 0.05 were considered to be statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="sec012">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="sec013">
        <title>Expression analysis of <italic>iclR</italic> and <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon genes</title>
        <p>The differential operation of the glyoxylate shunt in glucose-, succinate- and glucose+succinate-grown <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6 and SM11 was studied through expression analysis of the glyoxylate shunt (i.e. <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon) genes and its transcriptional repressor <italic>iclR</italic>. Genes of the glyoxylate shunt <italic>aceB</italic>, <italic>aceA</italic> and <italic>aceK</italic> were expressed only when glucose was the sole carbon source, whereas <italic>iclR</italic> was expressed when succinate was the sole carbon source or when present along with glucose (<xref rid="pone.0138235.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A and 1B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0138235.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138235.g001</object-id>
          <label>Fig 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Expression profile of <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon genes and <italic>iclR</italic> in glucose-, glucose+succinate-and succinate-grown <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> strains (a) SM6, (b) SM11, (c) SM6&#x394; and (d) SM11&#x394;.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0138235.g001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec014">
        <title><italic>iclR</italic> inactivation and confirmation</title>
        <p><italic>iclR</italic> deletion strains SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; retained kanamycin resistance while <italic>gfp</italic><sub>uv</sub> used as second selectable marker was lost after the second recombination. This was due to plasmid curing of pSMB5a and pSMB5b when transformant SM6 and SM11 were subjected to reinouclation in LB with kanamycin and temperature cycles, and <italic>kanR</italic> integration disrupts <italic>iclR</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0138235.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>). <xref rid="pone.0138235.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1C and 1D</xref> show expression analysis of <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon genes and <italic>iclR</italic> of glucose-, succinate- and glucose+succinate-grown SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394;. Expression of <italic>iclR</italic> was not observed in succinate- and glucose+succinate-grown <italic>iclR</italic> inactive SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394;.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec015">
        <title>Physiological activities and enzyme activities of the glyoxylate shunt and GO</title>
        <p><xref rid="pone.0138235.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2A and 2B</xref> show monoauxic growth profile of SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; when grown on glucose and succinate. No significant difference in growth pattern was observed for both mutants in either of the carbon sources as compared to the wildtype cultures. Glucose favoured the maximum growth, and cells entered exponential phase within 2&#x2013;3 h of inoculation, reaching maximum optical density (OD) with stationary phase in 4&#x2013;5 h. Growth on succinate was observed after a lag phase and was slower than on glucose. This may be because succinate is a poor carbon source for enterobacteria like <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Similarly, no significant difference was observed in the diauxic growth profile and carbon utilization pattern of <italic>iclR</italic> mutants SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394;, as compared to wildtype SM6 and SM11. Glucose was utilized preferentially over succinate in both the mutants and 90&#x2013;100% of glucose was consumed within first 5&#x2013;6 h of incubation, while succinate was utilized only when glucose was exhausted in the media (<xref rid="pone.0138235.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2C and 2D</xref>). The specific activities of ICL and GO in glucose- and succinate-grown SM6 and SM11 cells and their <italic>iclR</italic> inactivated counterparts SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; are depicted in <xref rid="pone.0138235.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0138235.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138235.g002</object-id>
          <label>Fig 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Monoauxic growth profile of (a) SM6&#x394; and (b) SM11&#x394;, and diauxic growth profile of (c) SM6&#x394; and (d) SM11&#x394;.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0138235.g002"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone.0138235.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138235.g003</object-id>
          <label>Fig 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Enzyme activity of glucose- and succinate-grown SM6, SM11, SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394;: (a) ICL (b) GO.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0138235.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p><italic>iclR</italic> inactivation resulted in 3.2 fold increase in ICL activity of succinate-grown SM6&#x394;, as compared to wildtype SM6, and in high activity in succinate-grown SM11&#x394;, whereas ICL was undetectable in SM11 strain. The ICL activity of succinate-grown SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; was 74.6% and 73.2% as compared to that of glucose-grown cells. The ICL activity in succinate-grown wildtype SM6 and SM11 cells was 20.7% and 0% respectively, when compared to the glucose-grown cells [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Similarly, an enhanced GO activity was observed in succinate-grown SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; (<xref rid="pone.0138235.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3A</xref>). Based on the published data [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and present findings, we propose a metabolic scheme that explains the MPS phenotype in the wildtype SM6 and SM11 strains during grown on glucose or on succinate (or on glucose+succinate) (<xref rid="pone.0138235.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0138235.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138235.g004</object-id>
          <label>Fig 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Carbon metabolism linked P solubilization in (A) glucose and (B) succinate or glucose+succinate-grown <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> SM6 and SM11.</title>
            <p>Glucose is metabolized by EMP pathway and acetate is overproduced, which can be then activated to acetyl-CoA. Acetyl-CoA is incorporated in the TCA and the glyoxylate shunt. During growth on succinate, gluconeogenesis is required for the formation of PEP and further intermediates of the EMP pathway, whereas the TCA cycle serves as the main catabolic process under these conditions. MS, malate synthase; ICL, isocitrate lyase; ICDP/K, isocitrate dehydrogenase kinase/phosphatase; IclR, isocitrate lyase repressor; <italic>P</italic>, promoter; POXB, pyruvate oxidase B; ACS, AMP-forming acetyl-CoA synthetase; PDHC, pyruvate dehydrogenase complex; PPS, phosphoenolpyruvate synthase; PKS, pyruvate kinase; PEP-CK, phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase; CS, citrate synthase; ACN, aconitase; SUC, succinyl-CoA synthetase complex; ICDH, isocitrate dehydrogenase; SDH, succinate dehydrogenase; FUM, fumarase; MDH, malate dehydrogenase.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0138235.g004"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec016">
        <title>P solubilization by <italic>iclR</italic> mutants</title>
        <p><xref rid="pone.0138235.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref> shows soluble P released in Pikovskaya broth with glucose and glucose+succinate. The maximum P solubilized by SM6 and SM11 strains in media with glucose+succinate was only 3.8 and 1.5%, respectively, as compared to P solubilized with glucose [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The amount of P solubilized in glucose media by the wildtype strains was almost equivalent to that of the corresponding <italic>&#x394;iclR</italic> strains. SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; were enhanced in P solubilization in glucose+succinate medium, reaching up to 54 and 59% in comparison to glucose medium. <xref rid="pone.0138235.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref> shows mineral phosphate solubilization in Pikovskaya agar and rock phosphate solubilization in TRP agar by SM6, SM11, SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; in presence of glucose and glucose+succinate.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0138235.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138235.g005</object-id>
          <label>Fig 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>P released by (a) SM6 and SM11, and (b) SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; in Pikovskaya broth with glucose (G) and glucose+succinate (GS).</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0138235.g005"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone.0138235.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138235.g006</object-id>
          <label>Fig 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>MPS phenotype of wildtype SM6 and SM11 on (a) TRP agar with glucose (b) TRP agar with glucose+succinate (c) Pikovskaya agar with glucose (d) Pikovskaya agar with glucose+succinate, and MPS phenotype of SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; on (e) TRP agar with glucose (f) TRP agar with glucose+succinate (g) Pikovskaya agar with glucose (h) Pikovskaya agar with glucose+succinate.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0138235.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec017">
        <title>IAA Production</title>
        <p>SM6 and SM11 produced 18.1 &#xB1; 0.9 &#x3BC;g ml<sup>-1</sup> and 18.7 &#xB1; 1.1 &#x3BC;g ml<sup>-1</sup> of IAA, respectively, while 17.6 &#xB1; 1.2 &#x3BC;g ml<sup>-1</sup> and 19.5 &#xB1; 1.1 &#x3BC;g ml<sup>-1</sup> IAA was produced by SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; respectively, in LB medium supplemented with tryptophan.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec018">
        <title>Effect of wildtype and <italic>iclR</italic> inactivated strains on plant growth</title>
        <p>Wildtype and <italic>&#x394;iclR</italic> strains improved plant growth over the control (<xref rid="pone.0138235.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Plants inoculated with the SM6 and SM11 strains increased root length and shoot length, while the growth improvement with SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; strains was even more prominent. SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; treated plants had significantly higher root length and shoot length compared to wildtype.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0138235.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138235.t003</object-id>
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Growth parameters of wheat plants in the presence of <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6, SM11, SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394; strains.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0138235.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0138235.t003"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#xA0;</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root length (cm) <xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shoot length (cm) <xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root: Shoot ratio</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry mass (mg) <xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.2 &#xB1; 1.8</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7 &#xB1; 1.7</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241.1 &#xB1; 19.5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7 &#xB1; 2.16</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8 &#xB1; 1.8</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">290.4 &#xB1; 17.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM11</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3 &#xB1; 1.9</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6 &#xB1; 1.5</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">282.9 &#xB1; 20.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6&#x394;</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.2 &#xB1; 2.4<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>&#x2020;</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5 &#xB1; 1.7</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">324.7 &#xB1; 22.8<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>&#x2020;</sup></xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM11&#x394;</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.9 &#xB1; 3.1<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>&#x2020;</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0 &#xB1; 1.8<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>&#x2020;</sup></xref></td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">330.2 &#xB1; 24.3<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>&#x2020;</sup></xref></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t003fn001">
              <p>* Significant as compared to control (P &#x2264; 0.05).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t003fn002">
              <p>&#x2020; Significant at P &#x2264; 0.05 as compared to their respective wildtype.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t003fn003">
              <p>Values for root length, shoot length and dry mass are mean &#xB1; standard deviation of 12 plants (n = 12).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec019">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="sec020">
        <title><italic>iclR</italic> and <italic>aceBAK</italic> expression</title>
        <p>Absence of expression of <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon genes was accompanied by the repression of phosphate solubilization and acid production in succinate or glucose+succinate-grown <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6 and SM11 [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>, IclR regulates the expression of the <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon coding for isocitrate lyase (AceA), malate synthase (AceB) and isocitrate dehydrogenase kinase/phosphatase (AceK) [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Isocitrate dehydrogenase kinase/phosphatase (AceK) phosphorylates isocitrate dehydrogenase (ICD), reducing the ICD activity and therefore the carbon flux through tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Repression of the glyoxylate shunt genes is relieved and the pathway is activated, when IclR levels are low or when <italic>iclR</italic> is inactivated. This in particular occurs when cells are grown on acetate [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138235.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], or in slow-growing glucose-utilizing cultures [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138235.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p>
        <p>The expression studies of <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon genes and <italic>iclR</italic> showed the repression of MPS phenotype by succinate in SM6 and SM11. ICL cleaves isocitrate to glyoxylate and succinate, and glyoxylate is oxidized by GO to produce oxalic acid [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Succinate in growth media induced the expression of <italic>iclR</italic>, which repressed <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon and oxalic acid-mediated MPS phenotype in SM6 and SM11. As <italic>iclR</italic> was not expressed in glucose-grown cells, the glyoxylate shunt and oxalic acid production were constitutive. Flow of carbon through the glyoxylate shunt can also be explained as a measure to utilize the acetate overproduced from pyruvate in glucose-grown cells. In <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>, acetate production is usually credited to the &#x201C;overflow metabolism&#x201D; [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], and is believed to be a result of an imbalance between the energy requirement, biosynthesis and glucose uptake [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec021">
        <title><italic>iclR</italic> inactivation</title>
        <p>In the <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic>, genes of the glyoxylate shunt are encoded in <italic>aceBAK</italic> operon and are under the direct negative control of repressor IclR [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138235.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The expression of <italic>aceBAK</italic> is induced, when organisms are grown on acetate or fatty acids [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The glyoxylate bypass is required for growth on fatty acids and acetate, as they enter intermediary metabolism as acetyl-CoA. When <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> is grown in excess of glucose, the carbon flux through glycolysis surpasses the capacity of the TCA cycle, and acetate accumulation occurs [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Difference in carbon flux through the glyoxylate shunt and the TCA cycle is observed in low acetate producer <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> K strain (JM109) and high acetate producer <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> B strain (BL21). In glucose-grown <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> B cell, acetate is produced from pyruvate by pyruvate oxidase (PoxB). The acetate accumulated in cell can be converted to acetyl-CoA by acetyl-CoA synthetase (Acs), or by reversing the phosphotransacetylase-acetate kinase (Pta-AckA) pathway [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Acetyl-CoA is metabolized through the TCA cycle and the glyoxylate shunt by ICL and MS [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0138235.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Under these conditions, activation of the glyoxylate shunt in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> B strains (BL21) has been proposed as a route for internal acetate utilization (acetyl-CoA consumption), in contrast to <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> K strain (JM109) where excess acetate is secreted out [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Acetyl-CoA utilization with a higher ICL activity by activation of the glyoxylate shunt has been observed in BL21 only and not in JM109 in high glucose batch cultures [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6 and SM11 apparently resembled <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> B strain, where operation of the glyoxylate shunt is constitutive when glucose is sole carbon source. Moreover, absence of acetic acid production by SM6 and SM11 [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] also related them to <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> B strain, in contrast to <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> K strain.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec022">
        <title>Physiological experiments and enzyme activities</title>
        <p>The release of soluble P in the medium is the result of organic acid production [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The growth pattern of both <italic>iclR</italic> deletion strains was similar to that of parental wildtype strains, as reported earlier [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. This showed that <italic>iclR</italic> inactivation did not interfere with glucose and succinate utilization. Unlike rhizobacteria <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> and <italic>Rhizobium</italic>, where C<sub>4</sub> acids like succinate and malate are preferred over glucose, enterobacteria and firmicutes utilize glucose as the most preferred carbon source [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. This is mainly because of the catabolite repression and carbon uptake PTS that controls the expression of carbon metabolism genes and carbon source uptake and subsequent utilization via EMP pathway. To further confirm that succinate mediated repression of MPS phenotype, activities of ICL and GO were analysed in glucose and succinate-grown cells of wildtype and SM6&#x394; and SM11&#x394;.</p>
        <p>The ICL and GO activities measured in glucose- and succinate-grown SM6 and SM11 cells (<xref rid="pone.0138235.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>) were similar to those reported previously [<xref rid="pone.0138235.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Interestingly, <italic>iclR</italic> inactivation did not alter ICL and GO activities of the glucose-grown cells. The possible explanation for these data is that the glucose-grown cells oxidise acetyl-CoA to glyoxylate via the glyoxylate cycle, and not via the classical TCA cycle, thus providing the substrate for oxalate synthesis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec023">
        <title>MPS phenotype of <italic>iclR</italic> mutants</title>
        <p>Although the release of P mediated by <italic>&#x394;iclR</italic> strains in glucose+succinate media was still not as high as in the media containing glucose only, the results are encouraging and reveal that regulators of carbon metabolism influence the MPS phenotype, depending on the nature of an available carbon source. Derepression of the MPS phenotype during growth on glucose+succinate observed in <italic>&#x394;iclR</italic> strains was due to enhanced organic acid production. This effect was accompanied by the acidification and rock phosphate solubilization in TRP media. Thus, the carbon source-mediated repression of the MPS phenotype may be one of the reasons of failure of several phosphate solubilizing microorganisms to improve plant growth in the field experiments. Indeed, the availability of multiple carbon sources in natural conditions may lead to repression of various functional genes, including those responsible for MPS phenotype. Identification and inactivation of such regulators may abolish the repression, thus resulting in engineering of microbes to constitutive P solubilization.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec024">
        <title>Plant experiments</title>
        <p>Both, the wildtype and <italic>&#x394;iclR</italic> strains of <italic>K</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic> SM6 and SM11 improved plant growth, whereas the mutant strains were significantly more efficient in terms of root and shoot length, root: shoot ratio and dry mass. This effect of <italic>iclR</italic> inactivation was not related to increase of IAA synthesis, but rather to the P release mediated by the oxalic acid production. Indeed, we showed that the synthesis of glyoxylate, oxalate precursor, was enhanced in the mutant. Thus, the repressor inactivation may result in better performance of PGP bacteria in the rhizosphere. Free-living N<sub>2</sub> fixers with relieved constitutive MPS phenotype can serve dual purpose to plants.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec025">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0138235.s001">
        <label>S1 Fig</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Diagrammatic representation of pSMB5a and pSMB5b.</title>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0138235.s001.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0138235.s002">
        <label>S2 Fig</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Strategy for insertional inactivation of <italic>iclR</italic> by allelic exchange.</title>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0138235.s002.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref001">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ahemad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of insecticides on plant growth-promoting activities of phosphate solubilizing rhizobacterium <italic>Klebsiella</italic> sp. strain PS19</article-title>. <source>Pestic Biochem Physiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>100</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref002">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ahemad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Toxicological effects of selective herbicides on plant growth promoting activities of phosphate solubilizing <italic>Klebsiella</italic> sp. strain PS19</article-title>. <source>Curr Microbiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>532</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>538</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00284-010-9740-0">10.1007/s00284-010-9740-0</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 20721665?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20721665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref003">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ahemad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biotoxic impact of fungicides on plant growth promoting activities of phosphate-solubilizing <italic>Klebsiella</italic> sp. isolated from mustard (<italic>Brassica campestris</italic>) rhizosphere</article-title>. <source>J Pest Sci</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>85</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref004">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Iniguez</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Triplett</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nitrogen fixation in wheat provided by <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> 342</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1078</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1085</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15497400?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15497400</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref005">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chelius</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Triplett</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Immunolocalization of dinitrogenase reductase produced by <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> in association with <italic>Zea mays</italic> L</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>783</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>787</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10653751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10653751</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref006">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuang</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Using confocal laser scanning microscope to visualize the infection of rice roots by GFP-labelled <italic>Klebsiella oxytoca</italic> SA2, an endophytic diazotroph</article-title>. <source>Acta Bot Sin</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>558</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>564</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref007">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caballero-Mellaod</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orozco</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martinez-Romero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Diazotrophic bacteria associated with banana (<italic>Musa</italic> spp.)</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>257</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref008">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meunchang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thongraar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Detection of <italic>nifH</italic> Sequences in sugarcane (<italic>Saccharum officinarum</italic> L.) and pineapple (<italic>Ananas comosus</italic> [L.] Merr.)</article-title>. <source>Soil Sci Plant Nutr</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>308</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref009">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gyaneshwar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parekh</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Role of soil microorganisms in improving P nutrition of plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>245</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref010">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zaidi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Role of phosphate-solubilizing microorganisms in sustainable agriculture-A review</article-title>. <source>Agron Sustain Dev</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref011">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>G&#xF6;rke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>St&#xFC;lke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Carbon catabolite repression in bacteria: many ways to make the most out of nutrients</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>613</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>624</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro1932">10.1038/nrmicro1932</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18628769?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18628769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref012">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>St&#xFC;lke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hillen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Carbon catabolite repression in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>201</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10322165?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10322165</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref013">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>. <article-title>Protein phosphorylation and allosteric control of inducer exclusion and catabolite repression by the bacterial phosphoenolpyruvate: sugar phosphotransferase system</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>53</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>120</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 2651862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2651862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref014">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rajput</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naresh</surname><given-names>Kumar G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rajkumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Repression of oxalic acid-mediated mineral phosphate solubilization in rhizospheric isolates of <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> by succinate</article-title>. <source>Arch Microbiol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>195</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>88</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00203-012-0850-x">10.1007/s00203-012-0850-x</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23124768?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23124768</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref015">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maloy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nunn</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genetic regulation of the glyoxylate shunt in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>149</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>180</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 7033207?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7033207</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref016">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sunnarborg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klumpp</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>LaPorte</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation of the glyoxylate bypass operon: cloning and characterization of IclR</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>172</volume>: <fpage>2642</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2649</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 2185227?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2185227</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref017">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ishihama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Two different modes of transcription repression of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> acetate operon by IclR</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>194</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12492863?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12492863</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref018">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Molina-Henares</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>. <article-title>The IclR family of transcriptional activators and repressors can be defined by a single profile</article-title>. <source>Protein Sci</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1207</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1213</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16597823?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16597823</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref019">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siddiquee</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arauzo-Bravo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effect of <italic>cra</italic> gene knockout together with <italic>edd</italic> and <italic>iclR</italic> genes knockout on the metabolism in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Arc Microbiol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>190</volume>: <fpage>559</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>571</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref020">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brinkrolf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brune</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tauch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Transcriptional regulation of catabolic pathways for aromatic compounds in <italic>Corynebacterium glutamicum</italic></article-title>. <source>Genet Mol Res</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>773</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>789</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17183485?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17183485</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref021">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genetic control of quorum-sensing signal turnover in <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>99</volume>: <fpage>4638</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4643</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11930013?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11930013</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref022">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Molina-Henares</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guazzaroni</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Members of the IclR family of bacterial transcriptional regulators function as activators and/or repressors</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>186</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16472303?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16472303</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref023">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gran</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jesseet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bloomt</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanahan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Differential plasmid rescue from transgenic mouse DNAs into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> methylation-restriction mutants (bacterial restriction/ DNA methylation/ cloning mammalian DNA/ heterogeneous transgene expression/ insulin gene regulation)</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>87</volume>: <fpage>4645</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4649</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 2162051?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2162051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref024">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>New pUC-derived cloning vectors with different selectable markers and DNA-replication origins</article-title>. <source>Gene</source><year>1991</year>;<volume>100</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>194</lpage><?supplied-pmid 1905257?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1905257</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref025">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fast, easy and efficient: site-specific insertion of transgenes into Enterobacterial chromosomes using Tn7 without need for selection of the insertion event</article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2180-6-39">10.1186/1471-2180-6-39</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 16646962?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16646962</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref026">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gory</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montel</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zagorec</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Use of green fluorescent protein to monitor <italic>Lactobacillus sakei</italic> in fermented meat products</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>194</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>133</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11164296?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11164296</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref027">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kornberg</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assay methods for key enzymes of the glyoxylate cycle</article-title>. <source>Proc Biochem Soc</source>. <year>1959</year>;<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>3P</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref028">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Akamatsu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Partial purification and characterization of glyoxylate oxidase from the brown-rot basidiomycete <italic>Tyromyces palustris</italic></article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>649</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>653</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref029">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Buch</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Archana</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Metabolic channeling of glucose towards gluconate in phosphate-solubilizing <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> P4 under phosphorus deficiency</article-title>. <source>Res Microbiol</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>159</volume>:<fpage>635</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>642</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.resmic.2008.09.012">10.1016/j.resmic.2008.09.012</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18996187?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18996187</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref030">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pikovskaya</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mobilization of phosphorus in soil connection with the vital activity of some microbial species</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>. <year>1948</year>;<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>362</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>370</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref031">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ames</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assay of inorganic phosphate, total phosphate and phosphatases</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol</source>. <year>1966</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>118</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref032">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Colorimetric estimation of indole acetic acid</article-title>. <source>Plant physiol</source>. <year>1951</year>;<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>192</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>195</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16654351?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16654351</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref033">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sachdev</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chaudhari</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kasture</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dhavale</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chopade</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Isolation and characterization of indole acetic acid (IAA) producing <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> strains from rhizosphere of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) and their effect on plant growth</article-title>. <source>Indian J Exp Biol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>993</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1000</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 20329704?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20329704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref034">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Patten</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schellhorn</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Positive selection for loss of RpoS function in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Mutat. Res</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>554</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>203</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15450418?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15450418</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref035">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rittinger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Negre</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Divita</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scarabel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bonod-Bidaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goody</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> isocitrate dehydrogenase kinase/phosphatase</article-title>. <source>Eur J Biochem</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>237</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>254</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8620880?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8620880</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref036">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cortay</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Negre</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galinier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duclos</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perriere</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cozzone</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation of the acetate operon in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>: purification and functional characterization of the IclR repressor</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>675</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>679</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 2001680?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2001680</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref037">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cozzone</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation of acetate metabolism by protein phosphorylation in enteric bacteria</article-title>. <source>Ann Rev Microbiol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>164</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9891796</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref038">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>. <article-title>A novel metabolic cycle catalyzes glucose oxidation and anaplerosis in hungry <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>278</volume>: <fpage>46446</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>46451</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12963713?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12963713</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref039">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maharjan</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seeto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferenci</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role of isocitrate lyase and the glyoxylate cycle in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> growing under glucose limitation</article-title>. <source>Res Microbiol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>156</volume>: <fpage>178</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>183</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15748982?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15748982</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref040">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kayoko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takefumi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Occurrence of enzyme systems for production and decomposition of oxalate in a white-rot fungus <italic>Coriolus versicolor</italic> and some characteristics of glyoxylate oxidase</article-title>. <source>Wood Res</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>83</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref041">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Acetic acid formation in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> fermentation</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>663</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>671</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 18600996?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18600996</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref042">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kleman</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strohl</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Acetate metabolism by <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in high-cell-density fermentation</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>60</volume>: <fpage>3952</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3958</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 7993084?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7993084</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref043">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aristidou</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>San</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Metabolic engineering of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> to enhance recombinant protein production through acetate reduction</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Prog</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>478</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 7654314?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7654314</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref044">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kornberg</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role and control of the glyoxylate cycle in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>. <year>1966</year>;<volume>99</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5337756</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref045">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Majewski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Domach</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Simple constrained optimization view of acetate overflow in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>732</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>738</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 18592570?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18592570</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref046">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>TDK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones-Mortimer</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kornberg</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>. <article-title>The enzymic interconversion of acetate and acetyl-coenzyme A in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Gen Microbiol</source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>336</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 21941?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21941</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref047">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>El-Mansi</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holms</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Control of carbon flux to acetate excretion during overflow in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>732</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>738</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref048">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van de Walle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shiloach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Proposed mechanism of acetate accumulation in two recombinant <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains during high density fermentation</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>57</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10099180</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref049">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fraga</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Phosphate solubilizing bacteria and their role in plant growth promotion</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Adv</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>319</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>339</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14538133?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14538133</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref050">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chakrabartty</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Succinate mediated catabolite repression of enzymes of glucose metabolism in root-nodule bacteria</article-title>. <source>Curr Microbiol</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>251</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref051">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Postma</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lengeler</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Phosphoenolpyruvate: carbohydrate phosphotransferase systems of bacteria</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>57</volume>: <fpage>543</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>594</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8246840?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8246840</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0138235.ref052">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hager</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phibbs</surname><given-names>PV</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>. <article-title>Catabolite repression control in Pseudomonads</article-title>. <source>Res Microbiol</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>147</volume>: <fpage>551</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>561</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 9084769?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9084769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
