<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genet Mol Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genet. Mol. Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gmb</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Genetics and Molecular Biology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1415-4757</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-4685</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Gen&#xE9;tica</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5004832</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1678-4685-GMB-2015-0232</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Plant Genetics</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Genome-wide association study of drought-related resistance traits in <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>
</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Qin</surname>
            <given-names>Peng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>Yu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>Yaodong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Kun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mao</surname>
            <given-names>Shuangshuang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Zhanyi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Jirui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Yaxi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>Yuming</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <given-names>Youliang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Triticeae Research Institute, Sichuan Agricultural University,
Wenjiang, Chengdu, China</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>College of Agronomy and Biotechnology, Yunnan Agricultural
University, Kunming, China</aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Institute of Animal Genetics and Breeding, College of Animal Science
and Technology, Sichuan Agricultural University, Chengdu, China</aff>
        <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Farm Animal Genetic Resources Exploration and Innovation Key
Laboratory of Sichuan Province, Sichuan Agricultural University, Chengdu, China</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="equal" id="fn1">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="c1">Send correspondence to Yaxi Liu. Triticeae Research Institute, Sichuan
Agricultural University, Wenjiang Chengdu 611130, China. E-mail:
<email>yaxi.liu@outlook.com</email>; <email>yaxi.liu@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>07</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jul-Sep</season>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>39</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>398</fpage>
      <lpage>407</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2016, Sociedade Brasileira de
Gen&#xE9;tica.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>License information: This is an open-access article distributed under the
terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (type CC-BY), which permits
unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original article is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p>The D-genome progenitor of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>),
<italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>, possesses numerous genes for resistance to
abiotic stresses, including drought. Therefore, information on the genetic
architecture of <italic>A. tauschii</italic> can aid the development of
drought-resistant wheat varieties. Here, we evaluated 13 traits in 373 <italic>A.
tauschii</italic> accessions grown under normal and polyethylene glycol-simulated
drought stress conditions and performed a genome-wide association study using 7,185
single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) markers. We identified 208 and 28 SNPs
associated with all traits using the general linear model and mixed linear model,
respectively, while both models detected 25 significant SNPs with genome-wide
distribution. Public database searches revealed several candidate/flanking genes
related to drought resistance that were grouped into three categories according to
the type of encoded protein (enzyme, storage protein, and drought-induced protein).
This study provided essential information for SNPs and genes related to drought
resistance in <italic>A. tauschii</italic> and wheat, and represents a foundation for
breeding drought-resistant wheat cultivars using marker-assisted selection.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Aegilops tauschii</kwd>
        <kwd>drought resistance</kwd>
        <kwd>genome-wide association study</kwd>
        <kwd>single nucleotide polymorphism</kwd>
        <kwd>wheat</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <equation-count count="5"/>
        <ref-count count="57"/>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The current global climate change is projected to have a significant impact on
temperature and precipitation profiles, with consequent increases in drought incidence
and severity. It is known that severe drought occurs in nearly half of the world's
countries (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Wilhite and Glantz, 1985</xref>). Since
drought is probably the major abiotic factor limiting yields, the development of crops
that are high yielding under environmentally stressful conditions is essential (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Ergen and Budak, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Fleury <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p>
      <p>Wheat (<italic>Triticum</italic> spp.) is the leading human food source, accounting for
more than half of the world's total food consumption (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Ergen and Budak, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Habash <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2009</xref>); therefore, it is a major target for the development of
cultivars that are high-yielding under water-limited conditions. For drought-related
research and the improvement of modern crop varieties, plants exhibiting high drought
resistance are the most suitable targets and the most promising sources of
drought-related genes and gene regions. Many wild species also retain superior genetic
resources that have not yet been investigated. One such species is <italic>Aegilops
tauschii,</italic> the diploid D-genome progenitor of hexaploid wheat (<italic>T.
aestivum</italic>). <italic>A. tauschii</italic> is more drought resistant than
<italic>T. aestivum</italic> and wild emmer wheat (<italic>T. dicoccoides</italic>)
and harbors drought-resistance traits that were lost during the breeding processes
(<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Ashraf <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).
Breeders have increasingly focused on <italic>A. tauschii</italic>, since an
understanding of the genetic basis of drought resistance in <italic>A. tauschii</italic>
can contribute to the development of drought-resistant wheat cultivars.</p>
      <p>Drought resistance is a quantitative trait with a complex phenotype affected by plant
development stages (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Budak <italic>et al.</italic>,
2013</xref>). Linkage analysis is the most commonly used strategy for detecting
quantitative trait loci (QTLs) in plants; however, linkage mapping using biparental
crosses has some serious limitations. This method can only reveal information regarding
two alleles at a given locus, or a few loci segregating in a studied population. In
addition, the genetic resolution of detected QTLs is poor (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Holland, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Navakode <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Furthermore, linkage analysis can only sample a small
fraction of all possible alleles in the parental source population, while the
development of mapping populations is costly and time-consuming.</p>
      <p>Association mapping (AM), also known as linkage disequilibrium mapping, relies on
existing natural populations or specially designed populations to overcome the
constraints of linkage mapping (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Pasam <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). This technique is a powerful tool to resolve complex
trait variation and identify different loci and/or novel and superior alleles in natural
populations (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Zhu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>).
In recent years, association studies have been extensively used to discover and validate
QTLs or genes for important traits and to map candidate genes in many crop plants,
including wheat. The benefit of this method over traditional bi-parental mapping
approaches depends on the extent of linkage (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Huang
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Kump
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Erena
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). In wheat, different association panels have
been used in many AM studies to identify loci controlling agronomic (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Breseghello and Sorrells, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Crossa <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Neumann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Bordes <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) and quality (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Ravel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bordes <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) traits.</p>
      <p>Only a few genome-wide association studies have been carried out in <italic>A.
tauschii</italic> for drought resistance traits. Here, we aimed to: 1) investigate
marker-trait associations for drought resistance based on a genome-wide AM approach
using single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) markers in a core collection of 373
<italic>A. tauschii</italic> accessions of diverse origin; 2) identify SNPs highly
associated with drought resistance traits; and 3) search for candidate genes controlling
these traits. This study could provide important information for cloning genes related
to drought-resistance in <italic>A. tauschii</italic> and develop resistant wheat
cultivars using marker-assisted selection.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Material and Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Plant materials and phenotypic evaluation</title>
        <p>The natural population used for the association analysis comprised of 373 <italic>A.
tauschii</italic> accessions collected by the Triticeae Research Institute of
Sichuan Agricultural University. <italic>A. tauschii</italic> plants were grown in a
phytotron in Wenjiang, Sichuan Province, China, from September 2012 to March 2013 and
evaluated under normal conditions (NC) and polyethylene glycol (PEG)-simulated
drought-stress conditions (SC) in a completely randomized design with four
replications per treatment. Hydroponic tanks were filled with standard Hoagland's
nutrient solution (1 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 2 mM
MgSO<sub>4</sub>7H<sub>2</sub>O, 4 mM CaNO<sub>3</sub>4H<sub>2</sub>O, 6 mM
KNO<sub>3</sub>, 0.046 mM H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3</sub>, 0.76 &#x3BC;M ZnSO<sub>4</sub>,
0.32 &#x3BC;M CuSO<sub>4</sub>5H<sub>2</sub>O, 9.146 &#x3BC;M MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.0161 &#x3BC;M
(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>6</sub> MoO<sub>4</sub>4H<sub>2</sub>O, and 100 &#x3BC;M NaFeEDTA;
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Hoagland and Arnon, 1950</xref>) with or without
PEG (19.2%) for SC and NC, respectively. Seedlings were grown at a temperature of
25/22 &#xB1; 1 &#xB0;C day/night, relative humidity of 65/85% day/night, and a 16-h photoperiod
with 500 mmolm<sup>-2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> photon flux density at the level of plant
canopy.</p>
        <p>Uniform seedlings were transferred to the phytotron 8 d after germination and
evaluated 22 d later with a WinRHizo Pro 2008a image analysis system (R&#xE9;gent
Instruments, Quebec, Canada) for the following traits: root length (RL), root
diameter (RD), the number of root tips (RT), and the number of roots with a diameter
of 0.000-0.500 mm (TNOR). The plants were then separated into shoots and roots for
measuring total fresh weight (TFW), root fresh weight (RFW), shoot fresh weight
(SFW), and shoot height (SH). To determine total dry weight (TDW), root dry weight
(RDW), and shoot dry weight (SDW), shoots and roots were stored in paper bags, heated
at 105 &#xB0;C for 30 min to kill the cells, and dried at 75 &#xB0;C until a constant mass was
obtained.</p>
        <p>Descriptive statistics, correlation analysis, analysis of variance, principal
component analysis and multiple linear stepwise regressions were conducted for all
traits using IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows 20.0 (IBM Corp., Chicago, IL, USA).
Heritability was calculated as follows (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Smith
<italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>):</p>
        <disp-formula id="eq1">
          <mml:math id="m1">
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mtext>H = VG / (VG + VE),</mml:mtext>
            </mml:mrow>
          </mml:math>
        </disp-formula>
        <p> where VG and VE represent estimates of genetic and environmental variances,
respectively.</p>
        <p>In order to eliminate individual variation resulting from inherent genetic
differences unrelated to drought resistance, the drought resistance index (DI) was
used as a standardizing measure across <italic>A. tauschii</italic> accessions and
calculated as follows (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bouslama and Schapaugh,
1950</xref>):</p>
        <disp-formula id="eq2">
          <mml:math id="m2">
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mtext>DI =</mml:mtext>
              <mml:msub>
                <mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mtext>SC</mml:mtext>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:msub>
              <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
              <mml:msub>
                <mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mtext>NC</mml:mtext>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:msub>
              <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
            </mml:mrow>
          </mml:math>
        </disp-formula>
        <p> where T<sub>SC</sub> and T<sub>NC</sub> are the traits measured for each plant under
SC and NC, respectively.</p>
        <p>We also calculated the weighted comprehensive evaluation value (D value) for each
genotype as follows (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Xie, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Zhou <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>):</p>
        <disp-formula id="eq3">
          <mml:math id="m3">
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:mtext>D =</mml:mtext>
              <mml:mo>&#xA0;</mml:mo>
              <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true">
                <mml:munderover>
                  <mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext>
                    <mml:mo>&#xA0;</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mtext>=</mml:mtext>
                    <mml:mo>&#xA0;</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mtext>1</mml:mtext>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext>
                </mml:munderover>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mtext>u(x</mml:mtext>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mtext>)</mml:mtext>
                  <mml:mo>&#xD7;</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext>
                    <mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:mstyle>
            </mml:mrow>
          </mml:math>
        </disp-formula>
        <p>where W<sub>j</sub> is the weighting variable calculated as:</p>
        <disp-formula id="eq4">
          <mml:math id="m4">
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:msub>
                <mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext>
                <mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext>
              </mml:msub>
              <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
              <mml:mfrac>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mtext>P</mml:mtext>
                    <mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true">
                    <mml:munderover>
                      <mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext>
                        <mml:mo>&#xA0;</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mo>&#xA0;</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext>
                    </mml:munderover>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mtext>P</mml:mtext>
                        <mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mstyle>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:mfrac>
            </mml:mrow>
          </mml:math>
        </disp-formula>
        <p>with P<sub>j</sub> being the percent of variance and u(Xj) the membership function
value calculated as:</p>
        <disp-formula id="eq5">
          <mml:math id="m5">
            <mml:mrow>
              <mml:msub>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mtext>u(x</mml:mtext>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext>
              </mml:msub>
              <mml:mtext>)</mml:mtext>
              <mml:mo>&#xA0;</mml:mo>
              <mml:mtext>=</mml:mtext>
              <mml:mo>&#xA0;</mml:mo>
              <mml:mfrac>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mtext>X</mml:mtext>
                    <mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mo>-</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mtext>X</mml:mtext>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>min</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mrow>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mtext>X</mml:mtext>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>max</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mo>-</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mtext>X</mml:mtext>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>min</mml:mi>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:mfrac>
            </mml:mrow>
          </mml:math>
        </disp-formula>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>10K Infinium iSelect SNP array and SNP genotyping</title>
        <p>The construction of the <italic>A. tauschii</italic> 10K SNP array was described
previously by <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Luo <italic>et al.</italic>
(2014)</xref>. A total of 7,185 SNP markers was mapped to an <italic>A.
tauschii</italic> genetic map and a physical map built by bacterial artificial
chromosome clones (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Luo <italic>et al.</italic>,
2014</xref>). SNPs were assayed according to the manufacturer's protocol
(Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA) at the Genome Center, University of California, Davis,
CA, USA. Normalized Cy3 and Cy5 fluorescence for each DNA sample was graphed using
Genome Studio (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA), resulting in genotype clustering for
each SNP marker. SNP genotyping was carried out as described previously by <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Population structure</title>
        <p>Population structure was estimated with a set of 7,185 SNP markers mapped to the
<italic>A. tauschii</italic> genetic map using STRUCTURE 2.3.3, which implements a
model-based Bayesian cluster analysis (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Pritchard
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Wang
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). The linkage ancestry model and the
allele frequency-correlated model were used. A total of 100 burn-in iterations
followed by 100 Markov chain Monte Carlo iterations for <italic>K</italic> = 1 to 10
clusters were used to identify the optimal range of <italic>K</italic>. Five runs
were performed separately for each value of <italic>K</italic>, and the optimal
<italic>K</italic>-value was determined using the delta <italic>K</italic> method
(<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Evanno <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>).
Using <italic>K</italic> = 4 (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2013</xref>), the population was divided into Subp1, Subp2,
Subp3, Subp4, and mixed individuals.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Genome-wide association study</title>
        <p>Marker-trait associations were calculated in Tassel 2.1 (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Bradbury <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) using both the general
linear model (GLM) and the mixed linear model (MLM). Both models used 6,905 SNP
markers with a minor allele frequency threshold (&gt; 0.05). To correct the
population structure, the GLM incorporated a <italic>Q</italic>-matrix and the MLM
incorporated <italic>Q</italic>- and <italic>K</italic>-matrices. The
Bonferroni-corrected threshold at <italic>&#x3B1;</italic> = 1 (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) was used as the cutoff value,
which was 144.823 &#xD7; 10<sup>-6</sup> with a corresponding -log
<italic>p</italic>-value of 3.839. Significant markers were visualized with a
Manhattan plot drawn in R 3.03 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org/">http://www.r-project.org/</ext-link>).
Important <italic>p</italic>-value distributions (observed vs. cumulative
<italic>p</italic>-values on a -log<sub>10</sub> scale) were displayed in a
quantile-quantile plot drawn in R. To find candidate genes, flanking genes, and
trait-related proteins, we performed a Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST)
search against the International Wheat Genome Sequencing Consortium database (IWGSC;
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wheatgenome.org/">http://www.wheatgenome.org/</ext-link>) using SNP sequences. The IWGSC BLAST
results were used to perform a BLAST search of the National Center for Biotechnology
Information (NCBI) database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>)
and then a direct BLASTx search of the NCBI database.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Phenotypic evaluation</title>
        <p>Significant phenotypic variation was observed for all traits, and the means were
significantly different between NC and SC (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table
1</xref>). The mean values of the root to shoot ratio of fresh weight (FRS), the
root to shoot ratio of dry weight (DRS), RT, and RL were higher under SC, whereas
RFW, SFW, RDW, SDW, SH, TFW, TDW, RD, and TNOR were lower under SC compared with
those under NC (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). Significant
differences between NC and SC were observed for all traits, except for RFW, FRS, TFW,
and TDW, indicating that most of the tested traits were significantly affected by
drought. Medium to high heritability estimates were obtained for most of the traits,
and heritability was higher for five traits under NC and seven traits under SC.
Heritability ranged from 0.333 to 0.971 under NC and 0.331 to 0.983 under SC (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). Pearson correlations were calculated
among all traits, and we found 56 and 50 significant correlation coefficients (P &lt;
0.05) under NC and SC, respectively (<inline-supplementary-material mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="1415-4757-gmb-1678-4685-GMB-2015-0232-Suppl01.pdf" id="d36e862" content-type="local-data">Table
S1</inline-supplementary-material>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="t1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Phenotypic variation in 13 traits in 373 <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>
accessions under the normal condition (NC) and the PEG-induced, simulated
drought-stress condition (SC).</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup width="16%" span="1">
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead style="border-top: thin solid; border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trait</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condition</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#xB1; s.d.</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CV(%)</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-value</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>h</italic><sub><italic>B</italic></sub>(%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN2">a</xref></th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RDW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016 &#xB1; 0.009</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.983</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.191<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">**</xref>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.431</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013 &#xB1; 0.009</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.672</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.440</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041 &#xB1; 0.020</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.342</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.498<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">**</xref>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.552</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022 &#xB1; 0.011</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.682</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.552</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRS</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.419 &#xB1; 0.285</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.962</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.497<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">**</xref>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.719</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.987 &#xB1; 1.792</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181.476</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.822</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RFW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.276 &#xB1; 0.130</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.209</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.287<sup>ns</sup>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.964</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.108 &#xB1; 0.048</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.921</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.958</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SFW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.278 &#xB1; 0.145</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.219</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.335<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">**</xref>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.924</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073 &#xB1; 0.034</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.294</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.920</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FRS</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.073 &#xB1; 0.649</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.544</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.142<sup>ns</sup>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.971</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.572 &#xB1; 0.556</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.415</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.983</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SH</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.267 &#xB1; 3.998</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.155</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.833<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">**</xref>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.333</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.785 &#xB1; 3.196</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.185</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.337</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RL</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">246.692 &#xB1; 129.523</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.504</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.049<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">**</xref>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.341</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">340.228 &#xB1; 415.846</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122.226</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.331</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RD</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.749 &#xB1; 33.842</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">436.727</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.66<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">**</xref>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.475</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.481 &#xB1; 10.981</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">315.422</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.440</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057 &#xB1; 0.025</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.074</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.521<sup>ns</sup>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.862</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035 &#xB1; 0.014</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.802</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.902</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TFW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.554 &#xB1; 0.264</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.622</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.592<sup>ns</sup>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.666</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.182 &#xB1; 0.075</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.300</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.927</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1229.254 &#xB1; 912.330</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.218</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.931<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">**</xref>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.343</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2180.079 &#xB1; 3181.680</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145.943</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.334</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNOR</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2148.141 &#xB1; 864.048</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.578</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.574<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">**</xref>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.342</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1158.575 &#xB1; 3163.958</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147.288</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.355</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="TFN1">
              <p>RFW: root fresh weight; SFW: shoot fresh weight; FRS: root to shoot ratio of
fresh weight; RDW: root dry weight; SFW: shoot dry weight; FRS: root to
shoot ratio of dry weight; SH: shoot height; TFW: total fresh weight; TDW:
total dry weight; TRL: total root length; RD: root diameter; RT: number of
root tips; TNOR: the number of root in diameter 0.000 to 0.500.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="TFN2">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>Broad-sense heritability of the tested traits.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="TFN3">
              <label>**</label>
              <p>significant at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="TFN7">
              <p>ns: not significant.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Principal component analysis (PCA) and multiple linear stepwise
regressions</title>
        <p>PCA were performed for all traits using DI (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table
2</xref>) that were highly correlated according to the Bartlett's test of
sphericity (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup> = 5056.738; P &lt; 0.001). To establish selection indices
involving multiple drought-resistance traits, a series of linear regressions were
performed for all traits. We built the regression to explain TDW and chose our
predictive variables through stepwise regression (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>). The final stepwise model explained 93.9% and 65.3% of the
phenotypic variation in TDW under NC and SC, respectively. The model contained nine
traits for NC (RFW, RDW, FRS, DRS, TFW, RD, RL, RT, and TNOR) and seven traits for SC
(RFW, RDW, FRS, DRS, TFW, RL, and TNOR).</p>
        <table-wrap id="t2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Principal component analysis (PCA). For trait abbreviations see <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>.</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup width="16%" span="1">
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead style="border-top: thin solid; border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trait</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC 1</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC 2</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC 3</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC 4</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RFW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.655</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.082</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.618</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.238</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SFW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.584</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.179</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.144</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.264</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FRS</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.050</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.831</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.469</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RDW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.734</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.348</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.210</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.350</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.365</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.244</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.365</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.677</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRS</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.483</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.411</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.400</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.495</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic vector</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SH</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.608</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.042</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.132</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.282</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TFW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.865</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.166</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.815</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.014</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.094</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.265</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RL</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.278</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.765</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.111</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RD</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.362</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.065</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.005</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.294</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.891</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.170</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNOR</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.295</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.891</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.167</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.154</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eigenvalues</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.720</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.731</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.538</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.400</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contribution %</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.614</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.005</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.831</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.766</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumulative contribution %</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.614</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.618</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.449</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.215</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="t3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Multiple linear stepwise regression to explain total dry weight (TDW) from
root traits built with <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> genotypes means. For
trait abbreviations see <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>.</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup width="25%" span="1">
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead style="border-top: thin solid; border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final stepwise model</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>2</sup>
</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDW = 0.011 &#x2013; 0.08RFW + 2.014RDW +
0.02FRS &#x2013; 0.032DRS + 0.089TFW + 0.00005817RD &#x2013; 0.000002274RL
-0.000001614RT + 0.000008294TNOR</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.939</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDW = 0.011 &#x2013; 0.033RFW + 0.92RDW &#x2013;
0.001FRS &#x2013; 0.003DRS &#x2013; 0.105TFW + 0.000002321RL + 0.000002292TNOR</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.653</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>We performed a comprehensive evaluation of drought resistance in <italic>A.
tauschii</italic> using D values and DI (<inline-supplementary-material mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="1415-4757-gmb-1678-4685-GMB-2015-0232-Suppl02.pdf" id="d36e1574" content-type="local-data"> Table
S2</inline-supplementary-material>). Among the 373 <italic>A. tauschii</italic>
accessions, AS623213 that had the highest D value and AS623095 that had the lowest D
value were selected as extremely resistant and susceptible genotypes, respectively.
Overall, we identified six genotypes (1.6%) with high resistance (D &#x2265; 0.5), 262
(70.2%) with moderate resistance (0.30 &#x2264; D &lt; 0.5), and 105 (28.2%) with low
resistance (D &lt; 0.30). Next, we observed that <italic>A. tauschii</italic>
accessions with a higher D value also had a higher DI (<inline-supplementary-material mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="1415-4757-gmb-1678-4685-GMB-2015-0232-Suppl02.pdf" id="d36e1583" content-type="local-data">Table
S2</inline-supplementary-material>), which suggested that the two selection
indicators were effective for screening <italic>A. tauschii</italic> under SC.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Marker-trait association analysis</title>
        <p>The Bonferroni-corrected threshold (-log <italic>p</italic> &gt; 3.839,
<italic>&#x3B1;</italic> = 1) was used as the cutoff value for identifying marker-trait
associations (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>,
2014</xref>). A total of 208 and 28 SNPs were detected by the GLM and MLM,
respectively, while 25 significant SNPs with genome-wide distribution (chromosomes
[Chr.] 1D-7D) markers were detected by both models (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>; <inline-supplementary-material mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" xlink:href="1415-4757-gmb-1678-4685-GMB-2015-0232-Suppl04.pdf" id="d36e1610" content-type="local-data">Figure
S1</inline-supplementary-material> and <inline-supplementary-material mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="1415-4757-gmb-1678-4685-GMB-2015-0232-Suppl03.xlsx" id="d36e1614" content-type="local-data">Table
S3</inline-supplementary-material>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="t4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Genome-wide association of 13 tested traits under the normal condition (NC)
and the PEG-induced, simulated drought-stress condition (SC) detected using
general linear (GLM) and mixed linear (MLM) models. For trait abbreviations see
<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>.</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup width="7%" span="1">
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead style="border-top: thin solid; border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Trait</th>
                <th align="center" colspan="5" style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000" rowspan="1">GLM</th>
                <th align="center" colspan="5" style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000" rowspan="1">MLM</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">No. Share<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN6">c</xref>
</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.sig<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN4">a</xref>
</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average
-log(<italic>P</italic>)</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range
-log(<italic>P</italic>)</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average R<sup>2</sup> (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN5">b</xref>
</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range R<sup>2</sup> (%) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN5">b</xref>
</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.sig<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN4">a</xref>
</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average
-log(<italic>P</italic>)</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range
-log(<italic>P</italic>)</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average R<sup>2</sup> (%) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN5">b</xref>
</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range R<sup>2</sup> (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN5">b</xref>
</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>NC</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FRS</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.476</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.843-5.522</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.958</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.183-6.240</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.970</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.732</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RD</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.055</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.884-4.334</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.367</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.160-4.702</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RDW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.314</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.891</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RFW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.555</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.873-6.217</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.087</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.243-7.128</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RL</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.734</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.866-7.607</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.912</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.896-8.144</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.635</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.858-5.551</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.674</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.866-6.016</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.980</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.805</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.703</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.855-6.332</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.983</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.983-6.860</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.040</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.803</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SFW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.564</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.878-6.596</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.883</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.074-7.277</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.122</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.109-4.136</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.932</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.912-4.951</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SH</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.932</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.410</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.567</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.901-6.883</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.826</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.044-7.508</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.217</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.033</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TFW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.763</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.875-6.930</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.116</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.062-7.653</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.893</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.857-3.930</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.566</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.516-4.616</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNOR</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.701</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.873-5.462</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.728</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.780-5.896</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.945</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.760</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>SC</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRS</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.238</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.197</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FRS</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.242</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.588</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RD</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.628</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.875-7.932</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.569</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.319-9.367</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.793</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.844-6.505</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.140</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.995-9.211</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RDW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.184</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.959-5.076</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.404</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.129-5.395</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.967</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.460</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SFW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.991</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.339</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.561</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.006-5.631</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.898</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.238-6.162</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.087</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.992-4.183</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.857</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.725-4.989</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TFW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.447</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.868-5.290</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.792</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.112-5.796</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.678</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.089-4.973</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.637</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.813-6.049</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNOR</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.148</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.708</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>DI</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRS</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.639</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.288</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.286</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.930</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FRS</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.264</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.868-5.330</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.965</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.370-6.229</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RD</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.432</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.432-4.432</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.154</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.154-5.154</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.225</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.225-4.225</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.133</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.133-5.133</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RL</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.425</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.979</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.848</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.513</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.323</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.872-4.906</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.228</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.415-6.447</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.401</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.838</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.850</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.421-5.085</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.625</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.064-5.907</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.274</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.059-4.490</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.902</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.604-5.199</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNOR</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.366</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.982-4.872</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.280</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.554-6.395</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.396</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.818</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Total</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>208</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>28</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>25</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="TFN4">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>Total number of significantly associated SNPs detected by GLM and MLM at the
threshold of -log<sup>10</sup>
<italic>p</italic> = 3.839</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="TFN5">
              <label>b</label>
              <p>R<sup>2</sup> value showing the percentage of explained phenotypic
variation</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="TFN6">
              <label>c</label>
              <p>Number of significant SNPs detected by both models</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Under NC, significant markers were detected by both the GLM and MLM for FRS, RT, SDW,
SFW, TDW, TFW, and TNOR (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>), and by the
GLM for RD, RDW, RFW, RL, and SH (partly shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). No significant markers were detected for FRS by any of the two
models.</p>
        <fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The p values of the SNPs and quantile-quantile (Q-Q) plots of p values for
total dry weight (TDW) under the normal condition (NC) and the PEG-induced,
simulated drought-stress condition (SC). Summary of GWAS results for TDW. A1
and A2) GLM and MLM results for association under NC condition. A3) Q-Q plots
of GLM and MLM under NC condition. A4 and A5) GLM and MLM results for
association under SC condition. A6) Q-Q plots of GLM and MLM under SC
condition.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1415-4757-gmb-1678-4685-GMB-2015-0232-gf01"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Under SC, significant markers were detected by both the GLM and MLM for RD, TDW, and
TFW, and by the GLM for FRS, RDW, RT, SFW, and TNOR (partly shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). No significant markers were detected for
RFW, RT, SH, and SDW by any of the two models.</p>
        <p>Numerous SNPs were significantly associated with the DI in both the GLM and MLM, and
a relatively large amount of phenotypic variation in DI was explained by the studied
markers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>).</p>
        <p>We performed a BLAST search against the IWGSC using the SNP sequences, and we found
that their chromosomal locations were different from those of the best hits returned
from IWGSC. For example, the SNP markers <italic>contig10767_892</italic> and
<italic>contig50332_70</italic> located on Chr. 7D and 6D, respectively, on the
genetic map of <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Luo <italic>et al.</italic>
(2014)</xref> were located on Chr. 5DL and 6BL, respectively, according to the
IWGSC BLAST results.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>QTLs and putative candidate genes associated with significant loci</title>
        <p>To compare the identified regions between the 373 <italic>A. tauschii</italic>
accessions, markers separated by less than 5 cM were considered to be part of the
same QTL (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Massman <italic>et al.</italic>,
2011</xref>). The results revealed three QTLs that were related to RD-SC, RD-DI,
and TFW-SC. To find candidate genes, flanking genes, and trait-related proteins, we
performed a BLAST search of the NCBI database using the IWGSC BLAST results and then
a direct BLASTX search of the NCBI database. Putative and flanking genes associated
with significant loci are listed in <inline-supplementary-material mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="1415-4757-gmb-1678-4685-GMB-2015-0232-Suppl03.xlsx" id="d36e2506" content-type="local-data">Table
S3</inline-supplementary-material>. We identified several candidate genes that
were associated with different traits. Examples include <italic>Rht-A</italic> that
was associated with TFW-SC, RD-SC, TNOR-NC, SDW-NC, SFW-NC, TDW-NC, and TFW-NC;
<italic>Rht-B</italic> associated with TFW-SC; <italic>Glo-2</italic> associated
with TFW-SC and TDW-NC; <italic>WM1.7</italic> associated with RD-SC and RD-DI; and
<italic>Acc-2</italic> associated with RD-SC, RD-DI, TDW-SC, TNOR-NC, and FRS-DI.
We also found two candidate vernalization-requirement genes, <italic>VRN2</italic>
and <italic>VRN-B1</italic>, suggesting that vernalization might be related to
drought resistance.</p>
        <p>We also identified a few putative candidate genes associated with phenotypic traits.
These genes could be roughly divided into three groups: the first group included
genes encoding enzymes, such as <italic>RUBISCO</italic>, <italic>CKX2.5</italic>,
<italic>Acc-1</italic> and <italic>Acc-2</italic>, suggesting that many
biochemical pathways were activated under SC; the second group included genes
encoding storage proteins, such as <italic>Glo-2</italic>, <italic>WM1.12</italic>,
and <italic>WM1.7</italic>, which might be activated in response to drought stress;
and the final group included genes encoding drought-induced proteins, such as
<italic>Hotr1</italic>, <italic>Rht-A</italic>, <italic>Rht-B</italic>,
<italic>VRN-B1</italic>, and <italic>VRN2</italic>, that might play a crucial role
in the drought-resistance reaction of <italic>A. tauschii</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Importance of the wheat wild relative <italic>A. tauschii</italic>
</title>
        <p><italic>A. tauschii</italic> possesses numerous traits of high agronomic interest,
such as yield, insect resistance, disease resistance, and drought resistance (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Cox, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Ma
<italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Assefa,
2000</xref>; <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Aghaee-Sarbarzeh <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2002</xref>), and its genes can be incorporated into the wheat
genome via intergenic crossing (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Valkoun <italic>et
al.</italic>, 1990</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Cox <italic>et
al.</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Ma,
2008</xref>). Many agronomically useful traits have been already incorporated into
wheat (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Raupp <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>;
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Cox and Hatchett, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Friebe <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>). In
addition, artificial hybridization between tetraploid wheat and <italic>A.
tauschii</italic> has resulted in allohexaploid wheat lines, known as
'resynthesized' or 'synthetic hexaploid' wheat (SW) (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Mujeeb-Kazi <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>), i.e. 'Chuanmai 42' (CM42),
which is derived from a cross between <italic>Triticum durum</italic> and <italic>A.
tauschii</italic> and is resistant to Chinese new stripe rust races (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p>
        <p>Based on the results of this study, we believe that drought resistance is another
<italic>A. tauschii</italic> trait that could be incorporated into the wheat
breeding programs. We identified <italic>A. tauschii</italic> accessions with high
drought resistance that could be used as germplasm resources to widen the genetic
diversity of cultivated wheat and, thus, to reduce the time required to breed for
drought resistance.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Loci controlling drought resistance traits</title>
        <p>Here, we reported the outcome of a genome-wide association study for the
identification of genomic regions in <italic>A. tauschii</italic> responding to NC
and SC. AM involved 7,185 SNP markers genotyped in a core collection of 373
<italic>A. tauschii</italic> accessions. Linkage mapping using different
segregation populations tested in different environments could be also applied to
detect QTLs, but there are only a few reports on QTL mapping related to
drought-resistance traits in <italic>A. tauschii</italic>, compared with the high
number of such studies in wheat using linkage mapping.</p>
        <p><xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Landjeva <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref>
detected QTLs for RL on Chr. 1A, 6D, and 7D under SC, while <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> found two QTLs for RL
associated with drought resistance on Chr. 6D in two F<sub>8:9</sub> recombinant
inbred line populations (Weimai 8 x Yannong 19 and Weimai 8 x Luohan 2). In our
study, we also identified a significant locus (<italic>contig03437_336</italic>) on
Chr. 6D (28.073 cM) that was associated with RL-DI, and we also found two loci
related to RD-SC and RD-DI on Chr. 7D. However, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Liu
<italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> found QTLs for RL on Chr. 2D and 5D under
two different water conditions. <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Quarrie <italic>et
al.</italic> (2005)</xref> mapped QTLs for drought resistance in hexaploid
wheat on Chr. 2D and 3D, and found that three yield QTL clusters were coincident with
<italic>Vrn-A1</italic> on Chr. 5AL and <italic>Vrn-D1</italic> on Chr. 5DL. By
comparison, we identified seven significant loci on Chr. 2D and one significant locus
on Chr. 2D. Furthermore, we found a candidate <italic>VRN2</italic> at the
significant loci <italic>GCE8AKX01BMYMJ_66</italic> and
<italic>GDEEGVY01D8PT5_76</italic> located on Chr. 5D and associated with RD-SC
and RD-DI. These results indicated that vernalization-required genes probably affect
drought resistance in wheat. These findings further suggested the importance of
exploring the relationship between drought resistance and vernalization-required
genes.</p>
        <p>Significant genome-wide loci were detected by both the GLM and MLM. Some traits were
associated with multiple chromosomes, including RD-DI associated with SNPs on Chr. 1D
and 6D, TFW-NC associated with SNPs on Chr. 1D and 5D, and RD-NC associated with SNPs
on Chr. 4D, 5D, and 7D. <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Massman <italic>et
al.</italic> (2011)</xref> stated that significant SNP markers separated by
less than 5 cM could be considered as a single QTL. Accordingly, GCE8AKX02IHJOC_389,
<italic>contig37658_165</italic>, and GA8KES402HD74L_87 (Chr. 1D) separated by
less than 1 cM were considered as a single QTL related to TFW-SC. Similarly,
GCE8AKX01BMYMJ_66 and GDEEGVY01D8PT5_76 (Chr. 5D) also separated by less than 1 cM
were considered as a single QTL related to RD-DI and RD-SC
(<inline-supplementary-material mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="1415-4757-gmb-1678-4685-GMB-2015-0232-Suppl03.xlsx" id="d36e2746" content-type="local-data">Table
S3</inline-supplementary-material>).</p>
        <p>Until the wheat genome map is complete, loci identified in this study as associated
with drought resistance traits cannot be directly compared with QTLs reported by
previous studies in wheat. In addition, since the genome of <italic>A.
tauschii</italic> is not equivalent to the D-genome of wheat, only approximate
chromosomal locations that control drought resistance traits can be inferred. For
example, <italic>contig10767_892</italic> located on Chr. 7D in <italic>A.
tauschii</italic> was found on Chr. 5DL in hexaploid wheat. Similarly,
<italic>contig50332_70</italic> located on Chr. 6D in <italic>A. tauschii</italic>
was found on Chr. 6BL in wheat. One possible reason for these differences could be
the translocation of chromosomal regions during the hexaploidization of common wheat,
in which <italic>A. tauschii</italic> was involved.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Analysis of putative candidate and flanking genes</title>
        <p>Drought resistance is a complex trait resulting from the interaction of root and
shoot traits. In response to drought stress, wheat has developed highly specialized
morphological, physiological and biochemical mechanisms to increase the efficiency of
nutrient and water acquisition from soil (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Ludlow and
Muchow 1990</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Richards <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Nicotra and
Davidson, 2010</xref>). These mechanisms are closely associated with genes
controlling drought resistance and apparently responsive traits under drought
conditions. Previous studies have reported many genes related to drought resistance
in wheat, such as <italic>DREB</italic> that plays a central role in plant stress
response (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Agarwal <italic>et al.</italic>,
2006</xref>; <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Mizoi <italic>et al.</italic>,
2012</xref>) and <italic>TaAIDFa</italic> that encodes a
C-repeat/dehydration-responsive element-binding factor responsive to drought (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Xu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). In addition,
the silencing of <italic>TaBTF3</italic> impairs resistance to drought stress,
suggesting that it may be involved in abiotic stress response in higher plants (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Kang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Jiang <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref> isolated a
strongly drought-induced C3H zinc finger gene, <italic>AetTZF1</italic>, in
<italic>A. tauschii</italic>. <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Uga <italic>et
al.</italic> (2013)</xref> characterized the <italic>DRO1</italic> gene that
controls root growth angle in rice, which was the first root QTL that cloned in a
crop species. Rice OsTZF1 confers increased stress resistance to drought by
regulating stress-related genes (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Jan <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).</p>
        <p>In this study, we identified several putative candidate genes associated with
phenotypic traits related to drought resistance. These genes could be broadly divided
into three groups: (1) genes related to various enzymes, suggesting that many
biochemical pathways are activated under drought conditions; (2) genes related to
storage proteins that may be synthesized in response to drought stress; and (3) genes
related to drought-induced proteins that probably play a crucial role in drought
resistance. These findings reflected the complexity of drought-resistance mechanisms
and the large number of genes involved in these mechanisms. Information on SNPs and
genes related to drought-resistance might provide a genetic basis for gene cloning
and marker-assisted selection in the wheat breeding programs.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>We performed a genome-wide association study for drought resistance traits in a
population of 373 <italic>A. tauschii</italic> accessions using 7,185 SNP markers and we
detected 25 significant markers using GLM and MLM analysis. Furthermore, we identified
candidate genes at significant loci and their flanking regions that might control
drought resistance traits, including genes encoding enzymes, storage proteins, and
drought-induced proteins. The results provided essential information on SNPs and genes
related to drought resistance in <italic>A. tauschii</italic> that could be used for
breeding drought-resistant wheat cultivars.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="other" id="fn2">
        <p>
          <italic>Associate Editor: Everaldo Gon&#xE7;alves de Barros</italic>
        </p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agarwal</surname>
              <given-names>PK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Agarwal</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reddy</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sopory</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Role of DREB transcription factors in abiotic and biotic stress
tolerance in plants</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell Rep</source>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>1263</fpage>
          <lpage>1274</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16858552</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aghaee-Sarbarzeh</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrahi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Friebe</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dhaliwal</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Transfer of leaf and stripe rust-resistance genes from
<italic>Aegilops triuncialis</italic> and <italic>Ae. Geniculata</italic> to
bread wheat</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <volume>127</volume>
          <fpage>377</fpage>
          <lpage>382</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ashraf</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozturk</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Athar</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <source>Salinity and Water Stress: Improving Crop Efficiency</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>243</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Assefa</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>Resistance to wheat leaf rust in <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>
Coss and inheritance of resistance in hexaploid wheat</article-title>
          <source>Genet Resour Crop Evol</source>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>140</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bordes</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ravel</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Le Gouis</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Charmet</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balfourier</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Use of global wheat core collection for association analysis of flour
and dough quality traits</article-title>
          <source>J Cereal Sci</source>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>137</fpage>
          <lpage>147</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bordes</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ravel</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jaubertie</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duperrier</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gardet</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heumez</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pissavy</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Charmet</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Le Gouis</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balfourier</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <article-title>Genomic regions associated with the nitrogen limitation response
revealed in a global wheat core collection</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>126</volume>
          <fpage>805</fpage>
          <lpage>822</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23192671</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bouslama</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schapaugh</surname>
              <given-names>WT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1950</year>
          <article-title>Stress tolerance in soybeans. I. Evaluation of three screening
techniques for heat and drought tolerance</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>933</fpage>
          <lpage>937</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bradbury</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kroon</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Casstevens</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramdoss</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buckler</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>TASSEL: Software for association mapping of complex traits in diverse
samples</article-title>
          <source>Bioinformatics</source>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>2633</fpage>
          <lpage>2635</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586829</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Breseghello</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sorrells</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Association mapping of kernel size and milling quality in wheat
(<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) cultivars</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>172</volume>
          <fpage>1165</fpage>
          <lpage>1177</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16079235</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Budak</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kantar</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yucebilgili Kurtoglu</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <article-title>Drought tolerance in modern and wild wheat</article-title>
          <source>Sci World J</source>
          <volume>2013</volume>
          <comment>548246</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>TS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1994</year>
          <article-title>Leaf rust-resistance genes Lr41, Lr42, and Lr43 transferred from
<italic>Triticum tauschii</italic> to common wheat</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>39</fpage>
          <lpage>43</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>TS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hatchett</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1994</year>
          <article-title>Hessian fly resistance gene H26 transferred from <italic>Triticum
tauschii</italic> to common wheat</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>958</fpage>
          <lpage>960</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>TS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raupp</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leath</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bockus</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1992</year>
          <article-title>Resistance to foliar diseases in a collection of <italic>Triticum
tauschii</italic> germplasm</article-title>
          <source>Plant Dis</source>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <fpage>1061</fpage>
          <lpage>1064</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Crossa</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burgueno</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dreisickacker</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vargas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Herrera-Foessel</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lillemo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trethowan</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warburton</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Franco</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Association analysis of historical bread wheat germplasm using
additive genetic covariance of relatives and population structure</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>177</volume>
          <fpage>1889</fpage>
          <lpage>1913</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17947425</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Erena</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patrick</surname>
              <given-names>PF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Byrne</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marta</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matthew</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <article-title>Genome-wide association mapping of yield and yield components of
spring wheat under contrasting moisture regimes</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>791</fpage>
          <lpage>807</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ergen</surname>
              <given-names>NZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Budak</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Sequencing over 13,000 expressed sequence tags from six subtractive
cDNA libraries of wild and modern wheats following slow drought
stress</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell Environ</source>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>220</fpage>
          <lpage>236</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19054353</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Evanno</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Regnaut</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goudet</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Detecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software
STRUCTURE: A simulation study</article-title>
          <source>Mol Ecol</source>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>2611</fpage>
          <lpage>2620</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15969739</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fleury</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jefferies</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuchel</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Langridge</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <article-title>Genetic and genomic tools to improve drought tolerance in
wheat</article-title>
          <source>J Exp Bot</source>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>3211</fpage>
          <lpage>3222</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20525798</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Friebe</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raupp</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McIntSCh</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1996</year>
          <article-title>Characterization of wheat alien translocations conferring resistance
to diseases and pests: Current status</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <fpage>59</fpage>
          <lpage>83</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Habash</surname>
              <given-names>DZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kehel</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nachit</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Genomic approaches for designing durum wheat ready for climate change
with a focus on drought</article-title>
          <source>J Exp Bot</source>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>2805</fpage>
          <lpage>2815</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19584119</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hoagland</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arnon</surname>
              <given-names>IR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1950</year>
          <article-title>The water-culture method for growing plants without
soils</article-title>
          <source>Circ Calif Agric Exp Stn</source>
          <volume>347</volume>
          <fpage>4</fpage>
          <lpage>32</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Holland</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Genetic architecture of complex traits in plants</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>156</fpage>
          <lpage>161</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17291822</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wei</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sang</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feng</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>TT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>ZW</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <article-title>Genome-wide association studies of 14 agronomic traits in rice
landraces</article-title>
          <source>Nature Genet</source>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>961</fpage>
          <lpage>967</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20972439</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jan</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maruyama</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Todaka</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kidokoro</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoshimura</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shinozaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakashima</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <article-title>OsTZF1, a CCCH-tandem zinc finger protein, confers delayed senescence
and stress tolerance in rice by regulating stress-related genes</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <volume>161</volume>
          <fpage>1202</fpage>
          <lpage>1216</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23296688</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>ZS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>GY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cui</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>LC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>YZ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2014</year>
          <article-title>Genome-Wide Analysis of the C3H Zinc Finger Transcription Factor
Family and Drought Responses of Members in <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>
</article-title>
          <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>1241</fpage>
          <lpage>1256</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kang</surname>
              <given-names>GZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>HZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>GQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>QX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>CW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <article-title>Silencing of TaBTF3 gene impairs tolerance to freezing and drought
stresses in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Mol Genet Genomics</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>591</fpage>
          <lpage>599</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23942841</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kump</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bradbury</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wisser</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buckler</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Belcher</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oropeza-Rosas</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zwonitzer</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kresovich</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McMullen</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ware</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Genome-wide association study of quantitative resistance to southern
leaf blight in the maize nested association mapping population</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>163</fpage>
          <lpage>168</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21217757</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Landjeva</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neumann</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lohwasser</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Molecular mapping of genomic regions associated with wheat seedling
growth under osmotic stress</article-title>
          <source>Biol Plant</source>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>259</fpage>
          <lpage>266</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>GQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>ZF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>WY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>ZH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qu</surname>
              <given-names>YY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>XC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Molecular mapping of stripe rust resistance gene YrCH42 in Chinese
wheat cultivar Chuanmai 42 and its allelism with Yr 24 and Yr26</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>1434</fpage>
          <lpage>1440</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16525837</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>XL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>RZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>XP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jing</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <article-title>Mapping QTLs for seedling root traits in a doubled haploid wheat
population under different water regimes</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <volume>189</volume>
          <fpage>51</fpage>
          <lpage>66</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ludlow</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muchow</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1990</year>
          <article-title>A critical evaluation of traits for improving crop yields in
water-limited environments</article-title>
          <source>Advan Agron</source>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>107</fpage>
          <lpage>153</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gu</surname>
              <given-names>YQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>You</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deal</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huo</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2014</year>
          <article-title>A 4-gigabase physical map unlocks the structure and evolution of the
complex genome of <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>, the wheat D-genome
progenitor</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>7940</fpage>
          <lpage>7945</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23610408</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singll</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muieeb-kazi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1995</year>
          <article-title>Resistance to stripe rust in <italic>Triticum turgidum</italic>, T.
<italic>tauschii</italic> and their synthetic hexaploids</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>117</fpage>
          <lpage>120</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Massman</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horsley</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neate</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dill-Macky</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chao</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schwarz</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muehlbauer</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>KP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Genome-wide association mapping of Fusarium head blight resistance in
contemporary barley breeding germplasm</article-title>
          <source>Mol Breeding</source>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>439</fpage>
          <lpage>454</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mizoi</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shinozaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2012</year>
          <article-title>Review AP2/ERF family transcription factors in plant abiotic stress
responses</article-title>
          <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
          <volume>1819</volume>
          <fpage>86</fpage>
          <lpage>96</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21867785</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mujeeb-Kazi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosas</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roldan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1996</year>
          <article-title>Conservation of the genetic variation of <italic>Triticum
tauschii</italic> in synthetic hexaploid wheats and its potential utilization
for wheat improvement</article-title>
          <source>Genet Resour Crop Evol</source>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>129</fpage>
          <lpage>134</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Navakode</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neumann</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobiljski</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lohwasser</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>B&#xF6;rner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2014</year>
          <article-title>Genome wide association mapping to identify aluminium tolerance loci
in bread wheat</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <volume>198</volume>
          <fpage>401</fpage>
          <lpage>411</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Neumann</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobiljski</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dencie</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Varshney</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Genome-wide association mapping: A case study in bread wheat
(<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>
          <source>Mol Breed</source>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>58</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nicotra</surname>
              <given-names>AB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davidson</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <article-title>Adaptive phenotypic and plant water use</article-title>
          <source>Funct Plant Biol</source>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>117</fpage>
          <lpage>127</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pasam</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malosetti</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Eeuwijk</surname>
              <given-names>FA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haseneyer</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kilian</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2012</year>
          <article-title>Genome-wide association studies for agronomical traits in a worldwide
spring barley collection</article-title>
          <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>16</fpage>
          <lpage>37</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22284310</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pritchard</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stephens</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Donnelly</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>Inference of population structure using multilocus genotype
data</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>945</fpage>
          <lpage>995</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10835412</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Quarrie</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steed</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Calestani</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Semikhodskii</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lebreton</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chinoy</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steele</surname>
              <given-names>ND</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pljevljakusi</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waterman</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weyen</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>A high-density genetic map of hexaploid wheat (<italic>Triticum
aestivum</italic> L.) from the cross Chinese Spring x SQ1 and its use to
compare QTLs for grain yield across a range of environments</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>865</fpage>
          <lpage>880</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15719212</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Raupp</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amri</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hatchett</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>TS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1993</year>
          <article-title>Chromosomal location of Hessian fly-resistance genes H22, H23 and H24
derived from <italic>Triticum tauschii</italic> in the D genome of
wheat</article-title>
          <source>J Hered</source>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>142</fpage>
          <lpage>145</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ravel</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martre</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Romeuf</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dardevet</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>El-Malki</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bordes</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duchateau</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brunel</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balfourier</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Charmet</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Nucleotide polymorphism in the wheat transcriptional activator Spa
influences its pattern of expression and has pleiotropic effects on grain protein
composition, dough viscoelasticity and grain hardness</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <volume>151</volume>
          <fpage>33</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B45">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Richards</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rebetzke</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Condon</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Herwaarden</surname>
              <given-names>AF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Breeding opportunities for increasing the efficiency of water use and
crop yield in temperate cereals</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>111</fpage>
          <lpage>121</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11756261</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B46">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuehl</surname>
              <given-names>RO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ray</surname>
              <given-names>IM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hui</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soleri</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1998</year>
          <article-title>Evaluation of simple methods for estimating broad-sense heritability
in stands of randomly planted genotypes</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>1125</fpage>
          <lpage>1129</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B47">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Uga</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sugimoto</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogawa</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rane</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishitani</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hara</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kitomi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inukai</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ono</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kanno</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <article-title>Control of root system architecture by DEEPER ROOTING 1 increases rice
yield under drought conditions</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>1097</fpage>
          <lpage>1102</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23913002</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B48">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Valkoun</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dostal</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kucerova</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1990</year>
          <chapter-title><italic>Triticum x Aegilops</italic> hybrids through embryo
culture</chapter-title>
          <source>Wheat</source>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
          <fpage>152</fpage>
          <lpage>166</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B49">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>ZX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>You</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wei</surname>
              <given-names>YM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zheng</surname>
              <given-names>YL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dvorak</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <article-title><italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> single nucleotide polymorphisms shed light on
the origins of wheat D-genome genetic diversity and pinpoint the geographic origin
of hexaploid wheat</article-title>
          <source>New Phytol</source>
          <volume>198</volume>
          <fpage>925</fpage>
          <lpage>937</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23374069</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B50">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wilhite</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glantz</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1985</year>
          <article-title>Understanding the drought phenomenon: The role of
definitions</article-title>
          <source>Water Int</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>111</fpage>
          <lpage>120</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B51">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xie</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1993</year>
          <source>Agricultural Science and the Method of Fuzzy Mathematics</source>
          <publisher-name>Huazhong University of Science Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Wuhan</publisher-loc>
          <fpage>99</fpage>
          <lpage>193</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B52">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>ZS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ni</surname>
              <given-names>ZY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nie</surname>
              <given-names>LN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>LC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>YZ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Characterization of the TaAIDF a gene encoding a CRT/DRE-binding
factor responsive to drought, high-salt, and cold stress in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Mol Genet Genomics</source>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>497</fpage>
          <lpage>508</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18800227</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B53">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>YL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>XH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>FH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wen</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2014</year>
          <article-title>Genome wide association studies using a new nonparametric model reveal
the genetic architecture of 17 agronomic traits in an enlarged maize association
panel</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Genet</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <elocation-id/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B54">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cui</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ding</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bao</surname>
              <given-names>YG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>QP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <article-title>Conditional and unconditional QTL mapping of drought-tolerance-related
traits of wheat seedling using two related RIL populations</article-title>
          <source>J Genet</source>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>213</fpage>
          <lpage>231</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23970077</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B55">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>HQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>SQ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Transfer of resistant genes from <italic>Aegilops tauschii L</italic>.
to <italic>Triticum aestivum L.</italic> and their mapping by SSR</article-title>
          <source>Zhongguo Nong Ye Da Xue Xue Bao</source>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>5</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B56">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>GS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mei</surname>
              <given-names>FZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>QZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>XT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Different wheat varieties during physiological index comprehensive
evaluation and prediction</article-title>
          <source>Zhongguo Nong Ye Ke Xue</source>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>1378</fpage>
          <lpage>1382</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B57">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gore</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buckler</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Status and prospects of association mapping in plants</article-title>
          <source>Int J Plant Genomics</source>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>5</fpage>
          <lpage>20</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <app-group>
      <app id="app1">
        <title>Supplementary Material</title>
        <p>The following online material is available for this article:</p>
        <p>
          <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="suppl1">
            <label>Table S1</label>
            <caption>
              <title> - Genetic correlation among selected traits</title>
            </caption>
            <media xlink:href="1415-4757-gmb-1678-4685-GMB-2015-0232-Suppl01.pdf">
              <caption>
                <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
          </supplementary-material>
        </p>
        <p>
          <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="suppl2">
            <label>Table S2</label>
            <caption>
              <title> - Top 10 and bottommost 10 genotypes on DI and D value</title>
            </caption>
            <media xlink:href="1415-4757-gmb-1678-4685-GMB-2015-0232-Suppl02.pdf">
              <caption>
                <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
          </supplementary-material>
        </p>
        <p>
          <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="suppl3">
            <label>Table S3</label>
            <caption>
              <title> - Significant SNPs and candidate genes</title>
            </caption>
            <media xlink:href="1415-4757-gmb-1678-4685-GMB-2015-0232-Suppl03.xlsx">
              <caption>
                <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
          </supplementary-material>
        </p>
        <p>
          <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="suppl4">
            <label>Figure S1</label>
            <caption>
              <title> - The p values of the SNPs and quantile-quantile (Q-Q) plots</title>
            </caption>
            <media xlink:href="1415-4757-gmb-1678-4685-GMB-2015-0232-Suppl04.pdf">
              <caption>
                <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
          </supplementary-material>
        </p>
        <p>This material is available as part of the online article from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/gmb">http://www.scielo.br/gmb</ext-link>
</p>
      </app>
    </app-group>
  </back>
</article>
