<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.0 20040830//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Microb Biotechnol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Microb Biotechnol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mbt2</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Microbial Biotechnology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1751-7915</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1751-7915</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BlackWell Publishing Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4408174</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25219642</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1751-7915.12158</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Biocontrol and plant growth-promoting activity of rhizobacteria from Chinese fields with contaminated soils</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Xuefei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
            <given-names>Dmitri V</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ke</surname>
            <given-names>Linfeng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
            <given-names>Olga V</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Mingming</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Thomashow</surname>
            <given-names>Linda S</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <given-names>Na</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Weller</surname>
            <given-names>David M</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Jibin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="au1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>State Key Laboratory of Agricultural Microbiology, College of Life Science and Technology, Huazhong Agricultural University</institution>
          <addr-line>Wuhan, Hubei, 430070, China</addr-line>
        </aff>
        <aff id="au2">
          <label>2</label>
          <institution>Department of Plant Pathology, Washington State University</institution>
          <addr-line>Pullman, WA, 99164-6430, USA</addr-line>
        </aff>
        <aff id="au3">
          <label>3</label>
          <institution>Department of Biological Sciences, The University of Southern Mississippi</institution>
          <addr-line>Hattiesburg, MS, 39406, USA</addr-line>
        </aff>
        <aff id="au4">
          <label>4</label>
          <institution>Agricultural Research Service, Root Disease and Biological Control Research Unit, United States Department of Agriculture</institution>
          <addr-line>Pullman, WA, 99164-6430, USA</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* For correspondence. E-mail <email>zhangjb05@163.com</email>; Tel. (+86)&#x2009;27&#x2009;872&#x2009;87701&#x2009;8206; Fax: (+86)&#x2009;27&#x2009;872&#x2009;87254. E-mail <email>david.weller@ars.usda.gov</email>; Tel: (+1)&#x2009;509&#x2009;335&#x2009;6210; Fax: (+1)&#x2009;509&#x2009;335&#x2009;7674.
</corresp>
        <fn>
          <p><bold>Funding Information</bold> This work was supported by the National Basic Research Program of China (973 Program, 2013CB127504) and an International Cooperation Project, the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities, China (Grant No. 2011PY122) (2011&#x2013;2012).</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>404</fpage>
      <lpage>418</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2014 The Authors. <italic>Microbial Biotechnology</italic> published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd and Society for Applied Microbiology.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The aim of this study was to inventory the types of plant growth-promoting rhizobacteria (PGPR) present in the rhizosphere of plants grown in soils contaminated with heavy metals, recalcitrant organics, petroleum sewage or salinity in China. We screened 1223 isolates for antifungal activity and about 24% inhibited <italic>R</italic><italic>hizoctonia solani</italic> or <italic>S</italic><italic>clerotinia sclerotiorum</italic>. Twenty-four strains inhibitory to <italic>R</italic><italic>.&#x2009;solani</italic>, <italic>G</italic><italic>aeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic> and/or <italic>S</italic><italic>.&#x2009;sclerotiorum</italic> and representing the dominant morphotypes were assayed for PGPR activity. Seven strains contained <italic>phlD</italic>, <italic>prnD</italic>, <italic>pltC</italic> or <italic>phzF</italic> genes and produced the antibiotics 2,4-diacetylphloroglucinol, pyrrolnitrin, pyoluteorin and phenazines respectively. Six strains contained <italic>acdS</italic>, which encodes 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid deaminase. Phylogenetic analysis of 16S rDNA and <italic>phlD</italic>, <italic>phzF</italic> and <italic>acdS</italic> genes demonstrated that some strains identified as <italic>P</italic><italic>seudomonas</italic> were similar to model PGPR strains <italic>P</italic><italic>seudomonas protegens</italic>&#x2005;Pf-5, <italic>P</italic><italic>seudomonas chlororaphis</italic> subsp. <italic>aureofaciens</italic> 30&#x2013;84 and <italic>P</italic><italic>.&#x2009;brassicacearum</italic>&#x2005;Q8r1-96. <italic>P</italic><italic>seudomonas protegens-</italic> and <italic>P</italic><italic>.&#x2009;chlororaphis-</italic>like strains had the greatest biocontrol activity against Rhizoctonia root rot and take-all of wheat. <italic>P</italic><italic>seudomonas protegens</italic> and <italic>P</italic><italic>.&#x2009;brassicacearum-</italic>like strains showed the greatest promotion of canola growth. Our results indicate that strains from contaminated soils are similar to well-described PGPR found in agricultural soils worldwide.</p>
        <p>Growth-promoting rhizobacteria in polluted soils</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Soil salinization and contamination by organic compounds (i.e. petroleum products and solvents) and heavy metals (i.e. Cd, Cr, Cu, Hg, Pb) are important environmental problems worldwide and have negative impacts on both human health and agricultural productivity (Jing <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Soil pollution is of particular concern in developing countries where rapid industrialization has led to contamination of agricultural lands, especially in small farms that are sources of food for consumption by local populations. In a survey of contamination levels of heavy metals in agricultural soils in China, metal concentrations of Cd were significantly higher than in non-contaminated soils (Wei and Yang, <xref rid="b64" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Similarly, because of the accumulation of mine tailing outfalls, the content of Cu in the wetlands of Daye County, Hubei province, was 18 times higher than the background value (Guo <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). The build-up of pollutants in soils and their subsequent leaching into the ecosystem has cascading effects, adversely impacting plant growth and yield (Cheng, <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">2003b</xref>; Huang <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Parida and Das, <xref rid="b44" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). The uptake of soil pollutants by crop plants and the resultant entry of carcinogens, endocrine disruptors and neurotoxins into the food chain are major concerns for human and animal health (Cheng, <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">2003a</xref>; Cai <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). In addition, soil pollutants can positively or negatively influence crop susceptibility to pathogens and insects (Elmer, <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Poschenrieder <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b51" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). For example, salinity can predispose plants to infection by soilborne pathogens or increase the incidence and severity of disease (Triky-Dotan <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b63" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Roubtsova and Bostock, <xref rid="b56" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). In contrast, exposure of wheat to a mild dose of cadmium induced resistance against <italic>Fusarium</italic> infection (Mittra <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b39" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>).</p>
      <p>Rhizobacteria are able to colonize and persist on roots and some, known as plant growth-promoting rhizobacteria (PGPR), are able to promote plant growth (Weller, <xref rid="b65" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). PGPR improve plant growth directly by supplying nutrients (e.g. phosphorous, nitrogen), producing phytohormones [e.g. indoleacetic acid (IAA)], and/or decreasing the level of ethylene that is produced when the plant is stressed (Li <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Lugtenberg and Kamilova, <xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). PGPR also antagonize plant pathogens and/or induce systemic resistance in the plant to disease (Weller <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b66" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Lugtenberg and Kamilova, <xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Because plants lack effector-triggered immunity to many soilborne pathogens, they rely on PGPR for defence against pathogen attack (Weller <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b66" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>).</p>
      <p>Soil pollution, especially by heavy metals, can also decrease the metabolic activity, biomass and diversity of microorganisms in the bulk soil and the rhizosphere (Sandaa <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b58" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Gremion <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Jing <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>) and limit the effectiveness of PGPR to protect roots against disease. However, PGPR with metal resistance and the ability to mitigate the toxic effects of soil pollutants are present in polluted soils (Huang <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Reed and Glick, <xref rid="b54" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Jing <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). For example, <italic>Pseudomonas asplenii</italic> AC isolated from polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon-contaminated soils significantly increased the root and shoot growth of canola in copper and creosote-contaminated soils (Reed and Glick, <xref rid="b54" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Salt-tolerant <italic>Pseudomonas chlororaphis</italic> TSAU13, isolated from the rhizosphere of wheat grown in a salinated soil (Egamberdieva and Kucharova, <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), improved the shoot and root growth of common bean grown in soil amended with NaCl and protected cucumber and tomato against <italic>Fusarium solani</italic> (Egamberdieva, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p>
      <p>Despite progress in understanding the crucial role of PGPR in helping plants adapt to environmental stress, major gaps remain in our knowledge of how soil pollution affects the population levels, diversity and activity of PGPR. Our study is part of an ongoing cooperative project in China and the United States with the goal of identifying new PGPR and characterizing their role in the promotion of soil and plant health. Our study focused on rhizobacteria isolated from Chinese soils polluted with heavy metals, recalcitrant organic compounds, petroleum sewage or excessive salinization. We have hypothesized that certain groups of PGPR and strains harbouring biocontrol and growth-promoting genes are cosmopolitan and conserved in soil microbiomes in agroecosystems worldwide regardless of the condition of the soil, and that plants enrich and support those PGPR best adapted to help them grow and resist diseases and other pests. Nothing is known about the composition of PGPR in soils from these polluted sites, thus making them ideal to test our hypothesis.</p>
      <p>Our specific objectives were to: (i) isolate and identify PGPR, (ii) determine their biocontrol activity against take-all disease and Rhizoctonia root rot on wheat, (iii) determine their growth-promoting activity on rapeseed/canola, and (iv) characterize their growth-promoting traits and genes. Wheat and rapeseed/canola were selected for our study because China is the world's largest producer of both of these crops and they are often grown in rotation. Rhizoctonia root rot caused by <italic>Rhizoctonia solani</italic> AG-8 and take-all caused by <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic> are two important soilborne diseases worldwide, against which wheat has no resistance (Cook <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Paulitz <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b1001" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Yang <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b68" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>); however, biocontrol with PGPR is a viable approach to controlling them. Poor emergence is a chronic problem in rapeseed/canola production in both China and the United States and application of PGPR as seed treatments can greatly enhance shoot and root growth.</p>
      <p>Here we report that strains of well-described PGPR species were among the common morphotypes from the rhizosphere of wheat and rapeseed grown in highly polluted soils in China. Strains of <italic>Lysobacter capsici</italic>, <italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic>, <italic>Pseudomonas protegens</italic> and those related to <italic>P.&#x2009;brassicacearum</italic> had some of the greatest biocontrol and/or growth promoting activity. PGPR genes in these morphotypes included <italic>phlD</italic>, <italic>phzF</italic>, <italic>prnD</italic>, <italic>pltC</italic> and <italic>acdS</italic>, and traits included the ability to produce 2,4-diacetylphloroglucinol (2,4-DAPG), phenazines, pyrrolnitrin, pyoluteorin, cellulase, siderophores, protease and IAA.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Population densities and antagonistic activity of rhizobacteria from contaminated soils</title>
        <p>The population sizes of total culturable aerobic, heterotrophic bacteria in the rhizosphere of wheat after three growth cycles in the greenhouse in the contaminated soils from five fields located in Hubei, Jiangxi and Jiangsu provinces of China ranged from 4.2&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>6</sup> to 3.4&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>8</sup>&#x2009;colony-forming units (cfu)&#x2009;g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> fresh weight of root (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>). Populations recovered from rapeseed grown in the same soils ranged from 3.6&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>5</sup> to 1.3&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>6</sup>&#x2009;cfu&#x2009;g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> fresh weight of root (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>). From the wheat and rapeseed rhizospheres, 1223 bacterial isolates (605 from wheat and 618 from rapeseed) were randomly selected from dilution plates of <sup>1</sup>/<sub>3</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;King's medium B (KMB) and <sup>1</sup>/<sub>10</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;tryptic soy agar (TSA). The percentage of isolates from wheat inhibitory to <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> and from rapeseed inhibitory to <italic>Sclerotinia sclerotiorum</italic> varied among soils but averaged 24% and 23% respectively (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>). Isolates from the field contaminated with recalcitrant organic compounds in Hukou County, Jiangxi province were the least inhibitory to <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> and <italic>S.&#x2009;sclerotiorum</italic> (6.7% and 15.1% respectively) as compared with isolates from the other soils.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Population densities of total culturable aerobic, heterotrophic bacteria in the rhizosphere of wheat and rapeseed and ability of the bacteria to inhibit soilborne pathogens <italic>in vitro</italic></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Wheat rhizosphere</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Canola rhizosphere</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-1">a</xref></th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil contaminant</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cfu&#x2009;g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> fresh weight root</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibitory to <italic>Rhizoctonia</italic> AG-8 (%)</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cfu&#x2009;g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> fresh weight root</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibitory to <italic>Sclerotinia sclerotiorum</italic> (%)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daye County</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heavy metals</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.48&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.85&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>7</sup></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.44&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>6</sup></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hukou County</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recalcitrant organic compounds</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.0&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>6</sup></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.02&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.41&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>5</sup></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jinmen City</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petroleum products</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.54&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.3&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>7</sup></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.35&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>5</sup></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qidong City (Dongyuan)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salt</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.4&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>8</sup></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.13&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>5</sup></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qidong City (Yinyang)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salt</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.39&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.37&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>8</sup></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.56&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.66&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>5</sup></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tf1-1">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>Soil samples were collected in Daye County and Jinmen City in Hubei province, Hukou county in Jiangxi province, and Qidong City near Dongyuan and Yinyang in Jiangsu province; GPS coordinates of these sites are 30&#xB0;10&#x2032;N, 114&#xB0;56&#x2032;E; 29&#xB0;46&#x2032;N, 116&#xB0;15&#x2032;E; 31&#xB0;01&#x2032;N, 112&#xB0;13&#x2032;E; 31&#xB0;58&#x2032;N, 121&#xB0;46&#x2032;E; and 31&#xB0;44&#x2032;N, 121&#xB0;54&#x2032;E respectively.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Crop and native plants and weeds were dug from the contaminated soil at each site, soil attached to the roots was removed, transported to Wuhan, and wheat or rapeseed was grown in the soil for three cycles. Population densities of total culturable, aerobic rhizosphere bacteria were determined by the end-point dilution assay and single colonies of bacteria were selected from plates of <sup>1</sup>/<sub>3</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;KMB or <sup>1</sup>/<sub>10</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;TSA at the end of the third growth cycle of wheat or rapeseed.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Identity of the PGPR and their biocontrol and growth-promoting traits and genes</title>
        <p>Twenty-four strains representative of the dominant morphotypes (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">2</xref>) were screened for growth-promoting and biocontrol-related traits and genes. Of these 24 strains, 15, 11 and 20, respectively, inhibited the growth of <italic>G.&#x2009;graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic> ARS-A1, <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> AG-8 C-1 and <italic>S.&#x2009;sclerotiorum</italic> MGSCF180002 (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">3</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Bacteria used in this study</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-1">a</xref></th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source and type of contamination</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus</italic> sp. TY5107</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qidong City (near Yinyang), Jiangsu Province, China (excessive salinization)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Delftia tsuruhatensis</italic> TM3205</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jinmen City, Hubei Province, China (petroleum products)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lysobacter capsici</italic> TM5405</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qidong City (near Yinyang), Jiangsu Province, China (excessive salinization)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lysobacter enzymogenes</italic> TM2502</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hukou County, Jiangxi Province, China (recalcitrant organic compounds)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Microbacterium hydrocarbonoxydans</italic> TY3211y</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jinmen City, Hubei Province, China (petroleum products)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Microbacterium hydrocarbonoxydans</italic> TY3517</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jinmen City, Hubei Province, China (petroleum products)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Paenibacillus polymyxa</italic> KM2501</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hukou County, Jiangxi Province, China (recalcitrant organic compounds)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Paenibacillus polymyxa</italic> KM4410</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qidong City (near Dongyuan), Jiangsu Province, China (excessive salinization)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY1205</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daye County, Hubei Province, China (heavy metals)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY1210</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daye County, Hubei Province, China (heavy metals)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KM3113</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jinmen City, Hubei Province, China (petroleum products)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KY5404</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qidong City (near Yinyang), Jiangsu Province, China (excessive salinization)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas chlororaphis</italic> KY5406</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qidong City (near Yinyang), Jiangsu Province, China (excessive salinization)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY3101</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jinmen City, Hubei Province, China (petroleum products)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY3116w</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jinmen City, Hubei Province, China (petroleum products)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KY3201</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jinmen City, Hubei Province, China (petroleum products)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY5511</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qidong City (near Yinyang), Jiangsu Province, China (excessive salinization)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KM2404</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hukou County, Jiangxi Province, China (recalcitrant organic compounds)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas protegens</italic> TM1109</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daye County, Hubei Province, China (heavy metals)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas protegens</italic> TY1502</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daye County, Hubei Province, China (heavy metals)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas protegens</italic> TY1508</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daye County, Hubei Province, China (heavy metals)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas protegens</italic> KY4410</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qidong City (near Dongyuan), Jiangsu Province, China (excessive salinization)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Serratia plymuthica</italic> KM3407</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jinmen City, Hubei Province, China (petroleum products)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Serratia plymuthica</italic> TM4307-1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qidong City (near Dongyuan), Jiangsu Province, China (excessive salinization)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;brassicacearum</italic> Q8r1-96</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quincy, WA, USA (wheat rhizosphere)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weller <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="b66" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Loper <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="b32" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> 30&#x2013;84</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glen Elder, KS, USA (wheat rhizosphere)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pierson and Thomashow, <xref rid="b49" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> Pf-5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Texas (cotton rhizosphere)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paulsen <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="b47" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> TX-1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Lansing, MI (thatch and soil of Kentucky bluegrass)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Powell <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="b52" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tf2-1">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>Strains number prefixes: KM, isolated from the wheat rhizosphere on <sup>1</sup>/<sub>3</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;KMB agar; TM, isolated from the wheat rhizosphere on <sup>1</sup>/<sub>10</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;TSA; KY, isolated from the rapeseed rhizosphere on <sup>1</sup>/<sub>3</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;KMB agar; TY, isolated from the rapeseed rhizosphere on <sup>1</sup>/<sub>10</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;TSA.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Biocontrol related genes and traits of Chinese strains and <italic>in vitro</italic> inhibition of soilborne pathogens<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-1">a</xref></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Strain</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Antibiotic biosynthesis genes</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Extracellular metabolites</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Inhibition of pathogen</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>phlD</italic>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>phzF</italic>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>prnD</italic>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>pltC</italic>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cel</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sid</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pro</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ggt ARS-A1</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rs AG-8</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ss</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus</italic> sp. TY5107</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>D.&#x2009;tsuruhatensis</italic> TM3205</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>L.&#x2009;capsici</italic> TM5405</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>L.&#x2009;enzymogenes</italic> TM2502</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M.&#x2009;hydrocarbonoxydans</italic> TY3211y</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M.&#x2009;hydrocarbonoxydans</italic> TY3517</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pa.&#x2009;polymyxa</italic> KM2501</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pa.&#x2009;polymyxa</italic> KM4410</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY1205</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY1210</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KM3113</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KY5404</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> KY5406</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>+</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY3101</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY3116w</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KY3201</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY5511</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KM2404</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> TM1109</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> TY1502</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> TY1508</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> KY4410</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S.&#x2009;plymuthica</italic> KM3407</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S.&#x2009;plymuthica</italic> TM4307-1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>+++</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>++</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tf3-1">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>Presence (+) or absence (<bold>&#x2212;</bold>) of genes required for the biosynthesis of 2,4- DAPG (<italic>phlD</italic>), phenazine (<italic>phzF</italic>), pyrrolnitrin (<italic>prnD</italic>) and pyoluteorin (<italic>pltC</italic>). Extracellular metabolites produced: cellulase (Cel), protease (Pro) and siderophores (Sid).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Isolates were tested <italic>in vitro</italic> for ability to inhibit the growth <italic>of R.&#x2009;solani</italic> AG-8 (Rs AG-8); <italic>G.&#x2009;graminis var. tritici</italic> ARS-A1 (Ggt ARS-A1); and <italic>S.&#x2009;sclerotiorum</italic> (Ss). Inhibition was scored as follows: <bold>&#x2212;</bold>, no inhibition;&#x2009;+&#x2009;, inhibition zone of &lt;&#x2009;5&#x2009;mm; ++, inhibition zone of 5 to 10&#x2009;mm; +++; and inhibition zone of &gt;&#x2009;10&#x2009;mm.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Results of traditional microbiological tests and analysis of partial 16S rDNA gene sequences (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">2</xref>) revealed that five of the 24 strains were Gram-positive and closely related to <italic>Bacillus, Paenibacillus polymyxa</italic> and <italic>Microbacterium hydrocarbonoxydans</italic>. The rest of the strains represented two different clades of Gram-negative bacteria and were closely related to several species within the <italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic> and <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic> groups, and to <italic>Lysobacter capsici, Lysobacter enzymogenes</italic>, <italic>Serratia plymuthica</italic> and <italic>Delftia tsuruhatensis</italic>. We subjected strains of the <italic>P.&#x2009;fluorescens</italic> group to the multilocus typing scheme of Mulet and colleagues (<xref rid="b41" ref-type="bibr">2009; 2010</xref>), which has proven to be useful for establishing phylogenetic relationships among pseudomonads and is based on sequences of 16S rDNA, <italic>gyrB</italic> and <italic>rpoD</italic> (Mulet <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b41" ref-type="bibr">2009; 2010</xref>). The results of molecular typing identified strains TY1502, TY1508, KY4410 and TM1109 as <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> and strain KY5406 as <italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Fig.&#x2009;S1</xref>). Strains TY1205, TY1210, KM3113 and KY5404 were identified as members of the <italic>P.&#x2009;corrugata</italic> subgroup and were closely related but not identical to the well-studied biocontrol species <italic>P.&#x2009;brassicacearum</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Fig.&#x2009;S1</xref>).</p>
        <p>All 24 strains produced one or more of the extracellular metabolites cellulase, protease and siderophores. Genes for the biosynthesis of the antibiotics 2,4-DAPG (<italic>phlD</italic>), phenazines (<italic>phzF</italic>), pyrrolnitrin (<italic>prnD</italic>) and/or pyoluteorin (<italic>pltC</italic>) were detected in strains of <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic>, <italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> and/or <italic>S.&#x2009;plymuthica</italic> (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">3</xref>) and the antibiotics themselves were detected in culture extracts analysed by thin-layer chromatography. These antibiotics are well known to function as major mechanisms of biocontrol of soilborne pathogens.</p>
        <p>The amplified fragments of <italic>phlD</italic>, <italic>phzF</italic>, <italic>prnD</italic> and <italic>pltC</italic> from these strains were sequenced and used in phylogenetic analyses together with corresponding alleles previously deposited in GenBank. Phylograms inferred from <italic>phlD</italic> and <italic>pltC</italic> sequences revealed that both of these genes from strains TM1109, TY1502, TY1508 and KY4410 were closely related to their homologues from <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Figs&#x2009;S2 and S3</xref>). Strains TM1109, TY1502, TY1508 and KY4410 also carried a <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens-</italic>like <italic>prnD</italic> allele and therefore had a combination of antibiotic biosynthesis pathways similar to those of the model biocontrol agents <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> strains Pf-5 and CHA0 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Fig.&#x2009;S4</xref>). The second <italic>prnD-</italic>positive <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> strain, KY5406, also carried <italic>phzF</italic> (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">3</xref>), a gene required for the production of phenazine antibiotics and highly conserved in all known phenazine producers. The <italic>prnD</italic> and <italic>phzF</italic> genes of KY5406 clustered with homologues from <italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Figs&#x2009;S4 and S5</xref>). Strain KY5406 also contained <italic>phzO</italic> (data not shown), a gene required for the biosynthesis of 2-hydroxylated phenazine compounds, indicating this strain is subsp. <italic>aureofaciens</italic>. Finally, two more <italic>prnD-</italic>positive strains, KM3407 and TM4307-1 (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">3</xref>), carried <italic>prnD</italic> alleles similar to those present in pyrrolnitrin-producing strains of <italic>Serratia</italic> spp. (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Fig.&#x2009;S4</xref>) and produced Prn <italic>in vitro</italic> (data not shown). In total, correlation of the antibiotic gene profiling with the taxonomic placement of the strains by partial 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis identified the antibiotic-producing strains as members of <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic>, <italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> subsp. <italic>aureofaciens</italic> and <italic>S.&#x2009;plymuthica</italic>.</p>
        <p>1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC) deaminase and IAA production by PGPR are important determinants in plant&#x2013;bacterial interactions, and secretion of these compounds can induce plants to produce longer and more vigorous roots (Penrose and Glick, <xref rid="b48" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). <italic>Delftia tsuruhatensis</italic> TM3205 and <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> strains KM3113, KY5404, TY1210, TY1205, KY3201 and TY3101 produced IAA in culture. PCR analysis demonstrated that the aforementioned <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> strains were positive for <italic>acdS</italic>, a gene required for the production of ACC deaminase (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">4</xref>), and the sequences of those strains closely resembled those from other fluorescent pseudomonads (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Fig.&#x2009;S6</xref>). All <italic>acdS</italic> sequences from the Chinese strains formed a distinct clade within the <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> group and clustered tightly with <italic>acdS</italic> from <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. 2&#x2013;3 (GenBank Accession No. EU520401). All <italic>acdS</italic>-positive strains grew in defined medium supplemented with ACC as a sole nitrogen source.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float">
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Growth promotion of canola roots by rhizobacteria applied as seed treatments in growth pouch experiments<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf4-1">a</xref></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>acdS</italic>
                </th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IAA</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 1 Root length</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase (%)</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 2 Root length</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase (%)</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 3 Root length</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase (%)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus</italic> sp. TY5107</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.5 BE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 GH</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x2212;</bold>18.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 I</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x2212;</bold>29.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>D.&#x2009;tsuruhatensis</italic> TM3205</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 AD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 DE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>L.&#x2009;capsici</italic> TM5405</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 BE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 H</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x2212;</bold>13.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>L.&#x2009;enzymogenes</italic> TM2502</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 EG</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x2212;</bold>4.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 H</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x2212;</bold>13.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M.&#x2009;hydrocarbonoxydans</italic> TY3211y</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 AD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 DF</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 FG</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M.&#x2009;hydrocarbonoxydans</italic> TY3517</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.2 DE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 DF</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 H</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x2212;</bold>3.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pa.&#x2009;polymyxa</italic> KM2501</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 AE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 FG</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x2212;</bold>11.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pa.&#x2009;polymyxa</italic> KM4410</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 E</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x2212;</bold>45.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 EG</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x2212;</bold>5.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KM3113</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 AD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KY5404</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.5 AC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 DF</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY1210</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 CDF</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY1205</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.5 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 AC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> KY5406</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 CE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 GH</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x2212;</bold>15.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 H</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x2212;</bold>13</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KY3201</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 CD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 EF</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY3101</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.5 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 DF</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY3116w</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.2 AD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 DE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 FG</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY5511</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 AD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 DE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 AE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KM2404</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 AC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 DF</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> KY4410</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 AD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 AE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> TM1109</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 BF</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> TY1502</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 BC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 BF</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> TY1508</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.5 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 AD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ck</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>&#x2212;</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.5 CE</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 DG</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3 GH</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tf4-1">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>Surface-sterilized canola seeds were soaked for 1&#x2009;h in each bacterial suspension. Control (CK), non-treated seeds were soaked in sterile water.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Presence (+) or absence (<bold>&#x2212;</bold>) of the <italic>acdS</italic> gene. Bacterial cultures were positive (+) or negative (<bold>&#x2212;</bold>) for the presence of IAA.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>% increase&#x2009;=&#x2009;[(root length of a treatment- root length of the control)/ root length of the control]&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;100%. Means in the same column followed by the same letter are not significantly different at <italic>P</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.05 according to Fisher's protected least significant difference test (LSD) or Kruskal&#x2013;Wallis all pairwise comparison test.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Exp, experiment; NT, not tested.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Biocontrol and growth-promoting activity of the rhizobacterial strains</title>
        <p>A subset of strains with the highest antagonistic activity and representative of the dominant morphotypes was selected to determine their biocontrol activity against take-all and Rhizoctonia root rot of wheat under greenhouse conditions in sterile, pasteurized and raw soils from Wuhan, China and Quincy, Washington. Most of the isolates provided some levels of reduction in root disease as compared with the pathogen-inoculated controls (Tables&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl5">5</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl7">7</xref>). However, strains identified as <italic>L.&#x2009;capsici</italic>, <italic>L.&#x2009;enzymogenes</italic>, <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> and <italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> provided the best and most consistent disease suppression across experiments and pathogens. <italic>Pseudomonas protegens</italic> TM1109 was especially effective in biocontrol of both take-all and Rhizoctonia root rot. These results indicate that indigenous rhizobacteria from the contaminated soil have the capacity to provide protection of plants against soilborne fungal pathogens. Surprisingly, application of <italic>S.&#x2009;plymuthica</italic> TM4307-1, which highly antagonized the pathogens <italic>in vitro</italic> (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">3</xref>), resulted in significantly higher levels of Rhizoctonia root rot (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl6">6</xref>). We speculate that TM4307-1 produces yet unidentified phytotoxic metabolite(s) since treatment of both wheat and canola with this bacterium resulted in significant stunting and bleaching of the seedlings and root damage.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl5" position="float">
          <label>Table 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Suppression of <italic>R</italic><italic>hizoctonia solani</italic>&#x2005;AG-8 in sterile soil in greenhouse pot experiments<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf5-1">a</xref></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Treatment</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Disease rating</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Shoot length (cm)</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 1</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 2</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 1</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 2</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.6 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.3 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.3 D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.6 BC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>L.&#x2009;capsici</italic> TM5405</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.6 D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.7 C</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.6 ABC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.9 A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>L.&#x2009;enzymogenes</italic> TM2502</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.7 CD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.7 BC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.0 ABC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.3 C</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pa.&#x2009;polymyxa</italic> KM2501</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.8 ABC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.5 BC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.4 BC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.1 B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pa.&#x2009;polymyxa</italic> KM4410</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.7 D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.3 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.7 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.3 B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> TM1109</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.6 BCD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.7 BC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.7 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.4 C</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tf5-1">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>CK1, control consisting of sterile soil from Wuhan, China not amended with inoculum of <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> and sown to non-treated seeds; CK2, control consisting of soil amended with <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> inoculum and sown to methyl cellulose coated seeds.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Severity of Rhizoctonia root rot was evaluated on a scale of 0&#x2013;8. Means in the same column followed by the same letter are not significantly different at <italic>P</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.05 according to Fisher's protected least significant difference test (LSD) or Kruskal&#x2013;Wallis all pairwise comparison test.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Exp, experiment.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="tbl6" position="float">
          <label>Table 6</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Suppression of <italic>R</italic><italic>hizoctonia solani</italic>&#x2005;AG-8 in Quincy virgin soil in a growth chamber tube assays<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf6-1">a</xref></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Treatment</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Disease rating</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Pasteurized soil</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Raw soil</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 1</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 2</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 3</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 4</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.8 B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.8 B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.6 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.7 AB</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.9 BC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.8 B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.6 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.6 A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>D.&#x2009;tsuruhatensis</italic> TM3205</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 ABC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 BC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>L.&#x2009;capsici</italic> TM5405</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.1 BCD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.8 B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.5 BC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.7 C</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>L.&#x2009;enzymogenes</italic> TM2502</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.9 ABC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.5 C</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pa.&#x2009;polymyxa</italic> KM4410</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.7 BCD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.9 B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.5 BC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4 C</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KM3113</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.7 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.6 BC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> KY5406</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.8 CD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.0 C</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.6 C</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.8 CD</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KM2404</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.9 BCD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.8 B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> KY4410</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.2 D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.1 D</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> TM1109</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.8 D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.8 C</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.2 D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.2 D</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S.&#x2009;plymuthica</italic> TM4307-1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.9 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.0 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tf6-1">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>CK1, soil not amended with <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> inoculum and sown to non-treated seed; CK2, soil amended with <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> inoculum and sown to methyl cellulose coated seed; and CK3, soil amended with oat-kernel inoculum and sown to non-treated seed.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Severity of Rhizoctonia root rot was evaluated on a scale of 0&#x2013;8. Experiments 1 and 2 were conducted in Quincy virgin soil that had been pasteurized (60&#xB0;C, 30&#x2009;min); experiments 3 and 4 were conducted in raw Quincy virgin soil. Means in the same column followed by the same letter are not significantly different at <italic>P</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.05 according to Fisher's protected least significant difference test (LSD) or Kruskal&#x2013;Wallis all pairwise comparison test.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Exp, experiment; NE, not evaluated.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="tbl7" position="float">
          <label>Table 7</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Suppression of <italic>G</italic><italic>.&#x2009;graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic>&#x2005;ARS-A1 in Quincy virgin soil in a growth chamber tube assays<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf7-1">a</xref></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Disease rating</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Pasteurized soil</th>
                <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Raw soil</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 1</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 2</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 3</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 4</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.2 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.8 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.9 ABC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.0 AB</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.0 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.8 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.0 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.0 A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>L.&#x2009;capsici</italic> TM5405</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.8 D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.0 BC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.7 E</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.4 BCD</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pa.&#x2009;polymyxa</italic> KM4410</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.3 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.9 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.9 BC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.2 ABC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> KY5406</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.2 CD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.2 D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.2 DE</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.0 E</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KM2404</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.2 AB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.0 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.0 CD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.0 ABC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> TM1109</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.1 D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.9 CD</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.8 E</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.3 DE</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S.&#x2009;plymuthica</italic> TM4307-1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.3 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.9 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.6 A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.4 AB</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tf7-1">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>CK1, Quincy virgin soil not amended with inoculum and sown to non-treated seed; CK2, soil amended with <italic>G.&#x2009;graminis</italic> var <italic>tritici</italic> inoculum and sown to methyl cellulose coated seed; and CK3, soil amended with <italic>G.&#x2009;graminis</italic> var <italic>tritici</italic> inoculum and sown to non-treated seed.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Severity of take-all was evaluated on a scale of 0&#x2013;8. Experiments 1 and 2 were conducted in pasteurized Quincy virgin soil (60&#xB0;C, 30&#x2009;min); experiments 3&#x2013;4 were conducted in raw Quincy virgin soil. Means in the same column followed by the same letter are not significantly different at <italic>P</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.05 according to Fisher's protected least significant difference test (LSD) or Kruskal&#x2013;Wallis all pairwise comparison test.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Exp, experiment.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Twenty-two of the 24 isolates were tested for the ability to promote canola root growth in growth pouch assays. The two <italic>S.&#x2009;plymuthica</italic> strains were eliminated from this assay because they enhanced disease when applied to wheat and caused stunting. Thirteen strains increased root growth significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.05) in at least one of the three experiments (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">4</xref>). <italic>Pseudomonas protegens</italic> and <italic>P.&#x2009;brassicacearum-</italic>like strains demonstrated the most consistent capacity to promote root growth and, on average, increased root length in canola by 41% to 42%, respectively, as compared with the non-treated controls. All <italic>P.&#x2009;brassicacearum-</italic>like isolates produced IAA and carried <italic>acdS</italic>. In contrast, strains of <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> had neither trait. Other tested <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> strains (i.e. KY3201, TY3101, Ty3116w, Ty5511 and KM2402) increased root length consistently but not always significantly, whereas strains of <italic>Bacillus</italic>, <italic>Paenibacillus</italic> and <italic>Lysobacter</italic> had no growth promotion activity. These results indicate that rhizobacteria from the contaminated soil have the capacity to directly enhance plant growth.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Tolerance to abiotic stressors</title>
        <p>Based on the results from the biocontrol and growth promotion assays, 10 of the 24 strains were selected and tested for tolerance to two heavy metals and high levels of salt by growing them in LB broth supplemented with CdCl<sub>2</sub>, CuCl<sub>2</sub> and NaCl. All 10 strains tolerated high levels of salt and grew well in up to 5&#x2013;7% NaCl. Similarly, these 10 strains grew in the presence of heavy metals and demonstrated minimal inhibitory concentrations (MICs) to Cu<sup>2+</sup> of &gt;&#x2009;4&#x2009;mM and Cd<sup>2+</sup> of &gt;&#x2009;1&#x2009;mM. Overall, <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> TM1109 was the most tolerant to these stressors (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl8">8</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl8" position="float">
          <label>Table 8</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) of heavy metals and salt for selected strains<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf8-1">a</xref></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isolate</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of soil contamination strain from</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cd<sup>2+</sup> (mM)</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu<sup>2+</sup> (mM)</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaCl (%)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>D.&#x2009;tsuruhatensis</italic> TM3205</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petroleum products</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KM3113</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petroleum products</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY1205</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heavy metals</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KY5404</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excessive salinization</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY1210</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heavy metals</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> KY5406</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excessive salinization</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. TY3101</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petroleum products</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. KY3201</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petroleum products</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> TM1109</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heavy metals</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> KY4410</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excessive salinization</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tf8-1">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>MICs were determined in Luria&#x2013;Bertani (LB) broth amended with CuCl<sub>2</sub> to give a range of concentrations from 3 to 6&#x2009;mM; CdCl<sub>2</sub> to give a range of concentrations from 0.4 to 2.0&#x2009;mM; and NaCl to give concentrations ranging from 0% to 8%.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Plants have evolved along with a rhizosphere microbiome that contributes to the growth and health of the plant (Pieterse <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b50" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Beneficial microbes that directly promote growth or defend roots are recruited by the roots from the bulk soil, making soil type an important determinant of the composition of the rhizosphere microbiome. However, the plant also strongly modulates the shape of the microbial community because both the quality and quantity of root exudates are regulated by the plant genotype (Bais <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Hartmann <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Our results support the hypothesis that certain groups of PGPR and biocontrol and growth-promoting genes are cosmopolitan and conserved in soil microbiomes worldwide. Driven by rhizodeposition, the plant enriches and supports PGPR best adapted to colonize the roots, antagonize pathogens, stimulate growth and/or initiate pattern-triggered immunity.</p>
      <p>We tested our hypothesis by characterizing culturable PGPR in the rhizospheres of wheat and rapeseed grown in soils from polluted fields, and assessed their growth-promoting and biocontrol abilities. After the most abundant bacterial morphotypes were isolated, the only other criterion we used for selecting the rhizobacteria was the ability to inhibit <italic>G.&#x2009;graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic>, <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> or <italic>S.&#x2009;sclerotiorum</italic>. This was done because <italic>in vitro</italic> inhibition of plant pathogens is a characteristic commonly found in many PGPR strains (Haas and D&#xE9;fago, <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) even though antibiosis does not predict biocontrol or growth-promoting activity. The 24 strains described here were shown to be most closely related to species known to have members with PGPR activity. Common among these strains were genes and traits that are well known to contribute to biocontrol and growth-promoting activity (Haas and D&#xE9;fago, <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Glick <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Loper <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Lugtenberg and Kamilova, <xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). For example, <italic>phzF</italic>, detected in <italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> subsp. <italic>aureofaciens</italic> KY5406, is a key gene in the biosynthesis of phenazine-1-carboxylic acid (PCA) and serves as a marker for the capacity of PGPR to produce one or more phenazines, a large class of broad-spectrum antibiotics produced by a variety of bacteria (Mavrodi <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">2006; 2010</xref>). Yang and colleagues (<xref rid="b68" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) showed that <italic>phzF</italic>-containing and PCA-producing <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp. colonized wheat grown in Hebei and Jiangsu provinces, China, and that these strains suppressed take-all. In the Pacific Northwest of the United States, PCA-producing pseudomonads are abundant on the roots of dryland wheat and suppress take-all and Rhizoctonia root rot (Thomashow and Weller, <xref rid="b62" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>; Mavrodi <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Phenazine-producing PGPR also contributed to the natural suppressiveness of soils in the Ch&#xE2;teaurenard region of France to Fusarium wilt (Mazurier <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b38" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). <italic>phlD</italic> is a key gene in the biosynthesis of the broad-spectrum antibiotic 2,4-DAPG in <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp. and 2,4-DAPG producers are responsible for the natural suppression of take-all of wheat in the United States and black root rot of tobacco in soils of the Morens region of Switzerland (Weller <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b66" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). 2,4-DAPG also induces systemic resistance in plants to pathogens (Weller <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b67" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). <italic>prnD</italic> and <italic>pltC</italic> are genes that encode for the biosynthesis of pyrrolnitrin and pyoluteorin, antibiotics that are highly active against <italic>Rhizoctonia</italic> and <italic>Pythium</italic> species respectively (Loper <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). The gene <italic>acdS</italic> encodes ACC deaminase, which promotes plant growth and development by decreasing ethylene levels in the plant. ACC deaminase-producing PGPR convert the ethylene precursor ACC to &#x3B1;-ketobutyrate and ammonia and can relieve stress resulting from pathogens, polyaromatic hydrocarbons, heavy metals, salt and drought (Glick <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>).</p>
      <p>To validate the biocontrol activity of our strains, we used the Rhizoctonia root rot- and take-all-wheat pathosystems. Strains of <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic>, <italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> subsp. <italic>aureofaciens</italic> and <italic>L.&#x2009;capsici</italic> provided the most consistent disease suppression and members of all three species are biocontrol agents of a broad range of diseases. For example, <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> Pf-5 produces a wide arsenal of antibiotics and toxins and approximately 6% of its genome is devoted to the production of secondary metabolites (Paulsen <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b47" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Loper <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Strain CHA0, isolated from a tobacco black root rot suppressive soil, is another notable <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> with exceptional biocontrol activity (Ramette <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b53" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Our four <italic>P</italic>. <italic>protegens</italic> strains, TM1109, TY1502, TY1508 and KY4410, contained the three antibiotic biosynthesis genes, <italic>phlD</italic>, <italic>prnD</italic> and <italic>pltC</italic>, and produced the antibiotics that are characteristic of Pf-5 and CHA0.</p>
      <p><italic>Pseudomonas chlororaphis</italic> subsp. <italic>aureofaciens</italic> contains <italic>phzO</italic> (Mavrodi <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), and besides PCA, it also produces hydroxyphenazines, which have characteristic orange and red colours and differ from PCA in antibiotic activity (Mavrodi <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Notable examples of <italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> subsp. <italic>aureofaciens</italic> with biocontrol activity include strains 30&#x2013;84 (Pierson and Thomashow, <xref rid="b49" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>) and TX-1 (Powell <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b52" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). In <italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic>, phenazine production also contributes to rhizosphere competence (Mavrodi <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). <italic>Lysobacter</italic> sp. strains also have broad antifungal and antibacterial activities. For example, Park and colleagues (<xref rid="b45" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) reported that <italic>L.&#x2009;capsici</italic> YC5194<sup>T</sup> inhibited <italic>Pythium ultimum</italic>, <italic>Colletotrichum gloeosporioides</italic>, <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic>, <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic>, <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic>, <italic>Botryosphaeria dothidea</italic> and <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>. <italic>Lysobacter</italic> sp. SB-K88 (formerly <italic>Stenotrophomonas</italic>) (Nakayama <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b42" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>) produced the antibiotics xanthobaccins A, B and C, and xanthobaccin A was involved in the suppression of Pythium damping-off of sugar beet (Islam <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>).</p>
      <p>To test our strains for the ability to directly promote plant growth, we used the canola root elongation assay, a model system commonly employed to demonstrate direct growth-promoting activity by PGPR (Patten and Glick, <xref rid="b46" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). The most consistent and effective growth promoters were strains of <italic>Delftia</italic> and <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> that produced IAA and, in the case of <italic>P.&#x2009;fluorescens-</italic> and <italic>P.&#x2009;brassicacearum</italic>-like strains, harboured <italic>acdS</italic>. Of these species, only <italic>P.&#x2009;fluorescens</italic> and <italic>P.&#x2009;brassicacearum</italic> have been reported to have direct growth-promoting ability (Belimov <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Glick <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Members of these two species also are biocontrol agents (Loper <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b32" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). <italic>Pseudomonas brassicacearum</italic> has commonly been isolated from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Brassica napus</italic> (Achouak <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>) and wheat (Ross <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b55" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). <italic>Pseudomonas brassicacearum</italic> strain Am3, with ACC deaminase activity, promoted root elongation of Indian mustard and increased root and shoot biomass of rapeseed and pea (Belimov <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Safronova <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b57" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). A mutation in <italic>acdS</italic> resulted in a loss of growth-promoting activity in <italic>P.&#x2009;brassicacearum</italic> (Belimov <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>).</p>
      <p>We tested 10 strains for tolerance to heavy metals and high levels of salt by growing them in broth supplemented with CdCl<sub>2</sub>, CuCl<sub>2</sub> and NaCl. Unfortunately, there are no records of how long the sampled fields have been polluted but discussions with local inhabitants indicated that some fields may have been in that condition for decades. Not surprising, all of the PGPR strains tested tolerated high levels of salt and demonstrated MICs to Cu<sup>2+</sup> and Cd<sup>2+</sup> on par or higher than those previously reported for strains adapted to survival in the presence of acute levels of heavy metal contamination of soil (Thomas <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b61" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Altimira <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Thus, our results confirm that PGPR species have adapted not only to a wide variety of cropping systems and crops but also to adverse environmental conditions. Of particular note are our strains of <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic>, which appeared to be especially well adapted to a wide variety of pollutants. Perhaps not surprisingly, analysis of the genome of <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> Pf-5 identified a considerable collection of efflux systems that provide protection against a range of toxic metabolites (Loper <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Evidence is accumulating that strains of <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> form the cornerstones of communities of microbial defenders of roots in rhizosphere microbiomes globally.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, Chinese farmers often must utilize all arable land, even polluted fields, because of the challenges of feeding a huge population. We inventoried PGPR in contaminated soils from sites representative of polluted fields supporting agricultural production. These sites were especially interesting because their microbiology previously had not been studied. Our findings demonstrate that well-described PGPR species and biocontrol and growth-promoting genes are common in the rhizosphere microbiome of plants grown in polluted Chinese soils. PGPR from such soils may be the best source of strains for commercial development given that in China nearly 50 million acres of arable land suffer from some type of soil pollution (Zhou, <xref rid="b70" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). With the world population expected to be 9&#x2013;11 billion by 2050, the challenge is to identify crop cultivars and cropping systems that make fuller use of indigenous and introduced PGPR for pest protection and growth promotion since the amount of arable land and water available for food production will likely continue to decrease.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>Experimental procedures</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Bacterial strains, soilborne pathogens and growth media</title>
        <p>Bacterial strains used in this study are listed in Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">2</xref>. <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> isolates were grown in KMB or one-third-strength KMB (<sup>1</sup>/<sub>3</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;KMB) agar or broth at 28&#xB0;C as described by Mavrodi and colleagues (<xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Other strains were grown in TSA or tryptic soy broth (TSB) or these media at one-tenth strength (<sup>1</sup>/<sub>10</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;TSB or TSA) (Mavrodi <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) at 28&#xB0;C. When needed to inhibit fungi, these media were supplemented with cycloheximide (100&#x2009;&#x3BC;g&#x2009;ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>). All strains were stored in 60% glycerol at &#x2212;80&#xB0;C. The fungal wheat root pathogens <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> (Sacc.) von Arx and Olivier var. <italic>tritici</italic> Walker isolate ARS-A1 (Yang <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b68" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) and <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> K&#xFC;hn [teleomorph <italic>Thanatephorus cucumeris</italic> (Frank) Donk] AG-8 isolate C-1 (Huang <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>), and the rapeseed/canola pathogen <italic>S.&#x2009;sclerotiorum</italic> (Lib.) de Bary isolate MGSCF180002 (from rapeseed) were grown at room temperature on one-fifth-strength homemade potato dextrose agar (<sup>1</sup>/<sub>5</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;PDA) (Yang <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b68" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). <italic>In vitro</italic> inhibition assays of pathogens by PGPR were conducted on full-strength PDA.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Sample collection</title>
        <p>Soil was sampled from five polluted sites in China: farmland contaminated with heavy metals in Daye County, Hubei Province; a riverside field at a recalcitrant organic sewage outlet in Gold Sand Bay Industrial Park, Hukou County, Jiangxi Province; farmland beside a petroleum products sewage outlet in Jinmen City, Hubei Province; and saline-alkali fields on two separate seaside farms in Qidong City (near Dongyuan and Yinyang respectively), Jiangsu Province. At each site, plants were dug to a depth of 30&#x2009;cm from five random locations. Two kilograms of soil surrounding the roots of plants from each location was placed in plastic bags, transported to the laboratory and stored at 4&#xB0;C until processed as described below.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Wheat and rapeseed greenhouse cycling assays in contaminated soils</title>
        <p>Soil from each location was sieved, put into three square pots (6.5&#x2009;cm high&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;7&#x2009;cm wide) and 10&#x2009;ml of a metalaxyl (Syngenta, Wilmington, DE, USA) solution (75&#x2009;mg&#x2009;l<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) was added to prevent damping-off disease caused by indigenous <italic>Pythium</italic> spp. Each pot served as a replicate. Six surface-sterilized seeds of wheat (cv. Zhengmai 9023) or rapeseed (cv. Xiangyou 571) were pre-germinated for 48&#x2009;h, sown in each pot and then covered with a 1.5&#x2009;cm-thick layer of sterile vermiculite. Each pot was then given 30&#x2009;ml of water. The pots were covered with a plastic bag for 4 days and incubated in a greenhouse (15&#x2013;18&#xB0;C; dark/light cycle, 12&#x2009;h). Each pot received 30&#x2009;ml of water two times weekly and diluted (1:3, vol/vol) Hoagland's solution once weekly. After 3 weeks, the seedlings were removed from the pots, roots were excised and soil and roots from all of the pots of the same treatment were mixed and added back to the pots and sown as before with wheat or rapeseed to begin a second growth cycle. At the end of the third growth cycle, roots from two randomly chosen plants from each pot were selected for enumeration of populations of total culturable aerobic, heterotrophic rhizobacteria (total bacteria) by the end-point dilution assay as described below.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Enumeration and isolation of rhizosphere bacteria</title>
        <p>Roots with adhering rhizosphere soil of two plants from the same pot were excised and placed in a 50&#x2009;ml screw-cap tube with 10&#x2009;ml of sterile distilled water, vortexed (1&#x2009;min) and sonicated in an ultrasonic cleaner (1&#x2009;min) to dislodge rhizobacteria (Mavrodi <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). The dilution endpoint assay with <sup>1</sup>/<sub>10</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;TSB plus cycloheximide was used to determine the population density of total bacteria as described by Mavrodi and colleagues (<xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). The 96-well microplates were incubated at room temperature in the dark, and after 72&#x2009;h, each well was scored for growth. At the end of the 3rd growth cycle, rhizobacteria were isolated by dilution plating of the root washings onto <sup>1</sup>/<sub>3</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;KMB agar and <sup>1</sup>/<sub>10</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;TSA, each with cycloheximide. Plates were incubated at room temperature for 2 to 3 days or until colonies were visible. Colonies of different morphotypes were re-streaked onto <sup>1</sup>/<sub>3</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;KMB and <sup>1</sup>/<sub>10</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;TSA plates and stored in 60% glycerol at &#x2212;80&#xB0;C.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Pathogen inhibition <italic>in vitro</italic></title>
        <p>Inhibition of soilborne pathogens by rhizobacteria was tested on PDA by two approaches. In the first, aliquots (20&#x2009;&#x3BC;l) from overnight broth cultures were introduced into a hole in the agar cut with a 5&#x2009;mm cork borer, 1&#x2009;cm from the edge of the Petri dish. A 5&#x2009;mm plug from a culture of <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> AG-8 or <italic>S.&#x2009;sclerotiorum</italic> grown on <sup>1</sup>/<sub>5</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;PDA was placed in the centre of the plate. Plates were incubated at 28&#xB0;C and scored after 4 days by measuring the distance between the edges of the bacteria and the fungal mycelium. Four isolates were tested on each plate and each isolate was tested three times. In a second approach, aliquots (2&#x2009;&#x3BC;l) from overnight cultures were spotted twice, 1&#x2009;cm from the edge of a plate of PDA, and a plug of <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> AG-8 was placed in the centre. For tests against <italic>G.&#x2009;graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic>, the plug of the fungus was placed in the centre of the plate 24&#x2009;h before the bacteria were spotted. The zone of inhibition was measured 5 days later. Each isolate was tested four times.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Morphological and physiological characteristics of isolates</title>
        <p>Selected isolates were characterized based on morphological and biochemical tests as described by Zhao and He (<xref rid="b69" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Morphological characteristics included colony morphology, pigmentation, cell shape and Gram stain reaction. Biochemical and physiological characterization included tests for starch hydrolysis, gelatin liquefaction, catalase production, pectin decomposition, indole production and production of phenazine-1-carboxylic acid, 2,4-DAPG, pyrrolnitrin and pyoluteorin. Cellulase activity was determined on carboxymethylcellulose (CMC) medium (per 1&#x2009;l: peptone, 10&#x2009;g; yeast extract, 10&#x2009;g; sodium CMC, 10&#x2009;g; NaCl, 5&#x2009;g; KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4,</sub> 1&#x2009;g; agar, 15&#x2009;g; pH 7.0). A 10&#x2009;&#x3BC;l aliquot of an overnight bacterial culture was spotted on sterile filter paper (5&#x2009;mm diameter, 0.5&#x2009;mm thick) on the surface of CMC agar. To visualize the zone of hydrolysis, plates were incubated at 28&#xB0;C for 48&#x2009;h, flooded with an aqueous solution of 0.1% Congo red for 1&#x2009;h and washed with 1&#x2009;M NaCl (Ghose, <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>). Protease activity, demonstrated by casein degradation, was indicated by the appearances of zones of clearing around colonies grown on milk agar (per 1&#x2009;l: dry skim milk, 100&#x2009;g; agar, 20&#x2009;g) after incubation at 28&#xB0;C for 3 days. Siderophores were detected on CAS (chrome azurols) agar plates (Shin <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b59" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Antibiotics (phenazine-1-carboxylic acid, pyrrolnitrin, pyoluteorin and DAPG) were isolated from bacterial cultures grown for 5 days on KMB agar by a modification of procedures described by Kraus and Loper (<xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>). Briefly, cells and spent agar (<italic>c</italic>. 15&#x2009;ml) were macerated with a mortar and pestle in an equal volume of acetone. The acetone was evaporated in a hood overnight and the residual aqueous phase was extracted twice with equal volumes of ethyl acetate. The ethyl acetate was recovered, dried and the residue was dissolved in 50&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of methanol. Samples (5 &#x3BC;l) of the extracts, standards of the four antibiotics, and positive control extracts from strains <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> Pf-5 and <italic>P.&#x2009;brassicacearum</italic> Q8r1-96 were spotted on silica gel (GHLF) thin layer chromatography plates (Analtech, Newark, DE, USA). The plates were developed with chloroform/acetone (9:1) and observed under UV light (254&#x2009;nm).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Amplification and sequencing of 16S rDNA, antibiotic biosynthesis and ACC deaminase genes</title>
        <p>Genomic DNA was extracted from strains using a QIAamp DNA Mini Kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA, USA) and quantified by fluorometry using a DNA quantitation kit (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). Genes encoding 16S rDNA, subunit B of DNA gyrase, sigma 70 factor of RNA polymerase and key antibiotic biosynthesis enzymes (i.e. <italic>phzF</italic>, <italic>phlD</italic>, <italic>prnD</italic> and <italic>pltC</italic>) were amplified by using published oligonucleotide primer sets (McSpadden Gardener <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b34" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; De Souza and Raaijmakers, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Mulet <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Mavrodi <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) and cycling conditions (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl9">9</xref>). The ACC deaminase gene (<italic>acdS</italic>) was targeted with primers F1936f-tail and F1938r-tail. These primers were derived from primers F1936 and F1938 (Blaha <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) by adding to their 5&#x2032;-ends sequences GCTCCTACTCTGTCACCTATC and CTGTCGCTCTGGCTGTC, respectively, for direct sequencing of <italic>acdS</italic> amplicons with primers Tail1 and Tail2 (Table&#x2009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl9">9</xref>). Amplification conditions for <italic>acdS</italic> included initial denaturation at 94&#xB0;C for 1&#x2009;min, followed by 10 cycles of 94&#xB0;C for 30&#x2009;s, 53&#xB0;C for 20&#x2009;s and 72&#xB0;C for 45&#x2009;s, followed by 25 more cycles with primer annealing temperature of 60&#xB0;C. All amplifications were performed with a PTC-200 gradient thermal cycler (Bio-Rad) using GoTaq DNA polymerase (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). The amplifications were carried out in 25&#x2009;&#x3BC;l reactions that contained 100&#x2009;ng of DNA; 1&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;GoTaq Flexi buffer, 200&#x2009;&#x3BC;M dNTPs, 1.5&#x2009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 20&#x2009;pmol of each primer pair and 1.2&#x2009;U of GoTaq Flexi DNA polymerase (Promega). Positive controls included DNA from <italic>P.&#x2009;chlororaphis</italic> subsp. <italic>aureofaciens</italic> TX-1 (<italic>phzF</italic>), <italic>P.&#x2009;brassicacearum</italic> Q8r1-96 (<italic>phlD</italic>, <italic>acdS</italic>) and <italic>P.&#x2009;protegens</italic> Pf-5 (<italic>phlD</italic>, <italic>prnD</italic>, <italic>pltC</italic>). Amplification products were cleaned with QIAquick PCR purification spin columns (Qiagen) and sequenced directly with a BigDye Terminator v. 3.1 cycle sequencing kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) at ELIM Biopharmaceuticals (Hayward, CA, USA).</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl9" position="float">
          <label>Table 9</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Target genes and PCR and primers used in this study</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence (5&#x2032;-3&#x2032;)</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annealing temp (&#xB0;C)</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative gene function</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplicon (bp)</th>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">16S</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8F</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGAGTTTGATCCTGGCTCAG</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">55</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Small-subunit rRNA</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1500</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Weisburg <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b1002" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1492R</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TACGGHTACCTTGTTACGACTT</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">
                  <italic>gyrB</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up-1G-</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YGCSGGCGGYAAGTTCGA</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">60</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">DNA gyrase subunit B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1208</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Mavrodi <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UP-2G-</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCRTCGACGTCVGCRTCGGT</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gyrBch1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGCYGGCGGTAAGTTCGA</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">57</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">DNA gyrase subunit B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1208</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gyrBch2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCGTCGACGTCRGCGTCGGT</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
                  <italic>rpoD</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PsEG30F</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATYGAAATCGCCAARCG</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">60</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sigma 70 factor of RNA polymerase</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">760</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Mulet <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PsEG790R</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGGTTGATKTCCTTGA</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>phl</italic>D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B2BF</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACCCACCGCAGCATCGTTTATGAGC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">66.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">2,4-DAPG-specific type III PKS</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">629</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">McSpadden Gardener <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b34" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BPR4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCGCCGGTATGGAAGATGAAAAAGTC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>phz</italic>F</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ps_ up 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCTTCACCCCGGTCAACG</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">57</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Phenazine biosynthesis enzyme</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">427</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Mavrodi <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ps_low 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCRTAGGCCGGTGAGAAC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>prn</italic>D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRND1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGGCGGGCCGTGGTGATGGA</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">65</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Pyrrolnitrin biosynthesis enzyme</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">786</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">De Souza and Raaijmakers, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRND2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YCCCGCSGCCTGYCTGGTCTG</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>plt</italic>C</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLTC1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AACAGATCGCCCCGGTACAGAACG</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">58</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Type I PKS</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">438</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">De Souza and Raaijmakers, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLTC2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGGCCCGGACACTCAAGAAACTCG</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">
                  <italic>acdS</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1936f-tail</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCTCCTACTCTGTCACCTATCGHGAMGACTGCAAYWSYGGC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">50</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">ACC deaminase- encoding gene</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">792</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">This study</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1938r-tail</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTGTCGCTCTGGCTGTCATCATVCCVTGCATBGAYTT</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tail1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCTCCTACTCTGTCACCTATC</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">60</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">See footnote</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Nikolic <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b43" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tail2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTGTCGCTCTGGCTGTC</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>The Tail1/Tail2 primer set was used for direct sequencing of <italic>acdS</italic> amplicons generated with primers F1936f-tail/F1938r-tail.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Sequence and phylogenetic analysis</title>
        <p>Sequence data were assembled and analysed using Geneious Pro v. 7.1.5 (Biomatters, Auckland, New Zealand). The 16S rDNA similarity searches and taxa assignments were carried out using the Classifier and SeqMatch tools available through the Ribosomal Database Project (http://rdp.cme.msu.edu). For antibiotic, ACC deaminase, <italic>gyrB</italic> and <italic>rpoD</italic> gene sequences, database searches for similar DNA and protein sequences were carried out with NCBI's BLAST network service (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST). Sequences were aligned and neighbour-joining phylogenies were inferred using the Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis software (MEGA) v. 5.2.2 (Tamura <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b60" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). DNA and protein distances were corrected by using the Kimura two-parameter (Kimura, <xref rid="b28" ref-type="bibr">1980</xref>) and Jones-Taylor-Thornton (Jones <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>) models of evolution, respectively, and bootstrap re-sampling with 1000 replicates was used to assess the reproducibility of clades in the inferred phylogenies.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Preparation of barley and oat grain inoculum</title>
        <p>Inocula of <italic>G.&#x2009;graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic> and <italic>R</italic>. <italic>solani</italic> AG-8 were prepared as described by Yang and colleagues (<xref rid="b68" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Briefly, oat or barley grains (250&#x2009;g) and water (350&#x2009;ml) were combined in a flask and autoclaved on each of two consecutive days. Sterilized grains were inoculated with pieces of agar cut from <sup>1</sup>/<sub>5</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;PDA plates of <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> or <italic>G.&#x2009;graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic>. After 21 days at room temperature, the colonized grains were tested for contamination, dried under a stream of sterile air and stored at 4&#xB0;C. Prior to use, inoculum was fragmented and sieved into sizes, with particles of 0.25&#x2013;0.5&#x2009;mm added to soil.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Bacterial treatment of wheat seed</title>
        <p>For biocontrol studies, seeds were coated with bacteria by methods similar to those of Yang and colleagues (<xref rid="b68" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Strains were inoculated onto plates of KMB or TSA and incubated at room temperature for 24&#x2013;48&#x2009;h. Bacteria were scraped into 1.0&#x2009;ml H<sub>2</sub>O, washed by centrifugation (twice for 3&#x2009;min at 14&#x2009;000&#x2009;r.p.m.) and then suspended in H<sub>2</sub>O. The concentration of the cell suspension was adjusted based on optical density (600&#x2009;nm), and an aliquot was mixed with a 2% solution of methylcellulose (MC) and deionized H<sub>2</sub>O. Wheat (130 seeds) was added into the mixture, shaken for 3&#x2009;min and seeds were dried under a stream of sterile air. To determine the final cfus per seed, 10 seeds were placed in a tube with 10&#x2009;ml of sterile water, vortexed (1&#x2009;min) and sonicated (1&#x2009;min). Population size as determined by the end-point dilution assay ranged from 10<sup>4</sup> to 10<sup>7</sup>&#x2009;cfu seed<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Biocontrol activity of rhizobacteria</title>
        <p>The biocontrol activity of strains was determined by several approaches, and against both Rhizoctonia root rot and take-all, in autoclaved, pasteurized (60&#xB0;C, 30&#x2009;min) and raw soil. For pot experiments, soil from a farm at Huazhong Agricultural University, Wuhan, China, was sieved, autoclaved and amended with barley grain inoculum of <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> (1%, w/w). Each plastic pot (10&#x2009;cm deep&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;6&#x2009;cm wide) was filled with a 5&#x2009;cm-thick layer of sterile vermiculite followed by 8&#x2009;g of infested soil. Four treated wheat seeds (cv. Yangmai 158) were sown on the surface of the soil and covered with a 1.5&#x2009;cm layer of sterile vermiculite. Controls included: control 1 (CK1), soil not amended with inoculum and sown to non-treated seeds; control 2 (CK2), soil amended with inoculum and sown to seed coated with MC; and control 3 (CK3), soil amended with inoculum and sown to non-treated seed. Each pot was given 10&#x2009;ml of 2.5&#x2009;mg&#x2009;ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> metalaxyl (Syngenta Wilmington, DE, USA) to prevent Pythium damping-off. Pots were covered with a plastic sheet to reduce evaporation, incubated at room temperature (22&#xB0;C) overnight and then transferred to a greenhouse (17&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5&#xB0;C). The plastic was removed when the tips of the shoots were visible. Each pot was watered twice weekly with water and once with <sup>1</sup>/<sub>3</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;Hoagland's solution (macro-elements only). Treatments were replicated five times and arranged in a randomized complete block design; each pot served as a replicate. After 3 to 4 weeks, the seedlings were removed from the pots, washed free of soil, and the plants were evaluated for disease severity on a scale of 0 to 8, where 0&#x2009;=&#x2009;no lesions evident and 8&#x2009;=&#x2009;seedling dead or nearly so (Huang <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). The length of the seedling shoot also was measured.</p>
        <p>Biocontrol studies of Rhizoctonia root rot and take-all were also conducted using the tube assay as described by Yang and colleagues (<xref rid="b68" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) with pasteurized or raw Shano sandy loam (Quincy virgin) from a non-cropped site near Quincy, WA, USA. Plastic tubes (2.5&#x2009;cm diameter, 16.5&#x2009;cm long) with a hole in the bottom were hung in plastic racks (200 per rack). Each tube had a cotton ball placed in the bottom, followed by a 6.5&#x2009;cm-thick column of sterile vermiculite, and then soil (10&#x2009;g), with or without inoculum of <italic>R.&#x2009;solani</italic> at 1.0 % (w/w) or <italic>G.&#x2009;graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic> at 0.7% (w/w). A 1.5&#x2009;cm-thick layer of vermiculite was placed over the infested soil, followed by three bacteria-treated wheat seeds (cv. Louise) and finally another 1.5&#x2009;cm-thick topping of vermiculite. Each tube then received 10&#x2009;ml of water with metalaxyl. Racks of tubes were covered with plastic sheets until shoots emerged and were incubated in a growth chamber (15&#x2013;18&#xB0;C; dark/light cycle 12&#x2009;h). Each cone was watered twice weekly with water and once weekly with <sup>1</sup>/<sub>3</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;Hoagland's solution. Seedlings were harvested after 3&#x2013;4 weeks and washed under a stream of water. The severity of Rhizoctonia root rot and take-all was evaluated on a scale of 0&#x2013;8 (Yang <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b68" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Detection of IAA</title>
        <p>IAA production was determined colorimetrically (Patten and Glick, <xref rid="b46" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Egamberdieva <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Strains were incubated with shaking for 48&#x2009;h at 28&#xB0;C in KMB broth alone or supplemented with 500&#x2009;&#x3BC;g per millilitre of tryptophan. Cultures were centrifuged at 13&#x2009;000&#x2009;r.p.m. for 10&#x2009;min and a 1&#x2009;ml aliquot of the supernatant was mixed vigorously with 4&#x2009;ml of Salkowski reagent. The mixture was incubated at room temperature for 25&#x2009;min and the absorbance of the pink colour was measured spectrophotometrically at 540&#x2009;nm. The concentration of IAA was determined by using a calibration curve of pure IAA (0, 20, 40, 60, 80 and 100&#x2009;&#x3BC;g&#x2009;ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) as a standard. Readings of &lt; 1&#x2009;&#x3BC;g&#x2009;ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> per OD<sub>600</sub> unit were considered as negative for IAA production.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Growth on ACC as a sole nitrogen source</title>
        <p>Strains were tested for ability to grow in a defined medium supplemented with ACC as a sole nitrogen source as described by Penrose and Glick (<xref rid="b48" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Strains were first cultured in 3&#x2009;ml of sterile DF salts minimal medium (pH 7.2): per litre, KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4,</sub> 4.0&#x2009;g; Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4,</sub> 6.0&#x2009;g; MgSO<sub>4</sub> 7H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.2&#x2009;g; glucose, 2.0&#x2009;g; gluconic acid, 2.0&#x2009;g; citric acid, 2.0&#x2009;g; trace elements (FeSO<sub>4</sub> 7H<sub>2</sub>O, 1&#x2009;mg; H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3</sub>, 10&#x2009;&#x3BC;g; MnSO<sub>4</sub> H<sub>2</sub>O, 11.19&#x2009;&#x3BC;g; ZnSO<sub>4</sub> 7H<sub>2</sub>O, 124.6&#x2009;&#x3BC;g; CuSO<sub>4</sub> 5H<sub>2</sub>O, 78.22&#x2009;&#x3BC;g; MoO<sub>3,</sub> 10&#x2009;&#x3BC;g); and (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub> SO<sub>4,</sub> 2.0&#x2009;g as a nitrogen source. After 72&#x2009;h of shaking at 28<sup>o</sup>C, a 5&#x2009;&#x3BC;l aliquot was transferred to 3&#x2009;ml sterile DF salts medium with 3.0&#x2009;mM ACC instead of (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub> SO<sub>4</sub> as the source of nitrogen. <italic>Pseudomonas brassicacearum</italic> Q8r1-96 was used as a positive control.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Canola root elongation assay</title>
        <p>A gnotobiotic canola root elongation assay was used to determine the ability of strains to promote growth (Egamberdieva <italic>et&#x2009;al</italic>., <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). An aliquot of an overnight culture was centrifuged, the cell pellet was washed twice and suspended in 1&#x2009;ml of sterile 0.03&#x2009;M MgSO<sub>4.</sub> The suspension was adjusted to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.15. Surface-sterilized spring canola seeds (cv. InVigor 8440) were soaked for 1&#x2009;h in 700&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of a bacterial suspension. Depending on the isolate, the concentration ranged from 10<sup>4</sup> to 10<sup>6</sup>&#x2009;cfu seed<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. Growth pouches were made using 1-gallon Ziploc plastic bags and sterile germination paper soaked with 50&#x2009;ml of <sup>1</sup>/<sub>5</sub>&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;Hoagland's solution. Twenty-five seeds of a single bacterial treatment were distributed along the germination paper and the paper was placed inside of the bag. Individual bags were then hung vertically, covered with aluminium foil for 1&#x2013;2 days and incubated at 20&#xB0;C in a dark/light cycle of 12&#x2009;h. The length of the primary roots was measured 5 days after sowing. Roots of seeds that failed to germinate 2 days after sowing were not measured. This study was conducted five times with three representative experiments shown.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Tolerance of bacteria to abiotic stress</title>
        <p>The tolerance of selected strains to copper, cadmium and NaCl was determined in Luria&#x2013;Bertani (LB) broth amended with CuCl<sub>2</sub> to give concentrations from 3 to 6&#x2009;mM; CdCl<sub>2</sub> to give concentrations from 0.4 to 2.0&#x2009;mM; and NaCl to give concentrations from 0% to 8%. Each well of a 96-well microplate was filled with 200&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of LB supplemented with the heavy metal or salt solutions and inoculated with 2&#x2009;&#x3BC;l of an overnight culture of each isolate (OD<sub>600</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.1). Each isolate at each concentration of heavy metal or salt was replicated eight times. The microplates were incubated at room temperature in the dark for 72&#x2009;h and assayed spectrophotometrically at 600&#x2009;nm using a model 680 microplate reader (Bio-Rad). An OD<sub>600</sub>&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;0.1 was scored as positive for growth. The MIC was defined as the lowest concentration that completely inhibited the growth of the isolate.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>Comparisons of means of root disease ratings were performed using standard analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Kruskal&#x2013;Wallis all pairwise comparisons (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&#x2264;&#x2009;0.05) (Statistix 8.1, Analytical Software, Tallahassee, FL, USA). Mean comparisons of plant height and root length among treatments were determined by ANOVA followed by using either the Fisher's protected least significant difference test (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.05) or the Kruskal&#x2013;Wallis all pairwise test (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.05). Bacterial population sizes were log transformed before analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Accession numbers</title>
        <p>Nucleotide sequences were deposited in GeneBank under the following accession numbers: <italic>pltC,</italic> KC357589 through KC357592; <italic>prnD,</italic> KC693004 through KC693007; <italic>phlD,</italic> KC693000 through KC693003; <italic>acdS,</italic> KC430107 through KC430112; <italic>gyrB</italic>, KM030038 through KM030046; <italic>rpoD</italic>, KM030047 through KM030055; 16S rDNA, KM030056 through KM030064. The <italic>phzF</italic> sequence of strain KY5406 was deposited under accession number KC572125.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>Mention of trade names or commercial products in this publication is solely for the purpose of providing specific information and does not imply recommendation or endorsement by the U.S. Department of Agriculture. USDA is an equal opportunity provider and employer.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec>
      <title>Conflict of interest</title>
      <p>None declared.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="b1">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Achouak</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sutra</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heulin</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meyer</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fromin</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Degraeve</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Pseudomonas brassicacearum</italic> sp. nov., and <italic>Pseudomonas thivervalensis</italic> sp. nov., two root-associated bacteria isolated from <italic>Brassica napus</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>
          <source>Int J Syst Evol Micr</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>9</fpage>
          <lpage>18</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Altimira</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yanez</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bravo</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonzalez</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rojas</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seeger</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization of copper-resistant bacteria and bacterial communities from copper-polluted agricultural soils of central Chile</article-title>
          <source>BMC Microbiol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>193</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22950448</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bais</surname>
              <given-names>HP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weir</surname>
              <given-names>TL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perry</surname>
              <given-names>LG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilroy</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vivanco</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of root exudates in rhizosphere interactions with plants and other organisms</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>233</fpage>
          <lpage>266</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16669762</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Belimov</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Safronova</surname>
              <given-names>VI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sergeyeva</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Egorova</surname>
              <given-names>TN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matveyeva</surname>
              <given-names>VA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsyganov</surname>
              <given-names>VE</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization of plant growth-promoting rhizobacteria isolated from polluted soils and containing 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate deaminase</article-title>
          <source>Can Microbiol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>642</fpage>
          <lpage>652</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Belimov</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dodd</surname>
              <given-names>IC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Safronova</surname>
              <given-names>VI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hontzeas</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Davies</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Pseudomonas brassicacearum</italic> strain Am3 containing 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate deaminase can show both pathogenic and growth-promoting properties in its interaction with tomato</article-title>
          <source>J Exp Bot</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>1485</fpage>
          <lpage>1495</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17322547</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Blaha</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prigent-Combaret</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mirza</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moenne-Loccoz</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phylogeny of the 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid deaminase-encoding gene <italic>acdS</italic> in phytobeneficial and pathogenic Proteobacteria and relation with strain biogeography</article-title>
          <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>455</fpage>
          <lpage>470</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16689877</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cai</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Long</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Food chain transfer of cadmium and lead to cattle in a lead-zinc smelter in Guizhou, China</article-title>
          <source>Environ Pollut</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>157</volume>
          <fpage>3078</fpage>
          <lpage>3082</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19573961</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cheng</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effect of heavy metal on plants and resistance mechanisms</article-title>
          <source>Environ Sci Pollut R</source>
          <year>2003a</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>256</fpage>
          <lpage>264</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cheng</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Heavy metal pollution in China: origin, pattern and control</article-title>
          <source>Environ Sci Pollut R</source>
          <year>2003b</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>192</fpage>
          <lpage>198</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cook</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schillinger</surname>
              <given-names>WF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Christensen</surname>
              <given-names>NW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rhizoctonia root rot and take-all of wheat in diverse direct-seed spring cropping systems</article-title>
          <source>Can J Plant Pathol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>349</fpage>
          <lpage>358</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>De Souza</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Raaijmakers</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Polymorphisms within the <italic>prnD</italic> and <italic>pltC</italic> genes from pyrrolnitrin and pyoluteorin-producing <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> and <italic>Burkholderia</italic> spp</article-title>
          <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>21</fpage>
          <lpage>34</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19719693</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b12">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Egamberdieva</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Pseudomonas chlororaphis</italic>: a salt-tolerant bacterial inoculant for plant growth stimulation under saline soil condition</article-title>
          <source>Acta Physiol Plant</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>751</fpage>
          <lpage>756</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b13">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Egamberdieva</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kucharova</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Selection for root colonizing bacteria stimulating wheat growth in saline soils</article-title>
          <source>Biol Fert Soils</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>563</fpage>
          <lpage>571</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b14">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Egamberdieva</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamilova</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Validov</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gafurova</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kucharova</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lugtenberg</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>High incidence of plant growth-stimulating bacteria associated with the rhizosphere of wheat grown on salinated soil in Uzbekistan</article-title>
          <source>Environ Microbiol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18211262</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b15">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Elmer</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Influence of formononetin and NaCl on mycorrhizal colonization and fusarium crown and root rot of asparagus</article-title>
          <source>Plant Dis</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <fpage>1318</fpage>
          <lpage>1324</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b16">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ghose</surname>
              <given-names>TK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Measurement of cellulase activities</article-title>
          <source>Pure Appl Chem</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>257</fpage>
          <lpage>268</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b17">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Glick</surname>
              <given-names>BR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheng</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Czarny</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Duan</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Promotion of plant growth by ACC deaminase-producing soil bacteria</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Plant Pathol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>119</volume>
          <fpage>329</fpage>
          <lpage>339</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b18">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gremion</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chatzinotas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaufmann</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>von Sigler</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harms</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Impacts of heavy metal contamination and phytoremediation on a microbial community during a twelve-month microcosm experiment</article-title>
          <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>273</fpage>
          <lpage>283</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19712410</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b19">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gao</surname>
              <given-names>ZY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deng</surname>
              <given-names>YM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>ZZ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Environmental geochemistry of abandoned flotation tailing reservoir from the Tonglvshan Fe-Cu sulfide mine in Daye, Central China</article-title>
          <source>B Environ Contam Tox</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <lpage>95</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b20">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haas</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>D&#xE9;fago</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Biological control of soil-borne pathogens by fluorescent pseudomonads</article-title>
          <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>307</fpage>
          <lpage>319</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15759041</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b22">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hartmann</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmid</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tuinen</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berg</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Plant-driven selection of microbes</article-title>
          <source>Plant Soil</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>321</volume>
          <fpage>235</fpage>
          <lpage>257</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b23">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>XD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>El-Alawai</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gurska</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glick</surname>
              <given-names>BR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Greenberg</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A multi-process phytoremediation system for decontamination of persistent total petroleum hydro-carbons (TPHs) from soils</article-title>
          <source>Microchem J</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <fpage>139</fpage>
          <lpage>147</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b24">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonsall</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
              <given-names>DV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weller</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thomashow</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transformation of <italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic> with genes for biosynthesis of phenazine-1-carboxylic acid improves biocontrol of Rhizoctonia root rot and in situ antibiotic production</article-title>
          <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>243</fpage>
          <lpage>251</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19712418</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b25">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Islam</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hashidoko</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deora</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ito</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tahara</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Suppression of damping-off disease in host plants by the rhizoplane bacterium <italic>Lysobacter</italic> sp. strain SB-K88 is linked to plant colonization and antibiosis against soilborne Peronosporomycetes</article-title>
          <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <fpage>3786</fpage>
          <lpage>3796</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16000790</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b26">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jing</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Role of soil rhizobacteria in phytoremediation of heavy metal contaminated soils</article-title>
          <source>J Zhejiang Univ Sci B</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>192</fpage>
          <lpage>207</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17323432</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b27">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>DT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>WR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thornton</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The rapid generation of mutation data matrices from protein sequences</article-title>
          <source>Computer Appl Biosci</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>275</fpage>
          <lpage>282</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b28">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kimura</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A simple method for estimating evolutionary rates of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequences</article-title>
          <source>J Mol Evol</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>111</fpage>
          <lpage>120</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7463489</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b29">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kraus</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Loper</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lack of evidence for a role of antifungal metabolite production by <italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic> Pf-5 in biological control of Pythium damping-off of cucumber</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>264</fpage>
          <lpage>271</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b30">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ye</surname>
              <given-names>ZH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of bacteria on enhanced metal uptake of the Cd/Zn-hyperaccumulating plant <italic>Sedum alfredii</italic></article-title>
          <source>J Exp Bot</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>4173</fpage>
          <lpage>4182</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18039737</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b31">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Loper</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
              <given-names>DY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Paulsen</surname>
              <given-names>IT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The genomic sequence of <italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic> Pf-5: insights into biological control</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>233</fpage>
          <lpage>238</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944380</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b32">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Loper</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hassan</surname>
              <given-names>KA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
              <given-names>DV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davis</surname>
              <given-names>EW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lim</surname>
              <given-names>CK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shaffer</surname>
              <given-names>BT</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparative genomics of plant-associated <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp: insights into diversity and inheritance of traits involved in multitrophic interactions</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Genet</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>e1002784</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22792073</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b33">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lugtenberg</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kamilova</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Plant-growth-promoting rhizobacteria</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>541</fpage>
          <lpage>556</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19575558</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b34">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McSpadden Gardener</surname>
              <given-names>BBM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
              <given-names>DV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomashow</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weller</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A rapid polymerase chain reaction-based assay characterizing rhizosphere population of 2,4-diacetylphloroglucinol-producing bacteria</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>44</fpage>
          <lpage>54</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944277</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b35">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
              <given-names>DV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blankenfeldt</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thomashow</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phenazine compounds in fluorescent <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp.: biosynthesis and regulation</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>417</fpage>
          <lpage>445</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16719720</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b36">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
              <given-names>DV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peever</surname>
              <given-names>TL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
              <given-names>OV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parejko</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raaijmakers</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lemanceau</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diversity and evolution of the phenazine biosynthesis pathway</article-title>
          <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <fpage>866</fpage>
          <lpage>879</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20008172</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b37">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
              <given-names>DV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
              <given-names>OV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parejko</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonsall</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kwak</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paulitz</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Accumulation of the antibiotic phenazine-1-carboxylic acid in the rhizosphere of dryland cereals</article-title>
          <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>804</fpage>
          <lpage>812</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22138981</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b38">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mazurier</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corberand</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lemanceau</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Raaijmakers</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phenazine antibiotics produced by fluorescent pseudomonads contribute to natural soil suppressiveness to Fusarium wilt</article-title>
          <source>ISME J</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>977</fpage>
          <lpage>991</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19369971</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b39">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mittra</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghosh</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henry</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mishra</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Das</surname>
              <given-names>TK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghosh</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Novel mode of resistance to <italic>Fusarium</italic> infection by a mild dose pre-exposure of cadmium in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol Bioch</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>781</fpage>
          <lpage>787</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b40">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mulet</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennasar</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lalucat</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Garc&#xED;a-Vald&#xE9;s</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An <italic>rpoD</italic>-based PCR procedure for the identification of <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> species and for their detection in environmental samples</article-title>
          <source>Mol Cell Probes</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>140</fpage>
          <lpage>147</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19268522</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b41">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mulet</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lalucat</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Garc&#xED;a-Vald&#xE9;s</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>DNA sequence-based analysis of the <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> species</article-title>
          <source>Environ Microbiol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>1513</fpage>
          <lpage>1530</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20192968</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b42">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nakayama</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Homma</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hashidoko</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mizutani</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tahara</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Possible role of xanthobaccins produced by <italic>Stenotrophomonas</italic> sp. strain SB-K88 in suppression of sugar beet damping-off disease</article-title>
          <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>4334</fpage>
          <lpage>4339</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508056</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b43">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nikolic</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schwab</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sessitsch</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Metagenomic analysis of the 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate deaminase gene (<italic>acdS</italic>) operon of an uncultured bacterial endophyte colonizing <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L</article-title>
          <source>Arch Mirobiol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>193</volume>
          <fpage>665</fpage>
          <lpage>676</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b44">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Parida</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Das</surname>
              <given-names>AB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Salt tolerance and salinity effects on plants: a review</article-title>
          <source>Ecotox Environ Safe</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>324</fpage>
          <lpage>349</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b45">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aslam</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeon</surname>
              <given-names>CO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>YR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Lysobacter capsici</italic> sp. nov., with antimicrobial activity, isolated from the rhizosphere of pepper, and emended description of the genus <italic>Lysobacter</italic></article-title>
          <source>Int J Syst Evol Microb</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>387</fpage>
          <lpage>392</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b46">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Patten</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Glick</surname>
              <given-names>BR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Role of <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic> indoleacetic acid in development of the host plant root system</article-title>
          <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>3795</fpage>
          <lpage>3801</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12147474</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b1001">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Paulitz</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smiley</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cook</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Insights into the prevalence and management of soilborne cereal pathogens under direct seeding in the Pacific Northwest, U.S.A</article-title>
          <source>Can J Plant Path</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>416</fpage>
          <lpage>428</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b47">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Paulsen</surname>
              <given-names>IT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Press</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ravel</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
              <given-names>DY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Myers</surname>
              <given-names>GSA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
              <given-names>DV</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Complete genome sequence of the plant commensal <italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic> Pf-5: insights into the biological control of plant disease</article-title>
          <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>873</fpage>
          <lpage>878</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980861</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b48">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Penrose</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Glick</surname>
              <given-names>BR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Methods for isolating and characterizing ACC deaminase-containing plant growth-promoting rhizobacteria</article-title>
          <source>Physiol Plantarum</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>118</volume>
          <fpage>10</fpage>
          <lpage>15</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b49">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pierson</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thomashow</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cloning and heterologous expression of the phenazine biosynthetic locus form <italic>Pseudomonas aureofaciens</italic> 30&#x2013;84</article-title>
          <source>Mol Plant-Microbe In</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>330</fpage>
          <lpage>339</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b50">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pieterse</surname>
              <given-names>CMJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zamioudis</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berendsen</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weller</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Wees</surname>
              <given-names>SCM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bakker</surname>
              <given-names>PAHM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Induced systemic resistance by beneficial microbes</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>347</fpage>
          <lpage>375</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b51">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Poschenrieder</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tolr&#xE0;</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barcel&#xF3;</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Can metals defend plants against biotic stress?</article-title>
          <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>288</fpage>
          <lpage>295</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16697693</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b52">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Powell</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vargas</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nair</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Detweiler</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chandra</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Management of dollar spot on creeping bentgrass with metabolites of <italic>Pseudomonas aureofaciens</italic> (TX-1)</article-title>
          <source>Plant Dis</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>19</fpage>
          <lpage>24</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b53">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ramette</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frapolli</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fischer-Le Saux</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gruffaz</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meyer</surname>
              <given-names>J-M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D&#xE9;fago</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Pseudomonas protegens</italic> sp. nov., widespread plant-protecting bacteria producing the biocontrol compounds 2,4-diacetylphloroglucinol and pyoluteorin</article-title>
          <source>Syst Appl Microbiol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>180</fpage>
          <lpage>188</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21392918</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b54">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Reed</surname>
              <given-names>MLE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Glick</surname>
              <given-names>BR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Growth of canola (<italic>Brassica napus</italic>) in the presence of plant growth-promoting bacteria and either copper or polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons</article-title>
          <source>Can J Microbiol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>1061</fpage>
          <lpage>1069</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16462865</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b55">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ross</surname>
              <given-names>IL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alami</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harvey</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Achouak</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ryder</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic diversity and biological control activity of novel species of closely related pseudomonads isolated from wheat field soils in South Australia</article-title>
          <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>1609</fpage>
          <lpage>1616</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10742249</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b56">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Roubtsova</surname>
              <given-names>TV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bostock</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Episodic abiotic stress as a potential contributing factor to onset and severity of disease caused by <italic>Phytophthora ramorum</italic> in <italic>Rhododendron</italic> and <italic>Viburnum</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Dis</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>912</fpage>
          <lpage>918</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b57">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Safronova</surname>
              <given-names>VI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stepanok</surname>
              <given-names>VV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Engqvist</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alekseyev</surname>
              <given-names>YV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Belimov</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Root-associated bacteria containing 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate deaminase improve growth and nutrient uptake by pea genotypes cultivated in cadmium supplemented soil</article-title>
          <source>Biol Fert Soils</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>267</fpage>
          <lpage>272</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b58">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sandaa</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Torvik</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Enger</surname>
              <given-names>&#xD8;</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daae</surname>
              <given-names>FL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castberg</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hahn</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysis of bacterial communities in heavy metal-contaminated soils at different levels of resolution</article-title>
          <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>237</fpage>
          <lpage>251</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10525180</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b59">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shin</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lim</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>NW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rhee</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>CAS agar diffusion assay for the measurement of siderophores in biological fluids</article-title>
          <source>Microbiol Meth</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>89</fpage>
          <lpage>95</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b60">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tamura</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dudley</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nei</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>1596</fpage>
          <lpage>1599</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488738</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b61">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohamed</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Haschne-Berger</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Merroun</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Merkel</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Interactions of <italic>Paenibacillus</italic> sp. and <italic>Sulfolobus acidocaldarius</italic> strains with U(VI)</article-title>
          <source>Uranium, Mining and Hydrogeology</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <publisher-loc>Berlin, Germany</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
          <fpage>703</fpage>
          <lpage>710</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b62">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thomashow</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weller</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Role of a phenazine antibiotic from <italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic> in biological control of <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic></article-title>
          <source>J Bacteriol</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>170</volume>
          <fpage>3499</fpage>
          <lpage>3508</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2841289</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b63">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Triky-Dotan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yermiyahu</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katan</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gamliel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of crown and root rot disease of tomato under irrigation with saline water</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <fpage>1438</fpage>
          <lpage>1444</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18943555</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b64">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wei</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A review of heavy metal contaminations in urban soils, urban road dusts and agricultural soils from China</article-title>
          <source>Microchem J</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>99</fpage>
          <lpage>107</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b1002">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weisburg</surname>
              <given-names>WG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barns</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pelletier</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lane</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>16S ribosomal DNA amplification for phylogenetic study</article-title>
          <source>J Bact</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>173</volume>
          <fpage>697</fpage>
          <lpage>703</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1987160</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b65">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weller</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> biocontrol agents of soilborne pathogens: Looking back over 30 years</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>250</fpage>
          <lpage>256</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944383</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b66">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weller</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Landa</surname>
              <given-names>BB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
              <given-names>OV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schroeder</surname>
              <given-names>KL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De La Fuente</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blouin Bankhead</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Role of 2,4-diacetylphloroglucinol-producing fluorescent <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp. in the defense of plant roots</article-title>
          <source>Plant Biol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>4</fpage>
          <lpage>20</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17058178</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b67">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weller</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
              <given-names>DV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Pelt</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pieterse</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Loon</surname>
              <given-names>LC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bakker</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Induced systemic resistance in Arabidopsis thaliana against <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv. <italic>tomato</italic> by 2,4-diacetylphloroglucinol-producing <italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic></article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>403</fpage>
          <lpage>412</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22409433</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b68">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
              <given-names>DV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mavrodi</surname>
              <given-names>OV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonsall</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parejko</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paulitz</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Biological control of take-all by fluorescent <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp. from Chinese wheat fields</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>1481</fpage>
          <lpage>1491</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22070279</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b69">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Microbiological Experiment</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <publisher-loc>Beijing, China</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Beijing Science Press</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b70">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Soil heavy metals and fluorine pollution and health</article-title>
          <source>Soil Pollution and Physical Health</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <publisher-loc>Beijing, China</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>China Environmental Science Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>132</fpage>
          <lpage>194</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <p>Additional Supporting information may be found in the online version of this article at the publisher's web-site:</p>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd1">
        <p><bold>Fig.&#x2009;S1.</bold>&#x2002;Neighbour-joining phylogeny inferred from concatenated housekeeping genes 16S, <italic>gyrB</italic> and <italic>rpoD</italic>. The concatenated housekeeping gene data set contained 2911 characters. Evolutionary distances were estimated using the Kimura two-parameter model of nucleotide substitution. Indels were ignored in the analysis and reproducibility of clades was assessed by bootstrap resampling with 1000 pseudoreplicates. The branch lengths are proportional to the amount of evolutionary change. The scale bars indicate substitution per site. Subgroups within the <italic>P</italic>. fluorescens lineage are defined according to Mulet and colleagues (2010).</p>
        <p><bold>Fig.&#x2009;S2.</bold>&#x2002;Neighbour-joining phylogeny inferred from data for aligned 578&#x2013;bp fragments of <italic>phlD</italic> sequences of fluorescent <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp. Indels were ignored in the analysis, and evolutionary distances were estimated using the Kimura two-parameter model of nucleotide substitution. Bootstrap values greater than 60% are indicated at the nodes, and the branch lengths are proportional to the amount of evolutionary change. Clades indicated by capital letters correspond to BOX-PCR genotypes of 2,4-diacetylphloroglucinol-producing <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp. as defined by De La Fuente and colleagues (2006).</p>
        <p><bold>Fig.&#x2009;S3.</bold>&#x2002;Neighbour-joining phylogeny inferred from data for aligned 390&#x2013;bp fragments of <italic>pltC</italic> sequences of fluorescent <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp. Indels were ignored in the analysis, and evolutionary distances were estimated using the Kimura two-parameter model of nucleotide substitution. Bootstrap values greater than 60% are indicated at the nodes, and the branch lengths are proportional to the amount of evolutionary change.</p>
        <p><bold>Fig.&#x2009;S4.</bold>&#x2002;Neighbour-joining phylogeny inferred from data for aligned 745&#x2013;bp fragments of <italic>prnD</italic> sequences of pyrrolnitrin-producing species. Indels were ignored in the analysis, and evolutionary distances were estimated using the Kimura two-parameter model of nucleotide substitution. Bootstrap values greater than 60% are indicated at the nodes, and the branch lengths are proportional to the amount of evolutionary change. Clades C1 through C2.4 correspond to distinct groups of pyrrolnitrin-producing bacteria as defined by Costa and colleagues (2009).</p>
        <p><bold>Fig.&#x2009;S5.</bold>&#x2002;Neighbour-joining phylogeny inferred from data for aligned 391&#x2013;bp fragments of <italic>phzF</italic> sequences of fluorescent <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp. Indels were ignored in the analysis, and evolutionary distances were estimated using the Kimura two-parameter model of nucleotide substitution. Bootstrap values greater than 60% are indicated at the nodes, and the branch lengths are proportional to the amount of evolutionary change. Clades A1 through A5 correspond to distinct groups of phenazine-producing bacteria as defined by Mavrodi and colleagues (2010).</p>
        <p><bold>Fig.&#x2009;S6.</bold>&#x2002;Neighbour-joining phylogeny inferred from data for aligned 714&#x2013;bp fragments of <italic>acdS</italic> sequences of ACC-deaminase-producing bacteria. Indels were ignored in the analysis, and evolutionary distances were estimated using the Kimura two-parameter model of nucleotide substitution. Bootstrap values greater than 60% are indicated at the nodes, and the branch lengths are proportional to the amount of evolutionary change. Clades A through C correspond to distinct groups of ACC-deaminase-producing bacteria as defined by Blaha and colleagues (2006).</p>
        <media mimetype="zip" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="mbt20008-0404-sd1.zip" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e7713" position="anchor"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </back>
</article>
