<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.1 20050630//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.1?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformation</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformation</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Bioinformation</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Bioinformation</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0973-8894</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">0973-2063</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Biomedical Informatics</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3400987</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">97320630008617</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6026/97320630008617</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Hypothesis</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Cloning and characterization of two neuropeptide genes from cereal cyst nematode, <italic>Heterodera avanae</italic> from India</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Thakur</surname>
            <given-names>Prasoon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sharma</surname>
            <given-names>Amita</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rao</surname>
            <given-names>Sashi B</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kumar</surname>
            <given-names>Mukesh</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>G</surname>
            <given-names>Nagavara Prasad</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tyagi</surname>
            <given-names>Nidhi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kamaraju</surname>
            <given-names>Divya</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Papolu</surname>
            <given-names>Pradeep</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Banakar</surname>
            <given-names>Prakash</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rao</surname>
            <given-names>Uma</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Division of Nematology, Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI), New Delhi-110012</aff>
        <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>The Ella Foundation, Hyderabad, India-500039</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>Uma Rao: <email>umarao@iari.res.in</email>Phone: 011-25842721</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>13</issue>
      <fpage>617</fpage>
      <lpage>621</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2012 Biomedical Informatics</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium,for non-commercial purposes, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The cereal cyst nematode, <italic>Heterodera avenae</italic> (Wollenweber, <italic>1924</italic>) is one of the most important plant parasitic nematodes of cereals.
It is an obligate sedentary endo parasite causing considerable crop losses in wheat, barley and oats worldwide. FMRFamide-like
peptides (FLPs) play critical role as neurotransmitters or neuromodulators in the nervous system and proposed as one of the
important targets for the plant parasitic nematode management. Therefore, for the first time we have cloned and characterized two
neuropeptide genes (<italic>flp-12</italic> and <italic>flp-16</italic>) from the cDNA library of feeding female of <italic>H. avenae</italic>. Sequence analysis of FLPs revealed
that both the neuropeptides are closely related with the parasitic as well as free-living nematodes. The <italic>flp-12</italic> contains putative 22
residue long signal peptide at N-terminal suggesting its association with extra-cellular functions, while <italic>flp-16</italic> does not contain
signal peptide. Besides this, we have found highly conserved motif KFEFIRF in <italic>flp-12</italic> and RFGK motif in <italic>flp-16</italic>. These two <italic>flp</italic> genes
could be interesting and potential targets for functional validation to explore their utility for designing management strategies.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>The Cereal cyst nematode (CCN) is a composite group of 12
species that infects graminaceous cereals and grasses resulting
in high crop losses and distributed worldwide 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>]. Among
them, the most economically important species is <italic>H. avenae</italic>
(Wollenweber, 1924) that can resist harsh environmental
conditions and spread through the means by which soil is
disseminated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>,
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]. Although chemical nematicides are the
most reliable means of controlling CCN; their use is consistently
being discontinued due to their toxicity to humans and the
environmental safety. Novel and specific targets are thus
needed to develop new strategies against these CCNs 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>].</p>
      <p>Neuromuscular system plays critical role in the location and
penetration of host roots, secretory activities, migration,
alimentation, and reproduction of plant parasitic nematodes
(PPNs). Neuropeptide signaling system has been proposed to
be the potential target for the management of plant parasitic
nematodes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. FMRFamide-like peptides (FLPs) have shown to
be widely expressed in the nervous system of the cyst-forming
nematodes, <italic>H. glycines, Globodera pallida</italic>, and <italic>G. rostochiensis</italic> 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>].
The largest families of neuropeptides in nematodes are the
FLPs, which possess a C-terminal Arg-Phe-NH2 signature and
play a central role in motor activities. There are 28 <italic>flp</italic> genes
reported in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> encoding at least 72 distinct
peptides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>]. In addition, 21 FLPs have been identified in
another very economically important species of the root knot
nematode, <italic>Meloidogyne incognita</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>]. Functions of <italic>flp</italic> genes are
regulated by MicroRNAs (miRNAs) and <italic>flp-12</italic> and <italic>flp-16</italic> were
identified as potential targets in pine wood nematode,
<italic>Bursaphelenchus xylophilus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>]. Although studies on role of FLPs
on behavior of plant parasitic nematodes are limited, a series of
RNA interference studies of <italic>flp</italic> genes in <italic>G. pallida</italic> revealed
aberrant behavioral phenotypes and migrational abilities 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>].
<italic>flp-12</italic> is predicted to be crucial for the normal muscular
function in <italic>G. pallida</italic> and <italic>M. incognita</italic> as it has interfered with
the nematode migration in a sand column in response to the
root defusates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>].</p>
      <p>In <italic>C. elegans</italic>, some <italic>flp</italic> gene knockouts have induced multiple
aberrant behavioral phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>] and each <italic>flp</italic> gene is
expressed in a unique set of neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>] consistent with FLPs
roles in a wide array of different motor behaviors. While
expression patterns of FLPs in plant parasitic nematodes (PPN)
do not appear to reflect those seen in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, a similar
restricted and unique neuronal expression pattern was reported
for five <italic>flp</italic> genes examined in <italic>G. pallida</italic> 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>]. CCN genomic
information is completely nonexistent and in the present study
for the first time, we have cloned and characterized two genes,
<italic>flp-12</italic> and <italic>flp-16</italic> from Indian isolates of <italic>H. avenae</italic> using
orthologous sequences present in <italic>M. incognita</italic>. These two
neuropeptides of <italic>H. avenae</italic> could be useful to design strategies
for its management.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
      <title>Methodology</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title><italic>Nematode collection and multiplication on wheat plants</italic>:</title>
        <p>Cysts of CCN were collected from wheat roots growing in the
fields of Indian Agricultural Research Institute, New Delhi,
India. Genetic homogeneity of the population was characterized
by sequencing and PCR - RFLP of ITS (Internal transcribed
spacers) of rDNA (ribosomal DNA). Genetically homogenous
populations were multiplied on wheat plants growing in pots
under green house conditions and mature brown cysts were
collected. Wheat plants were infected with juveniles and after 4
&#x2013; 8 weeks, feeding females protruding out of the wheat roots
were collected, frozen and used for RNA extraction.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title><italic>cDNA library construction, PCR amplification, cloning and sequencing of flp genes of H. avenae</italic>:</title>
        <p>Total RNA was extracted from approximately 500 mg of frozen
feeding females of <italic>H. avenae</italic>. Poly (A+) mRNA was purified and
a cDNA library was constructed using Clontech's smart cDNA
synthesis protocol as per manufacturer's instruction. <italic>Flp-12</italic> and
<italic>flp-16</italic> were PCR amplified from the cDNA library using the
primers designed based on the published nucleotide sequence
of <italic>flp-12</italic> and <italic>flp-16</italic> genes from <italic>M. incognita</italic>, (Accession No:
AY804187 and Accession No: EU549831 respectively). The
sequences of the primer sets were forward primer: 5'-
CCCAAGTTTGAGCTCTAAAAACAC 3'; reverse primer: 5'-
TCATCGTCCAAATCGAATGA3' for <italic>flp-12</italic> and forward
primer: 5'ATTTGATTGCCTCCTTAACACG3'; reverse primer:
5'- GTTTTGAATCTCTCCCAAATCG - 3' for <italic>flp-16</italic>.</p>
        <p>PCR amplification reactions were performed in 25 &#xB5;l reaction
volumes containing 2.5 &#xB5;l 10 x assay buffer (100mM Tris-HCl
(pH 8.8 at 25&#xB0;C), 500 mM KCl, 15 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1% gelatin,
0.05% Tween 20 and 0.05% NP-40), 200 &#xB5;M each of dATP,
dCTP, dGTP and dTTP (Fermentas), 16 ng primer, 1 unit of Taq
polymerase (MBI Fermentas, Genetix, India) and 1 &#xB5;l cDNA
library. The PCR cycles consisted of initial denaturation at 94&#xB0;C
for 4 min, followed by 35 cycles of amplification, denaturation
at 94&#xB0; C for 60 s, annealing at 55&#xB0;C for 30 s and extension at 720C
for 1 min with a final extension at 72&#xB0;C for 10 min. The
amplified product was run on 1.0% Agarose gel electrophoresis
to confirm the size of the amplified product.</p>
        <p>The fresh PCR product was cloned into pGEM-T cloning vector
(Promega, USA) using standard protocol. Freshly prepared
competent cells of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> DH5&#x3B1; were transformed with
the recombinant plasmids. Positive clones were selected by
using ampicillin, blue white colonies and colony PCR. Inserts
were confirmed by restriction digestion with EcoRI. The positive
clones were custom sequenced by ABI solid sequencing
platform.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title><italic>Computational Sequence Analysis</italic>:</title>
        <p>The amino acid sequences were deduced from the
corresponding nucleotide sequences by using ExPASy
translates available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://expasy.org/">http://expasy.org/</ext-link>. In order to find the
homology with the plant parasitic nematodes, we performed
the protein BLAST for the protein sequence and nucleotide
BLAST for the nucleotide sequences using default parameters
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. Comparison with the homologous sequences was done
with ClustalW [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]. Theoretical isoelectric point (pI) and
molecular weight (mw) for the conceptually translated protein
sequences were calculated by the Expasy Protparam tool. Gene
ontology term was assigned through AmiGO BLAST. Signal
peptides were predicted by the SignalP server [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>].</p>
        <p>Phylogenetic tree was plotted by the maximum likelihood
method based on the Jones-Taylor-Thornton model of amino
acid change using Bioedit software package 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title><italic>Cloning of flp genes from cDNA of H.avenae</italic>:</title>
        <p>The coding sequences of the two FLPs (<italic>flp-12</italic> and <italic>flp-16</italic>) were
amplified from the cDNA library of feeding female stage of <italic>H.
avenae</italic>. PCR amplification gave 349 bp and 310 bp for <italic>flp-12</italic>and
<italic>flp-16</italic> respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Amplified <italic>flp</italic> genes were cloned
into pGEM-T TA cloning vector and recombinant plasmids
were confirmed by colony PCR using specific gene primers.
Further the plasmids were prepared for the positive
recombinants and inserts were confirmed by restriction
digestion with EcoRI. The cloned genes were sequenced using
ABI solid sequencing platform and sequences are given in
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a &amp; 2b</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title><italic>Characterization of the sequences</italic>:</title>
        <p>Sequence of the partial cDNA of <italic>flp-12</italic> (349 bp) and <italic>flp-16</italic> (301
bp) obtained from cDNA library of <italic>H. avenae</italic> were submitted to
Genbank sequence database (Accession Nos: JF437713 and
JF437714). The percentage of the GC content was 35.2% and
39.2% for <italic>flp-12</italic> and <italic>flp-16</italic> respectively which were similar to
the previously reported GC content for other plant parasitic
nematodes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>]. BLASTN was carried out to determine the
homology against non-redundant Genbank database. <italic>flp-12</italic>
and <italic>flp-16</italic> showed 96% and 95 % identity respectively with that
of <italic>M. incognita</italic>. The nucleotide sequences conceptually
translated into the corresponding amino acids resulting in 107
(<italic>flp-12</italic>) and 99 (<italic>flp-16</italic>) amino acids were submitted to Genbank
(Accession no AEN71840 -<italic>flp-12</italic>) and AEN71841 -<italic>flp-16</italic>).
Further, Protparam results showed a molecular weight (mw) of
12562.5 daltons (Da) and a Theoretical pI of 7.92 for <italic>flp-12</italic> while,
mw for <italic>flp-16</italic> was 11765.1 Da and pI was 9.86. SignalP server
was used to identify the signal peptide in both the FLPs.
SignalP result of <italic>flp-12</italic> predicted 22 residue long signal peptide
at N-terminal (1-22) and no significant hits were obtained for
<italic>flp-16</italic>. This indicates that <italic>flp-12</italic> could be involved in extra
cellular function like signal transduction.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title><italic>Sequence comparison</italic>:</title>
        <p>Six in case of <italic>flp-12</italic> and four for the <italic>flp-16</italic> protein sequences of
closely related species were retrieved from Genbank database
using protein Blast Search. Best hits obtained with the <italic>M.
incognita</italic> for both FLPs were aligned pairwise to find the
similarity with <italic>H. avenae</italic>. Pairwise alignment of the <italic>flp-12</italic>
between <italic>H. avenae</italic> and <italic>M. incognita</italic> revealed the substitution of
Q-R,F-L,T-A,T-A and M-I at 6, 12, 20, 49 and 60<sup>th</sup> positions
respectively. However, in case of <italic>flp-16</italic> the substitution of I to K
at 25<sup>th</sup> amino acid position and deletion of E at the 52<sup>nd</sup> position
was observed in <italic>H. avenae</italic> sequence compared to <italic>M. incognita</italic>.
Further, the homologous sequences aligned using multiple
sequence alignment (MSA) suggested that <italic>flp-12</italic> is
comparatively more conserved than <italic>flp-16</italic> among the closely
related species. In addition, COOH terminal of <italic>flp-12</italic> is found to
be highly conserved with the motif, KFEFIRF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>).
Whereas, MSA of <italic>flp-16</italic> sequences revealed that [Y/F] [L/V]
RFGK motif has two repeats at COOH Terminal. However,
FVRFGK motif is conserved in the <italic>flp-16</italic> of both <italic>M. incognita</italic>
and <italic>H. avenae</italic>, whereas YLRFGK motif is conserved in the flp-14
of free living nematodes (<italic>C. brenneri, C. elegans</italic> and <italic>C. briggsae</italic>)
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3b</xref>). This strongly suggests that these conserved motifs
are essential in signal transduction mediated by GPCR (Gprotein
coupled receptor) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>,
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]. Analysis of <italic>flp-12</italic> and <italic>flp-16</italic>
of <italic>H. avenae</italic> suggested that <italic>flp-12</italic> to be more conserved across
parasitic nematodes with higher similarity to root knot
nematode species rather than the cyst nematodes. It has
diverged from the free living nematodes suggesting its vital role
for parasitism. Even though <italic>flp-16</italic> is found to be homologous
with free living counterparts, it is again highly similar to <italic>flp-16</italic>
of <italic>M. incognita</italic>. Further, AmiGO BLAST hit confirmed <italic>flp-12</italic>
involvement in receptor signalling pathway resulting in axon
guidance (GO: 0007411) and negative chemotaxis (GO: 0050919)
whereas, <italic>flp-16</italic> is involved in negative regulation of striated
muscle contraction (GO: 0045988).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title><italic>Phylogenetic analysis</italic>:</title>
        <p>Extending this study, we carried out phylogenetic analysis
among closely related species of <italic>H. avenae</italic>. We constructed the
phylogenetic tree of both <italic>flp-12</italic> and <italic>flp-16</italic> gene with parasitic as
well as free living nematodes. Phylogenetic tree grouped <italic>flp-12</italic>
of <italic>H. avenae</italic> with all PPNs. However very interestingly, it
showed more closeness to the two root knot nematode species,
<italic>M. incognita</italic> and <italic>M. minor</italic> than the cyst nematode species, <italic>G.
pallida</italic> and <italic>H. glycines</italic> confirming the results of BLAST.
However, Ascaris suum and <italic>C. brenneri</italic> formed two independent
out groups suggesting their evolutionary distance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4a</xref>).
Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>flp-16</italic> indicated that <italic>H. avenae</italic> and <italic>M.
incognita</italic> were grouped together with high level of similarity.
Additionally, it was also related to flp-14 of three free living
nematodes (<italic>C. elegans, C. briggsei</italic> and <italic>C. brenneri</italic>) 
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4b</xref>).
Significantly, phylogenetic analysis is in excellent agreement
with the MSA result confirming the similarity.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Present results indicate that FMRFamide like peptides are
important for both plant parasitic and free living nematodes
since they are conserved across different genera in spite of
evolutionary pressure for diversification. The observed results
confirm the phylogenetic relationship of these two genes
determined by MSA thus, enhancing the confidence. However,
<italic>flp-12</italic> is more conserved between the parasitic nematodes and
diverged from free living nematodes indicating their possible
role for parasitism. The application of RNAi to the identified
neuronal genes in <italic>H. avenae</italic> could open the door to unraveling
the underlying biology of these two flp genes in CCN. Work is
in progress on functional validation of these two neuro
peptides-encoding <italic>flp-12</italic> and 16 genes of <italic>H. avenae</italic> by RNAi
through soaking in double stranded RNA solution under <italic>in vitro</italic>
conditions.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We would like to thank Department of Biotechnology,
Government of India for the financial support and ICAR and
IARI for infrastructure facility to carry out the Research work.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="FN1" fn-type="other">
        <p><bold>Citation:</bold>Thakur <italic>et al</italic>, Bioinformation 8(13): 617-621 (2012)</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>G</surname>
              <given-names>Yan</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <fpage>216</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20128694</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>H</surname>
              <given-names>Abidou</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>J Nematol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>146</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19262854</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>A</surname>
              <given-names>Mokabli</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Nematology</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>171</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>MF</surname>
              <given-names>Andres</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Plant Pathol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>270</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>AG</surname>
              <given-names>Maule</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Curr Top Med Chem</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>733</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12052188</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>MJ</surname>
              <given-names>Kimber</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Mol Biochem Parasit</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>116</volume>
          <fpage>199</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11522352</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>SJ</surname>
              <given-names>Husson</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Commun Agric Appl Biol Sci</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <fpage>153</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16366296</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>P</surname>
              <given-names>Abad</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>909</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18660804</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>QX</surname>
              <given-names>Huang</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>PLoS One</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>13271</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20967259</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>MJ</surname>
              <given-names>Kimber</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Faseb J</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>1233</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17200420</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>JJ</surname>
              <given-names>Dalzell</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Int J Parasitol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19651131</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>LS</surname>
              <given-names>Nelson</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>281</volume>
          <fpage>1686</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9733518</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>K</surname>
              <given-names>Kim</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>J Comp Neurol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>475</volume>
          <fpage>540</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15236235</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>MJ</surname>
              <given-names>Kimber</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Int J Parasitol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>1095</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12117492</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>SF</surname>
              <given-names>Altschul</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>J Mol Biol</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>215</volume>
          <fpage>403</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>MA</surname>
              <given-names>Larkin</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Bioinformatics</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>2947</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17846036</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>TN</surname>
              <given-names>Petersen</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Nat Methods</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>785</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21959131</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>TA</surname>
              <given-names>Hall</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Symp Ser</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>95</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R19">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>TG</surname>
              <given-names>Geary</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Trends Pharmacol Sci</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>56</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15681019</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R20">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>TM</surname>
              <given-names>Kubiak</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>301</volume>
          <fpage>456</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12565883</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>PCR amplification of <italic>flp-12</italic> and <italic>flp-16</italic> genes from
cDNA library of <italic>Heterodera avenae</italic>. Lane 1:100 bp DNA marker;
2- flp12: 4- 100 bp DNA marker; 5- flp16</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="97320630008617F1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>cDNA sequence in lower case of <italic>flp-12</italic> (a) and <italic>flp-16</italic>;
(b) with the translated open reading frame. The deduced amino
acid sequence is shown in one-letter symbols.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="97320630008617F2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>MSA of the predicted amino acid sequence of the <italic>flp-12</italic> (a) and <italic>flp-16</italic> (b) from <italic>H. avenae</italic> with flp sequences from other
nematodes. The sequences are denoted by their Genbank identifier followed by the species abbreviation. Species abbreviations: Ha,
<italic>Heterodera avenae; Mi, Meloidogyne incognita; Mm, Meloidogyne minor</italic>; Gp, <italic>Globodera pallida</italic>; Hg, <italic>Heterodera glycines</italic>; As, <italic>Ascaris suum</italic>;
Cbe, <italic>Caenorhabditis brenneri</italic>; Ce, <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>; Cbi, <italic>Caenorhabditis briggsae</italic>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="97320630008617F3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
      <label>Figure 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Phylogenetic relationships of the predicted <italic>flp-12</italic> (a)
and <italic>flp-16</italic> (b) from <italic>H. avenae</italic> and FLP sequences from other
nematodes. The same homologous sequences as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>
were used in this analysis. Abbreviation: PPNs-Plant parasitic
nematodes.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="97320630008617F4"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
