<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Persoonia</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Persoonia</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Persoonia</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Persoonia : Molecular Phylogeny and Evolution of Fungi</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0031-5850</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1878-9080</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Nationaal Herbarium Nederland &amp; Centraallbureau voor Schimmelcultures</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3409409</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3767/003158512X652624</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>How important are conidial appendages?</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Crous</surname>
            <given-names>P.W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Verkley</surname>
            <given-names>G.J.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Christensen</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Casta&#xF1;eda-Ruiz</surname>
            <given-names>R.F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Groenewald</surname>
            <given-names>J.Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label> CBS-KNAW Fungal Biodiversity Centre, Uppsalalaan 8, 3584 CT Utrecht, The Netherlands;</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label> Microbiology, Department of Biology, Utrecht University, Padualaan 8, 3584 CH Utrecht, The Netherlands.</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label> Wageningen University and Research Centre (WUR), Laboratory of Phytopathology, Droevendaalsesteeg 1, 6708 PB Wageningen, The Netherlands.</aff>
      <aff id="A4"><label>4</label> Department of Botany, 430 Lincoln Drive, University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI 53706-1381, USA.</aff>
      <aff id="A5"><label>5</label> Instituto de Investigaciones Fundamentales en Agricultura Tropical &#x201C;Alejandro de Humboldt&#x201D;, Calle 1 Esq. 2, Santiago de Las Vegas, C. Habana, Cuba, C.P. 17200.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1">
corresponding author e-mail: <email>p.crous@cbs.knaw.nl</email>.
</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>28</volume>
      <fpage>126</fpage>
      <lpage>137</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2012 Nationaal Herbarium Nederland &amp; Centraalbureau voor Schimmelcultures</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/legalcode">
          <license-p>You are free to share - to copy, distribute and transmit the work, under the following conditions:</license-p>
          <license-p>Attribution: You must attribute the work in the manner specified by the author or licensor (but not in any way that suggests that they endorse you or your use of the work).</license-p>
          <license-p>Non-commercial: You may not use this work for commercial purposes.</license-p>
          <license-p>No derivative works: You may not alter, transform, or build upon this work.</license-p>
          <license-p>For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others the license terms of this work, which can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/legalcode">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/legalcode</ext-link>. Any of the above conditions can be waived if you get permission from the copyright holder. Nothing in this license impairs or restricts the author&#x2019;s moral rights.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract abstract-type="executive-summary">
        <p>The genus The genus <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> is used as a case study to evaluate the importance of conidial appendages for generic level classification of coelomycetous fungi. Based on morphology and sequence data of the large subunit nuclear ribosomal RNA gene (LSU, 28S) and the internal transcribed spacers and 5.8S rRNA gene of the nrDNA operon, the genus <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> is circumscribed, and an epitype designated for <italic>D. strigosum</italic>, the type of the genus. A further five species are introduced in <italic>Dinemasporium</italic>, namely <italic>D. pseudostrigosum</italic> (isolated from <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>, Germany and <italic>Stigmaphyllon sagraeanum</italic>, Cuba), <italic>D. americana</italic> (soil, USA), <italic>D. polygonum</italic> (<italic>Polygonum sachalinense</italic>, Netherlands), <italic>D. pseudoindicum</italic> (soil, USA), and <italic>D. morbidum</italic> (human sputum, Netherlands and hare dung, New Zealand). <italic>Brunneodinemasporium</italic>, based on <italic>B. brasiliense</italic>, is introduced to accommodate <italic>Dinemasporium</italic>-like species with tightly aggregated brown conidiogenous cells, and pale brown conidia. <italic>Dendrophoma</italic> (= <italic>Amphitiarospora</italic>) is reinstated as distinct from <italic>Dinemasporium</italic>, and an epitype designated for <italic>D. cytisporoides</italic>, characterised by its superficial, stipitate to cupulate conidiomata, and small conidia with two polar, tubular, exogenous appendages. The genus <italic>Stauronema</italic> is reduced to synonymy under <italic>Dinemasporium</italic>. <italic>Pseudolachnea</italic> (1-septate conidia) is supported as distinct from <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> (aseptate conidia), and <italic>P. fraxini</italic> introduced as a novel species. Taxa in this generic complex differ by combination of morphological characters of conidiomata, setae, conidia and appendages. Appendage morphology alone is rejected as informative at the generic level.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Chaetosphaeriaceae</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Dinemasporium</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>ITS</kwd>
        <kwd>LSU</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Sordariomycetes</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>systematics</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>In his revision of coelomycetous fungi with appendage bearing conidia, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nag Raj (1993)</xref> mentioned that in early papers dealing with these fungi, descriptions of novel taxa only rarely referred to the fact that conidia had appendages. In later years, these appendages were seen as taxonomically informative in separating species, especially in genera such as <italic>Coniella</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">van Niekerk et al. 2004</xref>), <italic>Phyllosticta</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Wulandari et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Glienke et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Wikee et al. 2011</xref>), <italic>Pestalotiopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Maharachchikumbura et al. 2011</xref>), <italic>Seimatosporium</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Barber et al. 2011</xref>), and <italic>Tiarosporella</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Crous et al. 2006</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Sutton &amp; Sellar (1966)</xref> categorised appendages by their structure and position, whether mucilaginous or cellular, endo- or exogenous, simple or branched, as well as their position on the conidium. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nag Raj (1993)</xref> further elaborated on these concepts, and defined nine appendage types (A&#x2013;I), with three subdivisions for appendage type A. He further highlighted the diversity that exists in appendage morphology, namely in shape (filiform, attenuated or podiform), position (apical, basal, lateral, or in combination), in patterns of distribution on the conidium, in branching, in integrity with the conidium, in sequence of development, and in structural changes (nucleate or not).</p>
      <p>Appendages usually relate to an ecological function linked to spore dispersal, and the colonisation of new substrates or niches. Appendages play an important role in spore attachment to substrates to ensure that the conidium can germinate and its hyphae can infect or colonise the substrate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nag Raj 1993</xref>). Conidial appendages are known to occur in coelomycetes in diverse habitats ranging from terrestrial to aquatic. Appendages have subsequently been used to support the combination or separation of taxa into different genera. One such genus is <italic>Dinemasporium</italic>, which forms the basis of the present study. It is characterised by superficial, cupulate to discoid conidiomata with brown setae, and phialidic conidiogenous cells that give rise to hyaline, oblong to allantoid, aseptate conidia with an appendage at each end.</p>
      <p>The genus <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> has several acknowledged synonyms, namely <italic>Dendrophoma</italic>, <italic>Pycnidiochaeta</italic>, and <italic>Amphitiarospora</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Sutton 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nag Raj 1993</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Sutton (1980)</xref> placed species with septate conidia in <italic>Pseudolachnea</italic>, while <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nag Raj (1993)</xref> separated <italic>Pseudolachnea</italic> (1-septate conidia) from <italic>Pseudolachnella</italic> (multiseptate conidia). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Saccardo (1884)</xref> established the subgenus <italic>Stauronema</italic> for taxa with conidia that had apical, basal as well as lateral appendages. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Sutton (1980)</xref> later elevated <italic>Stauronema</italic> to generic level, a proposal subsequently accepted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nag Raj (1993)</xref>.</p>
      <p>The aim of the present study is to investigate the taxonomic value of appendages as defining feature at generic level in coelomycetous fungi, by using <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> as a case study. A further aim is to clarify the phylogenetic position of the genus <italic>Dinemasporium</italic>, and to revisit its circumscription in relation to its synonyms and closely allied genera, many of which are distinguished by a combination of conidium septation and appendage morphology.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Isolates</title>
        <p>The majority of the strains used in the present study were obtained from the culture collection of the CBS-KNAW Fungal Biodiversity Centre (CBS) Utrecht, the Netherlands. Fresh collections were made from debris of diverse hosts by placing material in damp chambers for 1&#x2013;2 d. Single conidial colonies were established from sporulating conidiomata on Petri dishes containing 2 % malt extract agar (MEA; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Crous et al. 2009b</xref>) as described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Crous et al. 1991</xref>). Colonies were sub-cultured onto potato-dextrose agar (PDA), oatmeal agar (OA), MEA, and pine needle agar (PNA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Smith et al. 1996</xref>), and incubated at 25 &#xB0;C under continuous near-ultraviolet light to promote sporulation. Reference strains were deposited at the CBS.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>DNA isolation, amplification and analyses</title>
        <p>Genomic DNA was extracted from fungal colonies growing on MEA using the UltraClean<sup>TM</sup> Microbial DNA Isolation Kit (MoBio Laboratories, Inc., Solana Beach, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s protocol. The primers V9G (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">de Hoog &amp; Gerrits van den Ende 1998</xref>) and LR5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Vilgalys &amp; Hester 1990</xref>) were used to amplify part (ITS) of the nuclear rDNA operon spanning the 3&#x2032; end of the 18S rRNA gene, the first internal transcribed spacer (ITS1), the 5.8S rRNA gene, the second ITS region and the 5&#x2032; end of the 28S rRNA gene. The primers ITS4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">White et al. 1990</xref>) and LSU1Fd (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Crous et al. 2009a</xref>) were used as internal sequence primers to ensure good quality sequences over the entire length of the amplicon. The sequence alignment and subsequent phylogenetic analyses for all the above were carried out using methods described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Crous et al. (2006)</xref>. Gaps longer than 10 bases were coded as single events for the phylogenetic analyses; the remaining gaps were treated as &#x2018;fifth state&#x2019; data. Sequences derived in this study were lodged at GenBank, the alignment in TreeBASE (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.treebase.org/">www.treebase.org/</ext-link>), and taxonomic novelties in MycoBank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.MycoBank.org">www.MycoBank.org</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Crous et al. 2004</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Morphology</title>
        <p>Morphological descriptions are based on slide preparations mounted in clear lactic acid from colonies sporulating on PNA. Observations were made with a Zeiss V20 Discovery stereo-microscope, and with a Zeiss Axio Imager 2 light microscope using differential interference contrast (DIC) illumination and an AxioCam MRc5 camera and software. Colony characters and pigment production were noted after 1 mo of growth on MEA, PDA and OA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Crous et al. 2009b</xref>) incubated at 25 &#xB0;C. Colony colours (surface and reverse) were rated according to the colour charts of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Rayner (1970)</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>RESULTS</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Phylogeny</title>
        <p>Amplicons of approximately 1 700 bases were obtained of the ITS region (including the first approximately 900 bp of LSU) for the isolates listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. The LSU sequences were used to obtain additional sequences from GenBank, which were added to the alignment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) and the ITS to determine species identification (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>; discussed in species notes where applicable). The manually adjusted LSU alignment contained 42 sequences (including the outgroup sequence) and 798 characters including alignment gaps (available in TreeBASE) were used in the phylogenetic analysis; 151 of these were parsimony-informative, 136 were variable and parsimony-uninformative, and 511 were constant. Neighbour-joining analyses using three substitution models on the sequence alignment yielded trees with identical topologies to one another and support the same terminal clades as obtained from the parsimony analysis. The parsimony analysis of the LSU alignment yielded 142 equally most parsimonious trees (TL = 741 steps; CI = 0.533; RI = 0.662; RC = 0.353). The manually adjusted ITS alignment contained 31 sequences (including the outgroup sequence) and 514 characters including alignment gaps (available in TreeBASE) were used in the phylogenetic analysis; 203 of these were parsimony-informative, 60 were variable and parsimony-uninformative, and 251 were constant. Neighbour-joining analyses using three substitution models on the sequence alignment yielded trees with identical topologies to one another and support the same terminal clades as obtained from the parsimony analysis. The parsimony analysis of the ITS alignment yielded 3 equally most parsimonious trees (TL = 929 steps; CI = 0.553; RI = 0.706; RC = 0.390). All the species treated below are supported as distinct in the ITS phylogeny (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Taxonomy</title>
        <p><bold><italic>Brunneodinemasporium</italic></bold> Crous &amp; R.F. Casta&#xF1;eda, <italic>gen. nov.</italic> &#x2014; MycoBank MB800158</p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Type species. Brunneodinemasporium brasiliense</italic> Crous.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Etymology</italic>. Similar to <italic>Dinemasporium</italic>, but conidiogenous cells and conidia brown in colour.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><italic>Conidiomata</italic> stromatic, scattered or aggregated, superficial, dark brown to black, cupulate, unilocular, globose, setose; basal stroma of <italic>textura angularis. Setae</italic> abundant, brown to black, simple, septate, subulate to cylindrical, unbranched, smooth, thick-walled, multi-septate, arising randomly throughout basal stroma. <italic>Conidiophores</italic> lining the basal stroma in a dense layer, brown, septate, unbranched, cylindrical, thin-walled, smooth. <italic>Conidiogenous cells</italic> integrated, determinate, phialidic with conspicuous periclinal thickening at an attenuated apex, brown, smooth, subcylindrical to lageniform. <italic>Conidia</italic> hyaline to pale brown, aseptate, thin-walled, smooth, fusiform, gently curved or straight, apex obtuse to subobtusely rounded, base truncate, eguttulate or guttulate, with a single, cellular, unbranched, flexuous, with tubular appendage at each end, separated by a septum; basal appendage excentric.</p>
        <p><bold><italic>Brunneodinemasporium brasiliense</italic></bold> Crous &amp; R.F. Casta&#xF1;eda, <italic>sp. nov.</italic> &#x2014; MycoBank MB800159; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref></p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Etymology</italic>. Named after the country from where this fungus was collected, Brazil.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><italic>Conidiomata</italic> stromatic, scattered or aggregated, superficial, dark brown to black, cupulate, unilocular, globose, up to 600 &#x3BC;m diam, setose with a central buff conidial mass on PNA; basal stroma of <italic>textura angularis. Setae</italic> abundant, brown to black, simple, septate, subulate to cylindrical, with obtuse apex, unbranched, smooth, thick-walled, multi-septate, 200&#x2013;1300 &#x3BC;m long, 12&#x2013;15 &#x3BC;m diam at base, 5&#x2013;10 &#x3BC;m diam at obtuse apex, arising from basal stroma. <italic>Conidiophores</italic> lining the basal stroma in a dense layer, brown, 4&#x2013;6-septate, unbranched, cylindrical, thin-walled, smooth, 40&#x2013;70 &#xD7; 3&#x2013;4 &#x3BC;m. <italic>Conidiogenous cells</italic> integrated, determinate, phialidic with clearly visible periclinal thickening at apex 1.5&#x2013;2 &#x3BC;m diam, brown, smooth, subcylindrical to lageniform, 10&#x2013;16 &#xD7; 3&#x2013;4 &#x3BC;m. <italic>Conidia</italic> hyaline to pale brown, aseptate, thin-walled, smooth, fusiform, gently curved or straight, apex obtuse to subobtusely rounded, base truncate, eguttulate or guttulate, (17&#x2212;)18&#x2013;19(&#x2212;20) &#xD7; (2&#x2212;)2.5&#x2013;3 &#x3BC;m, with a single, unbranched, flexuous, tubular appendage at each end, 5&#x2013;7 &#x3BC;m long, apparently separated by a septum; basal appendage excentric.</p>
        <p>Culture characteristics &#x2014; Colonies flat, spreading, with sparse to moderate aerial mycelium. On MEA smoke grey (surface), with even, lobate margins, surrounded by a zone of diffuse, red pigment; reverse olivaceous grey in centre, outer region red due to diffuse pigment; on OA iron grey with even, lobate margin; on PDA surface isabelline, in outer region smoke grey, in reverse grey olivaceous.</p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Specimen examined</italic>. <sc>Brazil,</sc> Corcorvado, on decaying leaf, 12 Oct. 2002, <italic>R.F. Casta&#xF1;eda-Ruiz</italic> (holotype CBS H-20948, culture ex-type CBS 112007 = INIFAT CO2/51).</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Notes &#x2014; <italic>Brunneodinemasporium</italic> has randomly distributed setae throughout the basal stroma, which differs from <italic>Dinemasporium</italic>, which has a densely aggregated layer of brown conidiogenous cells with prominent periclinal thickening and apical taper, and conidia that appear pale brown, and have setae that separate from the conidia by a septum (though the latter is not clear under the light microscope, but differs from <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> s.str.).</p>
        <p><bold><italic>Dendrophoma</italic></bold> Sacc., Michelia 2: 4. 1880.</p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p>= <italic>Amphitiarospora</italic> Agnihothr., Sydowia 16: 75. 1962 (1963).</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Type species. Dendrophoma cytosporoides</italic> Sacc.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><italic>Conidiomata</italic> stromatic, scattered to gregarious, superficial, stipitate, globose and closed, becoming cupulate, unilocular, dark brown to black; basal excipulum brown, of dense <italic>textura intricata. Setae</italic> arising from the outer elements of excipulum, or restricted to base of conidioma, sparse, subulate to subcylindrical, apex blunt to acutely rounded, straight to curved, transversely septate, dark brown, thick-walled, smooth. <italic>Conidiophores</italic> arising from conidiomatal cavity, septate, branched, hyaline. <italic>Conidiogenous cells</italic> discrete, or integrated, terminal and lateral, lageniform to subcylindrical, hyaline, thin-walled, smooth. <italic>Conidia</italic> naviculate to botuliform, aseptate, hyaline, thin-walled, smooth, with an unbranched cellular appendage at each end.</p>
        <p><bold><italic>Dendrophoma cytosporoides</italic></bold> Sacc., Michelia 2: 4. 1880; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref></p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Basionym. Phoma cytosporoides</italic> Sacc. (as &#x2018;<italic>cytisporoides</italic>&#x2019;), Michelia 1, 5: 522. 1879.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>&#x2261; <italic>Dinemasporium cytosporoides</italic> (Sacc.) B. Sutton, Trans. Brit. Mycol. Soc. 48: 613. 1965.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>= <italic>Amphitiarospora neottiosporoides</italic> Agnihothr., Sydowia 16: 75. 1962 (1963).</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><italic>Conidiomata</italic> stromatic, scattered to gregarious, superficial, stipitate, at first globose and closed, then opening to become cupulate, up to 300 &#x3BC;m diam, unilocular, dark brown to black; basal excipulum brown, of dense <italic>textura intricata. Setae</italic> arising from the outer elements of excipulum, or restricted to base of conidioma, sparse, subulate to subcylindrical, apex blunt to acutely rounded, straight to curved, 2&#x2013;8-septate, dark brown, thick-walled, smooth, 100&#x2013;300 &#xD7; 4&#x2013;6 &#x3BC;m, apex 1&#x2013;1.5 &#x3BC;m wide. <italic>Conidiophores</italic> arising from conidiomatal cavity, septate, branched, hyaline, up to 40 &#x3BC;m long. <italic>Conidiogenous cells</italic> discrete or integrated, terminal and lateral, lageniform to subcylindrical, frequently in terminal whorls, hyaline, thin-walled, smooth, 6&#x2013;15 &#xD7; 1.5 &#x3BC;m. <italic>Conidia</italic> naviculate to botuliform, aseptate, hyaline, thin-walled, smooth, (3.5&#x2212;)4&#x2013;5(&#x2212;6) &#xD7; (1&#x2212;)1.5 &#x3BC;m, with an unbranched appendage at each end, 0.5&#x2013;1 &#x3BC;m long.</p>
        <p>Culture characteristics &#x2014; Colonies flat, spreading, with sparse aerial mycelium and even, lobate margins. On OA surface grey olivaceous, reverse olivaceous grey; on PDA surface brick to cinnamon, reverse dark brick.</p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Specimens examined</italic>. <sc>France,</sc> Rouen, L&#x2019; Abbee Letendre, on <italic>Ulmus</italic> sp., designated as lectotype of <italic>Phoma cytosporoides</italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Sutton (1965)</xref>, IMI 111879 ex Herb. PAD. &#x2013; <sc>Netherlands,</sc> Utrecht, Soest, near hospital, on <italic>Rhododendron</italic>, coll. <italic>A. Aptroot</italic>, isol. <italic>G. Verkley</italic>, 11 Nov. 1994 (epitype designated here CBS H-12004, culture ex-epitype CBS 223.95).</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Notes &#x2014; The characteristic features that separate <italic>Dendrophoma</italic> from <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> are conidiomata that are superficial and stipitate, becoming cupulate. The conidiogenous cells of <italic>Dendrophoma</italic> form a dense layer that gives rise to conidia with short, tubular exogenous appendages at each end, also differing from <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> s.str.</p>
        <p>Based on an examination of the holotype specimen, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Sutton (1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">1980)</xref> regarded <italic>Amphitiarospora</italic> as synonymous with <italic>Dinemasporium</italic>. The original description (conidia 4&#x2013;5 &#xD7; 1.5&#x2013;2 &#x3BC;m, setae 1&#x2013;2 &#x3BC;m; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Agnihothrudu 1962</xref>), indicated that <italic>A. neottiosporoides</italic> is synonymous with <italic>D. cytosporoides</italic>.</p>
        <p><bold><italic>Dinemasporium</italic></bold> L&#xE9;v., Ann. Sci. Nat., Bot., s&#xE9;r. 3, 5: 274. 1846.</p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p>= <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> (L&#xE9;v.) subg. <italic>Stauronema</italic> Sacc., Syll. Fung. 3: 686. 1884.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>&#x2261; <italic>Stauronema</italic> (Sacc.) Syd., P. Syd. &amp; E.J. Butler, Ann. Mycol. 14: 217. 1916.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>= <italic>Pycnidiochaeta</italic> Sousa da C&#xE2;mara, Agron. Lusit. 12: 109. 1950.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Type species. Dinemasporium strigosum</italic> (Pers.: Fr.) Sacc.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><italic>Conidiomata</italic> stromatic, cupulate, often discoid, superficial (also on SNA in culture), unilocular, setose, black, with basal stroma of <italic>textura angularis. Setae</italic> arise from the basal stroma and/or from excipular margin, unbranched, subulate to cylindrical, straight or curved, brown to dark brown, smooth or verruculose, with obtuse to acute apices. <italic>Conidiophores</italic> lining the inner cavity, mostly branched, septate, hyaline (at times brown at base), smooth, invested in mucus. <italic>Conidiogenous cells</italic> discrete or integrated, lageniform, subcylindrical or cylindrical, hyaline, smooth, with visible periclinal thickening. <italic>Conidia</italic> fusiform, naviculate or allantoid, aseptate, hyaline to pale brown, smooth, with a single, unbranched, filiform, cellular appendage at each end (not separated from body via septa); lateral appendages present or absent.</p>
        <p><bold><italic>Dinemasporium americana</italic></bold> Crous &amp; Tuthill, <italic>sp. nov.</italic> &#x2014; MycoBank MB800160; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref></p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Etymology.</italic> Named after its country of origin, Unites States of America.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><italic>Conidiomata</italic> stromatic, scattered or aggregated, superficial, dark brown to black, cupulate, unilocular, globose, up to 350 &#x3BC;m diam, setose with a central buff to rosy buff conidial mass on PNA; basal stroma of <italic>textura angularis</italic>, layer 20&#x2013;30 &#x3BC;m thick. <italic>Setae</italic> brown to black, simple, septate, subulate with acute apex, unbranched, smooth, thick-walled, up to 7-septate, 50&#x2013;200 &#xD7; 4&#x2013;10 &#x3BC;m, 1&#x2013;1.5 &#x3BC;m wide at acute apex, arising from basal stroma or lateral from excipulum. <italic>Conidiophores</italic> lining the basal stroma, prominently septate (&#x2212;8), branched, cylindrical, thin-walled, smooth, base pale brown, apex hyaline, up to 70 &#x3BC;m long. <italic>Conidiogenous cells</italic> determinate, phialidic with periclinal thickening, hyaline, smooth, subcylindrical, 7&#x2013;10 &#xD7; 2&#x2013;2.5 &#x3BC;m. <italic>Conidia</italic> hyaline, aseptate, thin-walled, smooth, naviculate to fusiform or ellipsoid, gently curved or straight, apex obtuse to subobtusely rounded, base truncate, eguttulate or guttulate, (9&#x2212;)12&#x2013;13(&#x2212;16) &#xD7; (2.5&#x2212;)3 &#x3BC;m, with a single, unbranched, flexuous, tubular appendage at each end, (11&#x2212;)12&#x2013;14(&#x2212;16) &#x3BC;m; basal appendage excentric.</p>
        <p>Culture characteristics &#x2014; Colonies spreading, erumpent, with moderate aerial mycelium. On MEA buff (surface), reverse cinnamon; on OA and PDA buff (surface and reverse).</p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Specimen examined.</italic> USA, Iowa, Cherokee County, Steele Prairie, A1 horizon soil, 1985, <italic>D.E. Tuthill</italic>, T93N R40W S16 (holotype CBS H-20949, dried culture of RMF 7507 = CBS 127127).</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Notes &#x2014; Isolate RMF 7507 was formerly treated as <italic>D. strigosum</italic>, but is specifically distinct. Although the conidiomata produced are similar in general morphology to those of <italic>D. strigosum</italic>, they differ by having shorter setae, larger conidia, longer appendages (setae 60&#x2013;400 &#x3BC;m long, conidia (9&#x2212;)10&#x2013;12(&#x2212;13) &#x3BC;m long, appendages 6&#x2013;9 &#x3BC;m long in <italic>D. strigosum</italic>).</p>
        <p><bold><italic>Dinemasporium morbidum</italic></bold> Crous, <italic>sp. nov.</italic> &#x2014; MycoBank MB800161; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref></p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Etymology</italic>. Name reflects on the unpleasant substrata from which the fungus was isolated.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><italic>Conidiomata</italic> stromatic, scattered or aggregated, superficial, dark brown to black, cupulate, unilocular, globose, up to 250 &#x3BC;m diam, setose with a central buff conidial mass on PNA; basal stroma of <italic>textura angularis</italic>, layer 20&#x2013;30 &#x3BC;m thick. <italic>Setae</italic> brown to black, simple, septate, subulate with acute apex, unbranched, smooth, thick-walled, up to 9-septate, 50&#x2013;330 &#xD7; 5&#x2013;10 &#x3BC;m, 1&#x2013;1.5 &#x3BC;m wide at acute apex, arising from basal stroma or lateral from excipulum. <italic>Conidiophores</italic> lining the basal stroma, hyaline, septate, sparingly branched, cylindrical, thin-walled, smooth, 30&#x2013;40 &#x3BC;m long. <italic>Conidiogenous cells</italic> determinate, phialidic with periclinal thickening, hyaline, smooth, subcylindrical to lageniform, 8&#x2013;13 &#xD7; 2&#x2013;2.5 &#x3BC;m. <italic>Conidia</italic> hyaline, aseptate, thin-walled, smooth, naviculate to fusiform or ellipsoid, gently curved or straight, apex obtuse to subobtusely rounded, base truncate, eguttulate or guttulate, (10&#x2212;)12&#x2013;14(&#x2212;15) &#xD7; (2.5&#x2212;)3 &#x3BC;m, with a single, unbranched, flexuous, tubular appendage at each end, (6&#x2212;)7&#x2013;10(&#x2212;12) &#x3BC;m; basal appendage excentric.</p>
        <p>Culture characteristics &#x2014; Colonies spreading, erumpent, with moderate aerial mycelium. On MEA, OA and PDA buff (surface), reverse buff with patches of cinnamon; sporulation rosy buff.</p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Specimens examined</italic>. <sc>Netherlands,</sc> from human sputum, 19 Nov. 1965, <italic>N.G.M. Orie</italic> and <italic>A. Kikstra</italic>, No. A 29/9 (holotype CBS H-12014, culture ex-type 129.66). &#x2013; <sc>New Zealand</sc>, South Island, Hobson&#x2019;s Nature trail near Highway 13, Arthur&#x2019;s Pass, on hare dung, Mar. 1995, <italic>D.P. Mahoney</italic>, CBS 995.97 = ATCC 200690.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Notes &#x2014; <italic>Dinemasporium morbidum</italic> has longer conidia and appendages than <italic>D. strigosum</italic>, which has conidia (9&#x2212;)10&#x2013;12 (&#x2212;13) &#x3BC;m long, with appendages 6&#x2013;9 &#x3BC;m long.</p>
        <p><bold><italic>Dinemasporium polygonum</italic></bold> Crous &amp; Verkley, <italic>sp. nov.</italic> &#x2014; MycoBank MB800162; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref></p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Etymology</italic>. Named after the host genus from which it was isolated, <italic>Polygonum.</italic></p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><italic>Conidiomata</italic> stromatic, scattered or aggregated, superficial, dark brown to black, cupulate, unilocular, globose, up to 250 &#x3BC;m diam, setose with a central buff to rosy buff conidial mass on PNA; basal stroma of <italic>textura angularis</italic>, layer 20&#x2013;30 &#x3BC;m thick. <italic>Setae</italic> brown to black, simple, septate, subulate with acute apex, unbranched, smooth, thick-walled, up to 9-septate, 100&#x2013;300 &#xD7; 5&#x2013;8 &#x3BC;m, 1&#x2013;1.5 &#x3BC;m wide at acute apex, arising from basal stroma or lateral from excipulum. <italic>Conidiophores</italic> lining the basal stroma, hyaline, septate, sparingly branched, cylindrical, thin-walled, smooth, 30&#x2013;60 &#x3BC;m long. <italic>Conidiogenous cells</italic> determinate, phialidic with periclinal thickening, hyaline, smooth, subcylindrical to lageniform, 7&#x2013;16 &#xD7; 2&#x2013;2.5 &#x3BC;m. <italic>Conidia</italic> hyaline, aseptate, thin-walled, smooth, naviculate to fusiform or ellipsoid, gently curved or straight, apex obtuse to subobtusely rounded, base truncate, eguttulate or guttulate, (9&#x2212;)10&#x2013;12(&#x2212;13) &#xD7; (2&#x2212;)2.5(&#x2212;3) &#x3BC;m, with a single, unbranched, flexuous, tubular appendage at each end, (9&#x2212;)10&#x2013;12(&#x2212;13) &#x3BC;m; basal appendage excentric.</p>
        <p>Culture characteristics &#x2014; Colonies spreading, erumpent, with moderate aerial mycelium. On MEA, OA and PDA buff (surface and reverse).</p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Specimen examined.</italic><sc>Netherlands</sc>, Soest, de Stompert, on <italic>Polygonum sachalinense</italic>, 22 Feb. 1995, coll. <italic>A. Aptroot</italic>, isol. <italic>G.J.M. Verkley</italic> (holotype CBS H-20950, culture ex-type CBS 516.95).</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Notes &#x2014; <italic>Dinemasporium polygonum</italic> has conidia with longer appendages than <italic>D. strigosum</italic> though shorter than in <italic>D. americanum</italic> (6&#x2013;9 &#x3BC;m long in <italic>D. strigosum</italic>, 11&#x2013;16 &#x3BC;m in <italic>D. americanum</italic>).</p>
        <p><bold><italic>Dinemasporium pseudoindicum</italic></bold> Crous &amp; M. Chr., <italic>sp. nov. &#x2014;</italic> MycoBank MB800163; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref></p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Etymology.</italic> Named after its morphological similarity to <italic>Stauronema indicum.</italic></p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><italic>Conidiomata</italic> stromatic, scattered or aggregated, superficial, dark brown to black, cupulate, unilocular, globose to oval, irregular in outline, 300&#x2013;400 &#x3BC;m diam, setose with a central cream conidial mass on PNA; basal stroma of <italic>textura angularis</italic>, layer 20&#x2013;30 &#x3BC;m thick. <italic>Setae</italic> brown, simple, septate, subulate with acute to obtuse apex, unbranched, smooth, thick-walled, up to 4-septate, 100&#x2013;400 &#xD7; 4&#x2013;8 &#x3BC;m, 1&#x2013;1.5 &#x3BC;m wide at acute apex, or 4 &#x3BC;m when obtuse at apex, arising from basal stroma or lateral from excipulum. <italic>Conidiophores</italic> lining the basal stroma, hyaline, but pigmented in basal part, septate, sparingly branched, cylindrical, thin-walled, smooth, 20&#x2013;40 &#x3BC;m long, invested in mucus. <italic>Conidiogenous cells</italic> determinate, phialidic with periclinal thickening, rarely indeterminate and proliferating percurrently at apex, hyaline, smooth, subcylindrical to lageniform, 5&#x2013;15 &#xD7; 2&#x2013;2.5 &#x3BC;m. <italic>Conidia</italic> hyaline, aseptate, thin-walled, smooth, naviculate to fusiform or ellipsoid, gently curved or straight, apex obtuse to subobtusely rounded, base truncate, eguttulate or guttulate, (9&#x2212;)10&#x2013;12(&#x2212;13) &#xD7; (3&#x2212;)3.5(&#x2212;4) &#x3BC;m, with a single, unbranched, flexuous, tubular appendage at each end; basal appendage excentric; apical and basal appendages 9&#x2013;22 &#x3BC;m long; lateral appendages 2, inserted 4&#x2013;6 &#x3BC;m below apex, 10&#x2013;17 &#x3BC;m long.</p>
        <p>Culture characteristics &#x2014; Colonies spreading, erumpent, with moderate aerial mycelium on OA, but with sparse aerial mycelium on PDA and MEA. On MEA rosy buff (surface), reverse cinnamon with patches of buff; on OA buff; on PDA grey olivaceous in centre, buff in outer region, and buff in reverse.</p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Specimen examined.</italic> USA, Kansas, near Manhattan, Konza Prairie Research Natural Area, long-term ecological research site, A1 horizon soil, tallgrass prairie, June 1987, <italic>M. Christensen</italic> (holotype CBS H-20951, culture ex-type RMF 8631 = CBS 127402).</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Notes &#x2014; Morphologically similar to <italic>Stauronema indicum</italic>, but distinct in that it has larger conidia and appendages of different length, and at different positions in relation to the conidial apex (conidia 7&#x2013;13 &#xD7; 2&#x2013;3 &#x3BC;m, terminal appendages 6.5&#x2013;17 &#x3BC;m, lateral appendages 8&#x2013;20 &#x3BC;m long, but 3&#x2013;4 &#x3BC;m below apex; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nag Raj 1993</xref>).</p>
        <p><bold><italic>Dinemasporium pseudostrigosum</italic></bold> Crous, <italic>sp. nov. &#x2014;</italic> MycoBank MB800164; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref></p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Etymology</italic>. Named after its morphological similarity to <italic>D. strigosum</italic>.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><italic>Conidiomata</italic> stromatic, scattered or aggregated, superficial, dark brown to black, cupulate, unilocular, globose, up to 250 &#x3BC;m diam, setose with a central buff to rosy buff conidial mass on PNA; basal stroma of <italic>textura angularis</italic>, layer 20&#x2013;30 &#x3BC;m thick. <italic>Setae</italic> brown to black, simple, septate, subulate with acute apex, unbranched, smooth, thick-walled, up to 7-septate, 100&#x2013;250 &#xD7; 5&#x2013;8 &#x3BC;m, 1&#x2013;1.5 &#x3BC;m wide at acute apex, arising from basal stroma or lateral from excipulum. <italic>Conidiophores</italic> lining the basal stroma, hyaline, septate, sparingly branched, cylindrical, thin-walled, smooth, 30&#x2013;40 &#x3BC;m long. <italic>Conidiogenous cells</italic> determinate, phialidic with periclinal thickening, hyaline, smooth, subcylindrical to lageniform, 10&#x2013;15 &#xD7; 2&#x2013;2.5 &#x3BC;m. <italic>Conidia</italic> hyaline, aseptate, thin-walled, smooth, naviculate to fusiform or ellipsoid, gently curved or straight, apex obtuse to subobtusely rounded, base truncate, eguttulate or guttulate, (10&#x2212;)12&#x2013;13(&#x2212;14) &#xD7; (2.5&#x2212;)3 &#x3BC;m, with a single, unbranched, flexuous, tubular appendage at each end, (11&#x2212;)13&#x2013;15(&#x2212;17) &#x3BC;m; basal appendage excentric.</p>
        <p>Culture characteristics &#x2014; Colonies spreading, erumpent, with moderate aerial mycelium. On MEA buff (surface), reverse cinnamon in middle, buff in outer region; on OA buff with profuse sporulation (peach in colour); on PDA dirty white to buff (surface and reverse).</p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Specimens examined.</italic><sc>Cuba,</sc> Granma, on <italic>Stigmaphyllon sagraeanum</italic>, 14 Mar 1991, <italic>R.F. Casta&#xF1;eda</italic>, INIFAT C91/88-1 = CBS 825.91. &#x2013; <sc>Germany,</sc> Monheim, on <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>, Sept. 1985, <italic>P. Reinecke</italic>, (holotype CBS H-12018, culture ex-type CBS 717.85).</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Notes &#x2014; Morphologically <italic>D. pseudostrigosum</italic> is similar to <italic>D. strigosum</italic>, but distinct in that it has larger conidia, and longer appendages.</p>
        <p><bold><italic>Dinemasporium strigosum</italic></bold> (Pers.: Fr.) Sacc., Michelia 2: 281. 1881; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref></p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Basionym. Peziza strigosa</italic> Pers.: Fr., Syst. Mycol. 2: 103. 1823.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>&#x2261; <italic>Polynema strigosa</italic> (Pers.: Fr.) Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen Vereins Naturk. 23&#x2013;24: 367. 1870.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>= <italic>Vermicularia graminum</italic> Lib., Pl. Crypt. Arduenna, fasc. (Li&#xE8;ge) 4: no. 348. 1837.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>&#x2261; <italic>Excipula graminum</italic> (Lib.) Corda, Icon. Fungorum (Prague) 3: 29. 1839.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>&#x2261; <italic>Dinemasporium graminum</italic> (Lib.) L&#xE9;v., Ann. Sci. Nat., Bot., ser. 3, 5: 274. 1846.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>= <italic>Excipula betulae</italic> Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen Vereins Naturk. 15: 64. 1860.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>&#x2261; <italic>Polynema betulae</italic> (Fuckel) Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen Vereins Naturk. 23&#x2013;24: 367. 1870.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>&#x2261; <italic>Dinemasporium betulae</italic> (Fuckel) Sacc., Syll. Fung. 3: 686. 1884.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>= <italic>Dinemasporium longisetum</italic> Syd., Ann. Mycol. 34, 4/5: 400. 1936.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>= <italic>Ellisiellina biciliata</italic> Sousa da C&#xE2;mara, Agron. Lusit. 11: 72. 1949.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>= <italic>Pycnidiochaeta biciliata</italic> Sousa da C&#xE2;mara, Agron. Lusit. 12, 1: 109. 1950.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>For additional synonyms see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Sutton (1980)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nag Raj (1993)</xref>.</p>
        <p><italic>Conidiomata</italic> stromatic, scattered or aggregated, superficial, dark brown to black, cupulate, unilocular, globose, up to 250 &#x3BC;m diam, setose with a central buff to rosy buff conidial mass on PNA; basal stroma of <italic>textura angularis</italic>, layer 20&#x2013;30 &#x3BC;m thick. <italic>Setae</italic> brown to black, simple, septate, subulate with acute apex, unbranched, smooth, thick-walled, up to 9-septate, 60&#x2013;400 &#xD7; 7&#x2013;10 &#x3BC;m, 1&#x2013;1.5 &#x3BC;m wide at acute apex, arising from basal stroma or lateral from excipulum. <italic>Conidiophores</italic> lining the basal stroma, hyaline, septate, sparingly branched, cylindrical, thin-walled, smooth, 30&#x2013;40 &#x3BC;m long. <italic>Conidiogenous cells</italic> determinate, phialidic with periclinal thickening, hyaline, smooth, subcylindrical to lageniform, 12&#x2013;15 &#xD7; 2&#x2013;2.5 &#x3BC;m. <italic>Conidia</italic> hyaline, aseptate, thin-walled, smooth, naviculate to fusiform or ellipsoid, gently curved or straight, apex obtuse to subobtusely rounded, base truncate, eguttulate or guttulate, (9&#x2212;)10&#x2013;12(&#x2212;13) &#xD7; (2&#x2212;)2.5(&#x2212;3) &#x3BC;m, with a single, unbranched, flexuous, tubular appendage at each end, (6&#x2212;)7&#x2013;8(&#x2212;9) &#x3BC;m; basal appendage excentric.</p>
        <p>Culture characteristics &#x2014; Colonies spreading, erumpent, with moderate aerial mycelium. On MEA buff (surface), rosy buff (reverse); on OA buff with profuse sporulation (peach in colour); on PDA buff (surface and reverse).</p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Specimens examined.</italic><sc>Belgium</sc>, Ardenne, on dried grass blades, Libert, Pl. Crypt. Arduennae, 1837, syntype of <italic>D. graminum</italic>, K(M) 175982. &#x2013; <sc>Germany</sc>, Baden-Werttemberg, Eberbach, on rotton wood of <italic>Betula</italic> sp., Fuckle&#x2019;s Fungi Rhenani exs 205, syntype of <italic>D. betulae</italic>, K(M) 175979; Brandenburg, Freienwalde near Oder, on leaves of <italic>Populus tremula</italic>, H. Sydow Mycotheca Germanica exs 2978, 30 Sept. 1934, syntype of <italic>D. longisetum</italic>, K(M) 175980; Monheim, on <italic>Secale cereale</italic>, May 1984, <italic>M. Hossfeld</italic>, (epitype designated here CBS H-20952, culture ex-epitype CBS 828.84). &#x2013; <sc>Netherlands,</sc> Beemster, from hay, <italic>M. Nieuwstad</italic>, Oct. 1978, specimen CBS H-12008, culture CBS 520.78; Wageningen, on <italic>Phragmites australis</italic>, 15 Nov. 2010, <italic>W. Quaedvlieg</italic>, CPC 18898, 18899. &#x2013; <sc>Portugal</sc>, Ribatejo, on leaves of <italic>Dactylis hispanica</italic>, Garcia Cabral 307, 30 Aug. 1950, holotype of <italic>Ellisiellina biciliata</italic> LISE 41853; Serra do Geres, on culms of <italic>Agrostis castellana</italic>, 9 July 1948, M.R. de J. Dias, holotype of <italic>Pycnidiochaeta biciliata</italic>, LISE 50037. &#x2013; <sc>South Africa</sc>, Western Cape Province, Bracken Nature Reserve, on <italic>Wildenovia incurvata</italic>, 18 Aug. 2011, <italic>A. Wood</italic>, CPC 19796, 19797. &#x2013; <sc>Sweden</sc>, on grass blades, <italic>E. Fries</italic>, Scler. Suecicae exs 136, isotype of <italic>Peziza strigosa</italic> K(M) 175981.&#x2013; USA: Illinois, Rockford, from <italic>Malus</italic>, J. Batzer, Sept. 2000, specimen CBS H-19787, culture CBS 18957.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Notes &#x2014; <italic>Dinemasporium strigosum</italic> and its purported synonyms have been treated by several authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Webster 1955</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Sutton 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nag Raj 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Yamaguchi et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Duan et al. 2007</xref>). The synonyms proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Sutton (1980)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nag Raj (1993)</xref> were accepted based on the examination of the type material cited above.</p>
        <p>Although <italic>D. strigosum</italic> was linked to a sexual state described as <italic>Phomatospora dinemasporium</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Webster 1955</xref>), the generic placement was questioned by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Rappaz (1992)</xref>, as other species of <italic>Phomatospora</italic> have been linked to hyphomycetes with <italic>Fusarium</italic>-like conidia. No sexual states were encountered or induced in the present study.</p>
        <p><bold><italic>Pseudolachnea</italic></bold> Ranoj., Ann. Mycol. 8: 593. 1910 [non <italic>Pseudolachnea</italic> Velen. 1934].</p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p>= <italic>Dinemasporiella</italic> Bub&#xE1;k &amp; Kab&#xE1;t, Hedwigia 52: 358. 1912; non <italic>Dinemasporiella</italic> Speg., Annales Mus. Nac. Buenos Aires 20: 366. 1910 (nom. dub.).</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>&#x2261; <italic>Dinemasporiopsis</italic> Bub&#xE1;k &amp; Kab&#xE1;t, nom. nov., apud Died., Krypt.-Fl. Mark Brandenburg 9: 750. 1915.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>= <italic>Chaetopatella</italic> Hino &amp; Katum., J. Jap. Bot. 33: 238. 1958.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Type species. Pseudolachnea hispidula</italic> (Schrad.) B. Sutton (= <italic>P. bubakii</italic> Ranoj.).</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><italic>Conidiomata</italic> stromatic, scattered to gregarious, cupulate, superficial, unilocular, setose, dark brown to black; basal stroma of <italic>textura angularis. Setae</italic> divergent, subulate with blunt or acute apices, unbranched, septate, thick-walled, smooth, dark brown. <italic>Conidiophores</italic> arising from the uppermost cells of the basal stroma and the inner cells of the excipulum, branched, septate, brown at base, hyaline in upper part, smooth, invested in a thin layer of mucus. <italic>Conidiogenous cells</italic> discrete, phialidic with periclinal thickening, cylindrical, hyaline, smooth. <italic>Macroconidia</italic> fusiform with obtuse ends, 1-septate, hyaline, smooth, guttulate, bearing an unbranched, short, cellular, filiform appendage at each end; appendages not delimited by septa, basal appendage excentric. <italic>Microconidia</italic> intermixed with macroconidia in same conidioma, fusiform, curved with rounded ends, aseptate, smooth, guttulate, lacking appendages.</p>
        <p><bold><italic>Pseudolachnea fraxini</italic></bold> Crous, <italic>sp. nov. &#x2014;</italic> MycoBank MB800165; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11</xref></p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Etymology.</italic> Named after the host from which it was collected, <italic>Fraxinus</italic>.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><italic>Conidiomata</italic> on OA stromatic, scattered to gregarious, cupulate, superficial, unilocular, setose, dark brown to black, up to 300 &#x3BC;m diam; basal stroma of <italic>textura angularis. Setae</italic> divergent, subulate with blunt or acute apices, unbranched, septate only at the base, thick-walled, smooth, dark brown, 40&#x2013;170 &#xD7; 4&#x2013;7 &#x3BC;m. <italic>Conidiophores</italic> arising from the uppermost cells of the basal stroma and the inner cells of the excipulum, sparsely branched and septate at the base, up to 20 &#x3BC;m long, brown at base, hyaline in upper part, smooth, invested in a thin layer of mucus. <italic>Conidiogenous cells</italic> discrete, phialidic with periclinal thickening, cylindrical, hyaline, smooth, 6&#x2013;12 &#xD7; 2&#x2013;3 &#x3BC;m. <italic>Macroconidia</italic> fusiform with obtuse ends, 1-septate, hyaline, smooth, guttulate, (12&#x2212;)15&#x2013;16(&#x2212;18) &#xD7; 2(&#x2212;2.5) &#x3BC;m, bearing an unbranched, short, cellular, filiform appendage at each end, 1.5&#x2013;2 &#x3BC;m long; appendages not delimited by septa, basal appendage excentric. <italic>Microconidia</italic> common, intermixed with macroconidia in same conidioma, fusiform, curved with rounded ends, aseptate, smooth, guttulate, (6&#x2212;)7&#x2013;9 &#xD7; (1&#x2212;)1.5 &#x3BC;m, lacking appendages.</p>
        <p>Culture characteristics &#x2014; Colonies flat, spreading, with sparse aerial mycelium and even, lobate margins. On MEA dirty white (surface), reverse cinnamon; on OA surface honey to isabelline, reverse honey; on PDA dirty white (surface and reverse).</p>
        <list list-type="simple">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Specimen examined.</italic><sc>Sweden,</sc> Uppland, Dalby par., Jerusalem, on <italic>Fraxinus excelsior</italic>, coll. <italic>K. &amp; L. Holm</italic>, isol. <italic>O. Constantinescu</italic>, 31 Mar. 1986 (holotype CBS H-20953, culture ex-type CBS 113701).</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Notes &#x2014; The ex-type culture of <italic>P. fraxini</italic> (CBS 113701) was originally identified as <italic>P. hispidula. Pseudolachnea fraxini</italic> differs from <italic>P. hispidula</italic> by having much smaller conidiomata, shorter setae, larger conidia (conidiomata 600&#x2013;1200 &#x3BC;m diam, setae 80&#x2013;220 &#x3BC;m long, conidia 11&#x2013;14 &#x3BC;m long in <italic>P. hispidula</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nag Raj 1993</xref>), and forms primarily microconidia in culture, an aspect not yet observed in <italic>P. hispidula</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>The present study examined the genus <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> with the aim of evaluating the importance of conidial appendages as taxonomic characters at generic level among coelomycetous taxa. <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> has several acknowledged synonyms, including <italic>Dendrophoma</italic>, <italic>Pycnidiochaeta</italic>, and <italic>Amphitiarospora</italic>. Species with septate conidia were allocated to other genera (<italic>Pseudolachnea</italic>, <italic>Pseudolachnella</italic>), while those with apical, basal and lateral setae, were placed in <italic>Stauronema</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Sutton 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nag Raj 1993</xref>).</p>
      <p>Based on these findings, a new genus, <italic>Brunneodinemasporium</italic> is introduced to accommodate a <italic>Dinemasporium</italic>-like species with tightly aggregated brown conidiogenous cells, and pale brown conidia. Furthermore, the genus <italic>Dendrophoma</italic> (= <italic>Amphitiarospora</italic>) is reinstated as distinct from <italic>Dinemasporium. Dendrophoma</italic> (which is based on <italic>D. cytosporoides</italic>) has superficial, stipitate to cupulate conidiomata, and small conidia with two polar, tubular, exogenous appendages, which separates it from <italic>Dinemasporium</italic>. The genus <italic>Stauronema</italic> is reduced to synonymy under <italic>Dinemasporium</italic>, and lateral conidial appendages rejected as a useful single character for generic separation. The genus <italic>Pseudolachnea</italic> (1-septate conidia) is supported as distinct from <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> (aseptate conidia), though no cultures were available to determine if <italic>Pseudolachnella</italic> (multi-septate conidia) needs to be reduced to synonymy with <italic>Pseudolachnea</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Sutton 1980</xref>), or retained as separate genus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nag Raj 1993</xref>).</p>
      <p>The genus <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> is a phylogenetically well-defined genus in the <italic>Chaetosphaeriaceae. Dinemasporium</italic> is circumscribed based on <italic>D. strigosum</italic>, which is also epitypified in this study. Five novel species are described from a collection of cultures formerly treated as <italic>D. strigosum</italic>. Taxa in this complex appear to differ by a combination of morphological features of the setae, conidia and conidial appendages.</p>
      <p>Other than revising taxa in the <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> complex, a major aim of the present study was to determine the relevance of appendages as delimiting feature at generic level in coelomycetous fungi. Conidial appendages have been used extensively to support the separation of species (e.g. <italic>Coniella</italic>, <italic>Phyllosticta</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">van Niekerk et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Glienke et al. 2011</xref>), but have also been used to separate genera of coelomycetous fungi (e.g. <italic>Discosia</italic>, <italic>Pestalotiopsis</italic>, <italic>Seimatosporium</italic>, <italic>Tiarosporella</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Crous et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Barber et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Maharachchikumbura et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Tanaka et al. 2011</xref>).</p>
      <p>Results from the present study revealed that conidial appendages in coelomycetes are not informative as generic characters when looked at in isolation, as recently reported for the <italic>Seimatosporium</italic> complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Barber et al. 2011</xref>). Although appendage morphology appeared to be highly informative at the species level (mucilaginous or cellular, endo- or exogenous, simple or branched, as well as their position on the conidium body), they appeared to be less informative when used in isolation as generic feature. We can conclude that genera separated chiefly on the basis of appendage morphology, e.g. <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> and <italic>Stauronema</italic>, or <italic>Seimatosporium</italic> and <italic>Vermisporium</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Barber et al. 2011</xref>), represent only two genera, namely <italic>Dinemasporium</italic> and <italic>Seimatosporium</italic>. This finding could also have implications for other more commonly encountered genera, e.g. <italic>Pestalotiopsis</italic> and <italic>Pestalotia</italic>, which are also separated solely on the basis of apical appendage morphology. <italic>Pestalotia</italic> (1839) predates <italic>Pestalotiopsis</italic> (1949), which will have serious implications for names in <italic>Pestalotiopsis</italic>, which is presently the more commonly used genus.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank the technical staff, Arien van Iperen (cultures), Marjan Vermaas (photo plates), and Mieke Starink-Willemse (DNA isolation, amplification and sequencing) for their invaluable assistance.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agnihothrudu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>1962</year><article-title>Notes on fungi from North-east India XIV &#x2013; A new genus of Discellaceae from Assam</article-title>. 
<source>Sydowia</source><volume>16</volume>: 
<fpage>73</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>76</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Crous</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Groenewald</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascoe</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Reassessing Vermisporium (Amphisphaeriaceae), a genus of foliar pathogens of eucalypts</article-title>. 
<source>Persoonia</source><volume>27</volume>: 
<fpage>90</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22403479</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crous</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gams</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Stalpers</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Stegehuis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>MycoBank: an online initiative to launch mycology into the 21st century</article-title>. 
<source>Studies in Mycology</source><volume>50</volume>: 
<fpage>19</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>22</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crous</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoch</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gueidan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, et al. 
<year>2009a</year><article-title>Phylogenetic lineages in the Capnodiales</article-title>. 
<source>Studies in Mycology</source><volume>64</volume>: 
<fpage>17</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20169022</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crous</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Slippers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingfield</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rheeder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marasas</surname><given-names>WFO</given-names></name></person-group>, et al. <year>2006</year><article-title>Phylogenetic lineages in the Botryosphaeriaceae</article-title>. 
<source>Studies in Mycology</source><volume>55</volume>: 
<fpage>235</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18490983</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crous</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Verkley</surname><given-names>GJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Groenewald</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
(eds). 
<year>2009b</year>
<source>Fungal Biodiversity. CBS Laboratory Manual Series 1</source>. 
<publisher-name>Centraalbureau voor Schimmelcultures</publisher-name>, 
<publisher-loc>Utrecht</publisher-loc></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crous</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingfield</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Mycosphaerella nubilosa a synonym of M. molleriana</article-title>. 
<source>Mycological Research</source><volume>95</volume>: 
<fpage>628</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>632</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Dinemasporium (coelomycetes)</article-title>. 
<source>Fungal Diversity</source><volume>26</volume>: 
<fpage>205</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>218</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glienke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stringari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fabris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kava-Cordeiro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
, et al. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Endophytic and pathogenic Phyllosticta species, with reference to those associated with Citrus Black Spot</article-title>. 
<source>Persoonia</source><volume>26</volume>: 
<fpage>47</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22025803</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoog</surname><given-names>GS de</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerrits van den Ende</surname><given-names>AHG</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Molecular diagnostics of clinical strains of filamentous Basidiomycetes</article-title>. 
<source>Mycoses</source><volume>41</volume>: 
<fpage>183</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9715630</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maharachchikumbura</surname><given-names>SSN</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chukeatirote</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahkali</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Pestalotiopsis &#x2013; morphology, phylogeny, biochemistry and diversity</article-title>. 
<source>Fungal Diversity</source><volume>50</volume>: 
<fpage>167</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>187</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nag Raj</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year> Coelomycetous anamorphs with appendage-bearing conidia. Mycologue Publications, Waterloo, Ontario.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niekerk</surname><given-names>JM van</given-names></name><name><surname>Groenewald</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Verkley</surname><given-names>GJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fourie</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingfield</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Crous</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Systematic reappraisal of Coniella and Pilidiella, with specific reference to species occurring on Eucalyptus and Vitis in South Africa</article-title>. 
<source>Mycological Research</source><volume>108</volume>: 
<fpage>283</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15185979</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rappaz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Phomatospora berkeleyi, P. arenaria and their Sporothrix anamorphs</article-title>. 
<source>Mycotaxon</source><volume>45</volume>: 
<fpage>323</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>330</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rayner</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1970</year><source>A mycological colour chart</source>. 
<publisher-name>Commonwealth Mycological Institute</publisher-name>, 
<publisher-loc>Kew</publisher-loc></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saccardo</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1884</year><source>Sylloge fungorum</source><volume>3</volume>: 
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>860</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingfield</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Crous</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Sphaeropsis sapinea and Botryosphaeria dothidea endophytic in Pinus spp. 
and Eucalyptus spp. in South Africa</article-title>. 
<source>South African Journal of Botany</source><volume>62</volume>: 
<fpage>86</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>88</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1965</year><article-title>Typification of Dendrophoma and a reassessment of D. 
obscurans</article-title>. 
<source>Transactions of the British Mycological Society</source><volume>48</volume>: 
<fpage>611</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>616</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1977</year><article-title>Coelomycetes VI. Nomenclature of generic names proposed for Coelomycetes</article-title>. 
<source>Mycological Papers</source><volume>141</volume>: 
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>253</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1980</year><source>The Coelomycetes: Fungi imperfecti with pycnidia, acervuli, and stromata</source>. 
<publisher-name>Commonwealth Mycological Institute</publisher-name>, 
<publisher-loc>Kew, Surrey</publisher-loc></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sellar</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1966</year><article-title>Toxosporiopsis n. gen., an unusual member of melanconiales</article-title>. 
<source>Canadian Journal of Botany</source><volume>44</volume>: 
<fpage>1505</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1513</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirayama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Okane</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosoya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Phylogeny of Discosia and Seimatosporium, and introduction of Adisciso and Immersidiscosia genera nova</article-title>. 
<source>Persoonia</source><volume>26</volume>: 
<fpage>85</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22025806</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vilgalys</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hester</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>Rapid genetic identification and mapping of enzymatically amplified ribosomal DNA from several Cryptococcus species</article-title>. 
<source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>172</volume>: 
<fpage>4238</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2376561</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1955</year><article-title>Graminicolous pyrenomycetes V. Conidial state of Leptosphaeria michotii, L. microspica, Pleospora vagans and the perfect states of Dinemasporium graminum</article-title>. 
<source>Transitions of the British Mycological Society</source><volume>38</volume>: 
<fpage>347</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>365</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruns</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>Amplification and direct sequencing of fungal ribosomal RNA genes for phylogenetics</article-title>. In: 
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Innis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelfand</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sninsky</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>
White</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>
(eds), 
<source>PCR protocols: a guide to methods and applications: 315&#x2013;322</source>. 
<publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>, 
<publisher-loc>San Diego, California, USA</publisher-loc></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wikee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Udayanga</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Crous</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chukeatirote</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>EHC</given-names></name></person-group>
, et al. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Phyllosticta &#x2013; an overview of current status of species recognition</article-title>. 
<source>Fungal Diversity</source><volume>51</volume>: 
<fpage>43</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>61</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wulandari</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name><surname>To-anun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Duong</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruyter</surname><given-names>J de</given-names></name></person-group>
, et al. <year>2009</year>
<article-title>Phyllosticta citriasiana sp. nov., the cause of Citrus tan spot of Citrus maxima in Asia</article-title>. 
<source>Fungal Diversity</source><volume>34</volume>: 
<fpage>23</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>39</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomoda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Omura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>A new species of Dinemasporium from sugar cane on Irabujima island, Japan</article-title>. 
<source>Mycoscience</source><volume>46</volume>: 
<fpage>367</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>369</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Collection details and GenBank accession numbers of isolates for which novel sequences were generated in this study.</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th>
            <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain accession no.<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn1-126-137"><sup>1</sup></xref></th>
            <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substrate</th>
            <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</th>
            <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collector(s)</th>
            <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">GenBank accession no.<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn2-126-137"><sup>2</sup></xref><hr/></th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITS</th>
            <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSU</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Brunneodinemasporium brasiliense</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 112007; INIFAT CO2/51</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decaying leaf</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R.F. Casta&#xF1;eda-Ruiz</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889272</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889288</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Dendrophoma cytisporoides</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 223.95</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Branches and twigs of <italic>Rhododendron</italic></td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netherlands</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A. Aptroot</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889273</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889289</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Dinemasporium americana</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 127127; RMF 7507</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A1 horizon soil of tallgrass prairie</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA:Iowa</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D.E. Tuthill</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889274</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889290</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Dinemasporium decipiens</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 592.73</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil under <italic>Elaeis guineensis</italic></td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suriname</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">J.H. van Emde</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889275</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889291</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Dinemasporium morbidum</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 129.66</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sputum of man</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netherlands</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N.G.M. Orie &amp; A. Kikstra</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889280</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889296</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 995.97; ATCC 200690</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hare dung</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New Zealand</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D.P. Mahoney</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889281</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889297</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Dinemasporium polygonum</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 516.95</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Polygonum sachalinense</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netherlands</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A. Aptroot</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889276</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889292</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Dinemasporium pseudoindicum</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 127402; RMF 8631</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A1 horizon soil of tallgrass prairie</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA:Kansas</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M. Christensen</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889277</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889293</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Dinemasporium pseudostrigosum</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 717.85</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P. Reinecke</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889278</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889294</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 825.91; INIFAT C91/88-1</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Stigmaphyllon sagraeanum</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cuba</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R.F. Casta&#xF1;eda</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889279</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889295</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Dinemasporium strigosum</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 520.78</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hay</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netherlands</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M. Nieuwstad</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889282</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889298</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 828.84</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf spot on <italic>Secale cereale</italic></td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M. Hossfeld</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889283</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889299</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CPC 18898</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Phragmites australis</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netherlands</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W. Quaedvlieg</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889284</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889300</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CPC 18957</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Malus</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA:Illinois</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">J. Batzer</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889285</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CPC 19796</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Wildenovia incurvata</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Africa</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A. Wood</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889286</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Pseudolachnea fraxini</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 113701; UPSC 1833</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <italic>Fraxinus excelsior</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K. &amp; L. Holm</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889287</td>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ889301</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn id="tfn1-126-137">
          <p><sup>1</sup> ATCC: American Type Culture Collection, Virginia, USA; CBS: CBS Fungal Biodiversity Centre, Utrecht, The Netherlands; CPC: Culture collection of P.W. Crous, housed at CBS; INIFAT: Alexander Humboldt Institute for Basic Research in Tropical Agriculture, Ciudad de La Habana, Cuba; RMF: Martha Christensen Soil Fungus Collection; UPSC: Uppsala University Culture Collection of Fungi, Botanical Museum University of Uppsala, Uppsala, Sweden.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="tfn2-126-137">
          <p><sup>2</sup> ITS: Internal transcribed spacers 1 and 2 together with 5.8S nrDNA; LSU: partial 28S nrDNA.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>The first of 142 equally most parsimonious trees obtained from a heuristic search with 100 random taxon additions of the LSU sequence alignment. The scale bar shows 10 changes, and bootstrap support values from 1 000 replicates are shown at the nodes. The species treated in this study are located in the coloured blocks. Branches present in the strict consensus tree are thickened and the tree was rooted to a sequence of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> (GenBank accession Z73326).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="per-28-126-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>The first of three equally most parsimonious trees obtained from a heuristic search with 100 random taxon additions of the ITS sequence alignment. The scale bar shows 25 changes, and bootstrap support values from 1 000 replicates are shown at the nodes. Genera are indicated in the coloured blocks and the names of genera treated in this study are written in red. Ex-type strains are printed in <bold>bold</bold>. Branches present in the strict consensus tree are thickened and the tree was rooted to a sequence of <italic>Cephalotheca sulfurea</italic> (GenBank accession AB278194).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="per-28-126-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p><italic>Brunneodinemasporium brasiliense</italic> (CBS 112007). a, b. Acervular conidiomata with setae; c. bases of setae; d. obtuse apices of setae; e, f. tightly aggregated layer of conidiogenous cells; g. squash of conidiogenous cells giving rise to conidia; h, i. conidia. &#x2014; Scale bars: b = 20 &#x3BC;m, all others = 10 &#x3BC;m; c applies to d; e applies to f, g.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="per-28-126-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p><italic>Dendrophoma cytosporoides</italic> (CBS 223.95). a. Stalked acervuli forming in culture; b&#x2013;d, f. conidiogenous cells; e. setae; g, h. conidia. &#x2014; Scale bars = 10 &#x3BC;m, except e = 20 &#x3BC;m.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="per-28-126-g004"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p><italic>Dinemasporium americana</italic> (CBS 127127). a, b. Acervular conidiomata forming in culture; c&#x2013;e. setae and conidiogenous cells; f. conidiogenous cells; g, h. conidia. &#x2014; Scale bars = 10 &#x3BC;m; e applies to f.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="per-28-126-g005"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 6</label>
      <caption>
        <p><italic>Dinemasporium morbidum</italic> (CBS 129.66). a, b. Acervular conidiomata forming in culture; c. setae. d, e. conidiogenous cells; f, g. bases and apices of setae; h, i. conidia. &#x2014; Scale bars = 10 &#x3BC;m, except a = 20 &#x3BC;m.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="per-28-126-g006"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 7</label>
      <caption>
        <p><italic>Dinemasporium polygonum</italic> (CBS 516.95). a, b. Acervular conidiomata forming in culture; c. setae; d, e. conidiogenous cells; f, g. conidia. &#x2014; Scale bars = 10 &#x3BC;m, except a, b = 20 &#x3BC;m.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="per-28-126-g007"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 8</label>
      <caption>
        <p><italic>Dinemasporium pseudoindicum</italic> (CBS 127402). a, b. Acervular conidiomata forming in culture; c, d. setae; e. conidiogenous cells; f&#x2013;h. conidia, showing apical, lateral and basal appendages. &#x2014; Scale bars = 10 &#x3BC;m, except a = 20 &#x3BC;m, applies also to b.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="per-28-126-g008"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F9" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 9</label>
      <caption>
        <p><italic>Dinemasporium pseudostrigosum</italic> (CBS 717.85). a, b. Acervular conidiomata forming in culture; c, d. setae; e, f. conidiogenous cells; g, h. conidia. &#x2014; Scale bars = 10 &#x3BC;m, except a = 20 &#x3BC;m, applies also to b.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="per-28-126-g009"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F10" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 10</label>
      <caption>
        <p><italic>Dinemasporium strigosum</italic> (CBS 828.84). a&#x2013;c. Acervular conidiomata forming in vivo; d, e. setae; f, g. conidiogenous cells; h, i. conidia. &#x2014; Scale bars = 10 &#x3BC;m, except a = 20 &#x3BC;m, applies also to b, c; d applies to e; f applies to g.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="per-28-126-g010"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F11" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 11</label>
      <caption>
        <p><italic>Pseudolachnea fraxini</italic> (CBS 113701). a, b. Acervular conidiomata forming in culture; c, d. setae; e, f. conidiogenous cells; g. h. macro- and microconidia. &#x2014; Scale bars = 10 &#x3BC;m, except a = 20 &#x3BC;m, applies also to b.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="per-28-126-g011"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
