<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Theor Appl Genet</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Theor. Appl. Genet</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>TAG. Theoretical and Applied Genetics. Theoretische Und Angewandte Genetik</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0040-5752</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1432-2242</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3374107</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1841</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-012-1841-7</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Paper</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A mutagenesis-derived broad-spectrum disease resistance locus in wheat</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Campbell</surname>
            <given-names>Jackie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Hongtao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Giroux</surname>
            <given-names>Michael J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Feiz</surname>
            <given-names>Leila</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jin</surname>
            <given-names>Yue</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Meinan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Xianming</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>Li</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+1-406-9945058</phone>
            <fax>+1-406-9947600</fax>
            <email>lhuang@montana.edu</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Plant Sciences and Plant Pathology, Montana State University, Bozeman, MT 59717-3150 USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Cereal Disease Laboratory, United States Department of Agriculture-Agricultural Research Service (USDA-ARS), St. Paul, MN 55108 USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Wheat Genetics, Physiology, Quality, and Disease Research Unit, United States Department of Agriculture-Agricultural Research Service (USDA-ARS), Pullman, WA 99164-6430 USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>The Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research, Ithaca, NY 14853-1801 USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Plant Pathology, Washington State University, Pullman, WA 99164-6430 USA </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="com">
          <p>Communicated by J. Snape.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>125</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>391</fpage>
      <lpage>404</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <p>Wheat leaf rust, stem rust, stripe rust, and powdery mildew caused by the fungal pathogens <italic>Puccinia triticina</italic>, <italic>P. graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic>, <italic>P. striiformis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic>, and <italic>Blumeria graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic>, respectively, are destructive diseases of wheat worldwide. Breeding durable disease resistance cultivars rely largely on continually introgressing new resistance genes, especially the genes with different defense mechanisms, into adapted varieties. Here, we describe a new resistance gene obtained by mutagenesis. The mutant, MNR220 (<italic>m</italic>utagenesis-derived <italic>n</italic>ew <italic>r</italic>esistance), enhances resistance to three rusts and powdery mildew, with the characteristics of delayed disease development at the seedling stage and completed resistance at the adult plant stage. Genetic analysis demonstrated that the resistance in MNR220 is conferred by a single semidominant gene mapped on the short arm of chromosome 2B. Gene expression profiling of several pathogenesis-related genes indicated that MNR220 has an elevated and rapid pathogen-induced response. In addition to its potential use in breeding for resistance to multiple diseases, high-resolution mapping and cloning of the disease resistance locus in MNR220 may lead to a better understanding of the regulation of defense responses in wheat.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2012</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) provides approximately 40 % of the food and 25 % of the calories consumed globally (Board <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2010</xref>). Bread wheat is an allohexaploid (2<italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;6<italic>x</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;42) consisting of three related genomes designated A, B, and D with an estimated genome size of 16,000&#xA0;Mb (Arumuganathan and Earle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1991</xref>). This complex species arose from two successive hybridization and speciation events involving domesticated and wild grasses (Dvo&#x159;&#xE1;k et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">1993</xref>; McFadden and Sears <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">1964</xref>; Sarkar and Stebbins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1956</xref>). The relatively recent speciation and domestication history of wheat led to limited genetic variation within the species.</p>
      <p>Modern wheat improvement efforts are centered on yield and increased resistance to biotic stresses, especially fungal pathogens. Disease resistance can be accomplished either through passive or active host defense mechanisms. Passive defense involves physical or chemical barriers to infection such as the cuticle and phytoanticipins presented by the host without direct pathogen recognition. Phytoanticipins are constitutively expressed tissue-specific antimicrobial chemicals (Bouarab et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2002</xref>) such as defensins that are found in the wheat endosperms (Colilla et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1990</xref>). Active defense, such as the hypersensitive response (HR), involves physiological changes in the host induced by pathogen recognition. Active defense involves signaling pathways such as those mediated by jasmonic acid (JA) and salicylic acid (SA). The SA signaling pathway is mainly induced by biotrophic pathogens and is correlated with high expression of specific <italic>PR</italic> genes (Glazebrook <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2005</xref>).</p>
      <p>The three wheat rusts are leaf rust caused by <italic>Puccinia triticina</italic> (<italic>Pt</italic>), stem rust caused by <italic>P. graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic> (<italic>Pgt</italic>), and stripe rust caused by <italic>P. striiformis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic> (<italic>Pst</italic>). Powdery mildew is caused by <italic>Blumeria graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic> (<italic>Bgt</italic>). Rusts and powdery mildew are biotrophs capable of causing large scale epidemics. Breeding resistance to these diseases is a major undertaking in wheat improvement worldwide. Types of rust and powdery mildew resistances are characterized as race specific or non-specific based on the mode of action. Race-specific resistance involves a gene-for-gene interaction between the host and pathogen (Flor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1956</xref>). This interaction depends on host recognition of pathogen effectors, or avirulence factors. This type of resistance is often controlled by a single host resistance gene (<italic>R</italic>-gene) that triggers programed cell death at the infection sites. Although race-specific resistance is often highly effective, it tends to be short-lived as host recognition is easily overcome by a change in or the deletion of the corresponding pathogen effector. Alternatively, race non-specific resistance is primarily conferred by multiple genes with intermediate or additive effects. As race non-specific resistance is not dependent upon a single gene-specific interaction it tends to be more durable. This type of resistance does not rely upon HR and confers resistance through retardation of disease development by a longer latent period, lower infection frequency, and/or reduced sporulation (Rubiales and Niks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">1995</xref>).</p>
      <p><italic>R</italic>-gene mediated resistance has been used by wheat improvement programs for decades to control wheat rust diseases. However, only relatively small set of effective, rust <italic>R</italic> genes deployed among cultivated varieties place a high selective pressure on pathogen populations. The selective pressure can lead to emergence of pathogen variants that avoid recognition by deployed <italic>R</italic> genes, and hence are capable of causing devastating disease epidemics. One of the most recent incidents occurred in 1999 when <italic>Pgt</italic> race TTKSK (or Ug99) was first identified in Uganda and subsequently caused stem rust epidemics in Kenya (Pretorius et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2000</xref>; Stokstad <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2007</xref>; Wanyera et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2006</xref>). Hence, breeding for rust resistance involves the continual introgression of new resistance genes into adapted cultivars. Here, we describe a wheat mutant identified from an ethylmethane sulfonate (EMS) mutagenized population created in the spring wheat cultivar Alpowa (PI 566596) that exhibits dominantly inherited resistance to the three rusts and powdery mildew.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Materials</title>
        <p>Plant materials Alpowa (PI 566596) and McNair 701 (CItr 15288) were obtained from the USDA National Plant Germplasm System (NPGS). Chinese Spring was provided by Dr. Luther Talbert at Montana State University. Avocet Susceptible (AvS) is an Australia spring wheat cultivar originally provided by Dr. Colin Wellings, Plant Breeding Institute, University of Sydney. Identification of MNR220 and development of the near isogenic lines (NILs) were outlined in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Resistant and susceptible NILs were developed after eight generations of selfing from one <italic>M</italic><sub>7</sub> heterozygous line 220-5. MNR220 heterozygous lines were selected at each generation with IT 2 to PBJL and confirmed with progeny tests of 20 seedlings.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>A scheme showing steps of mutant identification, confirmation and genetic analysis. M<sub><italic>n</italic>:<italic>n</italic>&#xA0;+&#xA0;1</sub> line is used to describe <italic>n</italic><sub>+1</sub> generation seeds that derived from one selected <italic>n</italic> generation plant</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="122_2012_1841_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
        <p>Leaf rust isolate PBJL was provided by Dr. Robert Bowden from USDA-ARS, Manhattan, KS. The other two leaf rust isolates SBDGD and BBBDD and one stripe rust isolate PST-139 were collected in Creston, MT. Stem rust isolates were from the collection of the Cereal Disease Laboratory (CDL), St. Paul, MN. Stripe rust isolates were from the USDA-ARS, Wheat Genetics, Quality, Physiology and Disease Research Unit, Pullman, WA.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>EMS-induced mutagenesis</title>
        <p>The mutagenized population screened here was created by EMS seed treatment of the soft, white, spring wheat cultivar Alpowa (Feiz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2009</xref>).</p>
        <sec id="Sec6">
          <title>Plant growth</title>
          <p>Seeds were germinated in 164&#xA0;mL cone-tainers (Stuewe &amp; Sons Inc., Tangent, OR) filled with 50:50 Mix with half of MSU Mix and half Sunshine Mix #1 by volume. Seedlings were grown in the MSU Plant Growth Center (MSU-PGC) greenhouse with 22/14 &#xB0;C day/night temperatures and a 16-h photoperiod. Plants were watered as needed and fertilized every other day with Peters General Purpose Plant Food (Scotts-Miracle-Gro Company, Marysville, OH).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Rust inoculation and disease assessment</title>
        <sec id="Sec8">
          <title>Leaf rust inoculation and disease assessment</title>
          <p>Leaf rust tests were conducted at MSU-PGC. Controlled greenhouse inoculations were performed on seedlings and adult plants. Each inoculation was conducted using race PBJL of <italic>P. triticina</italic>. The inoculum consisted of urediniospores suspended in Soltrol 170 Isoparaffin (Chempoint, Bellevue, WA). The spore inoculum density was calculated at 227,500 spores/ml using a Brightline hemocytometer as per the manufacturer&#x2019;s recommendations (Hausser Scientific, Horsham, PA). The inoculum was applied at a rate of 0.05&#xA0;mg spores/10&#xA0;&#x3BC;l Soltrol/plant using a Badger 350-3 airbrush gun (Badger Air-Brush Co., Franklin Park, IL). Spore germination rate was assessed on an inoculated microscope slide using a light microscope. Inoculated plants were immediately transferred to a Percival I-60D dew chamber (Percival Scientific Inc., Perry, IA) pre-conditioned to an air temperature of 15&#x2013;17 &#xB0;C and incubated for 24&#xA0;h. The plants were then transferred to the greenhouse bench and grown under the conditions described above. Disease responses were assessed when rust symptoms were fully expressed on Alpowa 8&#x2013;22&#xA0;dpi using the seedling 0&#x2013;4 IT scale (McIntosh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">1995</xref>; Stakman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">1962</xref>). In details, IT 0: no visible uredia; IT;: hypersensitive flecks; IT 1: small uredia with necrosis; IT 2: small- to medium-sized uredia with green islands surrounded by necrosis; IT 3: medium-sized uredia without necrosis; IT 4: large-sized uredia without necrosis. The variations within each class are indicated by the use of &#x2212; (less than average for the class) and + (more than average for the class). When variable reactions were observed, IT ranges are listed from lowest to highest.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec9">
          <title>Stripe rust inoculations and disease assessments</title>
          <p>The stripe rust nursery at the Northwestern Agricultural Research Station, Creston, MT was used for adult plant stripe rust assessments. The materials were planted in triplicated three hill plots 2&#xA0;m apart. Stripe rust was assessed at anthesis stage based on the disease severity scales described by McIntosh et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">1995</xref>).</p>
          <p>Additional stripe rust assessments were conducted under controlled greenhouse conditions in Pullman, WA. Races PST-78 and PST-127 were used separately in seedling and adult plant tests. About ten plants were used in each test. For the seedling tests, plants of Alpowa, MNR220 and AvS (used as a susceptible check) at the two-leaf stage were dust inoculated with a mixture of urediniospores and talc (Fisher, Pittsburgh, PA) in a ratio of 1:20 and incubated in a dew chamber at 10 &#xB0;C without light for 24&#xA0;h. The inoculated seedlings were grown in a growth chamber with a diurnal temperature cycle gradually changing from 4 &#xB0;C at 2:00 am to 20 &#xB0;C at 2:00&#xA0;pm with a 16-h photoperiod in each cycle. For the adult plant tests, plants at booting were inoculated, incubated in a dew chamber, and grown in a growth chamber in the same way as for the seedling tests, except with a diurnal temperature cycle gradually changing from 10 &#xB0;C at 2:00 am to 30 &#xB0;C at 2:00&#xA0;pm. Stripe rust infection types were assessed based on a 0 (immune)&#x2013;9 scale (highest susceptible) (Line and Qayoum <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1992</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec10">
          <title>Stem rust inoculation and disease assessment</title>
          <p>Stem rust assessments were conducted at both the MSU-PGC and the University of Minnesota. Tests with QFCSC and TLMKC were conducted at MSU-PGC. Inoculations were conducted in a similar manner to leaf rust with the following exceptions: the dew chamber was pre-conditioned to an air temperature of 19&#x2013;22 &#xB0;C and incubated for 24&#xA0;h, followed by incubation under high humidity and light intensity conditions for at least 3&#xA0;h before being transferred to the greenhouse. Assessments were made when Alpowa showed full susceptibility 10&#x2013;28 dpi using a modified Stakman et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">1962</xref>) 0&#x2013;4 IT scale (McIntosh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">1995</xref>).</p>
          <p>Stem rust tests with additional races including TTKSK (Ug99) and its variants were conducted at the USDA/University of Minnesota St Paul, MN, Disease Laboratory. Inoculation procedures and disease assessment were as described (Jin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>Genetic analysis</title>
        <p>For genetic analysis, homozygous mutant MNR220 (220-1) (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) at M<sub>6</sub> was crossed with Alpowa (as male parent) and Chinese Spring (as female parent). Ten F<sub>1</sub> individuals each from the two crosses were tested as resistant to PBJL and selfed to produce F<sub>2</sub> seeds with the possibility of outcrossing being prevented by the bagging of heads prior to anthesis. The 281 F<sub>2</sub> individuals used for segregation analysis were from a combination of three F<sub>1:2</sub> populations between MNR220 and Alpowa, and all 136 F<sub>2</sub> individuals between Chinese Spring and MNR220 were from one F<sub>1:2</sub> population. F<sub>2</sub> seedlings were inoculated with PBJL and ITs were assessed on a single plant at 8, 10 and 12 dpi three time points during disease development.</p>
        <p>In order to assess whether the same locus confers the resistance to leaf rust, stem rust and powdery mildew, we tested the three pathogens on each of the eight F<sub>2:3</sub> lines from MNR220/Alpowa and 98 F<sub>2:3</sub> lines from Chinese spring/MNR220 with three different sets of 20 seedlings each from the same F<sub>2:3</sub> line. If all three sets of 20 seedlings were not segregating or all three were segregating to the <italic>Pt</italic>, <italic>Pst</italic> and <italic>Bgt</italic> races, we describe the resistance to the three pathogens was co-segregating in this F<sub>2:3</sub> line.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>Genomic DNA isolation and marker analysis</title>
        <p>A cross between Chinese Spring and MNR220 was used for genetic mapping of the <italic>MNR220</italic> locus. Leaf tissues for genomic DNAs were collected from the parents and F<sub>2</sub> individual plants but genotypes of the F<sub>2</sub> plants were based on the tests of 20 seedlings from each of the F<sub>2:3</sub> lines. Genomic DNAs were isolated using the QIAGEN DNeasy Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen Sciences Inc, Germantown, MD). For bulked segregant analysis (Michelmore et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1991</xref>), two resistant and two susceptible DNA bulks were assembled using equal amounts of DNA from 5 or 10 homozygous resistant and 5 or 10 homozygous susceptible F<sub>2</sub> plants, respectively. Wheat simple sequence repeat (SSR) markers (<italic>Xgwm</italic>, <italic>Xwmc</italic>, <italic>Xbarc</italic>, <italic>Xcfa</italic>, <italic>Xcfd</italic> and <italic>Xcfp</italic> series) from 21 wheat chromosomes and some of the wheat EST-STS markers located on chromosome 2BS were used for screening polymorphisms between the two parents. Sequences of the primers of these SSR and EST-STS markers are available from GrainGenes2.0 website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wheat.pw.usda.gov">http://wheat.pw.usda.gov</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/SNP/primers/contig_primer_list.xls">http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/SNP/primers/contig_primer_list.xls</ext-link>. Then, the polymorphic markers between the parents were used to screen the resistant and susceptible bulks. The markers revealed the same polymorphic patterns between the parents and the resistant and susceptible bulks were tested in the entire population.</p>
        <p>PCR amplifications were conducted in 20&#xA0;&#x3BC;l reactions containing 20&#xA0;mM Tris&#x2013;HCl, pH 8.3, 100&#xA0;mM KCl, 3.0&#xA0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.4&#xA0;mM dNTP, 50&#xA0;ng of each primer, 100&#xA0;ng genomic DNA and 1.5&#xA0;U Taq DNA polymerase. Amplifications were performed at 94 &#xB0;C for 5&#xA0;min, followed by 40 cycles at 94 &#xB0;C for 45&#xA0;s, 50&#x2013;60 &#xB0;C (depending on specific primers) for 45&#xA0;s, and 72 &#xB0;C for 30&#xA0;s&#x2013;1&#xA0;min (depending on different primers), with a final extension at 72 &#xB0;C for 10&#xA0;min. PCR products were mixed with 3&#xA0;&#x3BC;l loading buffer (98 % formamide, 10&#xA0;mM EDTA, 0.25 % bromophenol blue, and 0.25 % xylene cyanol) and separated in 8 or 12 % non-denaturing polyacrylamide gels (39:1 acrylamide:bisacrylamide) (EMD Chemicals Inc, Gibbstown, NJ) and stained by GelRed (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec13">
        <title>Data analysis and genetic mapping</title>
        <p>Chi-squared test (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>) was used to evaluate deviations of observed data from theoretically expected segregation ratios. Linkages between molecular markers and the resistance gene were determined using Mapmaker 3.0b (Lincoln et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1992</xref>) with an LOD score of 3.0 as the threshold. The genetic map was drawn with the software Mapdraw V2.1 (Liu and Meng <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2003</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec14">
        <title>Transcript abundance analysis by RT-qPCR</title>
        <p>In order to assess the transcript abundances of seven <italic>PR</italic> genes, relative quantitative reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR) and gene-specific primers from Desmond et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2008</xref>), designed based on wheat sequences, were used. Inoculation with Soltrol 170 was used as mock control. Leaf tissues were collected at 0, 0.5, 1, 1.5 and 5.5 dpi with PBJL and stored at &#x2212;80 &#xB0;C until RNA isolation. Total RNA was isolated and treated with DNase I on column using the Qiagen RNeasy Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA) as per the manufacturer&#x2019;s suggestions. The quality and concentration of total RNA were assessed via agarose gels and 260/280<sub>ABS</sub> measurements on a NanoDrop 1000 spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Wilmington, DE). To exclude contamination with genomic DNA (gDNA) each RNA sample was used as template in a reverse transcriptase-free PCR reaction using the Actin (ACT) control primers specific to wheat as per the manufacturer&#x2019;s protocol. The same volume and concentration of the normalized RNA was used as template in each reaction as normalized ACT transcript abundance using iScript One-Step RT-PCR Kit with SYBR Green (Bio-Rad, Herculeqs, CA) as per the manufacturer&#x2019;s recommended protocol. Transcript abundance was quantified via real time PCR on a CFX96 real time PCR detection system (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA) using the iScript One-Step RT-PCR Kit with SYBR Green (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA) and gene-specific primers. Each reaction was conducted in triplicate of the two biological replicates and data were used only if the standard deviation between replicates was &#x2264;0.3 <italic>C</italic><sub>t</sub>. The ACT gene-specific primers are ACT forward.</p>
        <p>5&#x2032;AAATCTGGCATCACACTTTCTAC3&#x2032; and ACT reverse 5&#x2032;GTCTCAAACATATCTGGGTCATC3&#x2032;, amplified a 127-bp product of the coding sequence of the gene. All <italic>PR</italic> gene primer sets were based on Desmond et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2008</xref>. Transcript abundance was calculated with the threshold cycle (<italic>C</italic><sub>t</sub>) using the &#x394;&#x394;<italic>C</italic><sub>t</sub> method as described in the CFX96 manual (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA), where fold change&#xA0;=&#xA0;2&#xA0;&#x2212;&#xA0;&#x394;&#x394;<italic>C</italic><sub>t</sub> and percent transcript abundance&#xA0;=&#xA0;fold change&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;100. The transcript abundances for each group were calculated as the average plus or minus the average difference between the average and the highest and lowest values in that group. All statistical analyses were conducted using Microsoft Excel (Microsoft Corp., Redmond, WA).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec15" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec16">
        <title>Creation and identification of a new resistance gene</title>
        <p>The EMS-mutagenized population used in this study (Feiz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2009</xref>) was created using the soft white spring wheat cultivar Alpowa. Initial rust screening was done at the M<sub>4</sub> generation (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In detail, approximately 10 seedlings from each of 650 M<sub>4</sub> families were inoculated with <italic>Pt</italic> race PBJL. Response to the pathogen was assessed 8&#xA0;days post-inoculation (dpi) and described as infection type (IT) on a 0 (immune) to 4 (susceptible) scale (McIntosh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">1995</xref>). From the ~6,500 individual plants tested, 11 individual plants from different M<sub>4</sub> families were selected based on their enhanced resistance compared to wild-type Alpowa. The selected plants showed moderate resistance characterized by small pustules surrounded by necrosis with IT 22<sup>+</sup> and were rated as resistant. Alpowa had medium-sized pustules without necrosis and was rated as susceptible with IT 3. The resistance of each of the four selected plants was confirmed by M<sub>4:5</sub> progeny tests using the same <italic>Pt</italic> race on 20 M<sub>5</sub> seedlings. Here, we focus on one mutant line selected from 10 seedlings of a single M<sub>4</sub> family labeled as #220 in the mutagenized Alpowa population of Feiz et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2009</xref>). The single plant was selfed at the M<sub>4</sub> generation and the 20 M<sub>4:5</sub> seedlings were tested with PBJL, showing a segregation ratio of 17 resistant to 3 susceptible. Among the 20 seedlings, six resistant individuals labeled as 220-1 to 6 with IT 1-2 were selfed. Twenty seedlings from each of the M<sub>5:6</sub> were tested with PBJL, four M<sub>5:6</sub> lines (220-1, 220-2, 220-3, 220-4) showed non-segregating resistance with IT;1 on all 20 seedlings, indicating they were homozygous for PBJL resistance (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Hereafter, we designate the homozygous resistant plants derived from the #220-1 as mutant MNR220 (<italic>M</italic>utagenesis-derived <italic>N</italic>ew <italic>R</italic>esistance) and the mutated allele as <italic>MNR220</italic>.</p>
        <p>In addition to leaf rust tests, different seedlings of 220-1 M<sub>5:6</sub> line were tested with 13 <italic>Pgt</italic> races representing diverse virulence combinations, including races in the Ug99 lineage (Jin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2009</xref>). At the seedling stage, Alpowa and MNR220 showed similar ITs to RCRSC (IT 2<sup>&#x2212;</sup>), RKQQC (IT;1<sup>+</sup>), and QCCSM (IT 22<sup>+</sup>) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), suggesting that Alpowa was resistant to these three races. MNR220 showed moderately lower ITs to TRTTF (IT 12) and MCCFC (IT;1) compared to Alpowa, suggesting the mutant has enhanced resistance to these two races (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Alpowa exhibited ITs 34 to TLMKC, QFCSC, TPMKC, TTKSK, TTKST, and TTTSK, whereas MNR220 had distinctly low ITs;1<sup>+</sup> to these races.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Infection types (IT) of MNR220, Alpowa and McNair 701 challenged with races of <italic>Puccinia tritici</italic> (<italic>Pt</italic>), <italic>P. striiformis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic> (<italic>Pst</italic>), and <italic>P. graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic> (<italic>Pgt</italic>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Pathogen</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Race<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Growth stage</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Infection type<sup>a</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left">Alpowa</th><th align="left">MNR220</th><th align="left">McNair 701</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Pt</italic></td><td align="left">PBJL</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">3<sup>+</sup>4</td><td align="left">;2</td><td align="left">3<sup>+</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">Adult<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">S</td><td align="left">R</td><td align="left">S</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">SBDGD</td><td align="left">Adult<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">S</td><td align="left">I</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">BBBDD</td><td align="left">Adult<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">S</td><td align="left">I</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Pst</italic></td><td align="left">PST-78</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">PST-127</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">PST-127</td><td align="left">Adult<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">PST-127, PST-139</td><td align="left">Adult<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">S</td><td align="left">R</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Pgt</italic></td><td align="left">TLMKC</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">3<sup>&#x2212;</sup>4</td><td align="left">;1<sup>+</sup></td><td align="left">3<sup>+</sup>4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">QFCSC</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">34</td><td align="left">;1<sup>+</sup></td><td align="left">3<sup>+</sup>4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">TTKSK</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">3<sup>-</sup>3<sup>+</sup></td><td align="left">;</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">TTKST</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">3<sup>+</sup></td><td align="left">;1<sup>+</sup></td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">TTTSK</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">3<sup>+</sup></td><td align="left">;</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">TRTTF</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">22<sup>+</sup></td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">2<sup>+</sup>3<sup>&#x2212;</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">QTHJC</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">3<sup>+</sup></td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">MCCFC</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">;2</td><td align="left">;1</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">RCRSC</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">2<sup>&#x2212;</sup></td><td align="left">2<sup>&#x2212;</sup></td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">RKQQC</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">;1<sup>+</sup></td><td align="left">;</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">TPMKC</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">;</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">TTTTF</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">3<sup>+</sup></td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">QCCSM</td><td align="left">Seedling<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">2<sup>+</sup></td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Infection types indicated as per 0 (immune)&#x2013;4 (susceptible) scale was used for <italic>Pt</italic> and per 0 (immune)&#x2013;9 (susceptible) scale for <italic>Pst</italic> as described in McIntosh et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">1995</xref>). <italic>0</italic> no visible uredia,; hypersensitive flecks, <italic>1</italic> small uredia with necrosis, <italic>2</italic> small- to medium-sized uredia with green islands and surrounded by necrosis, <italic>3</italic> medium-sized uredia without necrosis, <italic>4</italic> large-sized uredia without necrosis. The variations in each class are indicated by the use of &#x2212; (less than average for the class) and + (more than average for the class). When variable reactions were observed IT ranges are listed from lowest to highest</p><p><sup>b</sup><italic>Pt</italic> race designation as per accepted nomenclature. The <italic>Pst</italic> races designations as per accepted nomenclature. <italic>Pgt</italic> race designation as per accepted nomenclature</p><p><sup>c</sup>Assessment of disease produced from controlled pathogen inoculations conducted in the MSU-PGC</p><p><sup>d</sup>Assessment of disease produced from exposure to native pathogen populations in the field at Creston, MT</p><p><sup>e</sup>Assessment of disease produced from controlled inoculations conducted in the greenhouse at Pullman, WA</p><p><sup>f</sup>Assessment of disease produced from controlled pathogen inoculations conducted in the contained laboratory at St Paul, MN; <italic>Pgt</italic> race Ug99 is the newly identified race and current focus of stem rust resistance breeding, therefore, the five-letter race identifications of Ug99 (TTKSK) and its derivatives are highlighted in gray</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>MNR220 was also tested with two <italic>Pst</italic> races at the seedling and one <italic>Pst</italic> race at the adult plant stages. At the seedling stage, MNR220 and Alpowa showed similar susceptible ITs to <italic>Pst</italic> races PST-78 (IT 7 and 8) and PST-127 (IT 8) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Additionally, at the adult plant stage, MNR220 and Alpowa showed similar resistant ITs 2 to PST-127 (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p>
        <p>The M<sub>6</sub> generation of MNR220 and Alpowa was planted at one field location in Creston, Montana in 2010 with three replications (3 hill plots/replication) for disease assessments at the adult plant stage to local <italic>Pt</italic> and <italic>Pst</italic> populations. The predominant <italic>Pt</italic> races were SBDGD and BBBDD and the <italic>Pst</italic> races were PST-127 and PST-139 (Wang and Chen, unpublished data). MNR220 showed an immune response to leaf rust and a resistance response to stripe rust, whereas Alpowa was susceptible to both diseases in the field (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec17">
        <title>Characteristics of the defense responses of MNR220 at the seedling and the adult plant stages</title>
        <p>The response of MNR220 to <italic>Pt</italic> race PBJL was dosage dependent and developmentally specific. At the seedling stage, both Alpowa and MNR220 showed necrosis at infection sites 3&#x2013;4&#xA0;dpi, but by 6&#xA0;dpi the rust on Alpowa was sporulating, whereas MNR220 had only necrosis flecks (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). The seedling low infection type normally can last until 18 dpi (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). The delayed sporulation observed on MNR220 at seedling stage became insignificant after 18 dpi when the infection types on MNR220 were the same as on Alpowa (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). However, when tested at the adult plant stage, infection and disease development on Alpowa mirrored seedling stage inoculations, whereas MNR220 showed only HR-like flecks from 6&#xA0;dpi until leaf senescence (around 35 dpi, data not shown). Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b only shows the infection types up to 24 dpi.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Leaf rust disease development at three time points post-inoculation with <italic>P. triticina</italic> race PBJL. <bold>a</bold> Infection types at the seedling stage. <bold>b</bold> Infection types at the adult plant stage</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="122_2012_1841_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
        <p>In order to evaluate the response spectra to another fungal pathogen, MNR220 was inoculated with a mixture of <italic>Bgt</italic> (unknown race identification) collected from the Plant Growth Center at Montana State University. The mutant&#x2019;s response to powdery mildew was similar to that observed in response to leaf rust, with the characteristics of delayed disease symptoms at the seedling stage. The first post-inoculation time point when the wild type and MNR220 had visually observable difference to <italic>Bgt</italic> was 12 dpi when Alpowa showed patches of mycelium and conidia on the leaf surface and MNR220 had almost none (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a); and the difference between wild type and the mutant was insignificant at 18 dpi. When inoculated with <italic>Bgt</italic> post-tiller development, MNR220 remained highly resistant until leaf senescence around 35 dpi, whereas Alpowa was fully susceptible (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Powdery mildew disease development at three time points post-inoculation with <italic>B. graminis</italic>. <bold>a</bold> Infection types at the seedling stage. <bold>b.</bold> Infection types at the adult plant stage</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="122_2012_1841_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec18">
        <title>Morphology of MNR220</title>
        <p>After crossing 220-1 with Alpowa and followed by four generations of backcrossing with Alpowa and selfing, lines that carried the resistance conferred by <italic>MNR220</italic> had few phenotypic differences from wild-type Alpowa. Under greenhouse conditions, the advanced MNR220 lines had similar tiller numbers, maturity date, and seed morphologies as Alpowa, but leaf senescence starting from the lower leaves 5~6&#xA0;days before heading was earlier than Alpowa (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Additionally, traits such as plant height, spike morphology, and tip sterility segregated in backcrossed and selfed MNR220 progenies. Importantly, none of the morphological differences between the mutant and the wild-type co-segregated with resistance to PBJL.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Adult plant phenotype. <bold>a</bold>. Alpowa and <bold>b.</bold> MNR220</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="122_2012_1841_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec19">
        <title>Genetic analysis and mapping of disease resistance locus in MNR220</title>
        <p>Crosses of M<sub>6</sub> MNR220 with spring wheat cultivars Alpowa (as male parent) and Chinese Spring (CItr 14108) (as female parent) were used for genetic analysis. Ten F<sub>1</sub> individuals each from the two crosses were tested as resistant to <italic>Pt</italic>-PBJL, indicating dominance of the mutant allele. Interestingly, F<sub>1</sub> individuals from the cross of Chinese Spring/MNR220 were more resistant (IT 1) to PBJL than those of cross MNR220/Alpowa (IT 2<sup>&#x2212;</sup>2). In addition, there were observable differences in the speed of leaf rust disease development between lines heterozygous and homozygous for the <italic>MNR220</italic> allele. On <italic>MNR220</italic> homozygous lines, small- to medium-sized uredinia developed at the infection sites by 16 dpi whereas on <italic>MNR220</italic> heterozygous lines, uredinia developed as early as 8 dpi. The segregation ratios of resistance to PBJL in the F<sub>2</sub> populations derived from the two crosses were consistent with expected segregation at a single dominant locus (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In addition, eight selected homozygous F<sub>2:3</sub> lines of MNR220/Alpowa (four resistant and four susceptible lines to <italic>Pt</italic> race PBJL) and 98 F<sub>2:3</sub> lines of Chinese Spring/MNR220 were also tested with <italic>Pt</italic> race PBJL, <italic>Pgt</italic> race TLMKC and a mixture of unknown races of <italic>Bgt</italic> (20 seedlings/line/race). Resistance to <italic>Pt, Pgt,</italic> and <italic>Bgt</italic> was perfectly co-segregated among the 8&#xA0;+&#xA0;98 lines.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Segregation analysis of seedling leaf rust resistance in the MNR220/Alpowa BC<sub>1</sub>F<sub>2</sub> and Chinese Spring/MNR220 F<sub>2</sub> populations</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Cross</th><th align="left" colspan="2">F<sub>2</sub> individuals<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Expected ratio<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="2">&#x3C7;<sup>2c</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic><sup>d</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left">Resistant</th><th align="left">Susceptible</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">MNR220/Alpowa</td><td align="left">210</td><td align="left">71</td><td align="left">3:1</td><td align="left">0.01</td><td align="left">0.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chinese Spring/MNR220</td><td align="left">100</td><td align="left">36</td><td align="left">3:1</td><td align="left">0.16</td><td align="left">0.69</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Number of individuals in F<sub>2</sub> populations assessed as resistant or susceptible to <italic>Pt</italic> race. PBJL based on 0 (immune)&#x2013;4 (susceptible) infection type scale</p><p><sup>b</sup>Expected Mendelian single gene segregation ratio (R:S)</p><p><sup>c</sup>Calculated Chi-square (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>)</p><p><sup>d</sup>The likelihood that the observed segregation ratio does not fit a 3:1 ratio. There was no segregation for leaf rust resistance observed in &gt;100 seedlings of each selfed Alpowa, or Chinese Spring</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Genetic mapping of the <italic>MNR220</italic> locus was based on the genomic DNAs from 95 individual F<sub>2</sub> plants and the genotypes of the corresponding F<sub>2:3</sub> lines from a cross between Chinese Spring/MNR220. Randomly selected 358 SSR markers that cover 21 chromosomes of hexaploid wheat were used to initially screen polymorphisms between Chinese spring and MNR220. Among them, 109 markers were polymorphic between the two parents. Only two markers (<italic>Xbarc55</italic> and <italic>Xwmc154</italic>) were polymorphic between the parents and the resistant and susceptible bulks. These markers are located on the short arm of chromosome 2B. Since then, 62 more SSR markers located on 2BS were screened, two more (<italic>Xgwm429</italic> and <italic>Xbarc183</italic>) revealed the same polymorphic patterns between the parents and the bulks. These four polymorphic markers were tested in the entire population. The <italic>MNR220</italic> locus was placed between <italic>Xgwm429</italic> and <italic>Xbarc183</italic>. Based on the physical location of these two SSR markers, the <italic>MNR220</italic> locus was narrowed down to a single deletion bin 2BS-0.53&#x2013;0.75 on chromosome 2B (Somyong et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2011</xref>). Therefore, 12 wheat EST-STS markers from that interval were used to screen polymorphism between the parents and the bulks. <italic>XBE497494</italic>-<italic>STS</italic> (developed from wheat EST BE497494) was the only marker that revealed polymorphism between the two parents and the bulks. Among the 5 polymorphic markers, 3 (<italic>Xbarc55</italic>, <italic>Xwmc154</italic>, and <italic>Xgwm429</italic>) were co-dominant, and 2 (<italic>Xbarc183</italic> and <italic>XBE497494</italic>-<italic>STS</italic>) were dominant. A linkage map including all five polymorphic markers and the <italic>MNR220</italic> locus was constructed and shown in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. The <italic>MNR220</italic> locus is flanked by the SSR marker <italic>Xbarc183</italic> and the STS marker <italic>XBE497494</italic>-<italic>STS</italic>. Marker <italic>Xbarc183</italic> is 12.6&#xA0;cM proximal to the <italic>MNR220</italic> locus, and <italic>XBE497494</italic>-<italic>STS</italic> is 9.3&#xA0;cM distal to the locus.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>Genetic map of the <italic>MNR220</italic> locus constructed with the DNAs from 95 individual F<sub>2</sub> plants and the genotypes from the corresponding F<sub>2:3</sub> lines from a cross between Chinese Spring and MNR220</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="122_2012_1841_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec20">
        <title>Expression profiling of pathogenesis-related (<italic>PR</italic>) genes</title>
        <p>In order to understand how the mutation in MNR220 altered the defense response regulation, we assessed the expression profiles of seven <italic>PR</italic> genes in near isogenic lines (NILs) with either homozygous <italic>MNR220</italic> or <italic>mnr220</italic> alleles derived from one selected heterozygous M<sub>7</sub> plant after eight generations of selfing and PBJL testing (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, for details, see &#x201C;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>&#x201D;). The seven <italic>PR</italic> genes were chosen based on their involvement in defense responses to fungal pathogens in wheat (Desmond et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2008</xref>) and the primers were designed based on wheat sequence and are able to amplify all three orthologous copies of each <italic>PR</italic> gene in hexaploid wheat genome (data not shown). The transcript abundances were measured using quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR). To estimate the basal expression levels of the <italic>PR</italic> genes in the NILs, we measured the gene transcript abundances in leaf tissues collected immediately after PBJL inoculation (0 time point) in both two leaf stage seedlings and adult plant flag leaves. The RT-qPCR results revealed similar patterns of transcript abundances for four of the seven selected <italic>PR</italic> genes at the seedling (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a) and the adult plant (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b) stages. These four <italic>PR</italic> genes (<italic>PR1,</italic><italic>PR2</italic>, <italic>PR3</italic>, and <italic>PR9</italic>) showed higher levels of transcript abundances in resistant <italic>MNR220</italic> than in susceptible <italic>mnr220</italic> NIL at both the seedling and adult plant stages. The differences between the <italic>MNR220</italic> and <italic>mnr220</italic> were more significant at the seedling stage than those at the adult plant stage for <italic>PR1</italic>, <italic>PR2</italic> and <italic>PR3</italic> and less significant for <italic>PR9</italic> at both stages (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a, b). Transcript abundances of <italic>PR5</italic> in adult plants were approximately fivefold higher in the <italic>MNR220</italic> NIL compared to <italic>mnr220</italic>. Similar transcript abundances of <italic>PR4</italic> were detected between the NILs at adult stage, but were approximately twofold higher in the <italic>MNR220</italic> NIL than <italic>mnr220</italic> at the seedling stage. In contrast, transcript abundances of <italic>PR10</italic> were higher in the <italic>MNR220</italic> NIL at the seedling stage, but lower in <italic>mnr220</italic> at the adult plant stage (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a, b).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#xA0;6</label><caption><p><italic>PR</italic> gene transcript abundance profiles. <bold>a</bold> RT-qPCR <italic>PR</italic> transcript abundance at seedling stage at 0 time point of PBJL inoculation. <bold>b.</bold> RT-qPCR <italic>PR</italic> gene transcript abundance at adult plant stage in the absence of pathogens. Transcript abundance, <italic>y</italic>-axis, given as percent abundance normalized to <italic>mnr220</italic>. <italic>Error bars</italic> represent standard deviation between biological replicates. Mean percent transcript abundance calculated using the &#x2206;&#x2206;<italic>C</italic><sub>t</sub> method between biological replicates&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;standard deviation. Unpaired two-tailed students <italic>t</italic> test between mean of mnr220 and MNR220 and statistical significance indicated as *0.025&#xA0;&#x2264;&#xA0;<italic>p</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.05, **0.01&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;<italic>p</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.025, ***<italic>p</italic>&#xA0;&#x2264;&#xA0;0.01</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="122_2012_1841_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
        <p>In order to analyze pathogen-induced changes in the seven <italic>PR</italic> gene expression levels during disease development, we measured transcript abundances at five time points post pathogen inoculation. The measurements were taken from leaves collected from bulks of five plants at 0, 0.5, 1, 1.5 and 5.5 dpi and averaged over two independent biological replications. Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> shows the differences between <italic>MNR220</italic> and <italic>mnr220</italic> at the levels of transcript abundances of the seven <italic>PR</italic> genes<italic>.</italic> The basal expressions of all seven <italic>PR</italic> genes in the <italic>MNR220</italic> NIL were a little higher than those in <italic>mnr220</italic> which was normalized as 100 and indicated by a horizontal dash line. The transcript abundances of all seven <italic>PR</italic> genes peaked at 0.5 dpi (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>), suggesting the largest difference between the NILs was at 0.5 dpi. The differences between the NILs were insignificant at 1.0 dpi (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>), suggesting the transcript abundances of the <italic>PR</italic> genes in the <italic>mnr220</italic> NIL have increased to similar levels as in the MNR220 NIL, but were 12&#xA0;h delayed (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). At 1.5 dpi, the relative expressions of <italic>PR</italic> genes were all below the dash line, indicating the transcript abundances of the <italic>PR</italic> genes in the <italic>MNR220</italic> NIL were lower than those in the <italic>mnr220</italic> NIL. At 5.5 dpi, the relative expressions of <italic>PR</italic> genes were all close to the dash line, indicating the transcript abundances of the <italic>PR</italic> genes in the <italic>MNR220</italic> NIL were similar to those in the <italic>mnr220</italic> NIL. This preliminary gene expression analysis indicates that these <italic>PR</italic> genes in the <italic>MNR220</italic> NIL were activated and responded to the pathogen earlier after infection than in the <italic>mnr220</italic> NIL.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#xA0;7</label><caption><p><italic>PR</italic> gene transcript abundance profiles during leaf rust disease development. RT-qPCR <italic>PR</italic> gene transcript abundance in response to PBJL at seedling stage. Transcript abundances in <italic>MNR220</italic> were normalized to <italic>mnr220</italic> at corresponding time point. <italic>Error bars</italic> represent standard deviation between biological replicates</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="122_2012_1841_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec21" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="Sec22">
        <title>A new seedling slow-rusting allele created in MNR220</title>
        <p>Rust resistance genes have two modes of action determined by pathogen interaction and are either race specific or race non-specific. Characteristics of race non-specific resistance include the &#x201C;slow-rusting&#x201D; resistance features, longer latent period, and decreased uredinial size and number (Dyck <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1987</xref>; German and Kolmer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1992</xref>; Singh and Gupta <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">1992</xref>; Singh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">1998</xref>). There are known slow-rusting stem (<italic>Sr2</italic>), leaf (<italic>Lr34</italic>, <italic>Lr46</italic>, and <italic>Lr67</italic>), and stripe (<italic>Yr18</italic>) rust resistance genes. <italic>Sr2</italic> is associated with a dark pigmentation trait, called pseudo-black chaff (PBC), expression of which is modified by both biotic and abiotic stresses (Kota et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2006</xref>). Durable resistance has been achieved in cultivars with <italic>Sr2</italic> and is enhanced by minor genes (Dyck <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1987</xref>). The resistance conferred by <italic>Lr34</italic> has been well studied (Dyck et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">1994</xref>; Singh and Rajaram <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">1992</xref>; Singh and Gupta <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">1992</xref>). The <italic>Lr34</italic> gene encodes a putative ABC transporter and confers non-hypersensitive resistance to multiple fungal pathogens in wheat (Krattinger et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2009</xref>). <italic>Lr34</italic> is characterized as an adult plant resistance gene because of the compatible interaction with the pathogen at the seedling stage although seedling resistance of <italic>Lr34</italic> can be induced by low temperature (Pretorius et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">1993</xref>).</p>
        <p>Alpowa is a soft, white, semi-dwarf, spring wheat cultivar released by Washington AES/USDA-ARS in 1994. Since its release, Alpowa was reported to carry the rust resistance genes <italic>Lr3a</italic>, <italic>Yr39</italic>, and <italic>YrAlp</italic> but carries neither <italic>Lr34</italic> nor <italic>Sr2</italic>. <italic>Lr3a</italic> does not confer resistance to the primary race <italic>Pt</italic> PBJL utilized in this study. The stripe rust resistance gene <italic>Yr39</italic> confers high-temperature adult plant (HTAP) and <italic>YrAlp</italic> confers all-stage resistance to a few old US <italic>Pst</italic> races (Lin and Chen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2007</xref>).</p>
        <p>The resistance conferred by <italic>MNR220</italic> has the characteristics of a slow-rusting resistance gene to leaf rust race PBJL at the seedling stage with a 10-day latency period increase, but complete resistance at the adult plant stage to leaf and stripe rusts and powdery mildew. MNR220 showed an early HR-like response to leaf rust and powdery mildew at the seedling and the adult plant stages, but the seedling resistance was compromised after 18 dpi, whereas the adult plant resistance remained effective. These developmental stage-dependent responses were further described in the gene expression profiles of seven <italic>PR</italic> genes at both the seedling and adult plant stages. The profiles revealed elevated expression of four <italic>PR</italic> genes in the absence of infection and a 12&#xA0;h earlier increase of all seven <italic>PR</italic> genes after pathogen attack in <italic>MNR220</italic> compared to <italic>mnr220</italic>. These results suggest that the mutation changes the regulation of the defense response leading to higher basal defense to certain fungal pathogens, but this basal defense response was eventually overcome by the pathogens at the seedling stage. Two <italic>PR</italic> genes showed different expression profiles between the NILs of <italic>MNR220</italic> and <italic>mnr220</italic> at the adult plant stage. Basal transcript abundance of <italic>PR5</italic> was fivefold higher in MNR220 at the adult plant stage. The <italic>PR5</italic> gene family encodes proteins with homology to thaumatin, osmotin and NP24 which are known to rapidly accumulate to high levels in response to biotic or abiotic stress (Velazhahan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">1999</xref>). This group of proteins has antifungal activity either by causing fungal membrane lysis at high concentrations or cell membrane leakage at low concentrations (Velazhahan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">1999</xref>). Transgenic tobacco, potato, and rice over-expressing <italic>PR5</italic> showed higher resistance to several fungal pathogens (Velazhahan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">1999</xref>). It is unclear whether the elevated level of <italic>PR5</italic> alone was sufficient to make the adult plant resistance complete.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec23">
        <title>Disease resistance in MNR220 is associated with changes in negative regulation</title>
        <p>Genetic and gene expression analysis revealed that MNR220 activates expression of five <italic>PR</italic> genes that were suppressed in MNR220 in the absence of pathogens. Suppression of <italic>PR</italic> gene expression is a negative regulation, which is thought to be an important mechanism to avoid inappropriate defense responses that are metabolically expensive, and may result in yield penalties to the plants (Brown <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2002</xref>).</p>
        <p>There are three possible mutational events that can change the negative regulation. The first possibility is a loss-of-function event where the mutation disrupts a wild-type negative regulator of resistance. A number of negative regulators of cell death have been identified by the occurrence of spontaneous necrotic lesions in mutants with inactivated regulators (Dangl and Jones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2001</xref>). These &#x201C;lesion mimic&#x201D; mutants often display increased resistance to pathogens but their mode of action remains unclear as in the <italic>acd1</italic>, <italic>lsd1</italic> and <italic>svn1</italic> mutations described in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (Lorrain et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2003</xref>; for review see Dangl and Jones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2001</xref>; McDowell and Dangl <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2003</xref>). The mutant MNR220 does not show lesion mimic, but starts leaf senescence earlier than wild-type Alpowa. However, this process is different from the flag leaf tip necrosis associated with the <italic>Lr34</italic> gene (Krattinger et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2009</xref>), the mutant leaves turn yellow similar to the aging process starting from the oldest leaves, while the flag leaves still maintain green. Alternatively, the mutation could disrupt a pathogen-required host factor. These host factors are negative regulators of disease resistance that are necessary for pathogen invasion. The <italic>Mlo</italic> gene family is an example of a host factor required by <italic>Bgt</italic> for invasion. <italic>Mlo</italic> genes encode heptahelical plasma membrane-localized proteins of unknown function (B&#xFC;schges et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1997</xref>; Panstruga <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2005</xref>).</p>
        <p>The second possibility is a gain-of-function event where the mutation creates a new functional resistance allele. This new resistance allele could activate the <italic>R</italic>-gene mediated defense response pathways. Several resistance gain-of-function mutations have been reported including the semidominant mutation <italic>ssi4</italic> (Shirano et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2002</xref>) and the dominant mutation <italic>snc1</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2003</xref>). The gain-of-function mutations in <italic>snc1</italic> and <italic>ssi4</italic> are the result of a constitutive activated R protein induction of defense response.</p>
        <p>The third possibility is a loss-of-function event where the mutation disrupts an <italic>R</italic>-gene suppressor. There are several reports of suppressors of rust resistance in wheat (Assefa and Fehrmann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2000</xref>; Kerber and Green <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1980</xref>; Knott <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2000</xref>; Nelson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1997</xref>) where the suppressor suppresses positive regulators of the defense response pathway. These suppressors have been shown to repress the effects of <italic>R</italic> genes located on the A or B genomes of bread wheat (Kerber and Green <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1980</xref>).</p>
        <p>It is unclear, without molecular cloning, whether the <italic>MNR220</italic> allele is a gain-of-function or a loss-of-function allele. With multiple highly conserved orthologous copies of each <italic>PR</italic> gene in hexaploid wheat, it is unknown which orthologs of each <italic>PR</italic> gene transcript abundance was altered by the mutation. However, compared to the <italic>mnr220</italic> NIL, the enhanced transcript levels of the <italic>PR</italic> genes in the mutant suggest the disease resistance in MNR220 is associated with changes in negative regulation in the defense pathways.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec24">
        <title>Resistance to multiple fungal pathogens is likely associated with a single locus in MNR220</title>
        <p>The mutation rate in the EMS-mutagenized population used in this study was estimated to be 1 in 11.5&#xA0;kb of DNA (Feiz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2009</xref>) which suggests that many mutations occurred in each individual. Several traits mostly from different mutations including plant height, spike morphology, and tip sterility, segregated in the selfed progeny of MNR220 but none co-segregated with disease resistance. Resistance to leaf rust, stem rust and powdery mildew co-segregated in total 106 F<sub>2:3</sub> lines derived from two crosses. It is therefore probable that resistance to multiple fungal pathogens in MNR220 is conferred by a single locus. Single gene multi-pathogen resistance is consistent with evidence suggesting limited sets of defense-related molecules in each host are used to defend against highly diverse pathogens (Dangl and Jones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2001</xref>), although more genes are likely to be involved in either enhancing or reducing the levels of defense response evidenced by our observation that F<sub>1</sub> individuals from the cross of Chinese Spring/MNR220 were more resistant to PBJL than those of cross of MNR220/Alpowa. This also supports the findings that even evolutionarily diverse pathogens target similar host defense immunity machinery (Mukhtar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2011</xref>). In addition to our report here, one other mutant plant conferring resistance to multiple rust pathogens has been reported in wheat (Boyd et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2006</xref>). Only large scale progeny testing and molecular cloning of the gene(s) will reveal the true basis of the MNR220 mutation. Molecular analysis of the disease resistance locus in MNR220 may lead to a better understanding of the regulation of defense response networks in wheat.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Dr. Luther Talbert and the Spring Wheat Breeding Lab at Montana State University for help with the field test at NWARC in Creston, MT and SSR primers used for genetic mapping, Dr. James Kolmer of the Cereal Disease Laboratory, St. Paul, MN 55108, USA for race identification of leaf rust collected in Creston, Montana 2010 and Dr. Robert McIntosh of the Plant Breeding Institute, Cobbitty, NSW2570, Australia for editing the manuscript. This research was supported by the Montana Wheat and Barley Committee and the BREAD program (grant IOS-0965429).</p>
      <sec id="d29e2430">
        <title>Open Access</title>
        <p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits any use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited.</p>
      </sec>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Arumuganathan</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Earle</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nuclear DNA content of some important plant species</article-title>
          <source>Plant Mol Bio Rep</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>208</fpage>
          <lpage>218</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02672069</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Assefa</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fehrmann</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Resistance to wheat leaf rust in <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> Coss. and inheritance of resistance in hexaploid wheat</article-title>
          <source>Genet Res Crop Evol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>140</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1008770226330</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Board WWAO (2010) In Economic Research Service, Foreign Agricultural Service, USDA, ed</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bouarab</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Melton</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peart</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baulcombe</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Osbourn</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A saponin-detoxifying enzyme mediates suppression of plant defences</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>418</volume>
          <fpage>889</fpage>
          <lpage>892</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature00950</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12192413</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boyd</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hart</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutants in wheat showing multipathogen resistance to biotrophic fungal pathogens</article-title>
          <source>Plant Pathol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>475</fpage>
          <lpage>484</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3059.2006.01402.x</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>JKM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Yield penalties of disease resistance in crops</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>339</fpage>
          <lpage>344</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5266(02)00270-4</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12179968</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>B&#xFC;schges</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hollricher</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Panstruga</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simons</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolter</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frijters</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daelen</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Diergaarde</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Groenendijk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>T&#xF6;psch</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vos</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salamini</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schulze-Lefert</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The barley <italic>Mlo</italic> gene: a novel control element of plant pathogen resistance</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>695</fpage>
          <lpage>705</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81912-1</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9054509</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Colilla</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rocher</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mendez</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>&#x3B3;-Purothionins: amino acid sequence of two polypeptides of a new family of thionins from wheat endosperm</article-title>
          <source>Fed Eur Biochem Soc Lett</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>270</volume>
          <fpage>191</fpage>
          <lpage>194</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(90)81265-P</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dangl</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>JDG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Plant pathogens and integrated defence responses to infection</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>411</volume>
          <fpage>826</fpage>
          <lpage>833</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35081161</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11459065</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Desmond</surname>
              <given-names>OJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manners</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schenk</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maclean</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kazan</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gene expression analysis of the wheat response to infection by <italic>Fusarium pseudograminearum</italic></article-title>
          <source>Physiol Mol Plant Pathol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>40</fpage>
          <lpage>47</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmpp.2008.12.001</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dvo&#x159;&#xE1;k</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Terlizzi</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>HB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Resta</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The evolution of polyploid wheats: identification of the A genome donor species</article-title>
          <source>Genome</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>21</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g93-004</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18469969</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dyck</surname>
              <given-names>PL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The association of a gene for leaf rust resistance with the chromosome 7D suppressor of stem rust resistance in common wheat</article-title>
          <source>Genome</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>467</fpage>
          <lpage>469</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g87-081</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dyck</surname>
              <given-names>PL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kerber</surname>
              <given-names>ER</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aung</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An interchromosomal reciprocal translocation in wheat involving leaf rust resistance gene <italic>Lr34</italic></article-title>
          <source>Genome</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>556</fpage>
          <lpage>559</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g94-079</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18470099</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Feiz</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beecher</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giroux</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>In planta mutagenesis determines the functional regions of the wheat puroindoline proteins</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>183</volume>
          <fpage>853</fpage>
          <lpage>860</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.109.106013</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19752217</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Flor</surname>
              <given-names>HH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Iacobellis</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Collmer</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hutcheson</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mansfield</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morris</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murillo</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schaad</surname>
              <given-names>NW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stead</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surico</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ullrich</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The complementary genic systems in flax and flax rust</article-title>
          <source>Advances in Genetics</source>
          <year>1956</year>
          <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Kluwer Academic Academic Presss</publisher-name>
          <fpage>29</fpage>
          <lpage>54</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>German</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kolmer</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effect of gene <italic>Lr34</italic> in the enhancement of resistance to leaf rust of wheat</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>97</fpage>
          <lpage>105</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00223987</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Glazebrook</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Contrasting mechanisms of defense against biotrophic and necrotrophic pathogens</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>205</fpage>
          <lpage>227</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.phyto.43.040204.135923</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16078883</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jin</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wanyera</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kinyua</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Njau</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fetch</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pretorius</surname>
              <given-names>ZA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yahyaoui</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization of seedling infection types and adult plant infection responses of monogenic <italic>Sr</italic> gene lines to race TTKS of <italic>Puccinia graminis</italic> f. sp <italic>tritici</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Dis</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>1096</fpage>
          <lpage>1099</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS-91-9-1096</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jin</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szabo</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pretorius</surname>
              <given-names>ZA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fetch</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Detection of virulence to resistance gene <italic>Sr24</italic> within race TTKS of <italic>Puccinia graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Dis</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>923</fpage>
          <lpage>926</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS-92-6-0923</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jin</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szabo</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rouse</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fetch</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pretorius</surname>
              <given-names>ZA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wanyera</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Njau</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Detection of virulence to resistance gene <italic>Sr36</italic> within the TTKS race lineage of <italic>Puccinia graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Dis</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>367</fpage>
          <lpage>370</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS-93-4-0367</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kerber</surname>
              <given-names>ER</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Green</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Suppression of stem rust resistance in the hexaploid wheat cv. Canthatch by chromosome 7DL</article-title>
          <source>Can J Bot</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>1347</fpage>
          <lpage>1350</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/b80-166</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Knott</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Inheritance of resistance to stem rust in medea durum wheat and the role of suppressors</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>98</fpage>
          <lpage>102</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2000.40198x</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kota</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spielmeyer</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McIntosh</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lagudah</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fine genetic mapping fails to dissociate durable stem rust resistance gene <italic>Sr2</italic> from pseudo-black chaff in common wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>492</fpage>
          <lpage>499</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-005-0151-8</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16311724</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krattinger</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lagudah</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spielmeyer</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huerta-Espino</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McFadden</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bossolini</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Selter</surname>
              <given-names>LL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keller</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A putative ABC transporter confers durable resistance to multiple fungal pathogens in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>323</volume>
          <fpage>1360</fpage>
          <lpage>1363</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1166453</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19229000</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>XM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetics and molecular mapping of genes for race-specific all-stage resistance and non-race-specific high-temperature adult-plant resistance to stripe rust in spring wheat cultivar Alpowa</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <fpage>1277</fpage>
          <lpage>1287</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-007-0518-0</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17318493</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lincoln S, Daly M, Lander E (1992) Constructing genetic maps with Mapmaker/EXP3.0 Whitehead Institute Technical Report, 3rd edn. Whitehead Institute, Cambridge</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Line</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qayoum</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Virulence, aggressiveness, evolution, and distribution of races of <italic>Puccinia striiformis</italic> (the cause of stripe rust of wheat) in North America. USDA-ARS</article-title>
          <source>Tech Bull</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>1788</volume>
          <fpage>44</fpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meng</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MapDraw: a Microsoft Excel macro for drawing genetic linkage maps based on given genetic linkage data</article-title>
          <source>Hereditas (Beijing)</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>317</fpage>
          <lpage>321</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lorrain</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vailleau</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balagu&#xE9;</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roby</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lesion mimic mutants: keys for deciphering cell death and defense pathways in plants</article-title>
          <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>263</fpage>
          <lpage>271</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1360-1385(03)00108-0</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12818660</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McDowell</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dangl</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Signal transduction in the plant immune response</article-title>
          <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>79</fpage>
          <lpage>82</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0968-0004(99)01532-7</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10664588</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McFadden</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sears</surname>
              <given-names>ER</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The origin of <italic>Triticum spelta</italic> and its free-threshing hexaploid relatives</article-title>
          <source>J Hered</source>
          <year>1964</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>107</fpage>
          <lpage>116</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McIntosh</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wellings</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Wheat rusts: an atlas of rust genes</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <publisher-loc>East Melbourne</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>CSIRO Publication</publisher-name>
          <fpage>28</fpage>
          <lpage>55</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Michelmore</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paran</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kesseli</surname>
              <given-names>VR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification of markers closely linked to disease-resistance genes by bulked segregant analysis: a rapid method to detect markers in specific genomic regions by using segregating populations</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>9828</fpage>
          <lpage>9832</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.88.21.9828</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1682921</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mukhtar</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carvunis</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dreze</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Epple</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steinbrenner</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tasan</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galli</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hao</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nishimura</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pevzner</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Donovan</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghamsari</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santhanam</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Romero</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poulin</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gebreab</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gutierrez</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tam</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Monachello</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boxem</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harbort</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McDonald</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gai</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Consortium</surname>
              <given-names>EUE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vandenhaute</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roth</surname>
              <given-names>FP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hill</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ecker</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vidal</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beynon</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Braun</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dangl</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Independently evolved virulence effectors converge onto hubs in a pant immune system network</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>333</volume>
          <fpage>596</fpage>
          <lpage>601</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1203659</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21798943</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nelson</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Autrique</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sorrells</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mapping genes conferring and suppressing leaf rust resistance in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>1928</fpage>
          <lpage>1935</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1997.0011183X003700060043x</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Panstruga</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Serpentine plant MLO proteins as entry portals for powdery mildew fungi</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Soc Trans</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>389</fpage>
          <lpage>392</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BST0330389</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15787613</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pretorius</surname>
              <given-names>ZA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kloppers</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drijepondt</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of inoculum density and temperature on three components of leaf rust resistance controlled by <italic>Lr34</italic> in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <lpage>96</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00033772</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pretorius</surname>
              <given-names>ZA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wagoire</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Payne</surname>
              <given-names>TS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Detection of virulence to wheat stem rust resistance gene <italic>Sr31</italic> in <italic>Puccinia graminis</italic>. f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic> in Uganda</article-title>
          <source>Plant Dis</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS.2000.84.2.203B</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rubiales</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niks</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization of <italic>Lr34</italic>, a major gene conferring nonhypersensitive resistance to wheat leaf rust</article-title>
          <source>Plant Dis</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>1208</fpage>
          <lpage>1212</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PD-79-1208</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sarkar</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stebbins</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Morphological evidence concerning the origin of the B genome in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Am J Bot</source>
          <year>1956</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>297</fpage>
          <lpage>304</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2438947</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR44">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shirano</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kachroo</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klessig</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A gain-of-function mutation in an Arabidopsis toll interleukin1 receptor-nucleotide binding site-leucine-rich repeat type <italic>R</italic> gene triggers defense responses and results in enhanced disease resistance</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>3149</fpage>
          <lpage>3162</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.005348</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12468733</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR45">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Expression of wheat leaf rust resistance gene <italic>Lr34</italic> in seedlings and adult plants</article-title>
          <source>Plant Dis</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <fpage>489</fpage>
          <lpage>491</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PD-76-0489</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR46">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rajaram</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetics of adult-plant resistance of leaf rust in &#x2018;Frontana&#x2019; and three CIMMYT wheats</article-title>
          <source>Genome</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>24</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g92-004</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR47">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mujeeb Kazi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huerta-Espino</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Lr46</italic>: a gene conferring slow-rusting resistance to leaf rust in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>890</fpage>
          <lpage>894</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO.1998.88.9.890</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944865</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR48">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Somyong</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Munkvold</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanaka</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benscher</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sorrells</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparative genetic analysis of wheat seed dormancy QTL with rice and Brachypodium identifies candidate genes for ABA perception and calcium signaling</article-title>
          <source>Funct Integr Genomics</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>479</fpage>
          <lpage>490</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10142-011-0219-2</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21468744</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR49">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stakman EC, Stewart DM, Loegering WQ (1962) Identification of physiologic races of <italic>Puccinia graminis</italic> var. <italic>tritici</italic>. In: Agricultural Research Service, Agriculture. USDA, Washington DC</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR50">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stokstad</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Deadly wheat fungus threatens world&#x2019;s breadbaskets</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>315</volume>
          <fpage>1786</fpage>
          <lpage>1787</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.315.5820.1786</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17395806</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR51">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Velazhahan</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Datta</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muthukrishnan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Iacobellis</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Collmer</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hutcheson</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mansfield</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morris</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murillo</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schaad</surname>
              <given-names>NW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stead</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surico</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ullrich</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The PR-5 family: thaumatin-like proteins</article-title>
          <source>Pathogenesis-related proteins in plants</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Kluwer Academic CRC Presss</publisher-name>
          <fpage>303</fpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR52">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wanyera</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kinyua</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jin</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The spread of <italic>Puccinia graminis</italic> f. sp. <italic>tritici</italic> with virulence on Sr31 in Eastern Africa</article-title>
          <source>Plant Dis</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <fpage>113</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PD-90-0113A</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR53">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goritschnig</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A gain-of-function mutation in a plant disease resistance gene leads to constitutive activation of downstream signal transduction pathways <italic>in suppressor of npr1-1, constitutive 1</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>2636</fpage>
          <lpage>2646</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.015842</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14576290</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>J. Campbell and H. Zhang contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
</article>
