<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3871689</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-14312</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084691</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Agriculture</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Crops</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cereals</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Wheat</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genetics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plant Genetics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Crop Genetics</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genomics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genome Analysis Tools</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genetic Maps</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Comparative Genomics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Plant Science</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Plant Genetics</subject>
              <subject>Plant Genomics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Comparative High-Resolution Mapping of the Wax Inhibitors <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> in Hexaploid Wheat</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Comparative Mapping <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> in Wheat</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Haibin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Qin</surname>
            <given-names>Jinxia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Han</surname>
            <given-names>Jun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaojie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ouyang</surname>
            <given-names>Shuhong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>Yong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Dong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Zhenzhong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Qiuhong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xie</surname>
            <given-names>Jingzhong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cui</surname>
            <given-names>Yu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Peng</surname>
            <given-names>Huiru</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Qixin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Zhiyong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>State Key Laboratory for Agrobiotechnology / Beijing Key Laboratory of Crop Genetic Improvement / Key Laboratory of Crop Heterosis Research &amp; Utilization, Department of Plant Genetics &amp; Breeding, China Agricultural University, Beijing, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Plant Science and Technology College, Beijing University of Agriculture, Beijing, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Tianzhen</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Nanjing Agricultural University, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>qxsun@cau.edu.cn</email> (QS); <email>zhiyongliu@cau.edu.cn</email> (ZL)</corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: ZL QS HP. Performed the experiments: HW JQ JH XZ SO YL DZ ZW. Analyzed the data: HW JQ JH ZW JX. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: HW JQ JH XZ SO YL DZ ZW QW JX YC. Wrote the paper: HW JH ZL.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <elocation-id>e84691</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Wu et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The wax (glaucousness) on wheat leaves and stems is mainly controlled by two sets of genes: glaucousness loci (<italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic>) and non-glaucousness loci (<italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic>). The non-glaucousness (<italic>Iw</italic>) loci act as inhibitors of the glaucousness loci (<italic>W</italic>). High-resolution comparative genetic linkage maps of the wax inhibitors <italic>Iw1</italic> originating from <italic>Triticum dicoccoides</italic>, and <italic>Iw2</italic> from <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> were developed by comparative genomics analyses of <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, sorghum and rice genomic sequences corresponding to the syntenic regions of the <italic>Iw</italic> loci in wheat. Eleven <italic>Iw1</italic> and eight <italic>Iw2</italic> linked EST markers were developed and mapped to linkage maps on the distal regions of chromosomes 2BS and 2DS, respectively. The <italic>Iw1</italic> locus mapped within a 0.96 cM interval flanked by the BE498358 and CA499581 EST markers that are collinear with 122 kb, 202 kb, and 466 kb genomic regions in the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> 5S chromosome, the sorghum 6S chromosome and the rice 4S chromosome, respectively. The <italic>Iw2</italic> locus was located in a 4.1 to 5.4-cM interval in chromosome 2DS that is flanked by the CJ886319 and CJ519831 EST markers, and this region is collinear with a 2.3 cM region spanning the <italic>Iw1</italic> locus on chromosome 2BS. Both <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> co-segregated with the BF474014 and CJ876545 EST markers, indicating they are most likely orthologs on 2BS and 2DS. These high-resolution maps can serve as a framework for chromosome landing, physical mapping and map-based cloning of the wax inhibitors in wheat.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was financially supported by the NSFC (31030056), MOST (2011AA100104), MOE (111-2-03), and Innovation Fund for Graduate Student of China Agricultural University. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="7"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The outermost wax layer protects plants from many types of biotic and abiotic stresses, such as drought, phytophagous insects, pathogens, solar radiation, and freezing temperatures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Eigenbrode1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Jenks1">[2]</xref>. One of the most important roles of the cuticle is to limit transpiration to reduce water loss and this provides a key mechanism for plant survival in water-limited environments, such as deserts, high mountains, saline-alkali lands, and coastal ecosystems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Riederer1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Schonherr1">[4]</xref>. Worldwide, bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) is one of the most important food sources for human beings. The wheat leaf, stem and, in some cases, spike surfaces are coated with cuticular waxes that confer a glaucousness characteristic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Jensen1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Bianchi1">[6]</xref>. Physiological studies in wheat by Johnson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Johnson1">[7]</xref> and Richards et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Richards1">[8]</xref> showed that glaucousness reduces transpiration and increased water use efficiency. More recently Zhang et al. demonstrated that glaucousness reduced cuticle permeability in the terms of non-stomatal water loss and chlorophyll efflux <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Zhang1">[9]</xref>. Bread wheat cultivars with non-glaucousness traits exhibit significant yield increases with reduced solar radiation losses that enable continued photosynthesis during the grain filling period <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Simmonds1">[10]</xref>, and the trait may also provide resistance to aphids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Lowe1">[11]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Glaucousness and non-glaucousness are parallel variations in wheat and its relatives. Classical genetic studies have shown that both the glaucousness and the non-glaucousness stem and leaf phenotypes are controlled by two sets of loci; the wax production genes <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic> and the wax inhibitor genes <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic>, respectively. The <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> non-glaucousness loci function as inhibitors of the <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic> glaucousness loci, and could also inhibit other wax production genes in the wax pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Jensen1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki2">[13]</xref>. Genetic analyses have indicated that the <italic>W1</italic> wax production gene and the <italic>Iw1</italic> wax inhibition gene are located on chromosome 2BS with a genetic distance of 2 cM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki1">[12]</xref>. However, <italic>W2</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> are separated on chromosome 2DS where the <italic>W2</italic> locus is close to the centromere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki1">[12]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Driscoll1">[15]</xref>. Two loci, <italic>Iw3</italic> and <italic>Ws</italic>, were also reported conditioning wax on spikes in wheat. Non-glaucousness locus <italic>Iw3</italic> was mapped on chromosome 1BS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Dubcovsky1">[16]</xref> and the <italic>Ws</italic> gene on the short arm of chromosome 1AS is responsible for glaucous spikes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Gadaleta1">[17]</xref>. In addition to these genes, a major QTL (<italic>QW.aww-3A</italic>) that accounts for up to 52 percent of the flag leaf glaucousness variation has been detected in a doubled-haploid (DH) population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Bennett1">[18]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Molecular mapping and cloning of genes controlling epicuticular wax in wheat is of great interests for understanding interactions between none-glaucousness genes (<italic>Iw</italic>) and glaucousness genes (<italic>W</italic>), as well as their effects on yield, and biotic and abiotic stresses. The <italic>Iw1</italic> locus originating in wild emmer is closely linked to the <italic>Xcdo456</italic> RFLP marker at the end of chromosome arm 2BS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Rong1">[19]</xref>. Liu et al. found that the <italic>Iw1</italic> locus is 18.77 cM away from the powdery mildew resistance gene <italic>MlIW170</italic> on chromosome 2BS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Liu1">[20]</xref>. Simmonds et al. also reported that the <italic>Iw1</italic> (<italic>Vir</italic>) gene conditioning a non-glaucousness phenotype maps to chromosome 2BS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Simmonds1">[10]</xref>. In a tetraploid wheat background, Yoshiya et al., have found that <italic>W1</italic> is linked to <italic>Iw1<sup>Dic</sup></italic>, but the relationship between <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw1<sup>Dic</sup></italic> was not confirmed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Yoshiya1">[21]</xref>, and in an <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> F<sub>2</sub> segregating population, the non-glaucous locus <italic>Iw2</italic> was located on chromosome 2DS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Watanabe1">[22]</xref>. In another report, the dominant non-glaucous locus <italic>Iw3672</italic> (<italic>Iw2</italic>) derived from a synthetic hexaploid wheat also mapped on 2DS by simple sequence repeat (SSR) and expressed sequence tag (EST) markers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Liu2">[23]</xref>. During development of a wheat genetic linkage map with a doubled haploid (DH) population derived from the TA4152&#x2013;60 synthetic hexaploid wheat line and the ND495 common wheat line, Chu et al., also located a dominant wax inhibitor <italic>Iw2</italic> on chromosome 2DS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Chu1">[24]</xref>. Compared to studies on the <italic>Iw</italic> non-glaucousness loci, little work has been done to map the <italic>W</italic> glaucousness loci in wheat, aside from <italic>W1</italic>, which has been mapped on chromosome 2BS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Yoshiya1">[21]</xref> and the <italic>Ws</italic> glaucous spike allele that is located at the terminus of chromosome 1AS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Gadaleta1">[17]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The development of a high-resolution genetic linkage map is essential for fine mapping and map-based cloning of genes of interest. However, it is a tedious undertaking to develop refined genetic maps and to clone genes from wheat due to the huge genome size (16,000 Mb), polyploidy, high content of repetitive DNA and un-availability of a reference genome sequence. However, since several grass species including <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> L., rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.), sorghum (<italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> L.), and maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.) have been sequenced, and genome information from these species provides important resources for comparative genomics approaches and for development of high-resolution genetic linkage maps of genes of interest in wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Devos1">[25]</xref>. Successful examples of such approaches have been documented during cloning of the wheat vernalization gene <italic>Vrn1</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Yan1">[26]</xref>, the earliness <italic>per se</italic> gene <italic>Eps-A<sup>m</sup>1</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Faricelli1">[27]</xref>, and the durable leaf rust resistance gene <italic>Lr34</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Krattinger1">[28]</xref>. Recently, the shotgun genome sequences of hexaploid wheat Chinese Spring <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Brenchley1">[29]</xref>, <italic>Triticum urartu</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Ling1">[30]</xref> and <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Jia1">[31]</xref> provide more information for marker development to the genes interested in wheat.</p>
      <p>In the present paper we have reported (1) identification and genetic analysis of the <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> wax inhibition genes originating from wild emmer and synthetic hexaploid wheat and (2) development of high-resolution comparative genetic linkage maps of <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> on chromosomes 2BS and 2DS, respectively.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Plant materials</title>
        <p>Three mapping populations were selected for mapping of the wheat wax inhibition genes <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic>. To map the <italic>Iw1</italic> locus, WE74, a non-glaucousness common wheat line derived from common wheat (glaucousness) and wild emmer (non-glaucousness) was used in crosses with Xuezao, a glaucousness common wheat line. These crosses produced a 4949 plant F<sub>2</sub> segregating population and each F<sub>2</sub> plant was bagged to harvest seeds for F<sub>3</sub> family genotyping. A 120 line DH population developed from a hybrid between the non-glaucousness TA4152&#x2013;60 synthetic hexaploid wheat line and ND495, a glaucousness common wheat line, was used to map the <italic>Iw2</italic> locus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Chu1">[24]</xref>. The newly developed International Triticea Mapping Initiative (ITMI) reference mapping population consisting of 1161 recombinant inbred lines (RIL) also was selected for mapping of the <italic>Iw2</italic> locus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Sorrells1">[32]</xref>. The glaucousness trait was phenotyped on each F<sub>2</sub> plant, F<sub>3</sub> family, RILs, and DH lines in field trials with adult plants. Chromosomal arm assignment and bin mapping of markers linked to the wax inhibition genes <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> were carried out with Chinese Spring (CS) and homoeologous group 2 nullisomic-tetrasomics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Sears1">[33]</xref>, ditelosomics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Sears2">[34]</xref> and deletion lines <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-EndoTRGill1">[35]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>PCR and product analysis</title>
        <p>Total genomic DNA was isolated from leaves by use of a cetyl trimethylammonium bromide (CTAB) protocol <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-SaghaiMaroof1">[36]</xref>. Non-glaucous and glaucous bulks, assembled with equal amounts of DNA from 10 homozygous non-glaucous and 10 homozygous glaucous F<sub>2</sub> plants, were used for bulked segregant analysis (BSA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Michelmore1">[37]</xref>. SSR and EST markers located on the short arms of homoeologous group 2 chromosomes were chosen for polymorphism screening [38,39, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/cgi-bin/graingenes/browse.cgi?class=marker">http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/cgi-bin/graingenes/browse.cgi?class=marker</ext-link>]. Primers for EST markers were designed from EST sequences derived from the public NCBI EST database. The primer-designed criteria included a Tm of 50&#x2013;65&#xB0;C with no greater than a 3&#xB0;C difference between primer pairs. Primer sequences and information about the bin-mapped EST markers are available at the GrainGenes database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wheat.pw.usda.gov">http://wheat.pw.usda.gov</ext-link>). Polymorphic markers between the parental wheat lines, as well as glaucous and non-glaucous bulks, were genotyped on each F<sub>2</sub> plant, RILs, and DH lines.</p>
        <p>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was performed in 10 &#xB5;l reactions containing 10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.3, 50 mM KCl, 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.2 mM dNTPs, 25 ng of each primer, 50 ng of genomic DNA, and 0.75 U of <italic>Taq</italic> DNA polymerase. Amplification of DNA was conducted at 94&#xB0;C for 5 min, followed by 40 cycles at 94&#xB0;C for 45 s, 50&#x2013;60&#xB0;C (depending on specific primers) for 45 s, and 72&#xB0;C for 90 s, and reactions were terminated after a final extension at 72&#xB0;C for 10 min. PCR products were mixed with 2 &#xB5;l of loading buffer (98% formamide, 10 mM EDTA, 0.25% bromophenol blue, and 0.25% xylene cyanol), separated on 8% non-denaturing polyacrylamide gels (39 acrylamide &#x2236; 1 bisacrylamide), and visualized following silver staining.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Comparative genomics analysis and EST marker development</title>
        <p>Polymorphic bin-mapped EST markers flanking the non-glaucousness loci <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> were used in BLAST searches of the <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, sorghum, and rice genome sequences to find orthologous genomic regions. Orthologous gene pairs in the corresponding genomic regions between the three species were located and used to search homologous wheat ESTs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>) that were used to design PCR primers using Primer5.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.wi.mit.edu/ftp/pub/software/primer5.0">http://www.genome.wi.mit.edu/ftp/pub/software/primer5.0</ext-link>). Polymorphic EST markers between non-glaucous and glaucous parental lines, as well as the bulk segregants, were used for genotyping three mapping populations to construct high-resolution genetic linkage maps.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Data analysis and genetic linkage map construction</title>
        <p>Chi-squared (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>) tests for goodness-of-fit were performed to estimate deviations of observed data from theoretically expected segregation ratios. Linkages between molecular markers and the wax inhibition loci were analyzed using Mapmaker 3.0 with a LOD score threshold of 3.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Lincoln1">[40]</xref>. The genetic linkage map was drawn with the software Mapdraw V2.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Liu3">[41]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Genetic analyses of wax inhibitors <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> in hexaploid wheat</title>
        <p>At the adult plant stage, leaves and stems of the common wheat line, WE74, and the TA4152&#x2013;60 and W7984 synthetic hexaploid wheat lines were non-glaucous, whereas the common wheat lines, Xuezao, ND495, and Opata M85, were glaucous. F<sub>1</sub> plants from the Xuezao/WE74, ND495/TA4152&#x2013;60, and W7984/Opata M85 crosses were non-glaucous, suggesting that the wax inhibitor genes in WE74, TA4152&#x2013;60 and W7984 are dominant. The F<sub>2</sub> population of Xuezao/WE74 segregated as 3730 non-glaucousness and 1219 glaucousness, which fits a 3&#x2236;1 ratio (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0084691-t001">Table 1</xref>). The F<sub>2&#x2236;3</sub> progenies segregated as 1269 homozygous non-glaucousness &#x2236; 2461 segregating &#x2236; 1219 homozygous glaucousness, as expected for a single gene segregation ratio of 1&#x2236;2&#x2236;1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0084691-t001">Table 1</xref>). The ND495/ TA4152&#x2013;60 DH lines segregated identical as reported by Chu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Watanabe1">[22]</xref>. The 1161 RILs of the ITMI population segregated as 549 non-glaucousness and 612 glaucousness to fit the expected 1&#x2236;1 ratio (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0084691-t001">Table 1</xref>). These results indicate that non-glaucousness in the WE74, TA4152&#x2013;60, and W7984 wheat lines is controlled by single dominant wax inhibitor gene. Since non-glaucousness originates from wild emmer in WE74 and synthetic wheat lines in TA4152&#x2013;60 and W7984, the non-glaucousness loci should be designated <italic>Iw1</italic> in WE74 and <italic>Iw2</italic> in TA4152&#x2013;60 and W7984, respectively.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0084691-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084691.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Genetic analysis of wax inhibitors <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> in hexaploid wheat.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0084691-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0084691.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mapping population</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-glaucousness<sup>*</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glaucousness<sup>*</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup><sub>0.05</sub></td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WE74 (<italic>Iw1</italic>)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xuezao</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xuezao/WE74</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xuezao/WE74 F<sub>2</sub></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3730</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1219</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4949</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.84</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xuezao/WE74 F<sub>3</sub></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1269(A)+2461(H)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1219(B)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4949</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.99</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W7984 (<italic>Iw2</italic>)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opata M85</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W7984/Opata M85 F<sub>1</sub></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W7984/Opata M85 RILs</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">549</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">612</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1161</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.84</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>A, H, B represent homozygous non-glaucousness, heterozygous and homozygous glaucousness, respectively.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Identification of SSR markers linked to <italic>Iw1</italic></title>
        <p>Because the <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> non-glaucousness genes are located on chromosomes 2BS and 2DS, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Simmonds1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Rong1">[19]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Chu1">[24]</xref>, SSR markers assigned to 2BS and 2DS were used preferentially for BSA. Linkage of the <italic>Xbarc297</italic> and <italic>Xwmc25</italic> polymorphic SSR markers to <italic>Iw1</italic> on chromosome 2BS was confirmed after genotyping the F<sub>2</sub> segregating populations of the parental lines Xuezao and WE74, as well as the non-glaucous and glaucous DNA pools of Xuezao/WE74 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084691-g001">Fig. 1b</xref>). Two SSR markers <italic>Xgwm614</italic> and <italic>Xgwm210</italic>, previously linked to <italic>Vir</italic> or <italic>Iw1</italic> on chromosome 2BS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Simmonds1">[10]</xref>, were not polymorphic between Xuezao and WE74, or the non-glaucous and glaucous DNA pools, and therefore could not be used for <italic>Iw1</italic> mapping.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0084691-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084691.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparative high-resolution genetic linkage maps of the wax inhibitors <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> in wheat.</title>
            <p>(1a) Physical bin map of <italic>Iw1</italic>. <italic>Iw1</italic> was mapped to distal bin 2BS3-0.84-1.00. (1b) Genetic linkage map of <italic>Iw1</italic> on wheat chromosome 2BS with genetic distances in cM shown on the left, markers shown on the right. (1c) The orthologous genomic region of <italic>Iw1</italic> on <italic>Brachypodium</italic> chromosome 5 with putative genes on the left. (1d) The orthologous genomic region of <italic>Iw1</italic> on sorghum chromosome 6 with putative genes on the right. (1e) The orthologous genomic region of <italic>Iw1</italic> on rice chromosome 4 with putative genes on the right. (1f) Genetic linkage map of <italic>Iw2</italic> on wheat chromosome 2DS using the ITMI population. Genetic distances in cM are shown on the left, and markers are shown on the right. (1g) DH population genetic linkage map of <italic>Iw2</italic> on wheat chromosome 2DS. The markers are shown on the left, and genetic distances in cM are shown on the right. The lines and green solid boxes indicated orthologous gene pairs and the blue solid boxes indicated non-orthologous genes between wheat, <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, rice and sorghum.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0084691.g001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Physical bin map of <italic>Iw1</italic> and the linked SSR and EST markers</title>
        <p>A set of Chinese Spring homoeologous group 2 nullisomic-tetrasomics, ditelosomics, and deletion lines <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Sears1">[33]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-EndoTRGill1">[35]</xref> were employed for physical bin mapping of <italic>Iw1</italic>. The <italic>Xwmc25</italic> and <italic>Xbarc297</italic> SSR markers were located on chromosome 2BS bin 0.84&#x2013;1.00 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084691-g001">Fig. 1a</xref>), indicating that the non-glaucousness locus <italic>Iw1</italic> was mapped on the distal part of 2BS.</p>
        <p>The wheat ESTs physically mapping on chromosome 2BS bin 0.84&#x2013;1.00 were screened for polymorphisms between Xuezao and WE74, as well as the non-glaucous and glaucous DNA pools. One EST marker, BE498358, was found to be linked to <italic>Iw1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084691-g001">Fig. 1b</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Comparative analysis of the <italic>Iw1</italic> genomic region</title>
        <p>The BE498358 EST sequence was used as a query to perform a Blast search against the <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, sorghum, and rice genome sequences. This search revealed that Bradi5g01130, Sb06g01410, and Os04g0136700 are orthologs of BE498358 located on the 5S, 6S, and 4S chromosomes of <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, sorghum, and rice respectively. Putative genes flanking Bradi5g01130, Sb06g01410, and Os04g0136700 were annotated and compared to identify orthologous gene pairs between the three species. The results indicate that a 462 kb genomic region in the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> chromosome 5S from Bradi5g01020 to Bradi5g01430 is syntenic to a 3.9 Mb region from Sb06g001110 to Sb06g002790 on sorghum 6S and a 5.6 Mb region from Os04g0118900 to Os04g0185100 on rice 4S (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0084691-t002">Table 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084691-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genes in the syntenic genomic region were then used to find homologous wheat ESTs to design primers and for polymorphism screening of the parental lines Xuezao and WE74, and the non-glaucous and glaucous DNA pools. Ten polymorphic EST markers were developed and used to genotype F<sub>2</sub> individuals and to construct a high-resolution genetic linkage map of <italic>Iw1</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0084691-t003">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084691-g001">Fig. 1b</xref>). All 11 EST markers mapped to the <italic>Iw1</italic> genomic region, and 8 of these could be used simultaneously to find orthologous gene pairs in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, sorghum, and rice syntenic genomic regions. The EST CJ876545 (which is an ortholog of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> gene Bradi5g01160), and ESTs CD927782 and CA695634 were excluded. However, the homologous CJ876545 sequences in sorghum and rice were not located on chromosomes 6S and 4S, but instead are located on chromosomes 10 (Sb10g005570) and 6 (Os06g0182500), respectively. CD927782 was developed from the rice gene Os04g0136900, but the homologous sequence of this gene could not be found in the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and sorghum genomes. CA695634 was located 5.57 cM away from <italic>Iw1</italic>, and thus was not used for further analysis. The <italic>Iw1</italic> locus co-segregated with the BF474014, CJ876545, and CD927782 EST markers and is flanked by BE498358 and CA499581 in a 0.96 cM interval in the wheat genome that is collinear with a 122 kb genomic region with 10 predicted genes that encompasses Bradi5g01130 to Bradi5g01220 in <italic>Brachypodium,</italic> a 202 kb genomic region (Sb06g001290 to Sb06g001410) with 13 predicted genes in sorghum, and a 466 kb genomic region in rice (Os04g0132300 to Os04g0137100) that has 12 predicted genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0084691-t002">Table 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084691-g001">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0084691-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084691.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Colinearity between Brachypodium, sorghum and rice in the syntenic genomic region of wheat wax inhibitors <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2.</italic></title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0084691-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0084691.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat EST</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brachypodium</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sorghum</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rice</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annotation</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJ519831</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01430</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g001110</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0118900</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJ949174</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01280</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g001240</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0129500</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sec24-like transport protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01270</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g001250</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0129600</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sec23/Sec24 zinc finger domain containing protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01260</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tyrosine specific protein phosphatase-like</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01250</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tyrosine specific protein phosphatase-like</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01240</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein transferase family protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJ777783</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01230</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g001270</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0131900</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDP-glucose:sterol glucosyltransferase</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CA499581</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01220</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g001290</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0132300</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAR2 family protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01210</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g001310</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0132500</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LRR receptor-like serine/threonine-protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01200</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-acylethanolamine amidohydrolase</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01190</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown protein/serine-type peptidase</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BF474014</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01180</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g001350</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0136700</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS domain containing protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJ876545</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01160</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LIM, zinc-binding; Ubiquitin interacting motif; DA1-large seed size</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01150</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant lipid transfer protein/protease inhibitor/seed storage</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD927782</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0136900</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01140</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g001410</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0137100</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pectate lyase 15-like</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BE498358</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01130</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g001410</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0137100</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pectate lyase 15-like</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01120</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g001420</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0137400</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01110</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB-ARC domain</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01100</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB-ARC domain</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01090</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB-ARC domain</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01080</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB-ARC domain</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01070</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB-ARC domain</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01060</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g001460</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0147200</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BQ841470</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01050</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g001460</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0150300</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01040</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01030</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g001490</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0154800</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJ886319</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01020</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb06g002790</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0185500</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zinc finger family protein</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD882067</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi5g01010</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Os04g0185100</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDT1-like protein a, chloroplastic-like</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0084691-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084691.t003</object-id>
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>EST markers of the wax inhibitors mapped in the <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> genomic regions.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0084691-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0084691.t003"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat EST</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward sequence (5'&#x2013;3')</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse sequence (5'&#x2013;3')</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJ519831</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">ATACCAAGCCTACTAAGACACTG</named-content>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">AAGGCATACTCAACAGAAATCA</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJ949174</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">TGCTTGGGAATCTGTAATGC</named-content>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">GCTAACAAATCTGTGGACCTT</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJ777783</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">GCACTCGAAATGACTGGACA</named-content>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">CACTGCCTTACACTGCAGGA</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CA499581</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">GTCACGCTCCTGCTCCTC</named-content>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">GCACCATCTTGATCCCTCTG</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BF474014</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">CCAGTACCTCGAGTCCCAGA</named-content>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">CGAAGAGGGCGTCGATCT</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJ876545</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">CAAAATGTGATGTCTGCAAGC</named-content>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">CGATAAGGCCGTTCATATTTGT</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD927782</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">TCAGGCAACCAAAACCCTTA</named-content>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">CCTTTTCTCCAGCTCAATCG</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BE498358</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">CAACTACTTCACCCACCACA</named-content>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">CACTGTGACCCAGGAGCATC</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BQ841470</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">TTGTTCCGCCTGTATGATGA</named-content>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">GGAATCCTCATTGGACGAGA</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJ886319</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">GCCATCGGCGTAGTCTTC</named-content>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">TGGCTTGAAGCAGTGGAAGT</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD882067</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">GCGGCAGAAGCTCATATCAT</named-content>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">TGGGACAAACTCTAGCAGCA</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CA695634</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">TTAGAAACGACAGTGCAGGG</named-content>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="gene">GGTGCAAGTACAGAGGAGCC</named-content>
                  </td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title>Comparative genetic mapping of <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic></title>
        <p>EST markers linked to <italic>Iw1</italic> were used to genotype the 1161 ITMI RILs and 120 DH lines of ND495/TA4152&#x2013;60 to develop a high-resolution genetic linkage map of <italic>Iw2</italic>. Eight EST markers linked to <italic>Iw1</italic> were polymorphic between ND495 and TA4152&#x2013;60, as well as W7984 and Opata M85, and were used to construct a linkage map of <italic>Iw2</italic> on wheat chromosome 2DS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084691-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). The <italic>Iw2</italic> locus co-segregated with EST markers BF474014 and CJ876545, and is flanked by the ESTs CJ886319 and CJ519831 within a 4.1 cM sequence in the ITMI RIL population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084691-g001">Fig. 1f</xref>) and a 5.4 cM interval in the ND495/TA4152&#x2013;60 DH population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084691-g001">Fig. 1g</xref>) on wheat chromosome 2DS which is collinear with a 2.3 cM genomic region spanning the <italic>Iw1</italic> locus on 2BS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084691-g001">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The aerial surfaces of most plants are coated by epicuticular waxes whose chemical and physical properties have important roles in interactions between plants and the environment. In wheat and its relatives, almost all species have parallel variations of glaucousness and non-glaucousness except for Einkorn (A genome), which is non-glaucousness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Bianchi1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki3">[14]</xref>. Genetic and cytological studies indicate that glaucousness is mainly controlled by two dominant genes, <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic>, that are located on the distal of 2BS and proximal of 2DS, respectively; and are thought to be homologous <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki2">[13]</xref>. However, the glaucousness phenotype (controlled by <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic>) is inhibited by the non-glaucousness <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> loci located on 2BS and 2DS, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki3">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Driscoll1">[15]</xref>. These results indicate that the glaucousness locus (<italic>W</italic>) itself, and interactions between the non-glaucousness (<italic>Iw</italic>) and glaucousness (<italic>W</italic>) loci are responsible for wax phenotypes in different wheat tissues.</p>
      <p>Cloning of wheat genes responsible for glaucousness and non-glaucousness will provide useful information about molecular interactions between the <italic>W</italic> and <italic>Iw</italic> loci, and the mechanisms whereby the waxy phenotypes are regulated. Our development of a high-resolution genetic linkage map is a first step towards fine mapping and map-based cloning of the glaucousness and non-glaucousness loci. However, additional refinements to the linkage maps are necessary before we can clone the respective genes and understand their relationships.</p>
      <p>Comparative genomics analyses have been applied widely to develop high-resolution genetic linkage maps of interesting genes in wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Devos1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Guyot1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Schnurbusch1">[43]</xref>. Macro-colinearity has been observed between wheat homoeologous group 2 chromosomes and <italic>Brachypodium</italic> chromosome 5, rice chromosome 4, and sorghum chromosome 6 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Devos1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Sorrells2">[44]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Luo1">[46]</xref>. Several studies have also revealed high levels of micro-colinearity in particular genomic regions between wheat, <italic>Ae. tauscii</italic>, <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, and rice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Liu1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Bossolini1">[47]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Valarik1">[51]</xref> even through their synteny is often interrupted by inversions, deletions, duplications, and rearrangements <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Sorrells2">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Luo1">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Bossolini1">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Lu1">[49]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In this study, we have found that a 3.2 cM genomics region spanning the <italic>Iw1</italic> locus in wheat chromosome 2BS was highly syntenic to a 462 kb genomic region on <italic>Brachypodium</italic> chromosome 5S, a 3.9 Mb region on sorghum 6S, and a 5.6 Mb region on rice chromosome 4S (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084691-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). However, gene duplications, insertions, and deletions were also observed in the syntenic genomic regions between wheat, <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, rice and sorghum. The <italic>Iw1</italic> co-segregating EST marker CJ876545 (orthologous to Bradi5g01160) is not found in the syntenic genomics regions of rice and sorghum, indicating that the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> gene order can serve as a better model than rice and sorghum for developing closely linked markers in wheat. However, another <italic>Iw1</italic> co-segregating EST marker, CD927782 (orthologous to Os4g0136900), was not located in the syntenic genomics region of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and sorghum, implying that the rice and sorghum genes can provide alternative information for marker development of some wheat genes.</p>
      <p>The bread wheat genome consists of three subgenomes (A, B, and D) that diverged from a common ancestor about 2.5&#x2013;4.5 MYA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Huang1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Dvorak1">[53]</xref>. The three subgenomes are still very closely related after hundreds of thousands of years of independent evolution and genetic linkage maps and comparative analyses over the past 20 years have revealed substantial conservation of orthologs among the A, B, and D subgenomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Rder1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Somers1">[39]</xref>. Conventional genetic analyses have also suggested that the <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic> glaucousness loci are duplicated genes and that the <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> non-glaucousness loci are also duplicated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki2">[13]</xref>. Additional molecular mapping experiments have revealed that both <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> are located on the distal part of chromosomes 2BS and 2DS, suggesting that they also may be orthologs. Low polymorphisms are observed on chromosome 2DS compared to chromosome 2BS, and of 11 EST derived markers mapping in the <italic>Iw1</italic> genomic region, only 7 are located on the <italic>Iw2</italic> genetic linkage map (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084691-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). An F<sub>2</sub> mapping population containing 4949 plants was used to narrow <italic>Iw1</italic> to a 0.96 cM genomic region flanked by the CA499581 and BE498358 EST markers and this region contained 10 predicted genes in the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> interval from Bradi5g01220 to Bradi5g01130, the same as the result of Adamski et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0084691-Adamski1">[54]</xref>. However, by using 1161 ITMI RILs, <italic>Iw2</italic> could only be narrowed to a 4.1 to 5.4-cM genomic region corresponding to 26 predicted genes flanked by the CJ949174 and CJ886319 EST markers from Bradi5g01280 to Bradi5g01020 in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>. In common wheat, mapping of genes on the D chromosomes are often more difficult. The <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> also present such an example. Comparative genetic mapping results indicated that <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> are located in the orthologous genomic regions of chromosomes 2BS and 2DS and function as orthologs. The mapping results from <italic>Iw1</italic> will greatly help identification of <italic>Iw2</italic> genes. The EST markers BF474014 and CJ876545 are homologous to Bradi5g01180 and Bradi5g01160 and their co-segregation with <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> can serve as starting points for chromosome landing, physical mapping and map-based cloning of the non-glaucousness genes in wheat.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors are grateful to Professor Andrew Jackson, University of Californian at Berkeley for improving the manuscript. We are also grateful to Dr. Steven S. Xu of USDA&#x2013;ARS, Northern Crop Science Laboratory, Fargo, North Dakota, USA, for providing the ND495/TA4152&#x2013;60 DH lines, Prof. Mark Sorrells, Cornell University, USA, for providing the ITMI RILs, and Prof. Bikram S. Gill and Mr. W. John Raupp, Wheat Genetics Resource Centre, Kansas State University, USA, for providing the Chinese Spring aneuploid and deletion stocks.</p>
      <p>All the mapping data, primers are publicly available in the GrainGenes database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/GG2/ggdb.shtml">http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/GG2/ggdb.shtml</ext-link>).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Eigenbrode1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eigenbrode</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Espelie</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Effects of plant epicuticular lipids on insect herbivores</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><volume>40</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>194</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Jenks1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jenks</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ashworth</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Plant epicuticular waxes: Function, production, and genetics</article-title>. <source>Hortic Rev</source><volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>68</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Riederer1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Riederer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Protecting against water loss: analysis of the barrier properties of plant cuticles</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source><volume>52</volume>: <fpage>2023</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11559738</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Schonherr1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schonherr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Water permeability of isolated cuticular membranes: The effect of cuticular waxes on diffusion of water</article-title>. <source>Planta</source><volume>131</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>164</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Jensen1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name> (<year>1962</year>) <article-title>Inheritance of the waxless character in wheat</article-title>. <source>Crop Sci</source><volume>2</volume>: <fpage>504</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>505</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Bianchi1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Figini</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Epicuticular waxes of glaucous and nonglaucous durum wheat lines</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source><volume>34</volume>: <fpage>429</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>433</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Johnson1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Yield, water relations, gas exchange, and surface reflectances of near-isogenic wheat lines differing in glaucousness</article-title>. <source>Crop Science</source><volume>23</volume>: <fpage>318</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>325</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Richards1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rawson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Glaucousness in wheat: Its development and effect on water-use efficiency gas exchange and photosynthetic tissue temperatures</article-title>. <source>Aust J Plant Physiol</source><volume>13</volume>: <fpage>465</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>473</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Zhang1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Genetic interactions underlying the biosynthesis and inhibition of &#xE2;-diketones in wheat and their impact on glaucousness and cuticle permeability</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>8(1)</volume>: <fpage>e54129</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23349804</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Simmonds1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leverington-Waite</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mapping of a gene (<italic>Vir</italic>) for a non-glaucous, viridescent phenotype in bread wheat derived from <italic>Triticum dicoccoides</italic>, and its association with yield variation</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>159</volume>: <fpage>333</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>341</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Lowe1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>HJB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>GJP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Nonglaucousness, a probable aphid resistance character of wheat</article-title>. <source>Ann Appl Biol</source><volume>106</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>560</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tsunewaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1966</year>) <article-title>Comparative gene analysis of common wheat and its ancestral species. II. Waxiness, growth habit and awnedness</article-title>. <source>Jap J Bot</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>254</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki2">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tsunewaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ebana</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Production of near-isogenic lines of common wheat for glaucousness and genetic basis of this trait clarified by their use</article-title>. <source>Genes Genet Syst</source><volume>74</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>41</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Tsunewaki3">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tsunewaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1962</year>) <article-title>Monosomic analysis of synthesized hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Jap J Genet</source><volume>37</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>168</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Driscoll1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name> (<year>1964</year>) <article-title>Chromosomes associated with waxlessness, awnedness and time of maturity of common wheat</article-title>. <source>Can J Genet Cytol</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>324</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>333</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Dubcovsky1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dubcovsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Echaide</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giancola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rousset</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Seed-storage-protein loci in RFLP maps of diploid, tetraploid, and hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>95</volume>: <fpage>1169</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1180</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Gadaleta1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gadaleta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giancaspro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giove</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zacheo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mangini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genetic and physical mapping of new EST-derived SSRs on the A and B genome chromosomes of wheat</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><volume>118</volume>: <fpage>1015</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1025</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19183861</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Bennett1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Izanloo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuchel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chalmers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Identification of novel quantitative trait loci for days to ear emergence and flag leaf glaucousness in a bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) population adapted to southern Australian conditions</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet (2012)</source><volume>124</volume>: <fpage>697</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>711</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Rong1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manisterski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A new powdery mildew resistance gene: introgression from wild emmer into common wheat and RFLP-based mapping</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>115</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>126</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Liu1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Identification and comparative mapping of a powdery mildew resistance gene derived from wild emmer (<italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> var. <italic>dicoccoides</italic>) on chromosome 2BS</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>124</volume>: <fpage>1041</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22170431</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Yoshiya1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yoshiya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuboyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Genetic mapping of the genes for non-glaucous phenotypes in tetraploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>177</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>297</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Watanabe1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takesada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ban</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Genetic mapping of the genes for glaucous leaf and tough rachis in <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>, the D-genome progenitor of wheat</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>144</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>123</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Liu2">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular mapping of a dominant non-glaucousness gene from synthetic hexaploid wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source><volume>155</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>78</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Chu1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Friesen</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Faris</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Whole genome mapping in a wheat doubled haploid population using SSRs and TRAPs and the identification of QTL for agronomic traits</article-title>. <source>Mol Breed</source><volume>22</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>266</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Devos1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Devos</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Updating the &#x201C;crop circle&#x201D;</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15752995</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Yan1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loukoianov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tranquilli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Helguera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fahima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Positional cloning of the wheat vernalization gene <italic>VRN1</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>100</volume>: <fpage>6263</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12730378</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Faricelli1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Faricelli</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Val&#xE1;rik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dubcovsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Control of flowering time and spike development in cereals: the earliness <italic>per se Eps-1</italic> region in wheat, rice, and <italic>Brachypodium</italic></article-title>. <source>Funct Integr Genomics</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19851796</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Krattinger1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krattinger</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lagudah</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spielmeyer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huerta-Espino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A putative ABC transporter confers durable resistance to multiple fungal pathogens in wheat</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>323</volume>: <fpage>1360</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19229000</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Brenchley1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brenchley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spannagl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>D'Amore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Analysis of the bread wheat genome using whole-genome shotgun sequencing</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <volume>491</volume>: <fpage>705</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>710</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23192148</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Ling1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>HQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Draft genome of the wheat A-genome progenitor <italic>Triticum urartu</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <volume>496</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23535596</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Jia1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title><italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> draft genome sequence reveals a gene repertoire for wheat adaptation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <volume>496</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23535592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Sorrells1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gustafson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benscher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Reconstruction of the Synthetic W7984 &#xD7; Opata M85 wheat reference population</article-title>. <source>Genome</source><volume>54</volume>: <fpage>875</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21999208</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Sears1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sears ER (1966) Nullisomic-tetrasomic combinations in hexaploid wheat. In: Riley R, Lewis KR Chromosome manipulation and plant genetics. Oliver and Boyd, Edinburgh, 29&#x2013;45.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Sears2">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sears ER, Sears LMS (1978) The telocentric chromosomes of common wheat. In: Ramanujam S Proc 5th Int Wheat Genet Symp. Indian Society of Genetics and Plant Breeding, New Delhi, 389&#x2013;407.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-EndoTRGill1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Endo TR &amp; Gill</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The deletion stocks of common wheat</article-title>. <source>Journal of Heredity</source><volume>87</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>307</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-SaghaiMaroof1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saghai-Maroof</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soliman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Ribosomal DNA spacer-length polymorphisms in barley: Mendelian inheritance, chromosomal location, and population dynamics</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>81</volume>: <fpage>8014</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6096873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Michelmore1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Michelmore</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paran</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kesseli</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Identification of markers closely linked to disease-resistance genes by bulked segregant analysis: a rapid method to detect markers in specific genomic regions by using segregating populations</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>88</volume>: <fpage>9828</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9832</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1682921</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Rder1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>R&#xF6;der</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Korzun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wendehake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plaschke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tixier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>A microsatellite map of wheat</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>149</volume>: <fpage>2007</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2023</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9691054</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Somers1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Isaac</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A high density microsatellite consensus map for bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>109</volume>: <fpage>1105</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15490101</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Lincoln1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lincoln S, Daly M, Lander E (1992) Constructing genetic maps with Mapmaker/EXP3.0 Whitehead Institute Techn Rep, 3rd edn. Whitehead Institute, Cambridge.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Liu3">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>MapDraw: a Microsoft Excel macro for drawing genetic linkage maps based on given genetic linkage data</article-title>. <source>Hereditas (Beijing)</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>321</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Guyot1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guyot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yahiaoui</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feuillet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title><italic>In silico</italic> comparative analysis reveals a mosaic conservation of genes within a novel collinear region in wheat chromosome 1AS and rice chromosome 5S</article-title>. <source>Funct Integr Genomics</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14767678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Schnurbusch1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schnurbusch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eastwood</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jefferies</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Fine mapping and targeted SNP survey using rice-wheat gene colinearity in the region of the <italic>Bo1</italic> boron toxicity tolerance locus of bread wheat</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>115</volume>: <fpage>451</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17571251</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Sorrells2">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>La Rota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bermudez-Kandianis</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kantety</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Comparative DNA sequence analysis of wheat and rice genomes</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source><volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1818</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1827</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12902377</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-TheInternationalBrachypodium1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>The International Brachypodium</surname><given-names>Initiative</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genome sequencing and analysis of the model grass <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>463</volume>: <fpage>763</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20148030</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Luo1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>You</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deal</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A 4-gigabase physical map unlocks the structure and evolution of the complex genome of <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>, the wheat D-genome progenitor</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>7940</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7945</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23610408</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Bossolini1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bossolini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wicker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Knobel</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Comparison of orthologous loci from small grass genomes <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and rice: implications for wheat genomics and grass genome annotation</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>49</volume>: <fpage>704</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>717</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17270010</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Faris1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Faris</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fellers</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Micro-colinearity between rice, <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, and <italic>Triticum monococcum</italic> at the wheat domestication locus <italic>Q</italic></article-title>. <source>Funct Integr Genomics</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18210171</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Lu1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Faris</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Macro- and micro-colinearity between the genomic region of wheat chromosome 5B containing the <italic>Tsn1</italic> gene and the rice genome</article-title>. <source>Funct Integr Genomics</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16372189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Griffiths1">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Foote</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bertin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wanous</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization of <italic>Ph1</italic> as a major chromosome pairing locus in polyploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>439</volume>: <fpage>749</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>752</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16467840</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Valarik1">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Valarik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Linkiewicz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dubcovsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A microcolinearity study at the earliness <italic>per se</italic> gene <italic>Eps-Am1</italic> region reveals an ancient duplication that preceded the wheat-rice divergence</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>112</volume>: <fpage>945</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16432738</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Huang1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sirikhachornkit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Faris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Genes encoding plastid acetyl-CoA carboxylase and 3-phosphoglycerate kinase of the <italic>Triticum</italic>/<italic>Aegilops</italic> complex and the evolutionary history of polyploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>99</volume>: <fpage>8133</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12060759</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Dvorak1">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dvorak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <name><surname>Akhunov</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Tempos of gene locus deletions and duplications and their relationship to recombination rate during diploid and polyploid evolution in the <italic>Aegilops</italic>-<italic>Triticum</italic> alliance</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>171</volume>: <fpage>323</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15996988</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0084691-Adamski1">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adamski</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mugford</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The inhibitor of wax 1 locus (Iw1) prevents formation of &#x3B2;- and OH-&#x3B2;-diketones in wheat cuticular waxes and maps to a sub-cM interval on chromosome arm 2BS</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <volume>74(6)</volume>: <fpage>989</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1002</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23551421</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
