<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3861272</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-21965</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081470</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>De-Etiolation of Wheat Seedling Leaves: Cross Talk between Heme Oxygenase/Carbon Monoxide and Nitric Oxide</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">De-Etiolation: Cross Talk between HO/CO and NO</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Yahui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Xinna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>Langlai</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shen</surname>
            <given-names>Wenbiao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Ningbo First Hospital, Ningbo, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>College of Life Sciences, Cooperative Demonstration Laboratory of Centrifuge Technique, Nanjing Agricultural University, State Key Laboratory of Crop Genetics &amp; Germplasm Enhancement, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Biotechnology Research Institute, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing, P.R. China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Datta</surname>
            <given-names>Prasun K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Temple University, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>702820686@qq.com</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: YL. Performed the experiments: YL. Analyzed the data: YL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YL. Wrote the paper: YL. Participated in finishing the experiment: XL. Guided the experiment: WS LX.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>12</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <elocation-id>e81470</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Liu et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Greening of etiolated plants is predominantly stimulated by light but the complete molecular mechanism is still unknown. Multiple studies currently focus on the important physiological effects of heme oxygenase (HO)/carbon monoxide (CO) in plants. In this report, firstly, the role of HO/CO in light-induced de-etiolation process was investigated. We discovered that light could significantly increase HO activities, <italic>HO-1</italic> gene expression, CO release, and chlorophyll accumulation, all of which were sensitive to zinc protoporphyrin (ZnPPIX), the potent inhibitor of HO-1, respectively. Both HO-1 inducer hematin (H) and CO aqueous solution were able to relieve etiolation in wheat seedling leaves under completely darkness by up-regulating endogenous HO/CO system, so as nitric oxide (NO) donor sodium nitroprusside (SNP) did. Similarly, endogenous NO production was also boost in response to light, SNP, hematin and CO aqueous solution in wheat seedling leaves. Additionally, the restoration of chlorophyll contents was blocked, when the inhibitor of mammalian nitric oxide synthase <italic>N<sup>G</sup></italic>-nitro-L-arginine methylester hydrochloride (L-NAME) or the specific scavenger of NO 2-(4-carboxyphenyl)-4, 4, 5, 5-tetramethylimidazoline-1-oxyl-3-oxide potassium salt (cPTIO) was added, respectively. Furthermore, the inducible effects of light were different from those of SNP, hematin, and CO on Pfr accumulation and <italic>PHYA</italic> transcripts. However, all of sodium nitroprusside (SNP), hematin, and CO could accelerate NO emission, which suggested that HO/CO in wheat seedlings de-etiolation under dark-light transition may have a cross talk with NO.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by the program for new century excellent talents in university (grant no. NCET-07-0441), and the 111 project of China (grant no. B07030). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="9"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>De-etiolation of etioplasts lack of chlorophyll is a complex developmental process that is triggered predominantly by light. One of the important light-dependent steps is the phototransformation of protochlorophyll (ide) to chlorophyll (ide) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Boardman1">[1]</xref>. During the subsequent greening period, the rapid accumulation of chlorophylls occurs. In fact, plants have developed elaborate photo sensory systems to optimize its growth and development to daily and seasonal changes. However, the complete molecular mechanisms by which light regulates development are largely unknown.</p>
      <p>Heme oxygenases (HOs, EC 1.14.99.3) were originally identified in animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Tenhunen1">[2]</xref>, which catalyzes the first and rate-limiting step in the degradation of heme. Via oxidation, HO cleaves heme molecules to yield equimolar quantities of biliverdin IX&#x3B1; (BV), carbon monoxide (CO), and free iron. Indeed, ample evidence currently supports the notion that HO serves to provide potent cytoprotective effects in many models of oxidant-induced cellular and tissue injury both in animals and plants. For example, recent works have indicated the enhancement of HO activities and transcripts in the antioxidant defense system in soybean leaves subjected to lower levels of cadmium (Cd) stress or UV-B irradiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Noriega1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Noriega2">[4]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Moreover, in plants, HOs are not only involved in adaptation or defense against oxidative stress, but also identified to regulate the first step of phycobilin biosynthesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Durski1">[5]</xref>. These linear tetrapyrrole molecules are precursors of the chromophores for the photoreceptor phytochromes, which are traditionally responsible for the detection of far-red light (FR) and red light (R). They are pigments consisting of a polypeptide of about 125 kD carrying a chromophore moiety, the phytochromobilin, which is a linear tetrapyrrole co-valently attached to a conserved cysteine residue in the N-terminal region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Cherry1">[6]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Schfer1">[9]</xref>. Phytochromes are encoded by gene families in all higher plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Sharrock1">[10]</xref>, each of which uniquely contributes to assemble holo-phytochromes for regulating plant photomorphogenesis.</p>
      <p>CO, catalyzed by HOs, was found to play various important physiological roles in animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Verma1">[11]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Zhuo1">[13]</xref>. More recently, it has been reported to be involved in various biological processes in plant kingdom. For instance, it acts as a compound with hormonal effects, including affecting the seed dormancy and germination <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Dekker1">[14]</xref>, inducing lateral root formation, involving in abscisic acid (ABA)-induced stomatal closure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Cao1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Cao2">[16]</xref>, alleviating the cadmium-induced oxidative damage in <italic>Medicago sativa</italic> seedling root tissues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Han1">[17]</xref> and even involving in the auxin-induced cucumber adventitious rooting process <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Xuan1">[18]</xref>, most of which were similar to some behaviors reported by NO in plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Beligni1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Delledonne1">[20]</xref>. Previous reports have shown that NO signal, which was mainly produced by nitric oxide synthase-like protein or nitrate reductase (NR, EC 1.6.6.1/2) in plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Delledonne1">[20]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Zemojtel1">[23]</xref>, participated in the course of wheat leaves de-etiolation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Beligni1">[19]</xref>. Considering the similarities between NO and CO, we hypothesized that CO might exert the same function. On the other hand, mounting evidence has demonstrated the presence of CO release in plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Han1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Wilks1">[24]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Schade1">[28]</xref>, which also provided the evidence for above hypothesis.</p>
      <p>To reveal the role of HO/CO system in light-induced de-etiolation, we analyzed the HO expression and CO release of wheat leaves in light-dark transition. In addition, we discussed the mechanism of hematin and CO on restoring the reduction of chlorophyll content in absence of light and suggested a possible link between HO/CO and NO.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Light-induced wheat seedlings de-etiolation is sensitive to ZnPPIX, the potent inhibitor of HO-1</title>
        <p>In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, genetic analysis of the <italic>HY1</italic> locus showed that <italic>hy1</italic> mutant plants display long hypocotyls and decrease chlorophyll accumulation consistent with a substantial deficiency in photochemical active phytochromes (phys) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Emborg1">[29]</xref>. Meanwhile, the potent HO-1 inhibitor ZnPPIX was first found to inhibit HO activity in both animal and plant tissues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Xuan1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Lamar1">[30]</xref>. In our test, comparison of the chlorophyll content in seedling leaves of wheat plants transferred from dark to light (D&#x2192;L) with dark-grown controls (D&#x2192;D) showed that transferred plants (D&#x2192;L) maintained relatively higher chlorophyll level after 3 days (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g001">Fig. 1</xref>), as found previously. Interestingly, above light-mediated effect was prevented when ZnPPIX was added (D&#x2192;L+ZnPPIX), further suggesting a possible interrelationship among light, HO-1, and chlorophyll content in our experimental conditions.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0081470-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081470.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Comparative effects of HO-1 inducer hematin, CO-saturated aqueous solution, and light on the restoration of chlorophyll content in etiolated wheat seedling leaves.</title>
            <p>14-day-old wheat seedlings were kept at 25&#xB0;C in continuous darkness for 5 days. After that, some were transferred into light, while others were still left in darkness without (D&#x2192;D) or with different contentions of hematin (1.0, 10, and 100 &#x3BC;M, D&#x2192;D+H1.0, 10, 100), and different saturations of CO aqueous solution (0.1, 1.0, 10, and 50%, D&#x2192;D+CO0.1, 1.0, 10, 50%). L&#x2192;L+ZnPPIX, D&#x2192;D+ZnPPIX, and D&#x2192;L+ZnPPIX D&#x2192;H10+Hb stand for combination with HO-1 specific inhibitor ZnPPIX (100 &#x3BC;M), and CO/NO scavenger hemoglobin (Hb, 0.1 gL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>), for additional 3 days. L&#x2192;L stands for wheat seedlings were grown in normal light cycle. Bars denoted by the same letter did not significantly differ at <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05 according to Duncan's multiple range tests.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081470.g001"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The effects of ZnPPIX on chlorophyll content in the presence of light treatment were also evaluated. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g001">Fig. 1</xref>, chlorophyll content of light-grown seedling leaves (L&#x2192;L) was markedly reduced by addition ZnPPIX (L&#x2192;L+ZnPPIX, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05). Similarly, inhibition of HO-1 activity with ZnPPIX in dark-grown sample resulted in a 33% decrease in chlorophyll content, confirming a possible physiological role for HO-1 in light-induced wheat seedlings de-etiolation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Both HO-1 inducer hematin and CO aqueous solution were able to restore the chlorophyll decrease of wheat seedling leaves in completely darkness</title>
        <p>In further investigations, we noticed that HO-1 inducer hematin (H) or CO aqueous solution (CO), when applied to etiolated wheat seedlings, could dose-dependently restore the loss of chlorophyll content induced by darkness pretreatment. In comparison with dark-grown control plants (D&#x2192;D), a maximal response at 10 &#x3BC;M hematin and 1.0% CO aqueous solution was observed. Additionally, above hematin-mediated effect was prevented when the CO scavenger hemoglobin (Hb) was added. Thus, above concentration of hematin and CO aqueous solution were used to investigate the role of the HO/CO system throughout this investigation. Furthermore, the results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g002">Fig. 2</xref> also confirmed that 10 &#x3BC;M hematin, as an effective inducer of HO-1, was able to partially reverse the negative impact of darkness on chlorophyll content in a time-dependent manner. In a word, above results further illustrated that both hematin and CO aqueous solution could exert the same inducible function as light in continuous darkness.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0081470-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081470.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Time course of chlorophyll accumulation following incubation in HO-1 inducer hematin in wheat seedling leaves.</title>
            <p>Before starting the experiments, 14-day-old wheat seedlings cultured in the Hoagland solution were kept in the light (L, 300 &#x3BC;mmol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) or dark for 5 days. Afterwards, seedlings were cultured in the Hoagland solution with or without 10 &#x3BC;M HO-1 inducer hematin (H) treatment, in the dark (D) for another 5 days. L&#x2192;L stands for wheat seedlings were grown in normal light cycle. Chlorophyll was extracted and quantified at various times. Bars denoted by the same letter did not significantly differ at <italic>P&lt;</italic>0.05 according to Duncan's multiple range tests.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081470.g002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Induction of HO/CO system in response to light treatment</title>
        <p>We analyzed the expression of <italic>HO-1</italic> mRNA in wheat seedling leaves in response to the transition from dark to light at different times. Quantitative real-time RT-PCR revealed that seedling leaves of wheat plants transferred from dark to light (D&#x2192;L) with dark- and light-grown controls (D&#x2192;D, and L&#x2192;L) brought about the highest induction of <italic>HO-1</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). For example, the results shown that <italic>HO-1</italic> mRNA level was increased more than 3 times after transition (12 h) respect to control values, while 1.5 time enhancement was observed at 6 h of transition. This fact indicated that <italic>HO-1</italic> gene response occurred in a time-dependent manner. On the other hand, treatment either with dark or light for 12 h produced the slightly decreased expression pattern of <italic>HO-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0081470-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081470.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Time course of <italic>HO-1</italic> gene expression in wheat seedling leaves during transition from dark to light for additional hours.</title>
            <p>A, <italic>HO-1</italic> mRNA expression was analyzed by quantitative real-time RT-PCR as described in Materials and Methods. B, CO release under different treatments at 12 h. Values were the mean &#xB1; SE of three independent experiments. Bars denoted by the different letter differed significantly at <italic>P&lt;</italic>0.05 according to Duncan's multiple range tests.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081470.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To assess whether the aforementioned different mRNA levels reflected changes in HO activities, enzyme activity determination was performed. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0081470-t001">Table 1</xref>, the observed differences in transcripts were also positively correlated with enzyme activities. Interestingly, it is noteworthy that, as expected, treatment with ZnPPIX in seedling leaves of wheat plants transferred from dark to light produced the significantly decrease of HO activity (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05). Moreover, the changes of CO content under different treatments were in conformity with HO activities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0081470-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081470.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Time course of changes in HO activities (U mg protein<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) during transition from dark to light.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0081470-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0081470.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment (h)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L&#x2192;L</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D&#x2192;D</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D&#x2192;L</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D&#x2192;L+ZnPPIX</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35&#xB1;0.05a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23&#xB1;0.02a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24&#xB1;0.07d</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21&#xB1;0.01a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51&#xB1;0.07c</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05&#xB1;0.02b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31&#xB1;0.09a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19&#xB1;0.04a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85&#xB1;0.04b</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05&#xB1;0.00b</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30&#xB1;0.05a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18&#xB1;0.07a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29&#xB1;0.01a</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04&#xB1;0.01b</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <p>&#x3BC;mmol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) or dark (D) for 5 d (25&#xB0;C). Afterwards, seedlings were cultured in the Hoagland solution with or without 100 &#x3BC;M HO-1 inhibitor ZnPPIX treatment, in the light (L) or dark (D) for another 12 h (25&#xB0;C). Before starting the experiments, 14-day-old wheat seedlings cultured in the Hoagland solution were kept in the light (L, 300 </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <p>&#xB1; SE of three different experiments with at least three replicated measurements. Different letters within columns indicate significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05) according to Duncan's multiple range test. Values are means </p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>HO activities and <italic>HO-1</italic> transcripts were increased in response to SNP, hematin, and CO aqueous solution in etiolated wheat seedling leaves</title>
        <p>The light-like effect of applying HO-1 inducer hematin or CO aqueous solution to dark-grown samples first led us to investigate whether changes in endogenous HO activities and <italic>HO-1</italic> transcripts occurred in response to hematin or CO aqueous solution, as well as these actions of light (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g003">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0081470-t001">Table 1</xref>), or a well known NO donor sodium nitroprusside (SNP). In our experimental conditions, 10 &#x3BC;M hematin (H), or 1.0% CO aqueous solution (CO), applied to dark-grown wheat seedlings, induced rapid enhancement of HO activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). The time course test shown that in comparison with dark-grown controls (D&#x2192;D), a rapidly maximum response was discovered as early as 1 day after different treatments (D&#x2192;D+S, D&#x2192;D+H, and D&#x2192;D+CO), followed by a gradual decrease until the third day (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). A weaker increased level of HO activities after treatment in the transition from dark to light (D&#x2192;L) was also observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). Meanwhile, changes in <italic>HO-1</italic> transcripts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g005">Fig. 5</xref>) were found to be similar to those for HO activities under different treatments. We also noted that the induction of HO expression elicited by hematin apparently preceded light-induced de-etiolation.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0081470-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081470.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of NO donor SNP, hematin and CO-saturated aqueous solution on HO activities in wheat seedling leaves after dark pretreatment.</title>
            <p>Before starting the experiments, 14-day-old wheat seedlings cultured in the Hoagland solution were kept in the light (L, 300 &#x3BC;mmol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) or dark (D) for 5 days. Afterwards, seedlings were cultured in the Hoagland solution without (D&#x2192;D) or with SNP (S, 100 &#x3BC;M), HO-1 inducer hematin (H, 10 &#x3BC;M), 1.0% CO-saturated aqueous solution (CO) in completely darkness for another 3 days. Values were the mean &#xB1; SE for at least three independent experiments. Bars denoted by the same letter did not significantly differ at <italic>P&lt;</italic>0.05 according to Duncan's multiple range tests.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081470.g004"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0081470-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081470.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>HO-1 inducer hematin, exogenous CO and light treatments induce <italic>HO-1</italic> gene expression in wheat seedling leaves after dark pretreatment.</title>
            <p>Before starting the experiments, 14-day-old wheat seedlings cultured in the Hoagland solution were kept in the light (L, 300 &#x3BC;mmol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) or dark (D) for 5 days. Afterwards, seedlings were cultured in the Hoagland solution without (D&#x2192;D) or with HO-1 inducer hematin (H, 10 &#x3BC;M), and 1.0% CO-saturated aqueous solution (CO) for another 12 h. <italic>HO-1</italic> mRNA expression was analyzed by quantitative real-time RT-PCR as described in Materials and Methods. Three independent experiments were performed, bars denoted by the same letter did not significantly differ at <italic>P&lt;</italic>0.05 according to Duncan's multiple range tests.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081470.g005"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>The application of L-NAME and cPTIO blocked the restoration of chlorophyll contents in etiolated wheat seedling leaves induced by SNP, hematin, and CO aqueous solution</title>
        <p>The observation that de-etiolation of wheat seedling leaves displayed similar sensitivity to light, SNP, hematin, and CO aqueous solution prompted us to examine the effects of the inhibitor of mammalian NOS-like protein (L-NAME) and a specific NO scavenger cPTIO on the changes of chlorophyll contents in etiolated wheat seedling leaves with or without SNP, hematin, and CO aqueous solution. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g006">Fig. 6</xref>, similar to the dark-induced decay of chlorophyll, the ameliorating effects of SNP (S), hematin (H), and CO aqueous solution (CO) on etiolation was significantly blocked by L-NAME or cPTIO, respectively. Further, the negative effects of L-NAME and cPTIO on light-induced de-etiolation were observed. These results suggested that endogenous NO is likely to be involved in de-etiolation elicited by light, hematin and CO aqueous solution, and that mammalian NOS-like enzyme-mediated NO production plays an important role in above process.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0081470-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081470.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>SNP, hematin, CO-saturated aqueous solution, CO scavenger hemoglobin, mammalian NOS-like inhibitor L-NAME, and the NO specific scavenger cPTIO differentially influence the chlorophyll content in etiolated wheat seedling leaves after dark pretreatment.</title>
            <p>Before starting the experiments, 14-day-old wheat seedlings cultured in the Hoagland solution were kept in the light (L, 300 &#x3BC;mmol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) or dark (D) for 5 days. Afterwards, seedlings were cultured in the Hoagland solution without or with 100 &#x3BC;&#x39C; SNP (S), 10 &#x3BC;M HO-1 inducer hematin (H), 1.0% CO aqueous solution (CO), 0.1 g L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> Hb, 200 &#x3BC;M L-NAME, 100 &#x3BC;M cPTIO, or the above combination treatments, in the light (L) or dark (D) for another 3 days. Values were the mean &#xB1; SE for at least three independent experiments. Bars denoted by the same letter did not significantly differ at <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05 according to Duncan's multiple range tests.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081470.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>NO production was increased in response to SNP, hematin, and CO aqueous solution in etiolated wheat seedling leaves</title>
        <p>To further confirm whether de-etiolation elicited by light, hematin, and CO aqueous solution is related to endogenous NO, Greiss reagent method (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g007">Fig. 7</xref>) or a fluorescence method with or without the specific fluorescent probe 4,5-diaminofluorescein diacetate (DAF-2 DA), the negative probe 4-amino fluorescein diacetate (AF 4-DA), and NO scavenger cPTIO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g008">Fig. 8</xref>), was used to evaluate the changes of NO signal, respectively. As expected <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Xie1">[31]</xref>, in comparison with the dark-grown control samples (D&#x2192;D), the time course experiments for additional three days illustrated that a burst of endogenous NO production appeared on the second day with light, SNP, hematin, and CO treatments, respectively, and then followed by a gradual decrease till the third day (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g007">Fig. 7</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0081470-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081470.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Time course of endogenous nitric oxide (NO) generation induced by SNP, hematin and CO aqueous solution in wheat seedling leaves.</title>
            <p>Before starting the experiments, 14-day-old wheat seedlings cultured in the Hoagland solution were kept in the light (L, 300 &#x3BC;mmol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) or dark (D) for 5 days (25&#xB0;C). Afterwards, seedlings were cultured in the Hoagland solution without or with 100 &#x3BC;&#x39C; SNP (S), 10 &#x3BC;M HO-1 inducer hematin (H), and 1.0% CO aqueous solution (CO), in the light (L) or dark (D) for another 3 days. NO contents were detected by using Greiss reagent. Values were the mean &#xB1; SE for at least three independent experiments. Bars denoted by the same letter did not significantly differ at <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05 according to Duncan's multiple range tests.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081470.g007"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0081470-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081470.g008</object-id>
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>NO accumulation in etiolated distilled water was taken as control.</title>
            <p>The distribution of nitric oxide (NO) in wheat seedling leaves induced by SNP, hematin, and CO aqueous solution in wheat seedling leaves. Before starting the experiments, 14-day-old wheat seedlings cultured in the Hoagland solution were kept in the light (L, 300 &#x3BC;mmol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) or dark (D) for 5 days. Afterwards, seedlings were cultured in the Hoagland solution without or with 100 &#x3BC;&#x39C; SNP (S), 10 &#x3BC;M HO-1 inducer hematin (H), and 1.0% CO aqueous solution (CO), in the light (L) or dark (D) for another 2 days. A, The NO distribution was detected by fluorescence probe DAF-2 DA and negative probe AF 4-DA 2 days after different treatments under fluorescence microscopy (TCS-SP2 confocal laser scanning microscope; Leica Lasertechnik GmbH). B, Mean relative DAF-2 DA and AF 4-DA fluorescence densities corresponding to samples without cPTIO treatment was given. Values were the mean &#xB1; SE for at least three independent experiments. Bars denoted by the same letter did not significantly differ at <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05 according to Duncan's multiple range tests. Bars&#x200A;=&#x200A;20 &#x3BC;m.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081470.g008"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Furthermore, a slight decrease of DAF-2 DA-dependent green fluorescence was firstly observed in the dark-grown sample (D&#x2192;D, 2 d) respect to the light-grown control (L&#x2192;L). The green fluorescence was increased by the addition of the NO donor SNP and reduced by the specific scavenger cPTIO, respectively, further confirming that DAF-2 DA-dependent green fluorescence is associated with endogenous NO concentration. As expected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g007">Fig. 7</xref>), an increase in endogenous NO production in seedling leaves was found upon exposure to light, SNP, hematin, and CO, as demonstrated by 37.4, 69.2, 47.7 and 36.6% induction of fluorescence intensity following 2 days. cPTIO, a specific scavenger of NO, also inhibited above inductions. Moreover, similar increase in fluorescence was not apparently observed when AF 4-DA, the negative control probe for DAF-2 DA, was applied, respectively. Together, these results reveal that an induction of endogenous NO production in the seedling leaves might be a critical event in above effects elicited by light, SNP, hematin, and CO aqueous solution during de-etiolation process.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Application of SNP, hematin and CO saturated aqueous solution induced the accumulation of Pfr in etiolated wheat seedling leaves</title>
        <p>Phytochromes are molecular light switches that regulate various aspects of plant growth and development. Phytochromes exist in two photointerconvertible forms, Pr and Pfr. Pfr is thought to be the active form of phytochrome, and can be converted back to Pr by far-red light. Therefore, we further detected the relative amount of Pfr to investigate whether HO/CO involving in light-mediated signals in plants depend on photoreceptors. Results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g009">Fig. 9</xref> illustrated that Pfr content in dark-grown plant (D&#x2192;D) was decreased with respect to the light-grown control (L&#x2192;L) (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05). By comparison, the dark-induced decrease of Pfr level was markedly recovered by SNP, hematin, and CO aqueous solution treatment for additional 3 days. On the other hand, ZnPPIX or cPTIO significantly blocked hematin-induced effects. Meanwhile, dark-light transition (D&#x2192;L) even led to the more serious decrease of Pfr content.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0081470-g009" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081470.g009</object-id>
          <label>Figure 9</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of treatment with SNP, hematin, CO-saturated aqueous solution, ZnPPIX, and cPTIO on Pfr contents (3 d) and expression profiles of <italic>PHYA</italic> expression (2 d).</title>
            <p>14-day-old wheat seedlings were grown for 5 days at 25&#xB0;C in continuous darkness (D) or light (L) at 300 &#x3BC;mmol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> before either being transferred into light or left in continuous darkness without or with 100 &#x3BC;M SNP, 10 &#x3BC;M hematin, 1.0% CO aqueous solution, 100 &#x3BC;M HO-1 specific inhibitor ZnPPIX, and 100 &#x3BC;M cPTIO, or their combination treatments, for another 3 days. <italic>PHYA</italic> mRNA expression was analyzed by quantitative real-time RT-PCR as described in Materials and Methods. Values were the mean &#xB1; SE for at least three independent experiments (n&#x200A;=&#x200A;20). Bars denoted by the same letter did not significantly differ at <italic>P&lt;</italic>0.05 according to Duncan's multiple tests.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081470.g009"/>
        </fig>
        <p>It is previously reported that in dark-grown seedlings, PHYA is the most abundant phytochrome, which is responsible for de-etiolation under far-red light <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Quail2">[8]</xref>. In the following test, we analyzed the expression profile of <italic>PHYA</italic> using quantitative real-time RT-PCR and discovered that SNP, hematin and 1.0% CO saturated solution all were able to induce <italic>PHYA</italic> gene expression as well as dark treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g009">Fig. 9A</xref>). However, D&#x2192;L treatment also exhibited no obvious positive effect.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In animal research, HOs have been widely studied and well understood. Recently, an increasing number of researches concentrate on its function in plants. It is an important effecter of growth, development and defense response, but there were few reports about the involvement of HO/CO in formation of photosynthetic performance. In our experiment, we discovered that when etiolated wheat seedling induced by darkness, were transferred to light for greening, HO activities, <italic>HO-1</italic> transcript, and CO release were obviously up-regulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g003">Fig. 3</xref>), which were consistent with the increase of chlorophyll content (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). However, addition of ZnPPIX blocks this inducible effect. It is suggested that HO/CO system might participate in light-induced wheat seedling de-etiolation.</p>
      <p>An earlier study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Huang1">[32]</xref> indicated that when treated with hematin, NaCl-induced chlorophyll decay of wheat seedling leaves was evidently reduced. Our results also confirmed that application of hematin, a HO-1 inducer or CO donor, could impair the reduction of chlorophyll contents in entirely darkness, but treatment with Hb (a CO scavenger) arrested this positive effects during the greening process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). The block action of Hb suggested that endogenous CO, may possibly from HO, be responsible for wheat seedling de-etiolation. Meanwhile, lower concentration of CO aqueous solution acted as the same function on restoring the decrease of chlorophyll contents, which also confirmed above hypothesis. Besides, hematin (H), or 1.0% CO aqueous solution (CO), could enhance HO activity in dark-grown wheat seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g004">Fig. 4</xref>), which suggested that hematin, acting as the substrate of endogenous HO and exogenous lower concentration of CO aqueous solution might regulate wheat seedling de-etiolation in absence of light through activating endogenous HO/CO system.</p>
      <p>Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Zhang1">[33]</xref> reported that endogenous NO participated in light-inducing greening of etiolated barley seedlings. In this study, based on the relationship between HO/CO and NO shown previously in animals and recently in plants, we investigated the putative role of NO in light, hematin, and CO-induced responses by determining NO <italic>in vivo</italic> using fluorescence probe as well as the usage of chemicals that can manipulate the NO concentrations during greening process. Our results indicated that hematin and CO could induce the production of endogenous NO and its peak value appeared on the second day, which lag behind the increase of HO activity. Application of NOS inhibitor L-NAME (200 &#x3BC;M) and NO scavenger cPTIO could block the increase of chlorophyll content induced by hematin and 1.0% saturated CO aqueous solution in etiolated wheat seedlings, which suggested that NO might intermediate wheat seedling de-etiolation aroused by light or hematin/CO. Intriguingly, we also discovered that SNP treatment could also induce the elevation of HO activities in time-dependent manner in wheat seedling greening process, which was indicated by Noriega et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Noriega2">[4]</xref> in soybean leaves. Based on these results, it is deduced that there exists the possible link between HO/CO and NO in wheat seedling de-etiolation in absence or presence of light.</p>
      <p>Phytochromes are traditionally known as biliprotein photoreceptors in plants and PHYA is predominantly responsible for de-etiolation. To investigate the role of phytochrome in light or hematin/CO induced de-etiolation, we analyzed the changes of Pfr content and discovered that the amount of Pfr and <italic>PHYA</italic> expression were more substantive in hematin/CO treated wheat seedlings in completely darkness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081470-g009">Fig. 9</xref>). Furthermore, continuous dark treatment (D&#x2192;D) also exhibited the same inducible effects. However, when wheat seedlings transferred from dark to light, both Pfr content and <italic>PHYA</italic> transcripts were decreased. From these data we could presume that hematin and CO accomplish wheat seedling de-etiolation process by increasing phytochrome expression through the following way: hematin and exogenous CO might activate endogenous HO activities to synthesize the precursors of the chromophores for the plant light-harvesting photobiliproteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Muramoto1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Muramoto2">[35]</xref>; another offspring, endogenous CO up-regulated the expression of phytochrome apoprotein genes. Afterwards, both of them linked together through a thiol-ether bond to form integrated phytochrome which could regulate chlorophyll accumulation through influencing the formation of 5-aminolevulinate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Masoner1">[36]</xref>. SNP, a potent NO donor have more obvious function on increasing the content of Pfr than that hematin and CO did; whereas, adding cPTIO led to the decrease. Therefore, it is speculated that phytochrome might mediate the HO/CO signal transduction and act as a downstream regulator of HO/CO and NO. The mechanism of HO/CO in regulating wheat seedlings greening in continuous darkness might be different from light inducible effects. Chlorophyll and heme are both synthesized in the plastid from ALA and share a common pathway between ALA and Proto IX <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-VonWettstein1">[37]</xref>. In the dark chlorophyll synthesis proceeds only as far as protochlorophyllide because the enzyme protochlorophyllide oxidoreductase (POR) has an absolute requirement for light. That etiolated seedlings transferred from dark to light activate the activity of POR, which finally leads to the chlorophyll accumulation. In the absence of light, the increase of HO activities accelerated the degradation of endogenous heme and consequently speeded up their common metabolic pathway, as a result, improving chlorophyll synthesis.</p>
      <p>To our knowledge, the present study provided the first description of endogenous HO/CO and NO in wheat seedling de-etiolation. Both hematin and SNP displayed effects on up-regulation of endogenous HO/CO system and NO releasing. The mutual induction effects suggested that there might be an inseparable relationship between HO/CO and NO during the greening process of wheat seedlings. Moreover, HO/CO system and NO might achieve the physiological function described above by modulating phytochrome transformation and synthesis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Plant Materials and growth condition</title>
        <p>Seeds of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) were carefully selected and sterilized with 5% NaClO for 15 minutes, then washed extensively with distilled water. These seeds firstly were germinated in plastic box wetted by distilled water at 28&#xB0;C in growth chamber in the darkness. After about 24 hours, all seeds burgeoning were moved to floating planks for about 3 days. Then the thriving seedlings were transferred to the plastic beakers and kept in growth chamber (12-h light period, 25&#xB0;C, humidity 50%&#xB1;4%; 12-h dark period, 18&#xB0;C, humidity 56%&#xB1;5%, MGC-300B, Shanghai Yiheng Technology Co., Ltd., China) with modified Hoagland solution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Gulick1">[38]</xref> containing 3 mM KNO<sub>3</sub>, 1 mM NH<sub>4</sub>H<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.5 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 5.5 mM Ca(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>, 50 mg of Fe-EDTA per liter (10% iron), 25 &#x3BC;M KCl, 12.5 &#x3BC;M H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3</sub>, 1 &#x3BC;M MnSO<sub>4</sub>, 1 &#x3BC;M ZnSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.25 &#x3BC;M CuSO<sub>4</sub>, and 2 &#x3BC;M H<sub>2</sub>MoO<sub>4</sub> for nearly 14 days. The irradiance was approximately 300 &#x3BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> provided by fluorescent lamps. The culture solution was renewed every other day until two fully expanded leaves appeared.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Chemicals</title>
        <p>All chemicals were purchased from Sigma (St Louis, MO, USA) unless otherwise stated. Sodium nitroprusside (SNP) was used at 0.1 mM as an NO donor. Hematin (H, C<sub>34</sub>H<sub>33</sub>N<sub>4</sub>O<sub>5</sub>Fe), was used as HO-1 inducer at concentrations of 1.0, 10, 100 &#x3BC;M. Also, Hemoglobin (Hb), obtained from Shanghai Boao Ltd., China, was chosen as the scavenger of CO/NO at the concentration of 0.1gL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Lamar1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Morita1">[39]</xref>. The compound 2-(4-carboxyphenyl)-4,4,5,5- tetramethylimidazoline-1-oxyl-3-oxide potassium salt (cPTIO) was used as a specific NO scavenger. <italic>N<sup>G</sup></italic>-nitro-L-arginine methylester hydrochloride (L-NAME) was used as the inhibitor of nitric oxide synthase (NOS) and the compound zinc protoporphyrin (ZnPPIX) was used as a potent inhibitor of HO-1. NO specific fluorophore 4,5-diaminofluorescein diacetate (DAF-2 DA) and AF 4-DA (4-amino fluorescein diacetate) was purchased from Calbiochem (San Diego, CA, USA), used at a final concentration of 10 &#x3BC;M <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-CorreaAragunde1">[40]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>CO-saturated aqueous solution preparation</title>
        <p>CO gas was prepared by heating concentrated sulfuric acid (H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) with formic acid (HCOOH) at the speed of 3&#x2013;5 seconds per drop. In our experiment, CO-saturated aqueous solution was freshly obtained by bubbling above CO gas gently through a glass tube into 300 ml of above Hoagland solution for about 30 min, a duration time long enough to make the solution saturated with CO. Then the saturated stock solution (100% of saturation) was immediately diluted with fresh prepared Hoagland solution to the concentration the experiment required (0.1, 1.0, 10 and 50% of saturation).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Treatments</title>
        <p>Wheat seedlings were grown in growth chamber until the second leaves were fully expanded nearly for 14 days. The further experimental design thus consisted of the following treatment groups: L&#x2192;L: stands for wheat seedlings were grown in normal condition. Other seedlings were kept in complete darkness for five days. After that, they were treated with different concentrations of hematin (1.0, 10, and 100 &#x3BC;&#x39C;) and CO-saturated aqueous solution (0.1, 1.0, 10, and 50%) for a few additional days in the dark (abbreviated to D&#x2192;D+H1.0, 10, and 100 or D&#x2192;D+CO0.1%, 1.0%, 10%, and 50%). Among them, 10 &#x3BC;&#x39C; hematin and 1.0% CO-saturated aqueous solution were chosen as the suitable treatment because of its better positive results, termed as D&#x2192;D+H and D&#x2192;D+CO in the following experiments. 100 &#x3BC;&#x39C; SNP treatment was brought into comparison (abbreviated to D&#x2192;D+S). D&#x2192;D stands for these five-day dark-treated seedlings were continuous kept in the darkness. When these etiolated seedlings were transferred to light again (300 &#x3BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>), it was abbreviated to D&#x2192;L. NOS inhibitor L-NAME (200 &#x3BC;M), NO scavenger cPTIO (100 &#x3BC;&#x39C;), NO/CO scavenger Hb (0.1 gL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>), and HO-1 inhibitor ZnPPIX (100 &#x3BC;&#x39C;) were used respectively. All groups were arranged in plastic beakers with at least three replicates. Additionally, all the containers were separated to avoid the CO gas escaping or any possible CO gas interference, and above solutions were renewed each day. All tests were carried out at least three independent sets of experiments with similar results.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Chlorophyll content determination</title>
        <p>Chlorophyll quantification was performed by the method described by Sa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Sa1">[41]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4f">
        <title>Heme oxygenase preparation and activity determination</title>
        <p>Preparation of crude membrane fractions and detection of HO activity were determined by the method of Liu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Liu1">[42]</xref>. HO activity was calculated by measuring the formation of biliverdin-IX&#x3B1; (BV). The concentration of BV was estimated using a molar absorption coefficient at 650 nm of 6.25 mM<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>cm<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> in 0.1 M HEPES-NaOH buffer (pH 7.2). One unit of activity (U) was calculated by taking the quantity of the enzyme to produce 1 nmol BV at 37&#xB0;C per 30 min.s</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4g">
        <title>Phytochrome content determination</title>
        <p>Phytochrome content was determined by the method of Lane et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Lane1">[43]</xref>. The phytochrome in wheat seedlings was assayed with a dual-wavelength difference photometer. The instrument measured the optical-density difference, &#x394;OD, between 730 and 800 mp, rather than the difference between 660 and 730 my, in order to eliminate the optical-density changes due to protochlorophyll transformations. The relative amounts of Pfr could be determined. After a given treatment, measurement of the sample would give a certain &#x394;OD reading, R1, on the instrument. The sample would then be irradiated with the actinic source of far-red light to convert any Pfr present to Pr and decrease the &#x394;OD reading to R2. The amount of Pfr would be equal to k (R1-R2), where k is a constant of proportionality. The difference between &#x394;OD readings is referred to as &#x394;(&#x394;OD).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4h">
        <title>Protein content determination</title>
        <p>Protein concentration was determined by the method of Bradford <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Bradford1">[44]</xref> using BSA as the standard.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4i">
        <title>Real-time RT-PCR analysis</title>
        <p>Real-time quantification RT-PCR reactions were performed in a step one plus real-time PCR system (Applied Biosystems, America) using the SYBR&#xAE; Premix Ex TaqTM (TaKaRa Bio Inc., Dalian, China) according to the manufacturer's instructions. The PCR reaction was performed using the following primers: for <italic>HO-1</italic> (GenBank ID: HM014348), (F: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2032;-AATACTGGGTTGGAGAGA-3&#x2032;</named-content> and R: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2032;-AGAAGTGGCAAATAAATG-3&#x2032;</named-content>); and for <italic>Actin</italic> (GenBank ID: AB181991), (F: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2032;-TCTGGTGATGGTGTGAGC-3&#x2032;</named-content> and R: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2032;-CGGTTGTTGTGAGGGAGT-3&#x2032;</named-content>). For <italic>PHYA</italic> (GenBank ID: AJ313099) (F: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2032;- TTACAGGGTATGATAGGG -3&#x2032;</named-content> and R: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2032;- AGTGGCTGGATAGTGC -3&#x2032;</named-content>). Gene-specific primers were designed with the software tool Primer Express (Applied Biosystems, Foster city, CA, USA). All reactions were set up in triplicate. Relative expression levels are presented as values relative to corresponding control sample at the indicated times, after normalization to <italic>Actin</italic> transcript levels.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4j">
        <title>NO content determination by using Greiss reagent</title>
        <p>NO content from wheat leaves was determined using the method described by Zhou et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Zhou1">[45]</xref>. Absorbance was assayed at 540 nm; NO content was calculated by comparison to a standard curve of NaNO<sub>2</sub>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4k">
        <title>Imaging of endogenous NO by LSCM</title>
        <p>In our experiment, 2.0&#x2013;2.5 mm transversal sections from the center of leaves, was further treated in the presence or absence of 1 mM cPTIO for 50 min, and then incubated with the specific fluorescent probe DAF-2 DA in 20 mM BES-KCL buffer (pH6.2) in darkness for 1 h. The extra probes were removed by washing the sections at 20 mM BES-KCL buffer three times for 15 min and then images were taken using a TCS-SP2 laser scanning confocal microscope (Leica lasertechnik Gmbh, Heidelberg, exciting with the 488 nm, and emission using 490&#x2013;530 nm for NO analysis). The negative probe AF 4-DA was also used as control. Experiments were repeated six times and similar results obtained. All manipulations were performed at 25&#xB0;C&#xB1;1&#xB0;C.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4l">
        <title>CO content determination</title>
        <p>The determination of CO content by gas chromatography and mass spectrometry (GC/MS) were carried out according to the method described by our previous report <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0081470-Liu1">[42]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4m">
        <title>Statistical analyses</title>
        <p>Each experiment was repeated at least three times with similar results. Values were expressed as means &#xB1; SE at least three replicates obtained from three independent experiments. Different measurements were subjected to analysis of variance (ANOVA) using SPSS with significances of <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05 and <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>Thanks Dr Evan Evans from the University of Tasmania, Australia, for his kind help in writing the manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Boardman1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boardman</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goodchild</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>Chlorophyll protein complexes and structure of mature and developing chloroplasts</article-title>. <source>Curr Top Bioener</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>109</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Tenhunen1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tenhunen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marver</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1968</year>) <article-title>The enzymatic conversion of heme to bilirubin by microsomal heme oxygenase</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>61</volume>: <fpage>748</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4386763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Noriega1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Noriega</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balestrasse</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Batlle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tomaro</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Heme oxygenase exerts a protective role against oxidative stress in soybean leaves</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>323</volume>: <fpage>1003</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15381099</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Noriega2">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Noriega</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yannarelli</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balestrasse</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Batlle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tomaro</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The effect of nitric oxide on heme oxygenase gene expression in soybean leaves</article-title>. <source>Planta</source><volume>226</volume>: <fpage>1155</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17569079</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Durski1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Durski</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The heme-oxygenase family required for phytochrome chromophore biosynthesis is necessary for proper photomorphogenesis in higher plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>126</volume>: <fpage>656</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402195</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Cherry1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hondred</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome requires the 6-kDa N-terminal domain for full biological activity</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>89</volume>: <fpage>5039</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1594611</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Quail1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome: a light-activated molecular switch that regulates plant gene expression</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Genet</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>389</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1812812</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Quail2">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boylan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parks</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Short</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Phytochromes: photosensory perception and signal transduction</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>268</volume>: <fpage>675</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7732376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Schfer1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sch&#xE4;fer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bowler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome-mediated photoperception and signal transduction in higher plants</article-title>. <source>EMBO Reports</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1042</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1048</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12429614</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Sharrock1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sharrock</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Novel phytochrome sequences in Arabidopsis thaliana: structure, evolution, and differential expression of a plant regulatory photoreceptor family</article-title>. <source>Genes &amp; Development</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1745</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2606345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Verma1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glatt</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ronnett</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Carbon monoxide: a putative neural messenger</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>259</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7678352</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Watts1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ponka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Effects of nitrogen monoxide and carbon monoxide on molecular and cellular iron metabolism: mirror-image effecter molecules that target iron</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source><volume>369</volume>: <fpage>429</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12423201</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Zhuo1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhuo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kandel</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Nitric oxide and carbon monoxide produce activity-dependent long-term synaptic enhancement in hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>260</volume>: <fpage>1946</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8100368</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Dekker1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hargrove</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Weedy adaptation in Setaria spp. V. Effects of gaseous environment on giant foxtail (Setaria faberii) (Poaceae) seed germination</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source><volume>89</volume>: <fpage>410</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21665636</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Cao1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007a</year>) <article-title>Involvement of carbon monoxide produced by heme oxygenase in ABA-induced stomatal closure in <italic>Vicia faba</italic> and its proposed signal transduction pathway</article-title>. <source>Chin Sci Bull</source><volume>52</volume>: <fpage>2365</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2373</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Cao2">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007b</year>) <article-title>Carbon monoxide promotes lateral root formation in rapeseed</article-title>. <source>J Integr Plant Biol</source><volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1007</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1016</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Han1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Carbon monoxide alleviates cadmium-induced oxidative damage by modulating glutathione metabolism in the roots of <italic>Medicago sativa</italic></article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source><volume>177</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18028301</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Xuan1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The heme oxygenase/carbon monoxide system is involved in the auxin-induced cucumber adventitious rooting process</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>148</volume>: <fpage>881</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>893</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18689445</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Beligni1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beligni</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lamattina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Nitric oxide stimulates seed germination and de-etiolation, and inhibits hypocotyl elongation, three light-inducible responses in plants</article-title>. <source>Planta</source><volume>210</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10664127</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Delledonne1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Delledonne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>NO news is good news for plants</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>390</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15922651</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Beligni2">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beligni</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lamattina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Nitric oxide in plants: The history is just beginning</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell &amp; Environ</source><volume>24</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>278</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Crawford1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tischner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heimer</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Response to Zemojtel, et al.: plant nitric oxide synthase: back to square one</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>526</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>527</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Zemojtel1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zemojtel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frohlich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palmieri</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kolanczyk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mikula</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Plant nitric oxide synthase: a never-ending story?</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>524</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17030145</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Wilks1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wilks</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name> (<year>1959</year>) <article-title>Carbon monoxide in green plants</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>129</volume>: <fpage>964</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>966</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13646627</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Siegel1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Renwick</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>1962</year>) <article-title>Formation of carbon monoxide during seed germination and seedling growth</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>137</volume>: <fpage>683</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17770955</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Lttge1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>L&#xFC;ttge</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Light-dependent net CO-evolution by C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> plants</article-title>. <source>Planta</source><volume>149</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24306193</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Tarr1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tarr</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zepp</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Direct carbon monoxide photoproduction from plant matter</article-title>. <source>J Geophys Res</source><volume>100</volume>: <fpage>11403</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11413</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Schade1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schade</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crutzen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>CO emissions from degrading plant matter (I)</article-title>. <source>Measurements Tellus B</source><volume>51</volume>: <fpage>889</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>908</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Emborg1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Emborg</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Noh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Multiple heme oxygenase family members contribute to the biosynthesis of the phytochrome chromophore in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>140</volume>: <fpage>856</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16428602</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Lamar1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lamar</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mahesh</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brann</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Regulation of gonadotrophin-releasing hormone (GnRH) secretion by heme molecules: a regulatory role for carbon monoxide?</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>137</volume>: <fpage>790</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8593832</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Xie1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>QS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Carbon monoxide enhances salt tolerance by nitric oxide-mediated maintenance of ion homeostasis and up-regulation of antioxidant defence in wheat seedling roots</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell &amp; Environ</source><volume>31</volume>: <fpage>1864</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1881</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Huang1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Carbon monoxide alleviates salt-induced oxidative damage in wheat seedling leaves</article-title>. <source>J Integr Plant Biol</source><volume>48</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>254</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Zhang1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Involvement of nitric oxide in light-mediated greening of barley seedlings</article-title>. <source>J Plant Physiol</source><volume>163</volume>: <fpage>818</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16777529</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Muramoto1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Muramoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kohchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis photomorphogenic mutant <italic>hy1</italic> is deficient in phytochrome chromophore biosynthesis as a result of a mutation in a plastid heme oxygenase</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10072395</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Muramoto2">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Muramoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsurui</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Terry</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kohchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Expression and biochemical properties of a ferredoxin-dependent heme oxygenase required for phytochrome chromophore synthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>130</volume>: <fpage>1958</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1966</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12481078</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Masoner1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Masoner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kasemir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Control of chlorophyll synthesis by phytochrome</article-title>. <source>Planta</source><volume>126</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>117</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-VonWettstein1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Von Wettstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gough</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kannangara</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Chlorophyll Biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant cell</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1039</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242396</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Gulick1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gulick</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dvo&#x159;&#xE1;k</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Gene induction and repression by salt treatment in roots of the salinity-sensitive Chinese Spring wheat and the salinity-tolerant Chinese Spring wheat Elytrigia elongate amphiploid</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>84</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16593798</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Morita1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perrella</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kourembanas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Smooth muscle cell-derived carbon monoxide is a regulator of vascular cGMP</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>92</volume>: <fpage>1475</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7878003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-CorreaAragunde1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Correa-Aragunde</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Graziano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lamattina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Nitric oxide plays a central role in determining lateral root development in tomato</article-title>. <source>Planta</source><volume>218</volume>: <fpage>900</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14716561</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Sa1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sa</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Carbon monoxide: a novel antioxidant against oxidative stress in wheat seedling leaves</article-title>. <source>J Integr Plant Biol</source><volume>49</volume>: <fpage>638</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>645</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Liu1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Carbon monoxide counteracts the inhibition of seed germination and alleviates oxidative damage caused by salt stress in <italic>Oryza sativa</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Sci</source><volume>172</volume>: <fpage>544</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>555</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Lane1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siegelman</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Firer</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>1963</year>) <article-title>Detection of Phytochrome in Green Plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>414</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16655807</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Bradford1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantization of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source><volume>72</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0081470-Zhou1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Nitric oxide is involved in abscisic acid-induced antioxidant activities in Stylosanthes guianensis</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source><volume>56</volume>: <fpage>3223</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16263901</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
