<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3841193</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-27550</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081606</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Transcriptional Reprogramming of Wheat and the Hemibiotrophic Pathogen <italic>Septoria tritici</italic> during Two Phases of the Compatible Interaction</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Transcriptomics of the Wheat-<italic>S.tritici</italic> Interaction</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Fen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Wanshun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>J&#xF8;rgensen</surname>
            <given-names>Hans J. L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Plant and Environmental Sciences, Faculty of Science, University of Copenhagen, Frederiksberg, Denmark</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>BGI-Tech, BGI, Shenzhen, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Yong-Hwan</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Seoul National University, Korea, Republic Of</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>yangf@plen.ku.dk</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: FY. Performed the experiments: FY WL HJLJ. Analyzed the data: FY WL HJLJ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: FY WL HJLJ. Wrote the manuscript: FY WL. </p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>11</issue>
      <elocation-id>e81606</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Yang et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The disease septoria leaf blotch of wheat, caused by fungal pathogen <italic>Septoria tritici</italic>, is of worldwide concern. The fungus exhibits a hemibiotrophic lifestyle, with a long symptomless, biotrophic phase followed by a sudden transition to necrotrophy associated with host necrosis. Little is known about the systematic interaction between fungal pathogenicity and host responses at specific growth stages and the factors triggering the transition. In order to gain some insights into global transcriptome alterations in both host and pathogen during the two phases of the compatible interaction, disease transition was monitored using pathogenesis-related gene markers and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signature prior to RNA-Seq. Transcriptome analysis revealed that the slow symptomless growth was accompanied by minor metabolic responses and slightly suppressed defences in the host, whereas necrotrophic growth was associated with enhanced host responses involving energy metabolism, transport, signalling, defence and oxidative stress as well as a decrease in photosynthesis. The fungus expresses distinct classes of stage-specific genes encoding potential effectors, probably first suppressing plant defence responses/facilitating the symptomless growth and later triggering life style transition and inducing host necrosis/facilitating the necrotrophic growth. Transport, signalling, anti-oxidative stress mechanisms and apoplastic nutrient acquisition play important roles in the entire infection process of <italic>S. tritici</italic>. Our findings uncover systematic <italic>S. tritici</italic>-induced expression profiles of wheat related to specific fungal infection strategies and provide a transcriptome resource for studying both hosts and pathogens in plant-Dothideomycete interactions. </p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by a postdoctoral grant from the Danish Research Council for Technology and Production (11-105997) to Dr. Fen Yang. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><italic>Septoria tritici</italic> (teleomorph <italic>Mycosphaerella graminicola</italic>) is the causal agent of septoria leaf blotch, a foliar disease of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) that poses a significant threat to global food production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. <italic>S. tritici</italic> penetrates host leaves through the stomata and grows slowly as filamentous hyphae in the intercellular spaces between the wheat mesophyll cells, typically up to 9&#x2013;11 days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Subsequently, the fungus exhibits a rapid switch to necrotrophy immediately prior to symptom expression at 12&#x2013;20 days after penetration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. This transition is associated with induction of host defence responses that have been suggested to share characteristics with host programmed cell death (PCD) and differential regulation of signalling pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The necrotrophic process involves cell-wall degradation and accumulation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, resulting in massive collapse of mesophyll tissue, leakage of nutrients from dying plant cells into the apoplastic spaces, rapid increase of fungal biomass and sporulation in characteristic necrotic foliar blotches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The key features of this fungus, distinguishing it from most other current models, are a very long period of symptomless growth prior to a rapid transition to necrotrophy and that it remains extracellular with respect to host cells during the entire infection process without forming any specialised feeding structures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. However, the molecular basis underlying this transition remains unclear. This basis includes what the pathogen relies on to facilitate the long initial symptomless growth and subsequently trigger the transition of its lifestyle associated with host cell death and how the fungus copes with the activation of plant responses during the different infection phases. To address these issues, several investigations have attempted to understand <italic>S. tritici</italic> gene function, particularly the role of small secreted protein effectors. Likewise, fungal transcriptome profiles have been studied in adaption to environmental changes as well as host responses in cultivars with different susceptibility to infection. The research has been facilitated by the publication of the full genome sequence of <italic>S. tritici</italic>, revealing 10933 genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>Effectors are believed to enable colonisation by the pathogen by interfering with a variety of plant-encoded virulence targets and to effectively suppress or activate defence responses. They can be recognised by disease resistance proteins, which subsequently trigger plant immunity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In <italic>S. tritici</italic>, it has been suggested that the effectors may trigger disease transition, appearance of disease lesions and host cell death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. The only effector described in <italic>S. tritici</italic> is a LysM homologue shown to contribute to virulence in wheat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Genes encoding secreted proteins with intragenic coding repeats within <italic>S. tritici</italic> populations were suggested to play potential roles as effectors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. <italic>In silico</italic> prediction of the secretome based on the full genome sequence identified 492 candidate virulence effectors and revealed a protein family encoding secreted (chloro)peroxidases, which is expanded within all family members of Mycosphaerellaceae [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Transcription profiling of <italic>S. tritici in planta</italic> using a microarray containing 2563 genes or expressed sequence tag (EST) libraries identified genes encoding cell-wall-degrading enzymes (CWDEs) and genes involved in signal transduction and transport [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] and revealed fungal physiological adaption with respect to membrane transport, chemical and oxidative stress mechanisms and metabolism during the rapid growth transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. However, these transcriptome studies provide limited or ambiguous information on fungal pathogenicity based on a low number of identifications (150 genes in the biotrophic phase and max. 450 genes in the necrotrophic phase). </p>
      <p>Studies on host responses in the wheat-<italic>S. tritici</italic> interaction revealed that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is important in the defence of wheat against the pathogen. During a compatible interaction, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> levels increased dramatically and peaked at the late necrotrophic stage, implying that this was likely a stress-response and not involved in defence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Other responses reported include expression of a wheat protein disulfide isomerase gene and pathogenesis-related (PR) genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] as well as structural defence responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Biochemical investigations furthermore showed DNA laddering, translocation of cytochrome c from mitochondria to the cytosol, loss of host cell membrane integrity, degradation of host total RNA and differential regulation of host mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathways during symptom development in a compatible interaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Recently, large-scale shotgun proteomics and phosphoproteomics have been conducted on <italic>S. tritici</italic>-infected wheat leaves from the symptomless stage, suggesting that resistance is likely related to rapidly and intensively triggered signal transduction cascades resulting in a multiple-level activation of transcription and translation processes of defence responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. </p>
      <p>Transcriptomics is an important tool to investigate the regulatory mechanisms between the host and the pathogen as it can shed light on the shifts of metabolic and cellular processes due to the interaction. Among the various technologies of transcriptome profiling, RNA-Seq has become a revolutionary tool and has recently been employed in the study of plant-pathogen interactions. It can distinguish between paralogous genes, detect and quantify transcripts of low or high abundance and identify transcript sequence polymorphisms and novel trans-splicing and splice isoforms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Moreover, there is no strict requirement for a reference genome sequence, which is required in hybridization-based approaches such as microarray. Although transcriptome studies have been carried out in <italic>S. tritici in vitro</italic> and <italic>in planta</italic>, limited information about fungal gene expression has been obtained, in particular during the initial symptomless stage, due to low fungal biomass hardly detected by previous technologies. In addition, lack of large-scale systematic studies of host responses to <italic>S. tritici</italic> at RNA level strongly encouraged us to investigate the host transcriptome responses to infection. </p>
      <p>Therefore, we used RNA-Seq in the present study to follow the transcriptional reprogramming with a key focus on both host and fungus simultaneously at distinct stages of the compatible interaction. These stages and disease transition were clearly defined by characterisation of fungal biomass, two essential plant PR genes/proteins (&#x3B2;-1,4-glucanase and chitinase) and ROS prior to transcriptome analysis. For the first time, we were not only able to study transcriptome changes (approx. 1800 transcripts) across the different growth phases in <italic>S. tritici</italic>, but also to obtain broad-spectrum insights into the host molecular responses corresponding to the distinct lifestyle phases of this pathogen. To our best knowledge, this is the first RNA-Seq study performed in a member of the Dothideomycetes. Our study has considerably expanded the knowledge obtained from previous gene expression investigations in <italic>S. tritici</italic>. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2.1">
        <title>Plant growth and inoculation</title>
        <p>Growth of the susceptible wheat cv. Sevin, preparation of inoculum of <italic>S. tritici</italic> isolate IPO323 and inoculation were performed as described by Shetty et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Control plants were mock-inoculated with water. Approximately 20 leaves were collected from two separate pots, serving as one biological replicate. Two biological replicates for inoculated and control samples were harvested every day from 3 to 14 days after inoculation (dai) and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen. The leaf samples were ground in liquid nitrogen and stored at -80 &#xB0;C until use. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2.2">
        <title>Histochemical staining for H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and visualization of fungal structures</title>
        <p><italic>In vivo</italic> detection of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> was carried out using 3,3&#x2019;-diaminobenzidine (DAB, Sigma) as described by Shetty et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The leaves were then cleared, stained by 0.1% Evans blue in lactoglycerol to visualise the fungal surface structures and studied by light microscopy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2.3">
        <title>Quantification of fungal biomass</title>
        <p>Total DNA was extracted from infected and control samples using the DNeasy Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen, Venlo, The Netherlands). Fungal DNA was determined by qPCR using primers for <italic>S. tritici</italic> mating type gene 1-1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] with total DNA as template as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2.4">
        <title>Enzyme assay and western blotting</title>
        <p>Water-soluble protein was extracted in 50 mM sodium acetate (pH 5.2) at 4 &#xB0;C. Protein concentration in the extracts was determined by the Bio-Rad Protein Assay (Bio-Rad) with bovine serum albumin as standard. &#x3B2;-1,3-glucanase activity was assayed as described by Shetty et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Briefly, protein samples were incubated with 0.1% (w/v) laminarin in 0.05 M sodium acetate buffer (pH 5.2) for 15 min at 37 &#xB0;C. The reaction was stopped by adding DNS reagent containing 0.5% (w/v) 3,5-dinitrosalicylic acid (Sigma) and 15% (w/v) potassium sodium tartrate tetrahydrate (Sigma) followed by boiling for 10 min. The absorbance was measured in an ELISA-reader at 540 nm. A standard curve relating the amount of glucose equivalents to the absorbance at 540 nm was used to determine the activity. Chitinase activity was measured by the Chitinase Assay Kit (Sigma) following the manufacturer&#x2019;s protocol. Five &#xB5;g protein were separated on Criterion<sup>TM</sup> XT Precast Gels (12% Bis-Tris, Bio-Rad) followed by blotting to nitrocellulose membranes (Whatman). Western blotting using rabbit antibodies against barley chitinase (kindly provided by David B. Collinge, University of Copenhagen) was performed as described by Yang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2.5">
        <title>RNA extraction and qPCR</title>
        <p>RNA extraction, gDNA removal, cDNA synthesis and qPCR were performed as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Primers for genes encoding wheat &#x3B2;-1,3-glucanase and chitinase were used according to Shetty et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. The wheat 25S rRNA gene (Forward primer: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2019;-AAGGCCGAAGAGGAGAAAGGT-3&#x2019;</named-content>; Reversed primer: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x2019;-CGTCCCTTAGGATCGGCTTAC-3&#x2019;</named-content>) served as reference gene. Relative expression of genes was determined using the formula: relative expression = 2<sup>-(&#x394;Ct target gene - &#x394;Ct reference gene)</sup> where Ct refers to the threshold cycle in PCR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. All relative expression values of genes are reported as means &#xB1;SD. Analysis to reveal significant differences in gene expression in infected Sevin <italic>versus</italic> the respective controls at each time point was performed by Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic>-test.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2.6">
        <title>Construction of cDNA library, data filtering and transcript assembly</title>
        <p>Total RNA (minimal 10 &#xB5;g, 400 ng &#xB5;l<sup>-1</sup>) was extracted from pooled leaf powder from two biological samples for each treatment using the Spectrum<sup>TM</sup> Plant Total RNA Kit (Sigma). RNA samples were subjected to DNase (Sigma) digestion to remove remaining DNA. mRNA was purified and enriched from total RNA samples by using poly-T oligo-coated magnetic beads (Invitrogen). Following purification and fragmentation, first-strand cDNA was generated using Superscript II reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen) and random hexamer primers. The cDNA was further converted into double stranded DNA using a strand-specific method according to Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. After quality control of the cDNA libraries, pair-end sequencing analysis was carried out via Illumina HiSeq&#x2122; 2000 at the Beijing Genomics Institute (Shenzhen, China) according to the Illumina manufacturer&#x2019;s protocol.</p>
        <p>To ensure the accuracy of subsequent analysis, raw sequences were cleaned by removal of adaptors and sequencing errors. The reads containing the sequencing adaptor, more than 5% unknown nucleotides and more than 30% bases of quality value less than 10, were eliminated. This output was termed &#x2018;clean reads&#x2019;, which was used for alignment. All the clean reads were deposited in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) and can be accessed in the Short Read Archive (SRA) linking to BioProject accession number: 196595. Prior to <italic>de novo</italic> assembly, the low-quality nucleotides at 3-ends were trimmed using a customer Perl script (CONDETRI: http://code.google.com/p/condetri) with the following parameters: hq=20, lq=10, frac=0.8, lfrac=0.1, minlen=40, mh=4, ml=1 and sc=64 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. To reduce the data complexity, two groups were generated from the clean reads from control (C<sub>4</sub>, C<sub>10</sub> and C<sub>13</sub>) and fungal infected (I<sub>4</sub>, I<sub>10</sub> and I<sub>13</sub>) samples for separate <italic>de novo</italic> assembly. The publicly available program Trinity (trinityrnaseq_r2012-05-18; http://trinityrnaseq.sourceforge.net/) was used for <italic>de novo</italic> transcriptome assembly of either group of trimmed clean reads to generate a set of contigs/transcripts with the following parameters: min_glue=2, SS_lib_type=RF, V=10, edge-thr=0.05, min_kmer_cov=3, path_reinforcement_distance=80 and group_pairs_distance=250 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. After the contigs from all samples were combined, the redundancy of contigs was removed and the contigs with partly overlap were elongated by the TGICL and Phrap assemblers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. The following parameters were used to ensure quality of assembly: a minimum of 95% identity between contigs, a minimum of 35 overlapping bases, a minimum of 35 scores and a maximum of 20 unmatched overhanging bases at sequence ends. Finally, based on the sequence similarity, the transcripts were divided into two classes: clusters (prefixed with &#x2018;CL&#x2019;) and singletons (prefixed with &#x2018;unigene&#x2019;). In each &#x2018;CL&#x2019;, the sequence similarity between transcripts was more than 70% and the transcripts were splice isoforms from one gene or paralogous gene.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2.7">
        <title>Identification of fungal transcripts, sequence annotation and bioinformatics analysis</title>
        <p>To identify the fungal transcripts, we BLAST searched all transcripts in the S. <italic>tritici</italic> genome (http://genome.jgi-psf.org/Mycgr3/Mycgr3.home.html). More than 80% in sequence similarity with regard to the alignment length was required to be considered as a fungal transcript. BLAST search against the fungal genome using a threshold of 50% similarity was performed as well. Fungal proteins were assessed for signal peptides using SignalP (http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/SignalP). For annotation, wheat and fungal transcripts, respectively, were aligned to four public databases [non-redundant protein database (Nr) in NCBI, non-redundant nucleotide database (Nt) in NCBI, Swiss-Prot and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathway database] by BLAST (E-value &lt;10<sup>-5</sup>). Gene ontology (GO) classification was analysed by the Blast2GO software (v2.5.0) based on Nr annotation.</p>
        <p>After annotation, the clean reads of each sample were mapped to all fungal and wheat transcripts using the SOAPaligner/soap2 software (BGI, China), allowing mismatches of no more than three bases, to obtain the transcripts from each sample. To minimize the influence of sequencing depth between samples, the total number of mapped reads was normalised by multiplying with a normalisation factor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Expression level of the transcript was based on the number of unique match reads calculated and normalised to fragments per kilobase per million mapped fragments (FPKM) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Analysis of differentially expressed wheat transcripts was performed as described by Chen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>], which was based on the Poisson distribution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>] and normalisation for differences in sequencing depth between samples and gene length. A threshold of FPKM &gt;2 in at least one sample, false discovery rate (FDR) &lt;0.05 and at least two-fold change in FPKM of the transcript from infected <italic>versus</italic> control samples at minimum one time point was used to define differentially expressed wheat transcripts (performed by the in-house Perl script).</p>
        <p>Principal component analysis (PCA) of sequencing data from all samples was performed by R script using log<sub>2</sub>FPKM values of transcripts in the samples. The expression profiles of the differentially expressed wheat transcripts [log<sub>2</sub>Ratio(infected/control)] and fungal transcripts (log<sub>2</sub>FPKM; FPKM&gt;2 at minimum one time point) over the time course were determined by clustering analysis based on the k-means method using Euclidean distance. Heat map analysis of the differentially expressed wheat transcripts [log<sub>2</sub>Ratio(infected/control)] over the time course was performed using R script.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3.1">
        <title>Development of a bioassay to determine the disease transition</title>
        <p>Given that the period of symptomless growth of <italic>S. tritici</italic> in wheat leaves can vary between experiments ranging from one week to several weeks and disease symptoms (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s001">Figure S1</xref>) are not uniform between leaves, we used the characteristic features of the biotrophic and necrotrophic phases in a bioassay to enable an interaction transcriptome analysis in the two distinct phases. The bioassay was based on characterisation of fungal biomass, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation and plant PR-genes/proteins (&#x3B2;-1,4-glucanase and chitinase). The onset of a measurable increase in <italic>S. tritici</italic> growth has been shown to occur at day 9 and 10 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Shetty et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] additionally reported dramatically enhanced expression of &#x3B2;-1,3-glucanase and chitinase genes from 9 dai followed by extensive H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation, cell collapse and appearance of macroscopic symptoms from 12 dai during the compatible interaction. Therefore, we performed these assays over time in the compatible interaction to define the disease transition state. In the present study, fungal hyphae penetrated the stomata in the epidermis directly causing relatively little H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation up to day 8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Increased accumulation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in the substomatal cavities correlated with arrest of the progressing hypha was observed by day 9 and 10 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g001">Figure 1</xref>), when strongly enhanced PR-gene expression and activity occurred in response to the fungus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g002">Figure 2B&#x2013;D</xref>). From 12 dai, the massive H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation in the mesophyll and hyphal development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g001">Figure 1</xref>) were consistent with a significant increase in the levels of fungal biomass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). These results collectively show that following a long period of slow symptomless growth, the fungus switched to necrotrophy by day 9&#x2013;10, advancing the increase in the biomass and massive H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production by day 12. </p>
        <fig id="pone-0081606-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081606.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Detection of hydrogen peroxide in <italic>S. tritici</italic>-infected wheat leaves from 3 to 14 dai.</title>
            <p>DAB was used for staining H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (red-brown staining). Fungal surface structures were stained with Evans blue. Arrows indicate attempted fungal penetration through the stomata. </p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081606.g001"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0081606-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081606.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The bioassay to follow disease transition from 3 to 14 dai.</title>
            <p>(A) Fungal biomass expressed as content of <italic>S. tritici</italic> DNA. Significant increases (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in levels of fungal DNA are indicated by asterisks. (B) Wheat &#x3B2;-1,3-glucanase and chitinase gene expression analysed by qPCR. (C) &#x3B2;-1,3-glucanase and chitinase protein activities expressed as released glucose (&#x3BC;M) and OD<sub>405</sub> measurement based on the assays, respectively. Significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) between infected and control samples are indicated by asterisks. (D) Chitinase protein expression in protein extracts from control (upper panel) and <italic>S. tritici</italic>-infected leaves (lower panel) analysed by western blotting. Bands indicate chitinase. Representatives of two biological replicates at each time point are shown for the control and infected plants.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081606.g002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3.2">
        <title>A snapshot of transcript profiles during the wheat-<italic>S. tritici</italic> interaction</title>
        <p>It is believed that the changes of lifestyle in a fungal pathogen and process of disease development are accompanied by stage-specific molecular events [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. To gain comprehensive information on the molecular and physiological bases during particular stages of the interaction between wheat and <italic>S. tritici</italic>, we explored the complexity of transcriptional reprogramming of both host and pathogen at three time points (day 4, 10 and 13) by RNA-Seq analysis. The time points were selected based on the bioassay of marker genes/proteins and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation and represented the initial symptomless phase, the intermediate transition stage and the necrotrophic phase, respectively. </p>
        <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0081606-t001">Table 1</xref> summarises the sequencing data from <italic>S. tritici</italic>-infected wheat leaves and their respective controls. The mRNA sequencing workflow is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s002">Figure S2</xref>. After the pre-processing of the reads, we obtained more than 12 million clean pair-end sequencing reads and 2G high-quality bases (Q20 bases approximately 97%) from both control samples and the mixed transcriptome samples (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0081606-t001">Table 1</xref>). In order to conduct dual sequencing analysis without the host reference genome, we used the <italic>de novo</italic> assembly method for control and infected samples separately. In total, 88770 non-redundant transcripts were obtained from all the samples including 12695 clusters (38680 transcripts) and 50090 singletons, the total length and N50 length of which were 63937118 bp and 1109 bp, respectively. Subsequently, we filtered the fungal transcripts by mapping all assembled transcripts to the fungal genome, resulting in identification of 1829 and 1811 fungal transcripts with a threshold of 50% and 80% sequence similarity, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s005">Table S1</xref>). In total, 313 fungal transcripts encoded proteins that were predicted to contain signal peptides. Functional categories were assigned to all annotated transcripts using GO classification and KEGG pathway analysis, resulting in 67610 and 1626 annotated wheat and fungal transcripts, respectively. Fungal (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s005">Table S1</xref>) and wheat (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s006">Tables S2, S3</xref>) transcripts with known function were grouped into 14 and 19 GO functional categories based on GO biological processes as well as 90 and 127 pathways, respectively. </p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0081606-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081606.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Overview of sequencing transcriptome data from wheat leaves.</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>4</sub></th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>10</sub></th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>13</sub></th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">I<sub>4</sub></th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">I<sub>10</sub></th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">I<sub>13</sub></th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of reads</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12330423</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12375478</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12583655</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12757779</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12426764</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13020331</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total base pairs (Mbp)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2220</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2228</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2265</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2297</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2237</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2344</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q20 (%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.65</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.84</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.61</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.43</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.06</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.12</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total number of contigs</td>
                <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">89315</td>
                <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">59389</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of contigs (bp)</td>
                <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">70551835</td>
                <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">31332619</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N50 length of contigs (bp)</td>
                <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">1233</td>
                <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">692</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of mapped fungal transcripts</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1578</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1692</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1822</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of wheat transcripts </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81976</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79407</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79642</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79032</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77927</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75461</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highly expressed fungal transcripts </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">761</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highly expressed wheat transcripts </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10158</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11908</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9563</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9372</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12715</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13690</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>The transcripts with FPKM&gt;10 are considered highly expressed. C<sub>4</sub>, control at 4 dai; C<sub>10</sub>, control at 10 dai; C<sub>13</sub>, control at 13 dai; I<sub>4</sub>, S<italic>. tritici</italic>-infected wheat at 4 dai; I<sub>10</sub>, S<italic>. tritici</italic>-infected wheat at 10 dai; I<sub>13</sub>, S<italic>. tritici</italic>-infected wheat at 13 dai.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Mapping the reads of each sample to wheat and fungal transcripts resulted in the identification of 1578, 1692 and 1822 fungal transcripts from infected samples at 4, 10 and 13 dai, respectively, as well as approximately 80000 non-redundant plant transcripts from each sample (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0081606-t001">Table 1</xref>). Nine, eleven and thirty-two low-expressed transcripts encoding tubulins, ATPases, ribosomal proteins and cytochrome b, respectively, were mapped as fungal transcripts from control samples, which is very likely due to the homology of these conserved genes between plant and the fungus. To further examine an overall relationship of the transcriptome data from different samples and effects of both fungal infection and interaction phases, PCA was conducted and clearly revealed that the greatest changes in host transcriptome were caused by the fungal infection following the interaction process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g003">Figure 3</xref>). In particular, the 13 day-infected sample was separated from all other samples by principal component 1, accounting for 73.9% of the variance, strongly suggesting the accelerated host-pathogen interplay during the necrotrophic stage.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0081606-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081606.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Principal component analysis of the transcriptome data.</title>
            <p>Principal components (PCs) 1, 2 and 3 account for 73.9, 11.6 and 7% of the variance, respectively. C<sub>4</sub>, control at 4 dai; C<sub>10</sub>, control at 10 dai; C<sub>13</sub>, control at 13 dai; I<sub>4</sub>, S. <italic>tritici</italic>-infected wheat at 4 dai; I<sub>10</sub>, S. <italic>tritici</italic>-infected wheat at 10 dai; I<sub>13</sub>, S. <italic>tritici</italic>-infected wheat at 13 dai.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081606.g003"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3.3">
        <title>Fungal transcriptome during the compatible interaction</title>
        <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g004">Figure 4</xref> presents ten clusters of expression profiles of fungal transcripts as well as functional category distribution frequencies of the transcripts in each cluster. Not surprisingly, the transcripts with known function annotated in metabolic and cellular processes were dominating in each cluster. The clusters fell into three groups based on the major profiling over the time course: group A consisted of cluster 1, 5, 9 and 10, the majority of 660 transcripts showing constant abundance; group B consisted of cluster 2, 3, 6, 7 and 8, the majority of 963 transcripts showing increased abundance; group C consisted of cluster 4, the majority of 206 transcripts showing decreased abundance at 10 dai and highest abundance at 13 dai. A substantially higher number of transcripts annotated in signalling, responses to stimuli, reproduction, localisation, metabolic and cellular processes and cellular component organisation or biogenesis were represented in group B compared to other two groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g004">Figure 4</xref>). In addition, several transcripts involved in primary and energy metabolism and a considerable number of highly abundant transcripts annotated as ribosomal proteins were present in group B (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s005">Table S1</xref>). The FPKM values of housekeeping transcripts such as ribosomal and tubulin transcripts increased approximately 10-fold at 13 dai compared to the symptomless stage. These data suggest a highly active metabolic growth and an increase in fungal biomass at the destructive necrotrophic phase. </p>
        <fig id="pone-0081606-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081606.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Functional category distribution in the ten expression clusters of fungal transcripts.</title>
            <p>The fungal transcripts were identified from <italic>S. tritici</italic>-infected wheat at 4, 10 and 13 dai. Expression level of the transcripts was calculated by log<sub>2</sub>FPKM. Histogram representation of the category distribution is expressed as percentage of the amount of transcripts belonging to the cluster. Transcripts coding for unknown products were included in the analysis. The clusters fall into three groups (A, B and C) based on the major profiling over the time course.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081606.g004"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Since the transcripts with the highest expression levels at specific growth stages likely play important roles in the control of the disease transition, we selected several transcripts with the highest expression levels at 4 dai (biotrophy) or 13 dai (necrotrophy) and listed them in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0081606-t002">Table 2</xref>. Besides the transcripts annotated as hypothetical proteins, most of which contained signal peptides and more than six cysteines, the transcripts were involved in pathogenesis and virulence, metabolism, signalling, transport, stress and defence, cell adhesion and cell wall degradation and remodelling (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0081606-t002">Table 2</xref>). Notably, these highly expressed transcripts at 4 and 13 dai precisely belonged to group A and B, respectively, indicating that the transition of <italic>S. tritici</italic> lifestyle was likely accompanied and regulated by the expression of stage-specific sets of genes. More interestingly, although seven transcripts involved in host cell wall degradation including glycoside hydrolase families 5, 16 and 76 in group A and glycoside hydrolase families 3 and clan CH-D in group C were identified, none of them were of high abundance at either stage (FPKM &lt;8; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s005">Table S1</xref>). </p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0081606-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081606.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Expression patterns of selected <italic>S. tritici</italic> transcripts during infection.</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th colspan="3" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>FPKM</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>ID</bold>
                </th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Annotation</bold>
                </th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>4 d</bold>
                </th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>10 d</bold>
                </th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>13 d</bold>
                </th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Biological process</bold>
                </th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>S</bold>
                </th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>C</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="8" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Transcripts highly expressed (FPKM &#x2265; 8) at 4 d</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96543</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydrophobin 2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathogenesis and virulence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70312</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peptidase S8 and S53</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74298</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucoamylase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77672</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Esterase/lipase/thioesterase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81692</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x3B2;-1,6-N-acetylglucosaminyltransferase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104538</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x3B2;-1,6-N-acetylglucosaminyltransferase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86867</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NADPH-dependent FMN reductase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100165</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fumarate lyase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108219</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autophagy-related protein 8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109517</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbohydrate kinase, PfkB</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102849</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homeobox transcription factor prospero</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44262</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiamine biosynthesis Thi4 protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104937</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyridoxamine 5'-phosphate oxidase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104409</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Similar to bacterial rhodopsin</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signalling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109991 93710</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serine/threonine protein kinase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">247.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signalling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99917</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serine/threonine protein kinase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signalling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97868</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tyrosine protein kinase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signalling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110667</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAS-domain protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">222.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signalling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39898</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aquaporin</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42411</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPR1/FUN34/yaaH membrane protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58200</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC transporter</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76071</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphate transporter</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105313</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sugar transporter superfamily</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64952</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyclophilin</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72265</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyclophilin</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106153</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbohydrate-binding WSC</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59219</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haem peroxidase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94368</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroperoxidase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101235</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroperoxidase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103393</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allergen V5/Tpx-1 related</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103593</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu<sup>2+</sup>/Zn<sup>2+</sup> superoxide dismutase 1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105791</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aldehyde dehydrogenase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101210</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zinc-containing alcohol dehydrogenase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56432</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fasciclin </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell adhesion</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104730</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">von Willebrand factor </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell adhesion</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100647</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chitinase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell wall degradation and remodelling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106219</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycolipid anchored surface protein GAS1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell wall degradation and remodelling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90001</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yeast PIR protein repeat-like</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell wall degradation and remodelling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69789</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94290</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106329</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103950</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111606</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="8" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Transcripts highly expressed (FPKM &#x2265; 10) at 13 d</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39947</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerato-platanin</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Host immune system</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105487</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peptidoglycan-binding LysM</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathogenesis and virulence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111221</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peptidoglycan-binding LysM</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathogenesis and virulence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88451</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Necrosis-inducing protein NPP1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathogenesis and virulence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104853</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ubiquinol-cytochrome C reductase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107092</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x3B2;-1,6-N-acetylglucosaminyltransferase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108724</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cysteine peptidase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95071</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleoside diphosphate kinase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57734</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G-protein beta WD-40 repeat</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signalling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86648</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G-protein beta WD-40 repeat</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signalling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69026</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Translationally controlled tumor protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signalling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78859</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EGF-like</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signalling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103900</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EGF-like</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signalling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106452</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serine/threonine protein kinase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signalling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100205</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phox-like</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signalling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65946</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amino acid permease</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73144</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ammonium transporter</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77435</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Porin, eukaryotic type</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65963</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytochrome b561 </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90089</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ankyrin</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82936</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plastocyanin-like</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98411</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytochrome P450</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55916</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutathione S-transferase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71387</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkyl hydroperoxide reductase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101587</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thioredoxin</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104975</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peroxiredoxin</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72449</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heat shock protein Hsp70</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83835</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heat shock protein Hsp70</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress and defence</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103427</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">von Willebrand factor</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell adhesion</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106780</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">von Willebrand factor</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell adhesion</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102341</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycolipid anchored surface protein GAS1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell wall degradation and remodelling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102481</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yeast PIR protein repeat-like</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell wall degradation and remodelling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104794</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chitinase</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell wall degradation and remodelling</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44596</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kinesin, motor region</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locomotion</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83064</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79161</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89705</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92097</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97031</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110220</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102792</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">277.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104404</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104444</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105825</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105826</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108482</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107904</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107286</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>FPKM indicates the expression level of the transcript. Most of the hypothetical proteins are small cysteine-rich proteins.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>S, SignalP; C, cluster number in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g004">Figure 4</xref>; d, days after inoculation.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Furthermore, since fungal secreted proteins may have potential roles as effectors, 313 transcripts encoding proteins containing signal peptides, the majority of which were hypothetical proteins, peptidases, glycoside hydrolases, antioxidants, kinases, heat shock proteins and oxidoreductases, were clustered to obtain the expression patterns (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s003">Figure S3A</xref>). Their expression levels increased (clusters 1, 3, 4, 7&#x2013;10) or remained constant (clusters 2, 5 and 6) over the time course. Likewise, of 492 candidate virulence effectors previously predicted <italic>in silico</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], 246 fungal transcripts were identified in the present study with increased or constant expression levels during infection (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s003">Figure S3B</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s005">Table S1</xref>). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3.4">
        <title>Wheat leaf transcriptome in response to infection</title>
        <p>In total, 33314 wheat transcripts, fulfilling the selection criteria, were identified in response to the pathogen (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s006">Table S2</xref>). Cluster analysis and category distribution were performed to assess the overall patterns of host transcriptome changes over the time course of infection (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s004">Figure S4</xref>). Clusters 1 and 3 contained 3266 transcripts mainly regulated by the fungus at 4 dai. Clusters 5, 6, 7 and 9 contained 16543 transcripts mainly regulated at 13 dai. Clusters 2, 4 and 8 contained 11324 transcripts mainly regulated at 10 dai. Additionally, cluster 10 contained 2181 transcripts down-regulated and up-regulated at 4 and 13 dai, respectively. The major transcripts in each cluster were annotated in signalling, response to stimuli, reproduction, regulation of biological process, metabolic and cellular processes, locomotion, localisation, development, cellular component organisation or biogenesis and biological adhesion. Considerably higher numbers of transcripts involved in metabolism, transport, defence and stress, signalling and cellular component organisation changed in abundance at 10 and 13 dai (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s004">Figure S4</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s006">Table S2</xref>), suggesting a strong induction of metabolic and defence-activities from 10 dai, which was associated with increased H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g001">Figure 1</xref>). </p>
        <p>To gain further insights into the responses of specific functions of host genes in fungal infection at different stages, we carried out a heat map analysis of the transcripts. This included genes specifically annotated in primary metabolism (e.g., metabolism of carbohydrates, nitrogen and amino acids as well as photosynthesis), transport (e.g., ATPases, ABC transporters, aquaporins and sugar, amino acid, peptide, nucleic acid and lipid transporters) and signalling [e.g., membrane-bond receptors, receptor kinases, G proteins, phospholipids, calcium-dependent protein kinases, MAPK pathways, WRKYs and other transcription factors, hormone pathways (salicylic acid, jasmonate, ethylene, auxin, gibberellic acid and brassinosteroid)] as well as genes involved in stress and defence (e.g., oxidative stress, detoxification, PR-genes, heat shock proteins, the phenylpropanoid pathway, LRR domain proteins and other stress-related genes) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g005">Figure 5</xref>). The analysis revealed two distinct gene expression patterns of the host in response to the fungus during the biotrophic and necrotrophic stages. At the early symptomless stage, the fungus caused minor alterations in the expression of host transcripts involved in primary metabolism, transport and signalling, although some transcripts significantly changing in abundance were observed. By contrast, a considerable number of transcripts involved in defence and defence-related signalling, encoding proteins such as antioxidants, PR-proteins, heat shock proteins, disease resistance proteins, WRKY transcription factors and NAC domain proteins were slightly down-regulated at this stage, even though some, such as receptor-like kinases and phytohormone-inducing proteins, could be up-regulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g005">Figure 5</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s006">Table S2</xref>). At the necrotrophic stage, great changes were observed in expression of host transcripts involved in host metabolism, transport, signalling and defence with up-regulation of a substantial number of transcripts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Furthermore, it is worth to note that levels of the major transcripts annotated in carbohydrate metabolism were up-regulated at this stage, whereas major transcripts annotated in photosynthesis were down-regulated. Additionally, several transcripts involved in anti-oxidative stress were strongly down-regulated at the late necrotrophic stage (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s006">Table S2</xref>), which was correlated to massive accumulation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g001">Figure 1</xref>). </p>
        <fig id="pone-0081606-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081606.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Heat map visualization of differentially expressed wheat transcripts.</title>
            <p>The plant transcripts are mainly involved in primary metabolism, signalling, transport and stress and defence in response to <italic>S. tritici</italic>. Differential expression patterns are based on the log<sub>2</sub> fold changes of transcript abundance in <italic>S. tritici</italic>-infected wheat <italic>versus</italic> controls at 4, 10 and 13 dai.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0081606.g005"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Understanding the molecular mechanisms underlying fungal infection and host plant defence is a prerequisite for understanding the host-pathogen interaction and can contribute to development of new strategies of crop protection against pathogen. A global study of host and fungal transcriptional reprogramming during the interaction allows us to gain insights into such mechanisms. Here, we report the first use of RNA-Seq technique in the compatible interaction between wheat and <italic>S. tritici</italic>, with particular focus on the metabolic and physiological alterations of both host and pathogen during the shift from biotrophic to necrotrophic growth stages. </p>
      <p>It has been suggested that the transition from slow biotrophic growth to rapid necrotrophic growth is associated with distinct expression patterns of genes regulated by nutrient status, revealed by comparison of transcriptomes between <italic>in planta</italic> transition/necrotrophic stage and <italic>in vitro</italic> nutrition-rich/limited conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Our interaction transcriptome analysis directly demonstrates two different phases of the compatible interaction: i) slow symptomless growth associated with minor host molecular responses and ii) necrotrophic feeding/high metabolic growth associated with enhanced metabolic and defence responses in plant. The symptomless growth of <italic>S. tritici</italic> was achieved by suppressing or attenuating host defence responses at transcription level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g005">Figure 5</xref>), despite up-regulation of some defence-related genes such as receptor kinases, phytohormone-inducing proteins and PR-2 and 3 as well as accumulation of stress-related compounds such as ROS. This symptomless growth is analogous with most biotroph lifestyles of both repression of plant defence responses and induction of host specific genes. However, accumulation of several defence-related proteins and down-regulation of several proteins involved in photosynthesis have been observed at the biotrophic stage as revealed by proteomics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Down-regulation of several defence-related transcripts and no alteration in the levels of several photosynthesis-related transcripts appear not to be correlated to the regulation behaviour of their protein products. The poor correlation between transcript and protein levels has been well demonstrated due to the regulation of transcription, RNA processing, translation and protein modifications and turnover and furthermore suggests that integrated &#x2018;omics&#x2019; studies are required to comprehensively understand the molecular processes in the biological system. On the other hand, the necrotrophic growth of <italic>S. tritici</italic> triggers the plant cells to create a highly defensive and metabolic active environment, generating ROS and strongly inducing defence, signalling and metabolism-related genes. The crosstalk between induced signalling events, including receptor-mediated signal perception, protein phosphorylation, ion fluxes, production of ROS, generation and regulation of secondary signalling molecules (e.g., phytohormones and WRKYs), leading to the activation of defence genes, has been well established as the mechanisms of host plant defence to different pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. More interestingly, the highly oxidative cell environment in wheat during the necrotrophic stage was accompanied by down-regulation of large number of plant transcripts encoding ROS-scavenging enzymes, thus allowing the ROS to accumulate. For some necrotrophic pathogens, it has been suggested that ROS accumulation and depletion of host antioxidants can result in increased susceptibility as well as host necrosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. Interestingly, this is not the case for <italic>S. tritici</italic> that is able to tolerate the high amounts of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulating during the necrotrophic growth phase, but does not thrive in this environment since scavenging of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> boosts fungal growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Furthermore, levels of transcripts involved in photosynthesis were suppressed during the necrotrophic phase, whereas carbohydrate and energy metabolism was up-regulated in the host and associated with enhanced defence responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. It has been demonstrated that the activation of plant defence responses is cost-intensive and causes a decrease in photosynthesis and an increased demand for assimilates, energy, reducing equivalents and carbon skeleton components that are provided by the primary metabolic pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. Simultaneously, the pathogen will put pressure on the host carbohydrate metabolism for its own needs, which will further increase the demand for assimilates. </p>
      <p>To date, little is known of the molecular mechanisms in <italic>S. tritici</italic> that promote an early symptomless, biotrophic phase and a late highly destructive necrotrophic stage or those that mediate the transition between the two. Previous investigations focused on the secreted protein effectors for facilitating the initial symptomless growth and triggering PCD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. We observed strong, differential and growth stage-specific expression of transcripts encoding several small secreted cysteine-rich proteins with unknown function at the two stages, a hydrophobin 2 during the biotrophic stage and two LysM proteins, a necrosis-inducing protein and a cerato-platanin during the necrotrophic stage, which may have potential roles in pathogenesis or suppressing plant defence. This observation suggests that <italic>S. tritici</italic> secretes distinct classes of proteins that may first suppress plant defence responses and later induce host necrosis. It has been reported that some fungal effectors, for instance, <italic>P. infestans</italic> Avr3a and SNE1 and <italic>P. sojae</italic> Avr1b, can suppress PCD or host defences during biotrophic stages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. On the other hand, the P. <italic>infestans PiNPP1.1</italic> gene encoding a NLP effector, which is only highly expressed during necrotrophy, induces necrosis and is suppressed by the SNE1 effector [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. Both LysM proteins identified in the present study have been functionally characterised, one of which was proposed to be an effector to facilitate the symptomless leaf colonisation of <italic>S. tritici</italic> through its activity in suppressing chitin-mediated plant defences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Surprisingly, LysM transcripts were highly expressed during the necrotrophic stage here, which was associated with increased fungal chitin/biomass and plant defence responses. Thus, our data suggest that <italic>S. tritici</italic> manipulates the suppression of chitin-mediated wheat defences during the entire infection process and may be important for disease development due to the increased level of biomass or chitin. Expression of a necrosis-inducing protein has also been found in the oomycete Phytophthora <italic>sojae</italic> during transition from biotrophy to necrotrophy in soybean, which suggests that this protein facilitates the plant colonisation during the necrotrophic growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. Three secreted necrosis-inducing protein effectors have been identified in barley pathogen <italic>Rhynchosporium commune</italic> and shown their contribution to disease development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. Cerato-platanin in phytopathogenic fungi acts as a phytotoxin and a pathogen-associated molecular pattern (PAMP) due to the induction of defence responses including phytoalexin synthesis and plant cell death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. Their strong expression at the transition and the necrotrophic stages, which was associated with the enhanced host defence responses, indicates a potential role in induction of the disease transition and/or facilitation of the necrotrophic growth. Fungal secreted small cysteine-rich hydrophobins have been implied in pathogenesis through acting as toxins or attaching fungal structures to the host surface [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. Eight hydrophobin-like proteins are predicted in the annotated <italic>S. tritici</italic> genome, four of which are secreted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. In addition to one highly expressed hydrophobin shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0081606-t002">Table 2</xref>, four additional hydrophobins were identified with one containing a signal peptide here (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s005">Table S1</xref>). We speculate that hydrophobins play a role in facilitating the initial symptomless growth through its ability of mediating fungal hypha to attack the host cells. </p>
      <p>The coverage of the transcripts encoding the proteins involved in transport, signalling and stress responses among the identified fungal transcripts was remarkable at both stages, indicating their important roles in facilitating both biotrophic and necrotrophic growth. Strongly expressed transcripts involved in defence-related signalling included G proteins, serine/threonine protein kinases (likely involved in MAPK pathways or Ca<sup>2+</sup> signalling), PAS-domain proteins functioning as sensors of oxygen, redox potential, light and other stimuli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>] and EGF-like proteins known for a role in the immune system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. Some of these identifications differed from the 74 transcripts involved in four MAPK pathways, the cAMP-dependent pathways and G-signalling identified in a previous <italic>in planta</italic> EST sequencing study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Disruption of <italic>S. tritici</italic> signalling genes can significantly affect and regulate the invasive growth, penetration or pathogenicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. With respect to highly expressed transport-related transcripts, different classes corresponding to two growth stages were identified. The nutrient uptake and transport facilitation appeared to be active particularly during the biotrophic stage in contrast to the primary metabolism-related transport during the necrotrophic growth. As described above, ROS accumulated in the host from 3 to 14 dai (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0081606-g001">Figure 1</xref>) and is considered as one of the primary responses to <italic>S. tritici</italic>, starting at the infection site during the biotrophic stage and spreading to the entire tissue at the late necrotrophic stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. ROS are effective in stopping growth of biotrophic pathogens. However, the roles of ROS in interactions with necrotrophic fungi are still ambiguous. It can both benefit and inhibit infection by necrotrophs, which may be able to produce ROS themselves and stimulate the ROS production from the hosts as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. To survive in the harsh oxidative environments and colonise host cells, <italic>S. tritici</italic>, therefore, has to develop mechanisms to scavenge ROS and protect against ROS-induced damage, particularly during the necrotrophic stage when massive ROS accumulation occurs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. This was evident in the present study by increased expression levels of several fungal transcripts during infection encoding ROS-scavenging proteins including peroxidases, Cu<sup>2+</sup>/Zn<sup>2+</sup> superoxide dismutases, glutathione S-transferases, hydroperoxide reductases, thioredoxins and peroxiredoxins as well as other stress-response proteins like cyclophilins and heat shock proteins (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081606.s005">Table S1</xref>). Furthermore, excessive ROS production in the fungal cells after expose to the stress can give rise to the accumulation of aldehydes and alcohols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. <italic>S. tritici</italic> may rescue itself by increased expression of aldehyde dehydrogenase and alcohol dehydrogenase for detoxification of alcohols and aldehydes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0081606-t002">Table 2</xref>). </p>
      <p>During the entire infection cycle, <italic>S. tritici</italic> grows intercellularly throughout the leaf mesophyll cell layer and the host cell walls appear not to be breached [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], although the fungus can express a series of genes encoding CWDEs <italic>in planta</italic>, in particular a large number during the very late necrotrophic stage when the foliar tissue is fully necrotic, reflecting that stage of pathogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. CWDEs are known to play a role in nutrient acquisition, host colonisation and pathogenicity in phytopathogenic fungi. However, scanning the S. <italic>tritici</italic> genome indeed revealed a relatively small number of genes annotated as CWDEs compared to some saprophytes and phytopathogenic fungi like <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>, <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> and <italic>Stagonospora nodorum</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Little is understood about the biological explanations for the strictly apoplastic colonising hyphae of <italic>S. tritici</italic> which do not breach host cell walls. In the present study, we identified relatively few transcripts encoding CWDEs expressed during the biotrophic and initial necrotrophic stages out of the total identifications and none of them was of high abundance, indicating that degradation of host cell walls may not play an essential role for nutrient acquisition and explaining the reduced capacity for breaching living host cell walls. Correspondingly, Rohel et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>] found that during the transition to necrotrophic growth where sporulation started, the fungus actually starved, indicating deficiency in obtaining sufficient nutrients. However, the fungus has to survive on the nutrients in the apoplast full of proteins, metabolites, sugars and ions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. Here, the identification of several transcripts annotated as peptidases, lipases and amylases with high abundance at two stages (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0081606-t001">Table 1, S2</xref>) suggests that degradation of host cell proteins, lipids and sugars can be an important source of fungal nutrients during colonisation. This is in agreement with the genomic mapping analysis revealing that several protease encoding gene families are expanded and 39 proteins have functions related to protein degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>].</p>
      <p>In summary, the disease transition was clearly defined by characterising accumulation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, PR-proteins and fungal biomass in order to carry out the transcriptome analysis at the biotrophic and necrotrophic stages of the compatible interaction between wheat and <italic>S. tritici</italic>. RNA-Seq enabled the identification of considerable numbers of fungal and wheat transcripts in response to the infection at both stages. The results suggest that successful leaf colonisation is achieved by suppressing host defence responses during the symptomless biotrophic stage, activation of signalling, transport and antioxidative mechanisms, apoplastic nutrient acquisition and secretion of distinct classes of stage-specific molecules including potential effectors. The necrotrophic growth triggers enhanced host responses including anti-stress and defences, energy metabolism, signalling and transport as well as decreased photosynthesis. This transcriptome study paves the way for more detailed work on <italic>S. tritici</italic> pathogenicity and wheat resistance to <italic>S. tritici</italic>, which will be important for future crop protection. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081606.s001">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Macroscopic appearance of susceptible wheat leaves after treatment with water (controls) or</bold><bold><italic>S. tritici</italic></bold>. The leaves were photographed from 3 to 14 dai.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0081606.s001.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081606.s002">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Schematic representation of RNA-Seq analysis of the interaction transcriptome between wheat and <italic>S. tritici</italic>.</bold> Total RNA was extracted from control and <italic>S. tritici</italic>-infected samples at 4, 10 and 13 dai. Illumina RNA-Seq was performed on cDNA libraries generated from each sample. All pre-processed reads of controls as well as the infected samples were combined and assembled. Subsequently, the transcripts from all the samples were combined, mapped to the fungal genome to filter out fungal transcripts prior to annotation. Finally, the clean reads of each sample were mapped to wheat and fungal transcripts. Bioinformatics analysis was conducted to obtain expression levels of both wheat and fungal transcripts in each sample and define differentially expressed wheat transcripts at each time point. </p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0081606.s002.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081606.s003">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Expression profiles of <italic>S. tritici</italic> transcripts encoding potential effector proteins identified from <italic>S. tritici</italic>-infected wheat at 4, 10 and 13 dai.</bold> Expression levels of the transcripts were calculated by log<sub>2</sub>FPKM. (A) Ten expression clusters of 313 fungal transcripts encoding proteins containing signal peptides. (B) Ten expression clusters of 246 fungal transcripts which have been identified in the present study and <italic>in</italic>
<italic>silico</italic> predicted as effectors by do Amaral et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>].</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0081606.s003.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081606.s004">
        <label>Figure S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Functional category distribution in the ten expression clusters of differentially expressed wheat transcripts.</bold> Differentially expressed plant transcripts in response to <italic>S. tritici</italic> at 4, 10 and 13 dai are presented by expression ratios of the transcripts in infected (I) <italic>versus</italic> control (C) samples in log<sub>2</sub>-scale. Histogram representation of the category distribution is expressed as percentage of the amount of transcripts belonging to the cluster. Transcripts coding for unknown products were included in the analysis.</p>
          <p>(TIFF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0081606.s004.tiff">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081606.s005">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>List of identified <italic>S. tritici</italic> transcripts during infection of wheat leaves at 4, 10 and 13 dai.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0081606.s005.xlsx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081606.s006">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>List of differentially expressed wheat transcripts in response to <italic>S. tritici</italic> at 4, 10 and 13 dai.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLSB)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0081606.s006.xlsb">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0081606.s007">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>List of identified wheat transcripts with no change in abundance during <italic>S. tritici</italic> infection at 4, 10 and 13 dai.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLSB)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0081606.s007.xlsb">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Daniel Amby (University of Copenhagen) for valuable scientific discussion and Haiyan Song (BGI) for the project coordination.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eyal</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Septoria</italic>
<italic>tritici</italic> and <italic>Stagonospora</italic>
<italic>nodorum</italic> blotch diseases of wheat</article-title>. <source>Eur J Plant Pathol</source><volume>105</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>641</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1008716812259">10.1023/A:1008716812259</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kema</surname><given-names>GHJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rijkenberg</surname><given-names>FHJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baayen</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Histology of the pathogenesis of <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic>
<italic>graminicola</italic> in wheat</article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source><volume>86</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>786</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1094/Phyto-86-777">10.1094/Phyto-86-777</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>M&#xF8;ller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gregersen</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Association of hydrogen peroxide with restriction of <italic>Septoria</italic>
<italic>tritici</italic> in resistant wheat</article-title>. <source>Physiol Mol Plant</source> P <fpage>62</fpage>: <comment>333&#x2013;346</comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Keon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Antoniw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carzaniga</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional adaptation of <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic>
<italic>graminicola</italic> to programmed cell death (PCD) of its susceptible wheat host</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>178</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>193</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1094/MPMI-20-2-0178">10.1094/MPMI-20-2-0178</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17313169">17313169</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17313169</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kema</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van der Lee</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verstappen</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lankhorst</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Large-scale gene discovery in the septoria tritici blotch fungus <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic>
<italic>graminicola</italic> with a focus on <italic>in</italic>
<italic>planta</italic> expression</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1249</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1260</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1094/MPMI-21-9-1249">10.1094/MPMI-21-9-1249</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18700829">18700829</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18700829</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The Wheat mitogen-activated protein kinases TaMPK3 and TaMPK6 are differentially regulated at multiple levels during compatible disease interactions with <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic>
<italic>graminicola</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>147</volume>: <fpage>802</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>815</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.108.119511">10.1104/pp.108.119511</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18441220">18441220</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18441220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mehrabi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>L&#xFC;tken</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haldrup</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kema</surname><given-names>GHJ</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Role of hydrogen peroxide during the interaction between the hemibiotrophic fungal pathogen <italic>Septoria</italic>
<italic>tritici</italic> and wheat</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source><volume>174</volume>: <fpage>637</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>647</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.02026.x">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.02026.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17447918">17447918</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17447918</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kombrink</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Motteram</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loza-Reyes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Analysis of two in <italic>planta</italic> expressed LysM effector homologs from the fungus <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic>
<italic>graminicola</italic> reveals novel functional properties and varying contributions to virulence on wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>156</volume>: <fpage>756</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>769</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.111.176347">10.1104/pp.111.176347</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21467214">21467214</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21467214</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>M&#x2019;Barek</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dhillon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wittenberg</surname><given-names>AHJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Finished genome of the fungal wheat pathogen <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic>
<italic>graminicola</italic> reveals dispensome structure, chromosome plasticity, and stealth pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002070</fpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21695235">21695235</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21695235</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Deller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The complex interactions between host immunity and non-biotrophic fungal pathogens of wheat leaves</article-title>. <source>J Plant Physiol</source><volume>168</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>71</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jplph.2010.05.024">10.1016/j.jplph.2010.05.024</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20688416">20688416</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20688416</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Antoniw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Motteram</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fraaije</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterisation of <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic>
<italic>graminicola</italic> secreted or surface-associated proteins with variable intragenic coding repeats</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>47</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.fgb.2009.10.009">10.1016/j.fgb.2009.10.009</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19887112">19887112</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19887112</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>do Amaral</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Antoniw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Defining the predicted protein secretome of the fungal wheat leaf pathogen <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic>
<italic>graminicola</italic></article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e49904</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0049904">10.1371/journal.pone.0049904</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23236356">23236356</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23236356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Keon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Antoniw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Metabolic and stress adaptation by <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic>
<italic>graminicola</italic> during sporulation in its host revealed through microarray transcription profiling</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Pathol</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>527</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>540</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1364-3703.2005.00304.x">10.1111/j.1364-3703.2005.00304.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20565677">20565677</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20565677</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Urmeev</surname><given-names>FI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Rapid induction of a protein disulfide isomerase and defense-related genes in wheat in response to the hemibiotrophic fungal pathogen <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic>
<italic>graminicola</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source><volume>53</volume>: <fpage>741</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>754</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/B:PLAN.0000019120.74610.52">10.1023/B:PLAN.0000019120.74610.52</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15010608">15010608</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Finnie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geshi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Effects of &#x3B2;-1,3-glucan from <italic>Septoria</italic>
<italic>tritici</italic> on structural defence responses in wheat</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source><volume>60</volume>: <fpage>4287</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4300</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jxb/erp269">10.1093/jxb/erp269</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19880540">19880540</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19880540</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Melo-Braga</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>J&#xF8;rgensen</surname><given-names>HJL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palmisano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Battle through signaling between wheat and the fungal pathogen <italic>Septoria</italic>
<italic>tritici</italic> revealed by proteomics and phosphoproteomics</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source><volume>12</volume>: <fpage>2497</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2508</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/mcp.M113.027532">10.1074/mcp.M113.027532</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23722186">23722186</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23722186</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>RNA-Seq: a revolutionary tool for transcriptomics</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>63</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrg2484">10.1038/nrg2484</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19015660">19015660</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015660</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Waalwijk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verstappen</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Waard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kema</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Isolation and characterization of the mating-type idiomorphs from the wheat septoria leaf blotch fungus <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic>
<italic>graminicola</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>35</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>286</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/fgbi.2001.1322">10.1006/fgbi.2001.1322</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11929216">11929216</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11929216</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spliid</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Investigation of the effect of nitrogen on severity of Fusarium head blight in barley</article-title>. <source>J Proteomics</source><volume>73</volume>: <fpage>743</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>752</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jprot.2009.10.010">10.1016/j.jprot.2009.10.010</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19895910">19895910</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19895910</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>J&#xF8;rgensen</surname><given-names>HJL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collinge</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Analysis of early events in the interaction between <italic>Fusarium</italic>
<italic>graminearum</italic> and the susceptible barley (<italic>Hordeum</italic>
<italic>vulgare</italic>) cultivar Scarlett</article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>3748</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3755</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/pmic.201000243">10.1002/pmic.201000243</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20925056">20925056</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20925056</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>J&#xF8;rgensen</surname><given-names>HJL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collinge</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Secretomics identifies <italic>Fusarium</italic>
<italic>graminearum</italic> proteins involved in the interaction with barley and wheat</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Pathol</source><volume>13</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>453</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1364-3703.2011.00759.x">10.1111/j.1364-3703.2011.00759.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22044785">22044785</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22044785</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Si</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dedow</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A low-cost library construction protocol and data analysis pipeline for Illumina-based strand-specific multiplex RNA-Seq</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e26426</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0026426">10.1371/journal.pone.0026426</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22039485">22039485</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22039485</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smeds</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>K&#xFC;nstner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>ConDeTri&#x2013;a content dependent read trimmer for Illumina Data</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e26314</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0026314">10.1371/journal.pone.0026314</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22039460">22039460</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22039460</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source><volume>29</volume>: <fpage>644</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>652</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nbt.1883">10.1038/nbt.1883</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21572440">21572440</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Antonescu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>TIGR Gene Indices clustering tools (TGICL): a software system for fast clustering of large EST datasets</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>651</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>652</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btg034">10.1093/bioinformatics/btg034</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12651724">12651724</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12651724</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oshlack</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A scaling normalization method for differential expression analysis of RNA-seq data</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>R25</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2010-11-3-r25">10.1186/gb-2010-11-3-r25</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20196867">20196867</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20196867</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>621</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>628</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.1226">10.1038/nmeth.1226</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18516045">18516045</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18516045</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title><italic>De</italic><italic>novo</italic> analysis of transcriptome dynamics in the migratory locust during the development of phase traits</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e15633</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0015633">10.1371/journal.pone.0015633</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21209894">21209894</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21209894</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Audic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Claverie</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The significance of digital gene expression profiles</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>986</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>995</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9331369">9331369</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9331369</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mart&#xED;n</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rech</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benito</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Plant defense mechanisms are activated during biotrophic and necrotrophic development of <italic>Colletotricum</italic>
<italic>graminicola</italic> in maize</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>158</volume>: <fpage>1342</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1358</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.111.190397">10.1104/pp.111.190397</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22247271">22247271</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22247271</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>CMJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cross talk in defense signaling</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>146</volume>: <fpage>839</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>844</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.107.112029">10.1104/pp.107.112029</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18316638">18316638</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18316638</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mahesh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The role of radical burst in plant defense responses to necrotrophic fungi</article-title>. <source>J Integr Agricult</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1305</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1312</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S2095-3119(12)60127-0">10.1016/S2095-3119(12)60127-0</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Primary metabolism and plant defense-fuel for the fire</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><volume>22</volume>: <fpage>487</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>497</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1094/MPMI-22-5-0487">10.1094/MPMI-22-5-0487</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19348567">19348567</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19348567</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>JIB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanneganti</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cakir</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huitema</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The C-terminal half of <italic>Phytophthora</italic>
<italic>infestans</italic> RXLR effector AVR3a is sufficient to trigger R3a-mediated hypersensitivity and suppress INF1- induced cell death in <italic>Nicotiana</italic>
<italic>benthamiana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>48</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>176</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02866.x">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02866.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16965554">16965554</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16965554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kale</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Conserved C-terminal motifs required for avirulence and suppression of cell death by <italic>Phytophthora</italic>
<italic>sojae</italic> effector Avr1b</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1118</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1133</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.107.057067">10.1105/tpc.107.057067</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18390593">18390593</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18390593</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Damasceno</surname><given-names>CMB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chakravarthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A secreted effector protein (SNE1) from <italic>Phytophthora</italic>
<italic>infestans</italic> is a broadly acting suppressor of programmed cell death</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>62</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>366</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04160.x">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04160.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20128886">20128886</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20128886</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>JKC</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Mediation of the transition from biotrophy to necrotrophy in hemibiotrophic plant pathogens by secreted effector proteins</article-title>. <source>Plant Signal Behav</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>769</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>772</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4161/psb.5.6.11778">10.4161/psb.5.6.11778</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20400849">20400849</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20400849</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Qutob</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kamoun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gijzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Expression of a <italic>Phytophthora</italic>
<italic>sojae</italic> necrosis-inducing protein occurs during transition from biotrophy to necrotrophy</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>32</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>373</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-313X.2002.01439.x">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2002.01439.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12410814">12410814</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12410814</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kirsten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Navarro-Quezada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Penselin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wenzel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matern</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Necrosis-inducing proteins of <italic>Rhynchosporium</italic>
<italic>commune</italic>, effectors in quantitative disease resistance</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1314</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1325</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1094/MPMI-03-12-0065-R">10.1094/MPMI-03-12-0065-R</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22712509">22712509</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22712509</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pazzagli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cappugi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The structure of the elicitor cerato-platanin (CP), the first member of the CP fungal protein family, reveals a double &#x3C8;&#x3B2;-barrel fold and carbohydrate binding</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>286</volume>: <fpage>17560</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>17568</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M111.223644">10.1074/jbc.M111.223644</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21454637">21454637</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21454637</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>W&#xF6;sten</surname><given-names>HAB</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Hydrophobins: Multipurpose proteins</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><volume>55</volume>: <fpage>625</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>646</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.micro.55.1.625">10.1146/annurev.micro.55.1.625</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11544369">11544369</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11544369</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhulin</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>PAS domains: internal sensors of oxygen, redox potential, and light</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><volume>63</volume>: <fpage>479</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>506</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10357859">10357859</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10357859</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coppel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Apical location of a novel EGF-like domain-containing protein of <italic>Plasmodium</italic>
<italic>falciparum</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><volume>127</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>68</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0166-6851(02)00308-0">10.1016/S0166-6851(02)00308-0</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12615336">12615336</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12615336</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="thesis"><name><surname>Mehrabi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Signaling pathways involved in pathogenicity and development of the fungal wheat pathogen <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic><italic>graminicola</italic></source>. <comment>PhD thesis</comment>, Wageningen University. </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B45">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>J&#xF8;rgensen</surname><given-names>HJL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collinge</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Roles of reactive oxygen species in interactions between plants and pathogens</article-title>. <source>Eur J Plant Pathol</source><volume>121</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>280</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10658-008-9302-5">10.1007/s10658-008-9302-5</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B46">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Asiimwe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schlunk</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kothe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Modulation of ethanol stress tolerance by aldehyde dehydrogenase in the mycorrhizal fungus <italic>Tricholoma</italic>
<italic>vaccinum</italic></article-title>. <source>Mycorrhiza</source><volume>22</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>484</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00572-011-0424-9">10.1007/s00572-011-0424-9</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22159964">22159964</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22159964</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B47">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rohel</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fraaije</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hollomon</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Exploring infection of wheat and carbohydrate metabolism in <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic>
<italic>graminicola</italic> transformants with differentially regulated green fluorescent protein expression</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>163</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1094/MPMI.2001.14.2.156">10.1094/MPMI.2001.14.2.156</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11204778">11204778</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11204778</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
