<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">G3 (Bethesda)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genetics</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>G3: Genes|Genomes|Genetics</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2160-1836</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Genetics Society of America</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3852385</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24122057</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">GGG_008847</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.113.008847</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Investigations</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>RNA-Guided Genome Editing for Target Gene Mutations in Wheat</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Upadhyay</surname>
            <given-names>Santosh Kumar</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kumar</surname>
            <given-names>Jitesh</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alok</surname>
            <given-names>Anshu</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tuli</surname>
            <given-names>Rakesh</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">National Agri-Food Biotechnology Institute, Department of Biotechnology, Government of India, Mohali, Punjab, India 160071</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <fn id="afn2">
          <p>Supporting information is available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1">http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1</ext-link>.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>1</label>Corresponding author: National Agri-Food Biotechnology Institute, Department of Biotechnology, Government of India, C-127, Industrial Area, S.A.S. Nagar, Phase 8, Mohali, Punjab, India-160071. E-mail: <email>rakeshtuli@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <fpage>2233</fpage>
      <lpage>2238</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2013 S. Upadhyay <italic>et al.</italic></copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Unported License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="2233.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>The clustered, regularly interspaced, short palindromic repeats (CRISPR) and CRISPR-associated protein (Cas) system has been used as an efficient tool for genome editing. We report the application of CRISPR-Cas&#x2013;mediated genome editing to wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>), the most important food crop plant with a very large and complex genome. The mutations were targeted in the <italic>inositol oxygenase</italic> (<italic>inox</italic>) and <italic>phytoene desaturase</italic> (<italic>pds</italic>) genes using cell suspension culture of wheat and in the <italic>pds</italic> gene in leaves of <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>. The expression of chimeric guide RNAs (cgRNA) targeting single and multiple sites resulted in indel mutations in all the tested samples. The expression of Cas9 or sgRNA alone did not cause any mutation. The expression of duplex cgRNA with Cas9 targeting two sites in the same gene resulted in deletion of DNA fragment between the targeted sequences. Multiplexing the cgRNA could target two genes at one time. Target specificity analysis of cgRNA showed that mismatches at the 3&#x2032; end of the target site abolished the cleavage activity completely. The mismatches at the 5&#x2032; end reduced cleavage, suggesting that the off target effects can be abolished <italic>in vivo</italic> by selecting target sites with unique sequences at 3&#x2032; end. This approach provides a powerful method for genome engineering in plants.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Cas</kwd>
        <kwd>cgRNA</kwd>
        <kwd>CRISPR</kwd>
        <kwd>genome editing</kwd>
        <kwd>indel</kwd>
        <kwd>wheat genome editing</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="6"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name> DJS Export </meta-name>
          <meta-value>v1</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Specific and effective genome editing through nontransgenic approaches is an area of high-priority research for the improvement of food crops. Several genome editing technologies like zinc finger nuclease (ZFN) and transcription activator&#x2013;like effector nuclease (TALEN) have been deployed for targeted genome modifications (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Gao 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), but these are rather complicated in design and need protein engineering for each target sequence. Recently, a new technology based on the type II prokaryotic clustered, regularly interspaced, short palindromic repeats (CRISPR) and CRISPR-associated protein (Cas) system has been developed as an effective tool for genome engineering (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Cong <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Mali <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). It is highly specific, inexpensive, and easy to engineer. CRISPR consists of an array of repeat sequences separated by &#x201C;spacer&#x201D; sequences that belong to the targeted gene/genome. A long primary transcript transcribes from CRISPR arrays and gets processed into short CRISPR RNAs (crRNAs). The crRNA consists of a conserved repeat sequence and a variable spacer sequence (guide) complementary to the target gene sequence (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Brouns <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Hale <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Trans activating crisper RNA (tracer RNA) is another important molecule that plays a critical role in the processing of pre-crRNA (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Chylinski <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). It is a short RNA sequence and is complementary to the CRISPR repeat. It activates the processing and maturation of pre-crRNA into the short crRNA by RNAseIII and Cas9. The ribonucleoprotein complex formed by short crRNA and Cas9 proteins binds to the target sequence by base pairing (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Jore <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) and causes sequence-specific dsDNA cleavage. A chimeric crRNA and tracer RNA hybrid has also been designed and has been reported to be as effective as those used individually (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Mali <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). The presence of a conserved sequence motif (NGG) known as protospacer adjacent motif (PAM) at 3&#x2032; downstream of target spacer sequence is also reported as essential for cleavage (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Gasiunas <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). The CRISPR-Cas system has been demonstrated to work efficiently for genome editing in bacterial, yeast, and animal systems (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Cong <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">DiCarlo <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Gasiunas <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Jinek <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Mali <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) and has been applied to plants recently (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Nekrasov <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Shan <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Although, some nonspecific editing has been reported (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Fu <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), the CRISPR-Cas system is very simple to design, highly effective (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Mali <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Cong <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), and can be improved in specificity.</p>
    <p>We report the application of the CRISPR-Cas&#x2013;mediated genome editing in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>), the most important food crop plant, and <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>, a model plant species. Mutations in the <italic>inositol oxygenase</italic> (<italic>inox</italic>) and <italic>phytoene desaturase</italic> (<italic>pds</italic>) genes in cell suspension culture of wheat and the <italic>pds</italic> gene in leaves of <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> were targeted. The efficacy of multiplexed CRISPR RNA, targeting two different positions in two separate genes, was also studied.</p>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2">
        <title>Synthesis of chimeric guide RNA encoding DNAs</title>
        <p>We targeted the <italic>inox</italic> and <italic>pds</italic> genes of wheat and the <italic>pds</italic> gene of <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> to demonstrate RNA-guided genome editing in plants. Partial gene sequences were amplified from genomic DNA of the wild-type plants. Target sites (also known as protospacer) of 20 nucleotides were selected manually (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/008847SI.pdf">Supporting Information</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf">File S1</ext-link>) following the criteria described previously (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Hwang <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Mali <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). The presence of NGG trinucleotide protospacer adjacent motif (PAM) at the 3&#x2032; end of the target region was an essential criterion in target selection. The chimeric guide RNAs (cgRNAs) were designed to target one or two sites in the targeted genes (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Hwang <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Mali <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). Overlapping primers were used for the synthesis of cgRNAs transcribing DNA. To develop duplex cgRNA for targeting two regions at one time, two cgRNAs were fused by using the <italic>Spe</italic>I restriction site. Assembled DNA was amplified by end primers, cloned, and sequenced.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3">
        <title>Construction of expression vectors</title>
        <p>Four types of expression vectors were prepared by cloning <italic>cgRNA</italic> and <italic>Cas9</italic> in different combinations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). Constitutive CaMVE35S promoter was used to drive the expression. We cloned <italic>cgRNA</italic> and <italic>Cas9</italic> alone, as well as together, in plant expression vector pBI121. The <italic>Cas9</italic> gene (4272 bp) including the FLAG tag and nuclear localization signal for eukaryotic expression was obtained from Addgene USA (Addgene plasmid 42229). The plant expression constructs and their target genes are provided in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/TableS1.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>.</p>
        <fig id="fig1" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Basic architecture of constructs used for CRISPR-Cas&#x2013;mediated genome editing and expression analysis of cgRNA and Cas9. (A) Architecture of constructs used for expression. The four types of constructs developed for the expression of cgRNA and Cas9 are shown. (B) RT-PCR analysis of expression of cgRNA and Cas9 in wheat: untransformed (lane 1); pCinox1-transformed (lane 2) suspension cells; and pCwpds1-transformed (lane 3) suspension cells RT-PCR analysis of expression of cgRNA and Cas9 in. <italic>N. benthamiana</italic>: untransformed (lane 4); pTpds1 (lane 5); pCas9-transformed (lane 6) leaf; and pCtpds1-transformed (lane 7) leaf. (C) Western blot analysis of Cas9 using anti-Flag antibody (FLAG tag attached at N-terminus of Cas9). Lane M, molecular weight marker; lane 1, untransformed; lane 2, pCinox1-transformed suspension cells of wheat; lane 3, pCwpds1-transformed suspension cells of wheat; lane 4, pCtpds1 agro-infiltrated; lane 5, untransformed <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="2233f1"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4">
        <title>Plant transformation</title>
        <p><italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain GV3101 was used for genetic transformation of <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> and wheat cells. Transient expression of cgRNA and Cas9 in different combinations in 3-wk-old to 4-wk-old <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> plant leaves was performed by agro-infiltration, as described by <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Bos <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref>. The infiltrated area was marked and used for DNA and RNA isolation 4 d after infiltration.</p>
        <p>To analyze the mutations in wheat, cell suspension culture developed from immature embryos was used for transformation following the protocol of <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Wu <italic>et al.</italic> (1998)</xref>. Transformed cells were enriched by antibiotic selection and used for the isolation of DNA, RNA, and protein.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s5">
        <title>RT-PCR for expression analysis of cgRNA and Cas9</title>
        <p>Total RNA was isolated from the transformed wheat suspension cells and agro-infiltrated area of <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves, and was used to make cDNA. PCR amplification was performed with the primers listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf">File S1</ext-link> for the analysis of cgRNA expression. Cas9 expression was analyzed by using primers Cas9 forward 5&#x2032; tctgtgggctgggccgtgatc 3&#x2032; and Cas9 reverse 5&#x2032; cagatccggttcttccgtctgg 3&#x2032;. Amplification of <italic>actin</italic> was used as control.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s6">
        <title>Western blotting</title>
        <p>Total soluble protein was extracted from transformed wheat suspension cells and <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves using the extraction buffer (20 mM Tris pH 8, 150 mM NaCl, 0.05% TritonX-100, and 100 &#xB5;M PMSF), separated on 10% SDS-PAGE, and transferred onto PVDF membrane. Cas9 protein was detected by using anti-FLAG antibody (FLAG tag was attached at N-terminus of Cas9).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s7">
        <title>Mutation analysis</title>
        <p>Mutations in targeted genes in plants were analyzed by PCR amplification and Sanger sequencing. Genomic DNA was isolated from transformed tissue and used as template in amplification. Primers from the vicinity of the targeted regions (highlighted in green in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf">File S1</ext-link>) were used for amplification of control and transformed samples. Ten cycles of amplification were performed. The amplified DNA was cloned and used for sequencing. Sequences were aligned against wild-type, and average mutation percentage was calculated from three independent replicates. A minimum of 75 clones were sequenced for each transforming event and used for the analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s8">
        <title>Specificity analysis of cgRNA</title>
        <p>To analyze the specificity of cgRNA in binding to the target region, several sets of mutations were made in protospacer 1 binding site of <italic>inox</italic> cgRNA (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf">File S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/TableS2.pdf">Table S2</ext-link>). Mutant cgRNA constructs were transformed with Cas9. Their editing potential was analyzed by amplification with the aforementioned primers and BsgI digestion (BsgI restriction site is present at target region in <italic>inox</italic> protospacer 1) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf">File S1</ext-link>). Mutated DNA could not be digested with BsgI. Average mutation percentage was estimated by densitometry.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="s9">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s10">
        <title>Target selection, construction of expression cassettes, and expression of Cas9 and cgRNAs</title>
        <p>Despite using the expression of complete crRNA and tracer RNA, we designed <italic>cgRNA</italic> for gene targeting as described previously (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Hwang <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Mali <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). This reduces the complexity of the system. The cgRNA consisted of mature crRNA fused with partial tracer RNA, which mimics the natural architecture of crRNA and tracer RNA duplex. We used an 80-nucleotides-long guide RNA scaffold sequences fused with 20-nucleotide target (spacer) sequences at 5&#x2032; end (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>).</p>
        <p>We targeted two regions in each gene, separately and together. Therefore, several combinations of expression constructs were developed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/TableS1.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>); a representative architecture is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>. Separate expression cassettes were developed for Cas9 (pCas9) and cgRNA (pTpds1 and pTpds2) to target the <italic>pds</italic> gene in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> and transformed into leaves by agro-infiltration in different combinations (pCas9 or pTpds alone or together in 1:1 ratio). No mutation was detected when Cas9 and cgRNA were taken, one at a time, as expected. Combined expression of pCas9 and pTpds in 1:1 ratio provided mutations that increased significantly when Cas9 and cgRNA were coexpressed using the construct pCtpds1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="t1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Average mutation rate at protospacer 1 of <italic>phytoene desaturase</italic> gene of <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> after agro-infiltration with different constructs</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <col width="44.37%" span="1"/>
            <col width="55.63%" span="1"/>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Construct Used</th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average Mutation (%) at Target Sites</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCas9</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pTpds1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCas9 and pTpds1 (1:1 ratio)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 (2/108)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCtpds1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7 (12/94)</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>RT-PCR of total RNA from transformed cells showed the expression of cgRNA and Cas9 in cells of both plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). Cas9 protein was also detected by Western blotting using anti-FLAG antibody against the FLAG tag attached at N-terminus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s11">
        <title>cgRNA-Cas9 guided genome editing in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic></title>
        <p>As described, we targeted two sites in the <italic>pds</italic> gene of <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves by agro-infiltration (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf">File S1</ext-link>). We detected mutations (deletions and insertions) in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> in 1.8% of the clones obtained from leaves infiltrated with the two <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> strains (containing pCas9 or pTpds1) mixed in 1:1 ratio. However, 12.7% indels were detected in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> when Cas9 and cgRNA were present within a single plasmid construct pCtpds1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>) and, hence, codelivered. In protospacer 2 region, 2.4% and 13.8% indels were detected with pCas9:pTpds2 (1:1) and pCtpds2 treatments, respectively. The results established that the co-delivery of cgRNA and Cas9 improved efficacy of the system. Therefore, in case of wheat only, co-delivery was used to examine the application of the CRISPR-Cas system. A maximum of 38 bp deletion and of 22 bp addition were detected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). The indel pattern was similar to that reported in other studies (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Hwang <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Mali <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Nekrasov <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Shan <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Maximum indels were noticed approximately 2&#x2013;3 bp away from the 5&#x2032; end of PAM.</p>
        <fig id="fig2" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Editing at protospacer 1 of <italic>phytoene desaturase</italic> (<italic>pds</italic>) gene of <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> by the CRISPR-Cas system. (A) Alignment of wild-type and sequences with indel at protospacer 1 of the <italic>pds</italic> gene. (B) and (C) Sanger sequencing of selected deletion and insertion mutants, respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="2233f2"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s12">
        <title>cgRNA-Cas9 guided genome editing in <italic>T. aestivum</italic></title>
        <p>Four regions of the two genes (<italic>inox</italic> and <italic>pds</italic>) were targeted for editing in suspension cells of wheat (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf">File S1</ext-link>). The rate of mutations observed in wheat was higher as compared to that in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic>. We observed 18&#x2013;22% mutations in different protospacers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>) in wheat. Both deletion and insertion mutations were detected. A maximum of 24 bp deletion and of 22 bp insertion were detected in <italic>inox</italic> protospacer 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). Indels were located at similar positions (2&#x2013;3 bp away from the 5&#x2032; end of PAM) in wheat, as observed in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> and as reported in other studies (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Hwang <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Mali <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Nekrasov <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Shan <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="t2" position="float">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Average indel percentage in <italic>T. aestivum</italic> at different protospacers with related expression cassettes</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="above" rules="groups">
            <col width="33.34%" span="1"/>
            <col width="33.33%" span="1"/>
            <col width="33.33%" span="1"/>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="center" scope="col" colspan="1">Expression Cassette</th>
                <th colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Indel (%)</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Protospacer 1</th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protospacer 2</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCinox1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9 (14/78)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCinox2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.7 (17/82)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCwpds1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3 (19/85)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCwpds2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4 (14/76)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCinox12</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7 (12/94)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2 (9/80)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCpin1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2 (8/78)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6 (7/81)</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>NA, not applicable.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <fig id="fig3" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>CRISPR-cas&#x2013;guided editing at protospacer 1 of <italic>inositol oxygenase</italic> (<italic>inox</italic>) gene of <italic>T. aestivum</italic>. (A) Alignment of wild-type and sequences with indel at protospacer 1 of <italic>inox</italic> gene. (B) and (C) Sanger sequencing of selected deletion and insertion mutants, respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="2233f3"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s13">
        <title>Duplex cgRNA-Cas9 induced deletion in <italic>inox</italic> gene</title>
        <p>To analyze the efficacy of duplex cgRNA targeting two sites simultaneously in one gene, we fused the two cgRNA (pCinox12) targeting the <italic>inox</italic> gene in wheat. The expression of duplex cgRNA caused indels at both the sites. However, the efficiency was lower as compared to that of the single cgRNA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). Approximately 11&#x2013;12% of mutations were detected at each site. Complete deletion of the region between two targeted sites was observed in 2.8% cases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig4" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Duplex cgRNA-Cas9&#x2013;induced deletion in <italic>inox</italic> gene. The figure shows that the targeting of two protospacers in one gene resulted into the deletion of the complete fragment between targeted regions.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="2233f4"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s14">
        <title>Multiple gene targeting with cgRNA-Cas9</title>
        <p>To detect the editing potential of cgRNA-Cas9 for more than one gene at a time, we fused cgRNA targeting the protospacer 1 of <italic>pds</italic> and <italic>inox</italic> genes of wheat (pCpin1). Expression of this cassette in suspension cells caused indels at both the target sites, although with different efficiency (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). Approximately 10% of indels were detected in <italic>pds</italic> and 8% were detected in <italic>inox</italic> gene.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s15">
        <title>Target specificity of cgRNA</title>
        <p>To evaluate the off-target effects of CRISPR, several sets of random mutations in protospacer 1 binding site of <italic>inox</italic> cgRNA were developed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/TableS2.pdf">Table S2</ext-link>) and transformed in suspension cells of wheat for coexpression with Cas9. The mutations at the 3&#x2032; end of the target binding region abolished the genome cleavage activity completely in the presence of a single base mismatch up to base 12. Multiple mutations up to the base 16 position also prevented cleavage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.008847/-/DC1/FigureS1.pdf">Figure S1</ext-link>), whereas single base mismatches at the 5&#x2032; end were tolerated to some extent and provided 1&#x2013;3% mutation.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s16">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The study demonstrates that the CRISPR-Cas system can be applied successfully to genome editing in very large genomes such as the 17 Gb hexaploid genome of wheat. The application of the CRISPR-Cas system has been demonstrated in bacteria, yeast, and animal cells with a high percentage of indels (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Cong <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Mali <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">DiCarlo <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Jinek <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Application of this system in plants has also been reported using transient expression by protoplast transformation and agro-infiltration (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Nekrasov <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Shan <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).</p>
      <p>We have demonstrated that CRISPR-Cas&#x2013;guided genome editing can be achieved by using wheat suspension cells. This makes the application of this technique simpler to crop plants that can be regenerated from cell cultures. We also showed that the deletion of a gene fragment can be achieved in wheat by simultaneous cleavage at two targeted sites within one gene. Similar deletion has been reported in the case of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; Mao <italic>et al.</italic> 2013), although its genome size is much smaller than the wheat genome. This result suggests that the method can be useful in deletion of target regions from the genome and the development of knockout mutants.</p>
      <p>We have also analyzed the efficacy of multiplex cgRNA targeting two genes at one time. Significant indels were detected in both the target genes in wheat. Because the experiment was performed with suspension cells, we cannot comment on whether both the target sites were mutated in the same cell or in different cells. However, the results establish that the method introduces mutations in multiple genes using the same expression cassette. Such results have been reported in the case of animal systems (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Cong <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) but have not been reported in plants.</p>
      <p>The CRISPR-Cas system is much simpler than the other reported systems such as ZFN and TALEN (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Gao 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). High-efficiency editing can be achieved even in large and complex plant genomes at each of the multiple targeted locations using the CRISPR-Cas system. Unlike ZFNs, it is not necessary to screen several cgRNAs to target the sites. Certain off-target mutations have also been reported (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Fu <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) in the case of mismatch at the 5&#x2032; end of the target binding region. We observed that even single mismatch toward the 3&#x2032; end until base 12 abolished the binding of CRISPR completely. Similar results have been reported in the case of animal and bacterial systems (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Cong <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Although our experiments for the detection of off-target binding do not include extensive analysis, the results suggested that off-target mutations can be avoided by careful selection of the target sequences. Instead of targeting the conserved and semiconserved regions, unique sequences should be chosen during CRISPR design, especially toward the 3&#x2032; side.</p>
      <p>Because of the simplicity in designing cgRNA (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Cong <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) and the applicability to a wide variety of plants and animals, the CRISPR-Cas system will be a very useful tool for reverse genetics as well as functional genomics. The necessity of NGG (PAM) at the 3&#x2032; of the target region is the only limitation for the target site.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supporting Information</title>
        </caption>
        <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_3_12_2233__index.html"/>
        <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_g3.113.008847_008847SI.pdf"/>
        <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_g3.113.008847_FigureS1.pdf"/>
        <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_g3.113.008847_FileS1.pdf"/>
        <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_g3.113.008847_FileS2.pdf"/>
        <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_g3.113.008847_TableS1.pdf"/>
        <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_g3.113.008847_TableS2.pdf"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank Dr. Siddharth Tiwari for providing wheat cell suspension culture. We thank National Agri-Food Biotechnology Institute (Department of Biotechnology, Government of India) for providing research support. S.K.U. thanks the Department of Science and Technology (DST), India, for a DST-INSPIRE Faculty Fellowship. J.K. is grateful to Council of Scientific and Industrial Research, India, for a Senior Research Fellowship. R.T. thanks DST for a JC Bose Fellowship.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn1">
        <p>Communicating editor: B. J. Andrews</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>Literature Cited</title>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brouns</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jore</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundgren</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westra</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slijkhuis</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x2003;<article-title>Small CRISPR RNAs guide antiviral defense in prokaryotes.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>321</volume>: <fpage>960</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>964</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18703739</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>J. I. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanneganti</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cakir</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huitema</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x2003;<article-title>The C-terminal half of <italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic> RXLR effector AVR3a is sufficient to trigger R3a-mediated hypersensitivity and suppress INF1-induced cell death in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>.</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><volume>48</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>176</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16965554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x2003;<article-title>TALENs: Customizable molecular DNA scissors for genome engineering of plants.</article-title><source>J. Genet. Genomics</source><volume>40</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>279</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23790626</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chylinski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Charpentier</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x2003;<article-title>The tracrRNA and Cas9 families of type II CRISPR-Cas immunity systems.</article-title><source>RNA Biol.</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23392241</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ran</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barretto</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x2003;<article-title>Multiplex genome engineering using CRISPR/Cas systems.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>339</volume>: <fpage>819</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>823</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23287718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DiCarlo</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Norville</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mali</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aach</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x2003;<article-title>Genome engineering in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> using CRISPR-Cas systems.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>4336</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4343</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23460208</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Foden</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khayter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeder</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x2003;<article-title>High-frequency off-target mutagenesis induced by CRISPR-Cas nucleases in human cells.</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source> 31: 822&#x2013;826. DOI: 10.1038/nbt.2623.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2623</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasiunas</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrangou</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siksnys</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x2003;<article-title>Cas9-crRNA ribonucleoprotein complex mediates specific DNA cleavage for adaptive immunity in bacteria.</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 109.</source><volume>109</volume>: <fpage>E2579</fpage>&#x2013;<fpage>E2586</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duff</surname><given-names>M. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graveley</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x2003;<article-title>RNA-guided RNA cleavage by a CRISPR RNA-Cas protein complex.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>139</volume>: <fpage>945</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>956</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19945378</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>W. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeder</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>S. Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x2003;<article-title>Efficient genome editing in zebrafish using a CRISPR-Cas system.</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><volume>31</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>229</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23360964</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jinek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>East</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x2003;<article-title>RNA-programmed genome editing in human cells.</article-title><source>Elife</source><volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e00471</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23386978</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jore</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundgren</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duijn</surname><given-names>E. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bultema</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westra</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x2003;<article-title>Structural basis for CRISPR RNA-guided DNA recognition by Cascade.</article-title><source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>18</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>536</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21460843</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Norville</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aach</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x2003;<article-title>Multiplex and homologous recombination&#x2013;mediated genome editing <italic>in Arabidopsis</italic> and <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> using guide RNA and Cas9.</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source> 31: 688&#x2013;691. DOI: 10.1038/nbt.2654.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2654</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mali</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Esvelt</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aach</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x2003;<article-title>RNA-guided human genome engineering via Cas9.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>339</volume>: <fpage>823</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>826</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23287722</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nekrasov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Staskawicz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J. D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamoun</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x2003;<article-title>Targeted mutagenesis in the model plant <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> using Cas9 RNA-guided endonuclease.</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source> 31: 691&#x2013;693. DOI: 10.1038/nbt.2655.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2655</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x2003;<article-title>Targeted genome modification of crop plants using a CRISPR-Cas system.</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source> 31: 686&#x2013;688. DOI: 10.1038/nbt.2650.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2650</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormac</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1998</year>&#x2003;<article-title><italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated stable transformation of cell suspension cultures of barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>).</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult.</source><volume>54</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>171</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeder</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Unger-Wallace</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoshaw</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x2003;<article-title>High frequency targeted mutagenesis in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> using zinc finger nucleases.</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume>107</volume>: <fpage>12028</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>12033</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20508152</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
