<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3869672</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-27114</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0082079</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Differentially Expressed Proteins Associated with Fusarium Head Blight Resistance in Wheat</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Proteins Associated with Wheat FHB Resistance</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Xianghui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fu</surname>
            <given-names>Jianming</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hiromasa</surname>
            <given-names>Yasuaki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pan</surname>
            <given-names>Hongyu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bai</surname>
            <given-names>Guihua</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Jinlin University, Changchun, Jilin, People's Republic of China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>United States Department of Agriculture/Agricultural Service, Hard Winter Wheat Genetics Research Unit, Kansas State University, Manhattan, Kansas, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Biochemistry, Kansas State University, Manhattan, Kansas, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff4">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Plant Pathology, Kansas State University, Manhattan, Kansas, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            <given-names>Wengui</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>National Rice Research Center, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>guihua.bai@ars.usda.gov</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: GB. Performed the experiments: XZ JF. Analyzed the data: XZ JF YH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: GB HP YH. Wrote the paper: XZ GB JF.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <elocation-id>e82079</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article, free of all copyright, and may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose. The work is made available under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons CC0</ext-link> public domain dedication.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Fusarium head blight (FHB), mainly caused by <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>, substantially reduces wheat grain yield and quality worldwide. Proteins play important roles in defense against the fungal infection. This study characterized differentially expressed proteins between near-isogenic lines (NILs) contrasting in alleles of <italic>Fhb1</italic>, a major FHB resistance gene in wheat, to identify proteins underlining FHB resistance of <italic>Fhb1</italic>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>The two-dimensional protein profiles were compared between the <italic>Fusarium</italic>-inoculated spikes of the two NILs collected 72 h after inoculation. The protein profiles of mock- and <italic>Fusarium</italic>-inoculated <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL were also compared to identify pathogen-responsive proteins.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Eight proteins were either induced or upregulated in inoculated <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL when compared with mock-inoculated <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL; nine proteins were either induced or upregulated in the <italic>Fusarium</italic>-inoculated <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL when compared with <italic>Fusarium</italic>-inoculated <italic>Fhb1<sup>&#x2212;</sup></italic>NIL. Proteins that were differentially expressed in the <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL, not in the <italic>Fhb1<sup>&#x2212;</sup></italic>NIL, after <italic>Fusarium</italic> inoculation included wheat proteins for defending fungal penetration, photosynthesis, energy metabolism, and detoxification.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>Coordinated expression of the identified proteins resulted in FHB resistance in <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL. The results provide insight into the pathway of <italic>Fhb1</italic>-mediated FHB resistance.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Research Initiative Competitive Grants CAP project 2011- 68002-30029 from the USDA National Institute of Food and Agriculture US Wheat and Barley Scab Initiative. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) Fusarium head blight (FHB), mainly caused by <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>, is a destructive wheat disease in warm and humid regions worldwide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bai1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bai2">[2]</xref>. FHB causes premature spike death or blighting and substantially reduces grain yield and quality <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bai1">[1]</xref>. A recent FHB outbreak erupted in the major wheat-growing areas in China and caused yield losses from 10 to 100% in 2012 [X-H. Zhang, 2012, unpublished data]. In the U.S., FHB has spread south and is becoming more frequent and severe in the Great Plains. Infected grains are contaminated with mycotoxins that are harmful to human and animal health when they are used as food or feed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bai2">[2]</xref>. The most common toxin associated with FHB is deoxynivalenol (DON); DON-contaminated wheat grains have undesirable end-use quality, thus low grain sale price.</p>
      <p>Although certain cultural practices or timely application of fungicides can reduce FHB damage, the most economically effective and environmentally friendly approach to reducing the losses caused by this disease is to grow resistant cultivars <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bai1">[1]</xref>. To date, a number of germplasm lines from China, Europe, and the U.S. have been identified with a high level of FHB resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bai1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Anderson1">[3]</xref>. Among them, &#x2018;Sumai3&#x2019; and its derivatives, such as &#x2018;Ning7840&#x2019;, showed the best resistance to FHB. <italic>Fhb1</italic> from Sumai3 has been used in breeding programs worldwide because it has shown the largest effect on FHB resistance identified so far <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bai2">[2]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Cuthbert1">[4]</xref>. Detailed wheat defense mechanisms against FHB infection, however, remain poorly characterized.</p>
      <p>Plants may mobilize a variety of biochemical and molecular defenses to delay pathogen growth or resist pathogen infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bowles1">[5]</xref>. An incompatible interaction between a host and a pathogen triggers defense responses through signaling pathways that can activate a broad series of defense responses to restrict pathogen growth or destroy the pathogen. These responses include hypersensitive reactions, deposition of cell wall reinforcing materials, and synthesis of a wide range of antimicrobial compounds such as pathogenesis-related (PR) proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Veronese1">[6]</xref>. Several gene expression studies have been conducted in an attempt to understand the molecular mechanisms of interaction between cereal crops and <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. In barley, microarray analysis revealed that a majority of host gene transcripts were expressed in the intermediate infection stage by <italic>F. graminearum</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Boddu1">[7]</xref>. In wheat, Pritsch et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Pritsch1">[8]</xref> observed that the transcripts of defense response genes, peroxidase and PR-1 to -5, accumulated as early as 6 to 12 h after wheat spikes were inoculated with <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. Gottwald et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Gottwald1">[9]</xref> suggested that Jasmonate and ethylene dependent defense and suppression of fungal virulence factors are major mechanisms of FHB resistance in wheat. Lemmens et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Lemmens1">[10]</xref> hypothesize that <italic>Fhb1</italic> resistance is due to a DON-glucosyl-transferase that detoxicify DON in Sumai3 or its derivatives; but several other more recent gene expression studies did not support the hypothesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Gunnaiah1">[11]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Zhuang1">[13]</xref>. Therefore, the genes involved in perceiving the pathogen attack signal and the gene expression cascade for FHB resistance remain to be elucidated.</p>
      <p>The proteomic approach is a powerful tool to study mechanisms of plant resistance to fungal infection. An initial proteomic study on the interaction between <italic>F. graminearum</italic> and wheat was conducted to identify FHB infection response proteins by comparing protein profiles of <italic>F. graminearum</italic>- inoculated with mock-inoculated wheat spikelets of &#x2018;Ning7840&#x2019;, an <italic>Fhb1</italic> carrier, and gel-based proteomic analysis of the resistant cultivar revealed accumulation of plant proteins involved in oxidative stress, PR responses, and nitrogen metabolisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Zhou1">[14]</xref>. A further study revealed upregulation of proteins in the antioxidant and jasmonic acid-signaling pathway and PR responses and amino acid synthesis after 3 days of inoculation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Zhou2">[15]</xref>. A similar study was done for an FHB-resistant Chinese landrace &#x2018;Wangshuibai&#x2019; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Wang1">[16]</xref>. Protein profiles in these studies were compared between a mock- and <italic>Fusarium</italic>-inoculated cultivar, however, which provides information only on how a plant responds to pathogen attack, not how the plant resisted the pathogen infection. Because <italic>Fhb1</italic> has shown the largest effect on FHB resistance among FHB resistance genes reported to date, comparative analysis of protein profiles of near-isogenic lines (NILs) contrasting in <italic>Fhb1</italic> alleles should shed light on wheat resistance mechanisms to FHB. Only one study compared protein profiles between NILs that were developed from two backcrosses and the resistant NIL contains 89% of recurrent genome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Gunnaiah1">[11]</xref>. A resistant NIL with a higher proportion of recurrent genome will minimize background effect on the expression of the resistance gene. We have developed such a set of NILs by transferring the <italic>Fhb1</italic> resistance allele to a susceptible cultivar (&#x2018;Clark&#x2019;) through backcrossing for seven times <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bernardo1">[17]</xref> and used the NILs to profile differentially expressed <italic>Fhb1</italic> related proteins.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Pathogen inoculum preparation</title>
        <p>The pathogen inoculum was a field isolate of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> that originated in Kansas. Mung bean broth medium was used to grow <italic>F. graminearum</italic> conidia, and was made by boiling 40 g of mung beans in a 1-l flask for 10 min, then removing the beans by filtering the liquid through a piece of cheesecloth. About 100 ml of the broth in each 250-ml Erlenmeyer flask was autoclaved, inoculated with the mycelium of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> when the liquid was cooled, and then placed on a shaker running at 220 RPM for 4 days at 25&#xB0;C to grow conidia. Conidial suspensions were diluted with autoclaved water to a final concentration of 100 spores/&#xB5;l and stored at 4&#xB0;C for inoculation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Plant materials and disease inoculation</title>
        <p>Two NILs, NIL75 (<italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL) and NIL98 (<italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>&#x2212;</sup>NIL), were developed by backcrossing &#x2018;Clark&#x2019; (a highly FHB susceptible parent) to &#x2018;Ning 7840&#x2019; (<italic>Fhb1</italic> donor) seven times <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bernardo1">[17]</xref>. <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL contains less than 0.5% of donor genome. After seedlings of both lines were vernalized for 6 weeks at 4&#xB0;C in a growth chamber, they were transplanted into 10.8-cm Dura-pots containing Metro-Mix 360 soil mix (Hummert Int, Earth City, MO) and grown in a greenhouse with 12 h supplemental light. For each treatment, 3 pots were transplanted with 5 plants per pot.</p>
        <p>At anthesis, 10 &#xB5;l of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> conidial suspension (100 spores/&#xB5;l) was injected into a spike with a syringe. Mock inoculation used the same amount of mung bean broth served as a negative control. For each treatment, 9 plants in three pots were inoculated with 3 spikes per pot. All inoculated spikes were misted with distilled water and bagged after inoculation to maintain inoculated spikes at 100% relative humidity. Previous reports indicated that most proteins related to FHB resistance expressed at 72 h after inoculation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Gunnaiah1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Zhou2">[15]</xref>, therefore all inoculated and control spikes were harvested 72 h after inoculation. The harvested tissues were placed immediately into liquid nitrogen and then stored in a &#x2212;80&#xB0;C freezer until protein extraction.</p>
        <p>The NILs were also evaluated for FHB resistance in a separated experiment using the same protocol as previously described. In each experiment, 5 pots per NIL with 5 plants per pot were inoculated with conidia at anthesis. FHB was scored at 18 days after inoculation and calculated as mean percentage of symptomatic spikelets per spike (PSS). The experiments were repeated twice.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Protein extraction and quantification</title>
        <p>Frozen mock- and <italic>Fusarium</italic>-inoculated spikes collected from each replication were weighed, transferred into a pre-chilled mortar, and ground into fine powder in liquid nitrogen. The powder was added with three times (g/ml) extraction buffer (50 Mm Tris-HCL, 2 mM EDTA, 10 mM &#x3B2;-mercaptoethanol, 10% glycerol (v/v), 1% protease inhibitor cocktail (v/v), mixed, and transferred into a 2.0-ml tube. The tube was centrifuged at 16,000 g for 20 min. The supernatant was transferred into a new tube for centrifuging again at 16,000 g for another 20 min. The supernatant in the new tube was aliquoted and frozen at &#x2212;80&#xB0;C. All the above procedures were operated at 4&#xB0;C. Proteins were cleaned up using a kit from Bio-Rad Laboratories Ltd. (Hercules, CA), and the pellets were re-suspended in a rehydration buffer (7M urea, 2M thiourea, 1% ASB-14, 40 mM Tris, 0.001% bromophenol blue, 1% DTT, and 1% Bio-lyte buffer). The procedure for protein quantification followed Fu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Fu1">[18]</xref>. Protease inhibitor cocktail for plant cell and tissue extracts was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Milwaukee, WI). All other reagents used for 2D-gel were purchased from Bio-Rad Laboratories Ltd.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Isoelectric focusing (IEF) and SDS&#x2013;PAGE</title>
        <p>Isolated proteins from three biological replications of each treatment were pooled and approximately 120 ug of each protein sample was mixed with the rehydration buffer (Bio-Rad Laboratories Ltd.) to a total volume of 350 &#xB5;l. All proteins were passively rehydrated for 16 h and absorbed into a 17-cm pH 3&#x2013;10 (NL) Bio-Rad Ready Gel Strip according to the manufacturer's instruction (Bio-Rad Laboratories Ltd.). The IEF steps were 100 V for 1 h, 250 V for 2 h, 500 V for 2 h, 1,000 V for 1 h, 4,000 V for 1 h, 8,000 V for 1 h with a linear gradient, holding at 8,000 V until a total of at least 95,000 Vh was reached, then holding at 500 V. Before SDS-PAGE, the IEF strips were equilibrated in 5 ml equilibration buffer I [6 M urea, 2% (w/v) SDS, 0.05 M Tris&#x2013;HCL (pH 8.8), 20% (v/v) glycerol, 2% (w/v) DTT] at ambient temperature for 15 min, then in the same volume of equilibration buffer II [6M urea, 2% (w/v) SDS, 0.05 M Tris&#x2013;HCL (pH 8.8), 20% (v/v) glycerol, 2.5% (w/v) iodoacetamide] for another 15 min. For SDS-PAGE, the strips were positioned on top of the second dimension 12% (w/v) polyacrylamide gel and sealed with 1% (w/v) agarose gel. The gels were run at 100 V for 60 min followed by 200 V for 6 h on PROTEAN II XI Cell (Bio-Rad Laboratories Ltd.).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Gel staining and image analysis</title>
        <p>SDS-PAGE gels were stained using the colloidal CBB G250 staining method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Candiano1">[19]</xref>. The stained gels were scanned on an EPSON 1680 scanner (EPSON, Long Beach, CA). Triplicate images from three independent gels (technical replications) for each treatment were obtained, and the normalized volumes of the three images were derived using Image Master 2D Platinum 6.0 DIGE software (GE Healthcare Biosciences, Pittsburgh, PA) and were averaged for quantification of each spot. Protein spots with at least 1.5-fold change in spot density and volume between infected and mock-inoculated samples or between inoculated NILs contrasting in <italic>Fhb1</italic> alleles were selected for further analysis. The selected protein spots were manually excised for sequencing.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>In gel digestion</title>
        <p>Excised gel pieces were incubated in 100 &#xB5;l of 50% acetonitrile at 30&#xB0;C for 10 min. After de-staining, the gel pieces were shrunk by adding 50 &#xB5;l of 100% acetonitrile for 10 min. After the solvent was discarded, the gel plugs were dried by a speed vacuum concentrator and incubated with 200 ng sequencing-grade trypsin (Trypsin Gold, Promega, Madison, WI) in 20 &#xB5;l of 20-mM ammonium bicarbonate. Upon rehydration, the gel plugs were incubated with an additional 20 &#xB5;l of 20-mM ammonium bicarbonate and 10% acetonitrile at 30&#xB0;C for 17 h. Tryptic peptides were recovered from the gel plugs using 100 &#xB5;l of 50% acetonitrile in 2% trifluoroacetic acid (TFA) at 30&#xB0;C for 30 min. Extracted peptides were concentrated in a speed vacuum concentrator and added with 100 &#xB5;l of 2% acetonitrile in 0.1% formic acid.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Protein identification</title>
        <p>Nano-HPLC was performed automatically using a micro-column switching device, Switchos (LC Packings, Amsterdam, the Netherlands), coupled to an autosampler, Famos (LC Packings), and a nanogradient generator, UltiMate Nano HPLC (LC Packings). Peptide solution (30 &#xB5;l) was loaded to a C18 reversed-phase capillary column (75 &#xB5;m ID&#xD7;15 cm, PepMap: Dionex) in conjunction with an Acclaim C18 PepMap trapping column (300 &#xB5;m ID&#xD7;10 mm, Dionex). Peptides were separated by a nanoflow linear acetonitrile gradient using buffer A (0.1% formic acid, 2% acetonitrile) and buffer B (0.1% formic acid, 80% acetonitrile), starting from 5% to 60% buffer B over 45&#x2009;min at a flow rate of 200&#x2009;nl/min. The column was then washed in 95% buffer B for 5 min. System-control software Hystar 3.2 (Bruker Daltonics Inc., Billerica, MA) was used to control the entire process. The eluted peptides were injected into an HCT Ultra Ion Trap Mass Spectrometer (Bruker Daltonics Inc., Billerica, MA). The mass spectrometer was set up in a data-dependent MS/MS mode to acquire full scans (m/z acquisition range from 300 to 1500 Da). The four most intense peaks in any full scan were selected as precursor ions and fragmented by collision energy. MS/MS spectra were interpreted and peak lists were generated by DataAnalysis 3.4 and Biotools 3.0 software (Bruker Daltonics Inc., Billerica, MA).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Bioinformatics</title>
        <p>Peptide masses were compared to the NCBInr (April, 2012) database and <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> EST database (downloaded in November 2012 from NCBI EST database) using MASCOT 2.3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.matrixscience.com">http://www.matrixscience.com</ext-link>) and Proteinscape 2 (Bruker Daltronics). The EST database included 858,408 EST sequences. The following parameters were used in all searches: maximum number of missed cleavages allowed was 2; mass tolerance was 1.2 Da for MS and 1.0 Da for MS/MS; and taxonomy was <italic>Triticum aestivums</italic>. Fixed modification was set on cystein with carbamidomethylation. Variable modification was done on methionine with oxidation and asparagine/glutamine with deamidation. The expectation values for accepting individual MS/MS spectra were 32 for protein database and 52 for EST database, which represent identity or extensive homology of probability lower than 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05). Peptides scoring less than 20 were rejected automatically to ensure that all protein identifications were reliable. Homology searches against matched EST sequences were conducted using the BLAST program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results and Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Unique wheat materials for profiling wheat defense-related proteins</title>
        <p>Although many studies have been done using gene expression assays <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Pritsch1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Gottwald1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Jia1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bernardo2">[20]</xref>, a limited number of protein-profiling studies on FHB resistance have been conducted to date. In most of these protein studies, protein profiles were compared between pathogen-inoculated and mock-inoculated plants from a single genotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Zhou1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Wang1">[16]</xref>, or from two unrelated genotypes that contrast in both disease resistance and genetic backgrounds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Zhou2">[15]</xref>. In these cases, many differentially expressed proteins between two treatments could be basal defense proteins or due to difference in genetic backgrounds; thus, most of them may not be the proteins underlying plant resistance to the pathogen. Only in one study, <italic>Fhb1</italic> NILs containing 89% of recurrent genome were used <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Gunnaiah1">[11]</xref>. In that study, <italic>Fhb1</italic> was derived from HC374 and might originate from either Wuhan (a unknown source of FHB resistance) from China or Nyubai from Japan. In this study, we developed a pair of NILs by backcrossing &#x2018;Clark&#x2019; (a U.S. winter wheat cultivar) to &#x2018;Ning7840&#x2019; (a <italic>Fhb1</italic> carrier derived from Sumai3) seven times to minimize the background difference between the NILs; thus, the selected NILs contrast in <italic>Fhb1</italic> alleles but share more than 99.5% recurrent genome and are ideal genetic materials for identifying proteins for FHB resistance related to <italic>Fhb1</italic>.</p>
        <p>To confirm the difference in FHB resistance between the two NILs, single-floret inoculation was conducted in the greenhouse. At 21 days after inoculation, the <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL showed infection either in inoculated spikelets only or spreading to one to several uninoculated spikelets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0082079-g001">Fig. 1</xref>); whereas the <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>&#x2212;</sup>NIL showed infection spread from the inoculated spikelet to most or all of uninoculated spikelets in the inoculated spikes and all infected spikelets were completely bleached. The mean PSS was 22.8% for the <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL and 76.0% for the <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>&#x2212;</sup>NIL over three greenhouse experiments, showing a significant contrast (53%) in PSS between the two contrasting NILs. The differentially expressed proteins in the <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL, not in the <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>&#x2212;</sup>NIL, after inoculation with <italic>F. graminearum</italic> are most likely related to FHB resistance regulated by <italic>Fhb1</italic>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0082079-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0082079.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Wheat spikes of <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL (NIL75, left spikes) and <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>&#x2212;</sup>NIL (NIL75, right spike) at 18th day after single spikelet inoculation with <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. <italic>F. graminearum</italic> infection did not spread or spread to only several uninoculated spikelets in <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL, but entire spike <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>&#x2212;</sup>NIL was blighted.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0082079.g001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Wheat proteins responsive to <italic>F. graminearum</italic> inoculation</title>
        <p>Protein profiles of spikes collected 72 h after inoculation with <italic>F. graminearum</italic> were compared with 72 h mock-inoculated spikes. Four proteins from seven spots were induced (qualitative difference) by <italic>F. graminearum</italic> inoculation, and they presented only in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>-inoculated <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL spikes, not in the mock-inoculated <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL spikes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0082079-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). These proteins were chloroplast oxygen-evolving enhancer protein 1 (OEE1, spots 3 and 4), PR-4 (spots 15 and 16), OEE 2 (spots 23 and 24), and single stranded nucleic acid binding (SSB) protein (spot 28) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0082079-g002">Fig. 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0082079-t001">Table 1</xref>). Eleven proteins from 17 spots were significantly upregulated (quantitative difference) in <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL spikes after <italic>F. graminearum</italic> inoculation when compared with the mock-inoculated spikes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0082079-g003">Fig. 3</xref>); they were Rossmann-fold NAD(P)(+)-binding proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0082079-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, spots 1 and 5), chloroplast OEE1 (spot 2), glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH, spot 6), superoxide dismutase (SOD, spots 9, 10 and 11), nucleoside diphosphate kinase (NDPK, spots 12 and 34), 20 kDa chaperonin (spot 17), OEE 2 (spots 18, 19, 20, 21), SSB protein (spot 27), and an unknown protein (spot 22) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0082079-g002">Fig. 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0082079-t001">Table 1</xref>). These proteins, either pathogen-induced or upregulated, were mainly involved in stress response, PR response, resistance to fungal penetration, plant photosynthesis, and energy metabolism. Some, such as GAPDH, SOD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Zhou1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Zhou2">[15]</xref>, and EEO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Wang1">[16]</xref>, have been reported previously as <italic>Fusarium</italic>-responsive proteins. Only two protein spots were upregulated in <italic>Fhb1<sup>&#x2212;</sup></italic>NIL spikes after <italic>F. graminearum</italic> inoculation when compared with the mock-inoculated spikes of the same NIL (Data not shown). The results suggest that <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL had a majority of genes that were either induced or upregulated in response to inoculation of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> than <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>&#x2212;</sup>NIL, which agrees with previous reports <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Gunnaiah1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Zhou2">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Wang1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Ding1">[21]</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0082079-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0082079.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Protein profiles of wheat spikes of <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL (NIL75) inoculated with <italic>F. graminearum</italic> (A) and mung bean broth (B) after 72 h.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0082079.g002"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0082079-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0082079.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Histograms show the volume changes of 15 upregulated spots in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>-inoculated NIL75 (<italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL) and mock-inoculated NIL75.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0082079.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0082079-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0082079.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Differentially expressed proteins identified by ESI&#x2013;MS/MS.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0082079-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0082079.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spot No.</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi number</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">description/function</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frame</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MW</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pI</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mascot Protein Score</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">unique peptides</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">coverage</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383674360|gb|HX134554.1|HX134554</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rossmann-fold NAD(P)(+)-binding proteins<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">529</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383674331|gb|HX134525.1|HX134525</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rossmann-fold NAD(P)(+)-binding proteins<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383633628|gb|HX052023.1|HX052023</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Photosystem II oxygen-evolving enhancer protein 1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">809</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|73912433</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aspartic proteinase [Triticum aestivum]</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">289</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383633628|gb|HX052023.1|HX052023</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Photosystem II oxygen-evolving enhancer protein 1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">664</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|73912433</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aspartic proteinase [Triticum aestivum]</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383633628|gb|HX052023.1|HX052023</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Photosystem II oxygen-evolving enhancer protein 1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">693</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383741321|gb|HX179787.1|HX179787</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rossmann-fold NAD(P)(+)-binding proteins<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">433</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383674331|gb|HX134525.1|HX134525</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rossmann-fold NAD(P)(+)-binding proteins</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">274</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|253783729</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">309</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383741321|gb|HX179787.1|HX179787</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenylcoumaran benzylic ether reductase (PCBER) like<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">284</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|131394</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen-evolving enhancer protein 2, chloroplastic</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">541</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|125663927</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manganese superoxide dismutase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|226897529</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superoxide dismutase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">244</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|226897529</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superoxide dismutase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383599548|gb|HX251834.1|HX251834</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleoside diphosphate kinase Group I (NDPk_I)-like<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">436</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383670986|gb|HX111086.1|HX111086</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase (Rubisco), small subunit<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|82619</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribulose-bisphosphate carboxylase (EC 4.1.1.39) small chain precursor</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|6048567</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathogenesis-related protein 4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|6048569</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathogenesis-related protein 4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383595701|gb|HX164281.1|HX164281</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 kDa chaperonin, chloroplastic-like<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">847</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|131394</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen-evolving enhancer protein 2, chloroplastic</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">445</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383675855|gb|HX136948.1|HX136948</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen-evolving enhancer protein 2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">372</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|131394</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen-evolving enhancer protein 2, chloroplastic</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">354</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|131394</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen-evolving enhancer protein 2, chloroplastic</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.d.</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|131394</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen-evolving enhancer protein 2, chloroplastic</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">393</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|131394</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen-evolving enhancer protein 2, chloroplastic</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">531</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|974605</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single-stranded nucleic acid binding protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">372</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|11990893</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase small subunit</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|974605</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single-stranded nucleic acid binding protein</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|11990897</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase small subunit</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383743921|gb|HX172565.1|HX172565</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleoside diphosphate kinase Group I (NDPk_I)-like<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">293</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383608201|gb|HX252082.1|HX252082</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WD40 domain<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">692</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|295917894</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beta-cyanoalanine synthase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|18146825</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chitinase 1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">778</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|1568639</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu/Zn superoxide dismutase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|196051131</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathogenesis related protein 10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383739814|gb|HX143464.1|HX143464</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleoside diphosphate kinase Group I (NDPk_I)-like<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|1572627</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu/Zn superoxide dismutase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|1572627</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu/Zn superoxide dismutase</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gi|383606411|gb|HX251502.1|HX251502</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actin depolymerisation factor/cofilin -like<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.7</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label>*</label>
              <p>indicates that matched sequence was found in the EST and its function was the same as indicated by BLAST search.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Wheat proteins associated with FHB resistance</title>
        <p>To identify wheat proteins associated with resistance to <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, the protein profiles of <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup>NIL</italic> and <italic>Fhb1<sup>&#x2212;</sup></italic> NILs were compared after inoculation with <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0082079-g004">Fig. 4</xref> presents representative gel images that were selected from three independent experiments showing differentially expressed proteins between the two inoculated NILs. Eight protein spots presented only in <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL, but not in the <italic>Fhb1<sup>&#x2212;</sup></italic>NIL after inoculated with <italic>F. graminearum</italic>; they were chloroplast OEE1 (spot 4) and OEE 2 (spot 19), Rossmann-fold NAD(P)(+)-binding proteins (spot 5), single-stranded nucleic acid binding protein (spot 28), beta-cyanoalanine synthase (CAS, spot 46), chitinase (spot 47), Cu/Zn SOD (spot 51), and actin depolymerisation factor (ADF)/cofilin-like (spot 52) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0082079-g004">Fig. 4</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0082079-t001">Table 1</xref>). Nine protein spots showed significantly higher levels of expression in <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL than in <italic>Fhb1<sup>&#x2212;</sup></italic>NIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0082079-g005">Fig. 5</xref>): Rossmann-fold NAD(P)(+)-binding proteins (spot 1), chloroplast OEE1 (spots 2 and 3), OEE2 (spot 7), SODs (spots 10, 11 and 50), PR-10 (spot 48), and NDPKI-like protein (spot 49). Most of these differentially expressed proteins in <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL were induced by <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, except CAS, chitinase, and ADF/cofilin. These proteins are mainly for oxidative stress responses, resistance to fungal penetration, plant photosynthesis, plant detoxification, etc. Some proteins such as SOD and chitinase have been reported previously as <italic>Fusarium</italic>-responsive proteins or resistance related proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Gunnaiah1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Zhou1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Zhou2">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Wang1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Ding1">[21]</xref>, but most are newly identified proteins related to FHB resistance in this study including an ADF/cofilin protein, CAS, NAD(P)(+)-binding protein, and NDPKI-like protein.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0082079-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0082079.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Enlarged partial gel images showing differentially expressed protein spots between inoculated resistant line <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL (NIL75) and inoculated susceptible line <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>&#x2212;</sup>NIL (NIL98).</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0082079.g004"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0082079-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0082079.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Histograms show the volume changes of 9 upregulated protein spots in the resistant NIL75 (<italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL) and the susceptible NIL98 (<italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>&#x2212;</sup>NIL) after inoculation with <italic>F. graminearum</italic>.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0082079.g005"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Resistance to pathogen penetration at the plant cell surface by formation of cell wall apposition (CWA), a physical and chemical barrier to cell penetration by a pathogen, is a key mechanism for plants. The actin cytoskeleton plays an important role in formation of CWA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Hardham1">[22]</xref>, and actin-binding proteins, such as ADF/cofilins, regulate the dynamic behavior of actin filaments during forming CWA. Actin dynamics demonstrated a role in the activation of gene-for-gene resistance of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> to <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv tomato <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Tian1">[23]</xref>; abiotic stresses also induced significant expression of ADF/cofilins in cereal plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Ali1">[24]</xref>. Thus, ADF/cofilins might be important proteins to protect plants against biotic and abiotic stresses. A high level of ADF/cofilin protein presented in only <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL suggests that CWA formation is an important initial step for wheat resistance to <italic>Fusarium</italic> early penetration in cell walls of spikelets in resistant wheat.</p>
        <p>Reactive oxygen species (ROS) such as H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> also play an important role in plant-pathogen interaction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Levine1">[25]</xref>. Pathogen-induced H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is required for peroxidase-dependent lignification that hinders the penetration of a pathogen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Hckelhoven1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Noctor1">[27]</xref>. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is very important for resistance to fungal basal penetration because enzymatic removal of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> enhances the fungal penetration on leaf epidermal cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Hckelhoven1">[26]</xref>. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is also required for protein cross-linking in cell wall at the site of pathogen contact to produce a stress; the host cells' generation of an oxidative burst also stresses the pathogen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Hckelhoven1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Noctor1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Brisson1">[28]</xref>. The cross-linking of proline-rich proteins in the cell wall makes plant cells more resistant to cell wall&#x2013;degrading enzymes produced by a pathogen and may entrap the fungal penetration peg in a CWA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Brisson1">[28]</xref>. In the barley&#x2013;<italic>B. graminis</italic> interaction system, the presence of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in CWAs can be used as a biochemical marker to identify nonpenetrated cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Hckelhoven2">[29]</xref>. Because H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is membrane-permeable, it may also act as a diffusible signal that leads to systemic acquired resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Noctor1">[27]</xref>; thus, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> might be a potent messenger in cell wall&#x2013;associated defense. In plant cells, SOD can rapidly convert the O<sup>2&#x2212;</sup> to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> that accumulates at the site of pathogen contact where CWA is formed, which restricts pathogen movement and reproduction, and prevents the spread of the pathogen to other parts of the plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Noctor1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Jimnez1">[30]</xref>. In this study, four spots of SODs were induced or upregulated in the inoculated <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL, not in the inoculated <italic>Fhb1<sup>&#x2212;</sup></italic>NIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0082079-g004">Fig. 4</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0082079-t001">Table 1</xref>); therefore, the SODs played a critical role in resistance to FHB penetration by strengthening cell walls. Several other studies also presented evidences to support that cell wall thickening is a major mechanism of FHB resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Gunnaiah1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Hardham1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Wang1">[16]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Plants may actively defend against pathogen infection by producing enzymes that digest fungal cell walls to stop fungal penetration. Because all true fungi contain chitin as a primary structural component of their cell walls, the chitinase family of PR proteins is of particular importance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Wessels1">[31]</xref>. Chitin in fungal cell walls can be hydrolyzed by chitinases into smaller oligomers or monomers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Wessels1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bishop1">[32]</xref>, so chitinases are considered to play a major role during plant&#x2013;fungus pathogenic interactions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Collinge1">[33]</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Meins1">[35]</xref>. Chitinase was reported to be upregulated in FHB-resistant wheat &#x2018;Ning7840&#x2019; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Zhou2">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bernardo2">[20]</xref>. Transgenic plants that overexpressed chitinases exhibited enhanced resistance to pathogens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Schlumbaum1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Shin1">[37]</xref>. Transgenic wheat that overexpressed a barley class II chitinase gene significantly increased Type II FHB resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Shin1">[37]</xref>. In this study, differentially expressed chitinase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0082079-g004">Fig. 4</xref>, spots 47 and 48) that presented only in the <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL provides another line of evidence that the degradation of fungal cell wells by chitinases enhances FHB resistance in wheat.</p>
        <p>Oxygen-evolving enhancer proteins (OEEs), consisting of three subunits [OEE1 (33 kDa), OEE2 (23 kDa), and OEE3 (16 kDa)], are nuclear-encoded chloroplast proteins and are peripherally bound to photosystem II (PSII) on the luminal side of the thylakoid membrane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Sugihara1">[38]</xref>. Photosynthetic oxygen evolution requires the interaction of several different yet closely coupled biochemical reactions. The light-capturing and charge-separating capacities of PSII must work in close cooperation with an oxygen-evolving complex capable of utilizing this oxidizing power to split water into oxygen and hydrogen. Electrons stripped from water during this reaction are funneled back into photochemical reaction center II, then transported through the electron transport chain to photosystem I, eventually to be used for the reduction of NADP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Mayfieldl1">[39]</xref>. Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Wang1">[16]</xref> found that OEE2 of PSII was upregulated in FHB resistant cultivar &#x2018;Wangshuibai&#x2019; after inoculation with <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. In barley, PSII oxygen-evolving complex protein 2 precursor was expressed in response to <italic>F. graminearum</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Geddes1">[40]</xref>. In the current study, both OEE1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0082079-g004">Fig. 4</xref>, protein spot 4) and OEE2 (spot 19) were detected in the <italic>F. graminearum</italic>-inoculated <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL, but not in the <italic>Fhb1<sup>&#x2212;</sup></italic>NIL, suggesting that the two OEEs played an important role in maintaining PSII activity when wheat was inoculated with <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. Mizobuchi and Yamamoto <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Mizobuchi1">[41]</xref> demonstrated that OEE1 was essential for oxygen evolving activity and PSII stability. In wheat FHB, the most obvious visual disease symptom on the spike of a susceptible plant infected by <italic>F. graminearum</italic> starts with chlorosis to bleached spikes; thus, photosynthesis in the infected spikes is significantly reduced or stopped completely in a susceptible genotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Ribichich1">[42]</xref>. Therefore, the recovery or turnover of OEEs in the inoculated FHB-resistant spikes may be attributed to maintaining the capacity of PSII for enhanced photosynthesis after <italic>F. graminearum</italic> attacks.</p>
        <p>A higher level of NAD(P)(+)-binding proteins detected in inoculated <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL than in <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>&#x2212;</sup>NIL also supported the idea that enhanced photosynthesis is related to FHB resistance. NAD(P)(+)-binding proteins bind nicotinamide dinucleotide (NAD) to catalyze reactions central to energy production, storage, and transfer. These reactions are essential to nearly all core metabolic pathways including photosynthesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bellamacina1">[43]</xref>. Glyceradehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) is a NAD(P)(+)-binding protein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bellamacina1">[43]</xref> and has been reported to be involved in photosynthetic metabolism and responses to abiotic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Yang1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Jeong1">[45]</xref> and biotic stresses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Laxalt1">[46]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Nucleoside diphosphate kinases (NDPKs) are primary metabolic enzymes that maintain the balance between cellular ATP and other nucleoside triphosphates and play regulatory roles in response to multiple stresses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Cho1">[47]</xref>. In rice, <italic>NDPK1</italic> was reported to be involved in the defense against bacterial infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Bellamacina1">[43]</xref>. <italic>NDPK</italic> transcript was upregulated in response to wounding in tomato <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Harris1">[48]</xref>, and transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> that overexpressed <italic>AtNDK1</italic> exhibited tolerance to paraquat (N,N&#x2032;-dimethyl-4,4&#x2032;-bipyridinium dichloride), suggesting a role for <italic>AtNDK1</italic> in ROS response <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Fukamatsu1">[49]</xref>. In this study, <italic>F. graminearum</italic> induced a higher level of NDPK1 expression in the <italic>Fusarium</italic>-inoculated <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL than <italic>Fhb1<sup>&#x2212;</sup></italic>NIL, which suggests that NDPK1 protein may be involved in defense against FHB infection in wheat.</p>
        <p>Many biotic and abiotic stress conditions can induce ethylene production in plants, while HCN is a byproduct in the ethylene pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Yip1">[50]</xref>. HCN is extremely toxic to plant cells, but beta-cyanoalanine synthase (CAS) can rapidly detoxify HCN and recycle the reduced nitrogen of cyanide for amino acid synthesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Takahashi1">[51]</xref>. Cell wall protein fractions from pathogens induced significant ethylene production in plants, and trace amounts of ethylene can elicit many physiological responses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Yip1">[50]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Peiser1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Toppan1">[53]</xref>; thus, the induced expression of CAS detoxified HCN resulting from the elevated level of ethylene production in cell wall protein&#x2013;treated plants and the high level of CAS activity were caused by the general response to ethylene production. A previous study reported that wheat spikes challenged with cell wall proteins from <italic>Pythium oligandrum</italic> had a significantly reduced number of infected spikelets compared with the control after <italic>F. graminearum</italic> inoculation and demonstrated that CAS induced by fungal elicitors reduced the level of <italic>Fusarium</italic> infection in wheat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Takenaka1">[54]</xref>. Several proteins in ethylene signal pathway have been associated with FHB resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Gottwald1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Ding1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Yang2">[55]</xref>. In this study, a high level of CAS (spot 46) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0082079-g004">Fig. 4</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0082079-t001">Table 1</xref>) was detected only in the <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL, not in the <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>&#x2212;</sup>NIL, indicating the important role of CAS and ethylene signaling in preventing FHB spread within a spike after <italic>Fusarium</italic> infection in wheat.</p>
        <p>Single stranded nucleic acid binding (SSB) protein is essential for DNA replication and repair in nearly all organisms, so it is crucial to genome maintenance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Ha1">[56]</xref>. SSB proteins bind with high affinity and specificity to ssDNA intermediates to protect them from degradation and destabilize inhibitory secondary structures within the ssDNA, and they regulate the activities of other proteins by direct binding to bring them to their sites of action on DNA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Ha1">[56]</xref>. In Arabidopsis, organellar single-stranded DNA binding protein 1 was shown to be required for mtDNA stability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Zaegel1">[57]</xref>. In this study, a significantly higher level of SSB protein was detected in inoculated <italic>Fhb1<sup>+</sup></italic>NIL than in <italic>Fhb1<sup>&#x2212;</sup></italic>NIL, suggesting the SSB protein may be actively involved in protection of ssDNA in mitochondrial or chloroplast from degradation in FHB-resistant genotypes.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Comparisons of protein expression profiles between the unique pair of NILs contrasting in <italic>Fhb1</italic> alleles identified nine types of either induced or upregulated proteins that were associated with wheat FHB resistance in the <italic>Fhb1</italic><sup>+</sup>NIL. These differentially expressed proteins may be involved in complicated processes to defend against fungal infection in FHB-resistant genotypes by degrading fungal cell walls and strengthening plant cell walls at the site of pathogen contact to hinder pathogen penetration; detoxifying toxic cyanide in the ethylene pathway; and maintaining photosynthesis and energy metabolism. Although the <italic>Fhb1</italic> was previously located on chromosome 3BS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0082079-Cuthbert1">[4]</xref>, whether the genes encoding these FHB resistance-related proteins are located on the same chromosome remains unknown. It is possible that <italic>Fhb1</italic> gene(s) on the chromosome 3BS trans-regulate the expression of some of these genes in downstream to provide FHB resistance; therefore, further cloning of <italic>Fhb1</italic> may elucidate the functions of <italic>Fhb1</italic> in the wheat FHB system.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>Disclaimer: USDA is an equal opportunity provider and employer. Mention of trade names or commercial products in this article is solely for the purpose of providing specific information and does not imply recommendation or endorsement by the U.S. Department of Agriculture. Contribution number 13-288-J from the Kansas Agricultural Experiment Station.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Bai1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>G-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shaner</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Scab of wheat: prospects for control</article-title>. <source>Plant Dis</source><volume>78</volume>: <fpage>760</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>766</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Bai2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>G-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shaner</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Management and resistance in wheat and barley to Fusarium head blight</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source><volume>42</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15283663</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Anderson1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stack</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waldron</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>DNA markers for Fusarium head blight resistance QTL in two wheat populations</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>102</volume>: <fpage>1164</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1168</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Cuthbert1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cuthbert</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cloutier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brule'-Babel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Fine mapping Fhb1, a major gene controlling Fusarium head blight resistance in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source><volume>112</volume>: <fpage>1465</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16518614</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Bowles1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bowles</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Defense-related proteins in higher plants</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><volume>59</volume>: <fpage>873</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>907</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2197993</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Veronese1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Veronese</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coca</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hernandez-Lopez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>In defense against pathogens. Both plant sentinels and foot soldiers need to know the enemy</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>131</volume>: <fpage>1580</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12692317</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Boddu1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boddu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kruger</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muehlbauer</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Transcriptome analysis of the barley-<italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> interaction</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16610744</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Pritsch1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pritsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muehlbauer</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bushnell</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Fungal development and induction of defense response genes during early infection of wheat spikes by <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>13</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10659706</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Gottwald1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gottwald</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Samans</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>L&#xFC;ck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Friedt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Jasmonate and ethylene dependent defence gene expression and suppression of fungal virulence factors: two essential mechanisms of Fusarium head blight resistance in wheat?</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>13</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22857656</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Lemmens1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lemmens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scholz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berthiller</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Asta</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koutnik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The ability to detoxify the mycotoxin deoxynivalenol colocalizes with a major quantitative trait locus for Fusarium head blight resistance in wheat</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1318</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16478051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Gunnaiah1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gunnaiah</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kushalappa</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duggavathi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Integrated metabolo-proteomic approach to decipher the mechanisms by which wheat QTL (Fhb1) contributes to resistance against <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue>: <fpage>e40695</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22866179</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Jia1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muehlbauer</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Transcriptome analysis of a wheat near-isogenic line pair carrying Fusarium head blight&#x2013;resistant and &#x2013;susceptible alleles</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1366</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19810806</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Zhuang1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Identification of functional genic components of major Fusarium head blight resistance quantitative trait loci in wheat cultivar Sumai 3</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><volume>26</volume>: <fpage>442</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23234406</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Zhou1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W-C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riechers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Identification of proteins induced or upregulated by Fusarium head blight infection in the spikes of hexaploid wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Genome</source><volume>48</volume>: <fpage>770</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16391683</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Zhou2">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W-C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eudes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laroche</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Identification of differentially regulated proteins in response to a compatible interaction between the pathogen <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> and its host, <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic></article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>4599</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16858732</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Wang1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>QF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Differential proteomic analysis of proteins in wheat spikes induced by. <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>4496</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16222720</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Bernardo1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bernardo</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Single nucleotide polymorphism in wheat chromosome region harboring <italic>Fhb1</italic> for Fusarium head blight resistance</article-title>. <source>Mol Breed</source><comment>DOI <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007s110320119565y/s11032-011-9565-y">10.1007s110320119565y/s11032-011-9565-y</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Fu1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Momcilovic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clemente</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nersesian</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trick</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Heterologous expression of a plastid EF-Tu reduces protein thermal aggregation and enhances CO2 fixation in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) following heat stress</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source><volume>68</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18622733</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Candiano1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Candiano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bruschi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Musante</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Blue silver: A very sensitive colloidal Coomassie G-250 staining for proteome analysis</article-title>. <source>Electrophoresis</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1327</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15174055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Bernardo2">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bernardo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guenzi</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Fusarium graminearum-induced changes in gene expression between Fusarium head blight-resistant and susceptible wheat cultivars</article-title>. <source>Funct Integr Genomics</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16636822</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Ding1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Resistance to hemi-biotrophic <italic>F. graminearum</italic> infection is associated with coordinated and ordered expression of diverse defense signaling pathways</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue>: <fpage>e19008</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21533105</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Hardham1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hardham</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takemoto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Cytoskeleton and cell wall function in penetration resistance</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>342</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17627866</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Tian1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chaudhry</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruzicka</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meagher</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis actin-depolymerizing factor AtADF4 mediates defense signal transduction triggered by the <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> effector AvrPphB</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>150</volume>: <fpage>815</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19346440</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Ali1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Proteomic analysis of rice leaf sheath during drought stress</article-title>. <source>Proteome Res</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>396</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>403</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Levine1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tenhaken</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> from the oxidative burst orchestrates the plant hypersensitive disease resistance response</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>79</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7954825</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Hckelhoven1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>H&#xFC;ckelhoven</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Cell wall&#x2013;associated mechanisms of disease resistance and susceptibility</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source><volume>45</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17352660</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Noctor1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Noctor</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Foyer</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Ascorbate and glutathione: keeping active oxygen under control</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol</source><volume>49</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012235</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Brisson1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brisson</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tenhaken</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Function of oxidative cross-linking of cell wall structural proteins in plant disease resistance</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1703</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12244231</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Hckelhoven2">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>H&#xFC;ckelhoven</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fodor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Preis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kogel</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Hypersensitive cell death and papilla formation in barley attacked by the powdery mildew fungus are associated with hydrogen peroxide but not with salicylic acid accumulation</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>119</volume>: <fpage>1251</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10198083</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Jimnez1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jim&#xE9;nez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Del-Rio</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sevilla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Evidence for the presence of the ascorbate-glutathione cycle in mitochondria and peroxisomes of pea leaves</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>114</volume>: <fpage>275</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12223704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Wessels1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wessels</surname><given-names>JGH</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Developmental regulation of fungal cell-wall formation</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source><volume>32</volume>: <fpage>413</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>437</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Bishop1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mitchell-Olds</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Rapid evolution in plant chitinases: molecular targets of selection in plant-pathogen coevolution</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>97</volume>: <fpage>5322</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10805791</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Collinge1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Collinge</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kragh</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Plant chitinases</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8401605</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Kasprzewska1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kasprzewska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Plant chitinases &#x2013;regulation and function</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Biol Lett</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>809</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12949620</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Meins1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Meins</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fritig</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Linthorst</surname><given-names>HJM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Plant chitinase genes</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol Rep</source><volume>12</volume>: <fpage>S22</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>S28</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Schlumbaum1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schlumbaum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mauch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>V&#xF6;geli</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Plant chitinases are potent inhibitors of fungal growth</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>324</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>367</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Shin1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackintosh</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heinen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Radmer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Transgenic wheat expressing a barley class II chitinase gene has enhanced resistance against <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source><volume>59</volume>: <fpage>2371</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18467324</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Sugihara1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sugihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanagata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dubinsky</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karube</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization of cDNA encoding oxygen evolving enhancer protein 1 increased by salt treatment in the mangrove <italic>Bruguiera gymnorrhiza</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1279</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11092914</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Mayfieldl1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mayfieldl</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennoun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rochaix</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Expression of the nuclear encoded OEE1 protein is required for oxygen evolution and stability of photosystem II particles in <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic></article-title>. <source>EMBO</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>318</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Geddes1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Geddes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eudes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laroche</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Selinger</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Differential expression of proteins in response to the interaction between the pathogen <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> and its host, <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic></article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>545</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18232057</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Mizobuchi1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mizobuchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Assembly of photosystem II polypeptides and expression of oxygen evolution activity in the chloroplasts of <italic>Euglena gracilis</italic> Z during the dark-light transition</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><volume>977</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Ribichich1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ribichich</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vegetti</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Histopathological spikelet changes produced by <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> in susceptible and resistant wheat cultivars</article-title>. <source>Plant Dis</source><volume>84</volume>: <fpage>794</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>802</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Bellamacina1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bellamacina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The nicotinamide dinucleotide binding motif: a comparison of nucleotide binding proteins</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1257</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8836039</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Yang1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Stress responses and metabolic regulation of glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase genes in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>101</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8278495</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Jeong1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Improvement of salt tolerance in transgenic potato plants by glyceraldehyde-3 phosphate dehydrogenase gene transfer</article-title>. <source>Mol Cells</source><volume>12</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>185</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Laxalt1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Laxalt</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cassia</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanllorenti</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madrid</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andreu</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Accumulation of cytosolic glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase RNA under biological stress conditions and elicitor treatments in potato</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source><volume>30</volume>: <fpage>961</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8639754</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Cho1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eun</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Enhanced expression of a gene encoding a nucleoside diphosphate kinase 1 (OsNDPK1) in rice plants upon infection with bacterial pathogens</article-title>. <source>Mol Cells</source><volume>18</volume>: <fpage>390</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15650338</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Harris1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Isolation of an mRNA encoding a nucleoside diphosphate kinase from tomato that is up-regulated by wounding</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>739</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8061324</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Fukamatsu1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fukamatsu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yabe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hasunuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis NDK-1 is a component of ROS signaling by interacting with three catalases</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><volume>44</volume>: <fpage>982</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14581623</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Yip1">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Cyanide metabolism in relation to ethylene production in plant tissues</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>88</volume>: <fpage>473</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16666329</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Takahashi1">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hase</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakaho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Beta-cyanoalanine synthase as a molecular marker for induced resistance by fungal glycoprotein elicitor and commercial plant activators</article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source><volume>96</volume>: <fpage>908</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18943757</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Peiser1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peiser</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Formation of cyanide from carbon 1 of 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid during its conversion to ethylene</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>81</volume>: <fpage>3059</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3063</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16593463</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Toppan1">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Toppan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Esquerre-Tugate</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Cell surfaces in plant-microorganism interactions IV. Fungal glycopeptides which elicit the synthesis of ethylene in plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>75</volume>: <fpage>1133</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16663747</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Takenaka1">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takenaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nishio</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Induction of defense reactions in sugar beet and wheat by treatment with cell wall protein fractions from the mycoparasite <italic>Pythium oligandrum</italic></article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source><volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1228</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944321</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Yang2">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>J&#xF8;rgensen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collinge</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title><italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> and its interactions with cereal heads: studies in the proteomics era</article-title>. <source>Front Plant Sci</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23450732</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Ha1">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kozlov AG. Lohman</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Single-molecule views of protein movement on single-stranded DNA</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biophys</source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22404684</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0082079-Zaegel1">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zaegel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guermann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Le Ret</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andre's</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The plant-specific ssDNA binding protein OSB1 is involved in the stoichiometric transmission of mitochondrial DNA in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>18</volume>: <fpage>3548</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17189341</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
