<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Database (Oxford)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Database (Oxford)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">databa</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">databa</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Database: The Journal of Biological Databases and Curation</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1758-0463</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4830907</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/database/baw060</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">baw060</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Database Tool</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>PmiRExAt: plant miRNA expression atlas database and web applications</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gurjar</surname>
            <given-names>Anoop Kishor Singh</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="baw060-aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Panwar</surname>
            <given-names>Abhijeet Singh</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="baw060-aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gupta</surname>
            <given-names>Rajinder</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="baw060-aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mantri</surname>
            <given-names>Shrikant S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="baw060-aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="baw060-cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="baw060-aff1"><sup>1</sup>Computational Biology Laboratory, National Agri Food Biotechnology Institute (NABI), Mohali, Punjab, India</aff>
        <aff id="baw060-aff2"><sup>2</sup>HPC-Tech, Center for Development of Advance Computing (C-DAC), Pune, Maharashtra, India</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="baw060-cor1">*Corresponding author: Tel: <phone>+91 (172) 4990104</phone>; Fax: <fax>+91 172 4604888</fax>; Email: <email>shrikant@nabi.res.in</email> or <email>bioinfoman3@gmail.com</email></corresp>
        <fn id="baw060-FM1">
          <p>Citation details: Gurjar,A.K.S., Panwar,A.S., Gupta,R. <italic>et al.</italic> PmiRExAt: plant miRNA expression atlas database and web applications. <italic>Database</italic> (2016) Vol. 2016: article ID baw060; doi:10.1093/database/baw060</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>2016</volume>
      <elocation-id>baw060</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2016. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" license-type="creative-commons">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>High-throughput small RNA (sRNA) sequencing technology enables an entirely new perspective for plant microRNA (miRNA) research and has immense potential to unravel regulatory networks. Novel insights gained through data mining in publically available rich resource of sRNA data will help in designing biotechnology-based approaches for crop improvement to enhance plant yield and nutritional value. Bioinformatics resources enabling meta-analysis of miRNA expression across multiple plant species are still evolving. Here, we report PmiRExAt, a new online database resource that caters plant miRNA expression atlas. The web-based repository comprises of miRNA expression profile and query tool for 1859 wheat, 2330 rice and 283 maize miRNA. The database interface offers open and easy access to miRNA expression profile and helps in identifying tissue preferential, differential and constitutively expressing miRNAs. A feature enabling expression study of conserved miRNA across multiple species is also implemented. Custom expression analysis feature enables expression analysis of novel miRNA in total 117 datasets. New sRNA dataset can also be uploaded for analysing miRNA expression profiles for 73 plant species. PmiRExAt application program interface, a simple object access protocol web service allows other programmers to remotely invoke the methods written for doing programmatic search operations on PmiRExAt database.</p>
        <p><bold>Database URL:</bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pmirexat.nabi.res.in">http://pmirexat.nabi.res.in</ext-link>.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Discovery of functional endogenous microRNAs (miRNAs), which negatively regulate gene expression at the post-transcriptional level in eukaryotes, has dramatically increased in the recent past. Software, tools and web servers enabling large scale RNA-seq and small RNA (sRNA)-seq expression meta-analysis along with comparative and integrative interpretation have started to proliferate. RNASeqExpressionBrowser (<xref rid="baw060-B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) and RNA-Seq Atlas (<xref rid="baw060-B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) offers gene expression analysis and visualization, MIRPIPE (<xref rid="baw060-B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) supports quantification of miRNAs in niche model organisms lacking genomic sequences, mirEX<sup>2</sup> (<xref rid="baw060-B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) supports pri-miRNA expression analysis for <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana, Hordeum</italic>
<italic>v</italic><italic>ulgare and Pellia endiviifolia</italic>, omiRas (<xref rid="baw060-B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) is used for differential expression (DE) between two given conditions by uploading sRNA sequencing data and PsRobot (<xref rid="baw060-B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) takes sRNA sequence fasta or plain text files as input. omiRas and PsRobot require genome sequences for analysis and prediction of new miRNA. miRNA play important role in plant development during different growth stages and stress conditions. Understanding gene regulatory networks involving plant miRNA is critical to design biotechnology-based approaches for crop improvement (<xref rid="baw060-B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Here, we report PmiRExAt, a new online database resource that provides the most comprehensive comparative view yet of plant miRNAs (miRs) expression in multiple tissues and development stages of wheat (W), rice (R) and maize (M).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Data sources, data mining and analysis</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Non-redundant miRNA collection</title>
        <p>In this study, the miRNA sequences of three majorly cultivated food crops namely wheat, rice and maize were retrieved from miRBase (release 20) (<xref rid="baw060-B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), plant miRNA database (PMRD) (<xref rid="baw060-B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) and recent publications. miRNA sequence redundancy was removed using perl script. One thousand eight hundred and fifty-nine non-redundant (NR) out of 2045 redundant miRNA of wheat, 2330 NR out of 3509 redundant miRNA of rice and 283 NR out of 630 redundant miRNA of maize were analysed further (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="baw060-F1">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="baw060-T1">Table 1</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>).
<fig id="baw060-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Methodology flow chart showing source of raw data collected, scripts and programmes used in processing files to generate results, database of pre-computed values of processed files.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="baw060f1p"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="baw060-T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Dataset and miR statistics<xref ref-type="fn" rid="baw060-TF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant species</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rice</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maize</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PMRD</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2773</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">269</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">miRBase(release 20)</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">713</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">321</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR known miRNA from PMRD and miRBase(release 20)</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2309</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">233</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">miR families</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2066</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recent publication miRNA added</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1806 (<xref rid="baw060-B10" ref-type="bibr">10&#x2013;14</xref>, miRBase (release 21), PNRD)</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (<xref rid="baw060-B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (<xref rid="baw060-B16" ref-type="bibr">16&#x2013;19</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total NR miRNA (miRBase + PMRD + publication miRs)</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1859</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2330</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">283</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Datasets analysed</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total number of reads analysed</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">342 103 946</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 536 339 049</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">616 360 780</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="baw060-TF1"><label>a</label><p>This table briefs about the miRNA source and their number of families, NR miRNAs, number of datasets for a species and total number of reads in these available datasets.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>sRNA sequencing libraries (datasets) collection</title>
        <p>The next generation sequencing (NGS) data of sRNA of wheat, rice and maize were collected from sequence read archive (SRA) database publicly available from National Center of Biotechnology Information (NCBI) website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra</ext-link>) (<xref rid="baw060-B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Twenty-one sRNA datasets (<xref rid="baw060-B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="baw060-B21" ref-type="bibr">21&#x2013;24</xref>) for four types of wheat tissues (leaf, spike, generic sample and whole plant), 53 sRNA datasets (<xref rid="baw060-B25" ref-type="bibr">25&#x2013;32</xref>) for nine types of rice tissues (whole plant, root, shoot, leaf, panicle, anther, embryo, endosperm and seedling) and 43 sRNA datasets (<xref rid="baw060-B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="baw060-B33" ref-type="bibr">33&#x2013;40</xref>) for 11 types of maize tissues (whole plant, root, shoot, leaf, ear, anther, tassel, pollen, silk, 5-day-old coleoptile and seedling), comprising in total 2.4+&#x2009;billion sequence reads were collected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="baw060-F1">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="baw060-T1">Table 1</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>). SRA files were converted into fasta format using fastq_dump function of fastx-toolkit and fastq to fasta using perl script and finally these fasta files were converted into databases by makeblastdb command of NCBI basic local search alignment tool (BLAST) 2.2.28+&#x2009;package. Respective species NR miRNA were BLASTn against NGS reads databases and results were filtered on the basis of perfect match for developing expression count matrixes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="baw060-F1">Figure 1</xref>). The size distribution of miRNA was estimated by adding expression count of same size miRNAs and taking percent value against total count of expressing miRNA in particular library (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Development of miRNA expression matrix</title>
        <p>SRA datasets were converted into BLAST databases by multiple steps of file processing using SRA toolkit and NCBI BLAST 2.2.28+&#x2009;package (<xref rid="baw060-B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Collected NR mature miRNA were used as query against respective wheat, rice and maize sRNA databases. BLASTn program and in-house shell scripts were used for computing miRNA abundance, following stringent criteria of 100% identity, 0 mismatch and 100% miRNA sequence coverage with sRNA database reads.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Data normalization and visualization</title>
        <p>Normalization was done by converting hit counts into transcript per million (TPM&#x2009;=&#x2009;number of miR count in dataset&#x2009;&#xD7; 1&#x2009;000&#x2009;000/total reads in dataset). Heatmaps were developed after log<sub>2</sub> transformation of TPM values. Normalized expression data (TPM) was sorted on ordinal basis and distributed in 10 categories according to the respective species miRNA numbers for each library/dataset. The heatmaps were developed for each species showing category 1&#x2013;10 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2 and Table S2</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Identification and profiling of conserved miRNA</title>
        <p>Conserved miRNA between W, R and M were identified on the basis of 100% sequence similarity. We found 51 conserved sequences in WRM (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>). These 51 miRNA were profiled against all 117 datasets of WRM (wheat-rice-maize). Forty-three miRNA of wheat out of 51 conserved miRNA were showing cumulative abundance above 100, likewise 48 of rice and 44 of maize (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S3</ext-link>). Conserved miRNA sequences belong to 24 miRNA families (miR156, miR159, miR160, miR164, miR166, miR167, miR168, miR169, miR171, miR172, miR2118, miR319, miR390, miR393, miR394, miR395, miR396, miR399, miR408, miR437, miR444, miR528, miR827 and miRf10461). Composition and length distribution of conserved miRNAs between W, R and M were plotted (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S4</ext-link>). We also identified 1639 unique miR in wheat, 2182 unique miR in rice and 137 unique miR in maize. Targets for these miRNA were predicted using psRNAtarget (<xref rid="baw060-B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>) tool at default parameters (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S3</ext-link>). Targets were predicted against available Unigene data files on psRNATarget interface (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S3</ext-link>).</p>
        <p>Conserved miRNA correlation matrix was also calculated for all datasets (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Differential expression analysis</title>
        <p>EdgeR package (<xref rid="baw060-B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) was used to calculate DE of miRNA. Library-wise DE analysis was performed using normalized TPM values of each library.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Tissue preferential analysis</title>
        <p>miRNA showing tissue preferential expression were screened by the cumulative TPM 80-fold greater than the mean TPM from other tissues (<xref rid="baw060-B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) along with Shannon entropy calculations using ROKU package (<xref rid="baw060-B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). We used default parameter of ROKU viz. upperlimit was kept at default value of 0.25 (specifying the maximum percent of tissue as outlier to each miRNA). ROKU picks tissue-specific patterns from expression data of different tissues and it ranks genes by its overall tissue-specificity using Shannon entropy and an outlier detection method for detecting tissues specific to each gene. Shannon entropy was introduced by Claude Shannon for use in communications technology. It is a measure of the information content. Using the combined approach, we found 14 miRNA preferentially expressing in leaves and 2 in spikes of wheat, whereas in rice 2 miRNA in root, 10 in leaf, 5 in anther and 8 in endosperm and in maize 1 miRNA in shoot, 2 in leaf, 2 in anther, 10 in ear, 1 in pollen and 1 in silk (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="baw060-F2">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="baw060-T2">Table 2</xref>). EdgeR package was also used for computing tissue-wise DE for pair of tissue of interest verses mean TPM from other tissues. Logarithmic fold change (logFC), logarithmic counts per million (logCPM), <italic>P</italic>-value and false discovery rate (FDR) values for such cases are available in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S5</ext-link>.
<fig id="baw060-F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Tissue preferential expression heatmap of wheat (<bold>A</bold>), rice (<bold>B</bold>) and maize (<bold>C</bold>). The tissue preferential miRNA were filtered on the basis of fold change (above 80-fold) expression as compared with other miRNA expression and the fold change values were calculated by cumulative TPM values of one tissue versus average of cumulative TPM of other tissues.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="baw060f2p"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="baw060-T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Tissue preferential miRNA list on the basis of fold change<xref ref-type="fn" rid="baw060-TF2"><sup>a</sup></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tissue</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Wheat tissue preferential miR<hr/></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Rice tissue preferential miR<hr/></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Maize tissue preferential miR<hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">miR_ID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold change</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shannon entropy</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">miR_ID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold change</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shannon entropy</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">miR_ID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold change</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shannon entropy</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR3979-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">322.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR3979-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">655.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shoot</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zma_miR_Seq07a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tae-miR156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR159e</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.142</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">zma-miR399b-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">185.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tae-miR156a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR1882e-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">415.469</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">zma-miR399d-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tae-miR2004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">339.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR2876-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176.546</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tae-miR2007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1023.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR2877</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131.767</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ath-miR169b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR396g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.339</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR1432-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR812k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5539.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tae-miR3131a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">235.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR3980a-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136.328</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR530-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR5827</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptc-miR156k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR1317</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.808</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">wheat-miR-363</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miRf10677-akr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.762</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">wheat-miR-392</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">wheat-miR-611</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">447.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">wheat-miR-683</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">198.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tae-miR2074_npr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spike</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tae-miR2016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tae-miR9677a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4098.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Panicle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anther</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR5484</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">255.586</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">zma-miR2275b-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR5485</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">796.998</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">zma-miR2275a-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">271.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR5486</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">167.182</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR5487</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">219.912</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR5490</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.212</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embryo</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endosperm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR1855</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.5798</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR1858a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128.149</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR1866-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">364.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR1874-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">187.517</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR1877</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">299.926</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR2091-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">273.874</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miR2102-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">226.394</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osa-miRf10941-akr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.026</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ear</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">zma-miR-n2g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">zma-miRs15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">zma-miRs18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zma_miR_Seq01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zma_miR_Seq04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5132029</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zma_miR_Seq06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238.282</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2583411</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zma_miR_Seq10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.1634</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.558418</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zma_miR_Seq12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">220.186</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2781626</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zma_miR_Seq14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">383.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.213312</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zma_miR_Seq15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">233.921</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2566291</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tassel</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pollen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">zma-miR159h-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.3895</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5971372</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">zma-miR167e-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117.691</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4833388</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coleoptile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="baw060-TF2"><label>a</label><p>NA, &#x2009;not available.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>New reported miRNA profiling</title>
        <p>To capture latest research insights, miRNA expression matrix were computed for novel plant miRNA from recent publications viz. miRNA sequences of wheat (<xref rid="baw060-B10" ref-type="bibr">10&#x2013;14</xref>, <xref rid="baw060-B46" ref-type="bibr">46&#x2013;48</xref>), rice (<xref rid="baw060-B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) and maize (<xref rid="baw060-B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="baw060-B16" ref-type="bibr">16&#x2013;18</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S5</ext-link>), which are not submitted in any public database like miRBase (release 20) and PMRD. Meanwhile, miRBase (version 21) was also released in June 2014, so we also collected miRNA from it. Total 1806 W, 23 R, 50 M novel miRNA were collected. We compared these miRNA sequences with the miRBase (release 20) and PMRD miRNA and made a NR sequences file for each species. These NR new miRNA were profiled against 21 W, 53 R and 43 M datasets. For each of these miRNA targets were predicted by psRNATarget (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S3</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>PmiRExAt database architecture and web interface</title>
        <p>PmiRExAt is created with a motive to make miRNA expression database searching easier and user friendly. The web portal is designed with responsive web design approach aimed at crafting it to provide an optimal viewing experience. PmiRExAt has been developed using open source Web 2.0 technologies to enhance the user experience at the web portal. It is developed using Java EE 6 standard and with model&#x2013;view&#x2013;controller (MVC) software pattern. MySQL database is used at backend. PmiRExAt uses power of Ajax to asynchronously call server and to provide results on the same page without page refreshing. We have made use of Hibernate object-relational mapping which consistently offers superior performance over straight Java Database Connectivity (JDBC) code in terms of runtime performance and is designed to work in an application server cluster and deliver a highly scalable architecture.</p>
        <p>PmiRExAt uses Highcharts application program interface (API) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.highcharts.com">http://www.highcharts.com</ext-link>) to generate heatmap (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="baw060-F3">Figure 3</xref>) and it also use Morpheus API (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/cancer/software/morpheus">http://www.broadinstitute.org/cancer/software/morpheus/</ext-link>) for clustering. PmiRExAt uses cocktail of different web technologies and other third party libraries to provide the user a pleasant experience at PmiRExAt. It uses Bootstrap front end framework to support various screen sizes and Ajax to update web pages asynchronously by exchanging small amounts of data with the server behind the scenes. This means that only parts of a web page get updated without reloading the whole page and thus eliminates the need for unnecessary page reloads.
<fig id="baw060-F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Architectural diagram of PmiRExAt<bold>.</bold> This architectural diagram displays basic design concept of PmiRExAt in MVC architectural pattern and collaboration of the MVC components.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="baw060f3p"/></fig>
</p>
        <p>PmiRExAt uses jQuery Tag-it plugin to handle multi-tag fields as well as tag suggestions/auto-complete which thus relieves the user of remembering all miRNAs and dataset names; auto completer automatically suggests all names present at PmiRExAt database as soon as user starts typing for names. For generating the heatmaps, it uses Highcharts charting library which generates interactive and dynamic maps. On hovering the cursor over the heatmap, it displays related information on Tooltip for each point on the heatmap.</p>
        <p>PmiRExAt also has an API which has published functionalities provided by the web interface to other software components, which want to use already present functionalities of the web interface. API offers application-components like getting all sequences, species or to perform search on PmiRExAt database using multiple search criteria.</p>
        <p>There are multiple tabs on web interface which provides the desired browsing, download and custom search options (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="baw060-F4">Figure 4</xref>). PmiRExAt users can do desired data mining in this rich processed resource. Apart from availability of intuitive web server interface, PmiRExAt also caters a simple object access protocol (SOAP) web service which allows other programmers to remotely invoke the methods written for doing search operations on database. Quick start guide (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary File S1</ext-link>) will help users in using web interface and API.
<fig id="baw060-F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>PmiRExAt features (web screen shots). (<bold>A</bold>) Search by miR ID: meant to search a miR expression by providing the miRNA Id. (<bold>B</bold>) Search by miRNA sequence: meant to search a miR expression by providing the miRNA sequence as available in miRBase (release 20, 21), PMRD, PNRD or as given in added publications. (<bold>C</bold>) Browse expression of conserved miRNA: sequences across wheat, rice and maize. (<bold>D</bold>) Browse expression of individual miRNA: in all datasets of particular species. (<bold>E</bold>) Related data: information of datasets and the miRNA sequences can be explored hereby using hyperlinks of miRNA and datasets. (<bold>F</bold>) PmiRExAt API: to use PmiRExAt API, user need to create a web service client in respective platform/language in which user want to use PmiRExAt API. (<bold>G</bold>) Heatmap: expression visualization is supported by heatmaps which is based on log TPM values. (<bold>H</bold>) Tissue preferential expression: the expression matrix of miRNA in selected tissue, filtered on the basis of fold change. (<bold>I</bold>) Download section: the pre-computed matrixes of all data and information of datasets can be downloaded here. (<bold>J</bold>) Custom search: this is a advanced feature enabling users to profile expression of novel miRNA against available 117 datasets or profile 73 plant species miRNA in user uploaded new dataset. (<bold>K</bold>) Job tracking: as user submit the job, system generates a key which is useful in tracking the job status and downloading the results. (<bold>L</bold>) DE analysis: search DE of miRNA by choosing dataset pair or browse DE between pair of control verses condition libraries.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="baw060f4p"/></fig>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Comparative analysis of web resources for miRNA expression analysis</title>
        <p>sRNA-seq data can be analysed in many ways to find out different aspects of research. Many tools have been developed to analyse data for miRNA expression. Here, we compared features of such available web resources against PmiRExAt to highlight the advantages offered by PmiRExAt. See feature comparison in <xref ref-type="table" rid="baw060-T3">Table 3</xref>.
<table-wrap id="baw060-T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Comparative feature between PmiRExAt and other web resources of miRNA expression analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">S.No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feature</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">mirEX/miREX<sup>2</sup> (<xref rid="baw060-B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="baw060-B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PsRobot (<xref rid="baw060-B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">omiRas (<xref rid="baw060-B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIRPIPE (<xref rid="baw060-B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PmiRExAt</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Browse pre-computed expression matrixes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species genome required for analysis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence conservation analysis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">API</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publically available datasets expression count database</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direct downloads of expression matrixes and heatmaps</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filter tissue preferential expressing miR on the basis of Shannon entropy and fold change</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contains novel miR reported in latest publication expression data</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Usage and utility</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Search miRNA expression by miRNA IDs or sequences</title>
        <p>A NR database of wheat 1859 miRNA, rice 2330 miRNA and maize 283 miRNA was developed from miRBase (release 20, 21), PMRD, plant non-coding RNA database (PNRD) and few miRNA from the publications (<xref ref-type="table" rid="baw060-T1">Table 1</xref>). On the basis of &#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;1000 TPM in individual datasets, 45 miRNA in wheat, 55 miRNA in rice and 27 miRNA of maize were considered highly expressing miRs. There were many miRNA which were showing zero cumulative abundance (576/1859 wheat, 320/2330 rice and 23/283 maize).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Search miRNA expression in particular tissue of species</title>
        <p>Expression of miRNA in a particular tissue can be searched by choosing the tissues of analysed datasets of selected species. User can select one or more than one tissue at a time. After clicking on search button, the expression count matrix will be displayed on interface. User can save expression matrix by &#x2018;Export table data&#x2019; button and user can also click on the hyperlink of miRs which will lead to the source database miRBase (release 21) and PMRD of miRNA for getting more information about the miRNA precursor, stem loop structure, function and its target. User can also generate expression heatmap by clicking on &#x2018;Generate heatmap&#x2019; button and can also generate clustered heatmap. User can download the heatmap in different picture formats like jpeg, pdf, etc. from &#x2018;chart context menu&#x2019; at upper most right-hand side of heatmap.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Custom search for newly detected miRNA sequences in 117 datasets</title>
        <p>Maximum five novel sequences can be uploaded at a time for computing their expression matrix against 117 WRM datasets. For this user will have to select &#x2018;Start Search&#x2019; from drop down menu of &#x2018;Custom search&#x2019; then user can input miRNA sequences in fasta format. User has to enter a functional email ID for receiving the result. User can also customize BLASTn parameters viz. percent identity, mismatch and query coverage or user can choose default values. After user has submitted the job, a random key unique to each job is generated on interface that can be used to track the running job or downloading the results.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Custom search of miRNAs expression in new library of sRNA sequences</title>
        <p>Newly generated sRNA libraries can be analysed for the PmiRExAt miRs and all other plant species miRNA sequences of miRBase (release 21). Here, user needs to register to get benefits of this facility. After registering the user needs to login and upload the SRA file in zip format and choose the desired plant species to develop expression matrix. Custom search feature is also facilitated with tracking the running job status or download the results by entering the key generated at the time of job submission.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>SOAP API and client</title>
        <p>There is link to access SOAP web service and Wsdl for API. SOAP message can be formulated and parsed in any chosen languages by application developers. This functionality will be helpful to other programmers/software components to connect to PmiRExAt API.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Download files</title>
        <p>All the processed data contained in database that is used to generate the expression tables and heatmaps can be downloaded.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conclusion and future work</title>
      <p>PmiRExAt database interface has the following unique features: (i) to search miRNA expression by miRNA ID/s or sequence/s. (ii) To search miRNA expression in particular datasets or tissue/s. (iii) To filter tissue preferentially expressing miRNA. (iv) &#x2018;Browse&#x2019; or &#x2018;Search&#x2019;, &#x2018;DE&#x2019; on the basis of edgeR calculation. (v) To browse miRNA expression across species. (vi) To compute and profile expression of newly detected miRNA sequence in 117 datasets, and also new datasets can be uploaded for expression profiling with NR miRNAs of WRM and other 70 plant species mature miR from miRBase (release 21, June 2014). (vii) High-resolution heatmaps are generated on the web interface that helps in visualization and interpretations. This web resource and service will help plant science community in studying expression patterns of miRNAs. This website and web service is free and open to all users. Meta-analysis of the publicly available sRNA-seq datasets showed significant expression patterns of several miRs. Data mining in this developed resource has already led to identification of tissue preferential expressing and conserved miRNA. PmiRExAt will help in exploring public sRNA-seq expression data to find supporting evidence for users&#x2019; findings and hypotheses. These expression profiles can be used as a proxy for relative expression levels of miRNA sequences. It will aid in studying plant miRNA gene function by studying where, when and in response to what these miRNA are expressed.</p>
      <p>As we expect this project to get bigger in near future, so PmiRExAt is developed keeping an eye on the scalable aspects of the datasets viz. species, miRs, etc. We will keep adding novel miRNA sequences and new sRNA libraries of wheat, rice and maize for better comparative analysis. We will also be adding other agri-food plant species in PmiRExAt database. We will further classify datasets on the basis of developmental stage for more specificity in comparative analysis of miRNA. Micro RNA expression matrices will be useful for studying miRNA regulatory networks in plants.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary data</title>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://database.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/database/baw060/-/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link> are available at <italic>Database</italic> Online.</p>
      <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Data</title>
        </caption>
        <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_2016_baw060_index.html"/>
        <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="x-zip-compressed" xlink:href="supp_baw060_suppl_data.zip"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>The authors thank Executive Director, NABI for encouragement and advice. Technical networking assistance from Sukhjinder Singh, NABI is greatly appreciated.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This work was financially supported by the core grant of National Agri-Food Biotechnology Institute (NABI), Mohali, India an autonomous institute of Department of Biotechnology, Government of India. Funding for open access charge- National Agri-Food Biotechnology Institute (NABI), Mohali, India.</p>
      <p><italic>Conflict of interest</italic>. None declared.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors&#x2019; Contribution</title>
      <p>Project conceptualization and study design: SSM; Data collection and analysis : AKSG; Database design and web interface development: ASP Manuscript preparation and approval of final draft: AKSG, ASP, RG and SSM.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="baw060-B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nussbaumer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kugler</surname><given-names>K.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>K.C</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>RNASeqExpressionBrowser - a web interface to browse and visualize high-throughput expression data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>2519</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2520</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24833805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krupp</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquardt</surname><given-names>J.U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahin</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>RNA-Seq Atlas-a reference database for gene expression profiling in normal tissue by next-generation sequencing</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1184</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1185</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22345621</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuenne</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preussner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>MIRPIPE : quantification of microRNAs in niche model organisms</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>3412</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3413</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25165094</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zielezinski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolata</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alaba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>mirEX 2.0 - an integrated environment for expression profiling of plant microRNAs</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>., <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>144.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26141515</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#xFC;ller</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rycak</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>omiRas: a web server for differential expression analysis of miRNAs derived from small RNA-Seq data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>2651</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2652</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23946503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>PsRobot: a web-based plant small RNA meta-analysis toolbox</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>22</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-based biotechnology for plant improvement</article-title>. <source>J. Cell. Physiol.</source>, <volume>230</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24909308</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grocock</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Dongen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>miRBase: microRNA sequences, targets and gene nomenclature</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>D140</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>D144</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381832</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>PMRD: plant microRNA database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>806</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>813</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Uncovering small RNAmediated responses to cold stress in a wheat thermosensitive genic male-sterile line by deep sequencing</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>., <volume>159</volume>, <fpage>721</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>738</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22508932</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>A.R</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>A comprehensive genome-wide study on tissue-specific and abiotic stress-specific miRNAs in <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>e95800</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24759739</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Whole-genome discovery of miRNAs and their targets in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>., <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>142.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24885911</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>K.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dole&#x17E;el</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>A chromosome-based draft sequence of the hexaploid bread wheat (Triticum aestivum) genome</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>345</volume>(<issue>6194</issue>), <fpage>1251788</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25035500</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Identification and comparative analysis of differentially expressed miRNAs in leaves of two wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) genotypes during dehydration stress</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>., <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25592487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Identification of 23 novel conserved microRNAs in three rice cultivars</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>, <volume>548</volume>, <fpage>285</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>293</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25038275</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterisation of maize microRNAs involved in developing ear</article-title>. <source>Plant Biol.</source>, <volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>9</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23668946</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Identification and validation of miRNAs associated with the resistance of maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.) to <italic>Exserohilum turcicum.</italic></article-title>
<source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B18">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Identification of miRNAs and their target genes in developing maize ears by combined small RNA and degradome sequencing</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>25.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24422852</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B19">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thiebaut</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grativol</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide identification of microRNA and siRNA responsive to endophytic beneficial diazotrophic bacteria in maize</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>766.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25194793</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B20">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leinonen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugawara</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shumway</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The sequence read archive</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20805246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B21">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Novel microRNAs uncovered by deep sequencing of small RNA transcriptomes in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) and <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> (L.) Beauv</article-title>. <source>Funct. Integr. Genomics</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>499</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>511</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19499258</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B22">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanzetti</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Small RNAs, DNA methylation and transposable elements in wheat</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>408.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20584339</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B23">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterization of wheat long non-protein coding RNAs responsive to powdery mildew infection and heat stress by using microarray analysis and SBS sequencing</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>., <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>61.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21473757</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B24">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kenan-Eichler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leshkowitz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Wheat hybridization and polyploidization results in deregulation of small RNAs</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>188</volume>, <fpage>263</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>272</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21467573</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B25">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Deep sequencing on genome-wide scale reveals the unique composition and expression patterns of microRNAs in developing pollen of <italic>Oryza sativa.</italic></article-title>
<source>Genome Biol</source>., <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>R53.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21679406</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B26">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Strand-specific RNA-seq reveals widespread occurrence of novel cis-natural antisense transcripts in rice</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>721.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23259405</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B27">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ai</surname><given-names>T.B</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA profiles and their control of male gametophyte development in rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol. Biol</source>., <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>85</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>102</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22403030</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B28">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romag</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Physiological stressors and invasive plant infections alter the small RNA transcriptome of the rice blast fungus, <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae.</italic></article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>326.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23663523</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B29">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stroud</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>S.A</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Plants regenerated from tissue culture contain stable epigenome changes in rice</article-title>. <source>Elife</source>, <volume>2013</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B30">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Imprinted expression of genes and small RNA is associated with localized hypomethylation of the maternal genome in rice endosperm</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</source>., <volume>110</volume>, <fpage>7934</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7939</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23613580</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B31">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Deep RNA sequencing at single base-pair resolution reveals high complexity of the rice transcriptome</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>., <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>646</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>654</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20305017</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B32">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addo-Quaye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Transcriptome-wide identification of microRNA targets in rice</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>., <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>742</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>759</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20202174</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B33">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A genome-wide characterization of microRNA genes in maize</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>., <volume>5</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>e1000716</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19936050</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B34">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gent</surname><given-names>J.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Strong epigenetic similarity between maize centromeric and pericentromeric regions at the level of small RNAs, DNA methylation and H3 chromatin modifications</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1550</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1560</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22058126</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B35">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>W.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Win</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Repeat associated small RNAs vary among parents and following hybridization in maize</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</source>., <volume>109</volume>, <fpage>10444</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10449</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22689990</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B36">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>S.A</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Plant microRNAs display differential 3&#x2019; truncation and tailing modifications that are ARGONAUTE1 dependent and conserved across species</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>2417</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2428</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23839787</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B37">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nobuta</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shrivastava</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Distinct size distribution of endogeneous siRNAs in maize: evidence from deep sequencing in the mop1-1 mutant</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A</source>., <volume>105</volume>, <fpage>14958</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>14963</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18815367</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B38">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Detailed analysis of a contiguous 22-Mb region of the maize genome</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>., <volume>5</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>e1000728</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19936048</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B39">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>Y.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X.Y</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>High-throughput sequencing of small RNAs from pollen and silk and characterization of miRNAs as candidate factors involved in pollen-silk interactions in maize</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>8</volume>(<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>e72852</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23991159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B40">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Regulski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kendall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The maize methylome influences mRNA splice sites and reveals widespread paramutation-like switches guided by small RNA</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>., <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1651</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1662</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23739895</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B41">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulouris</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Avagyan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>BLAST+: architecture and applications</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>421.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003500</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B42">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P.X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>PsRNATarget: a plant small RNA target analysis server</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>155</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>159</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20817928</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B43">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G.K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>edgeR: a bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>139</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>140</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B44">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide survey of tissue-specific microRNA and transcription factor regulatory networks in 12 tissues</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep</source>., <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>5150.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24889152</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B45">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadota</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>ROKU: a novel method for identification of tissue-specific genes</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>294.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16764735</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B46">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterization of microRNAs in the flag leaf and developing seed of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>289.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24734873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B47">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozomara</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>MiRBase: annotating high confidence microRNAs using deep sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>68</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B48">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>PNRD : a plant non-coding RNA database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="baw060-B49">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bielewicz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolata</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zielezinski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>mirEX: a platform for comparative exploration of plant pri-miRNA expression data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic acids research</source>., <volume>40</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>), <fpage>D191</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>D197</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22013167</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
