<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2882260</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erq097</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Papers</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Dosage effect of the short arm of chromosome 1 of rye on root morphology and anatomy in bread wheat</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sharma</surname>
            <given-names>Sundrish</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>DeMason</surname>
            <given-names>Darleen A.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ehdaie</surname>
            <given-names>Bahman</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lukaszewski</surname>
            <given-names>Adam J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Waines</surname>
            <given-names>J. Giles</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Department of Botany and Plant Sciences, University of California, Riverside, CA 92521-0124, USA</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed: E-mail: <email>giles.waines@ucr.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>5</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>5</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>61</volume>
      <issue>10</issue>
      <fpage>2623</fpage>
      <lpage>2633</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>9</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2010 The Author(s).</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
          <license-p>This paper is available online free of all access charges (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html">http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html</ext-link> for further details)</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The spontaneous translocation of the short arm of chromosome 1 of rye (1RS) in bread wheat is associated with higher root biomass and grain yield. Recent studies have confirmed the presence of QTL for different root morphological traits on the 1RS arm in bread wheat. This study was conducted to address two questions in wheat root genetics. First, does the presence of the 1RS arm in bread wheat affect its root anatomy? Second, how does root morphology and anatomy of bread wheat respond to different dosages of 1RS? Near-isogenic plants with a different number (0 to 4 dosages) of 1RS translocations were studied for root morphology and anatomy. The F<sub>1</sub> hybrid, with single doses of the 1RS and 1AS arms, showed heterosis for root and shoot biomass. In other genotypes, with 0, 2, or 4 doses of 1RS, root biomass was incremental with the increase in the dosage of 1RS in bread wheat. This study also provided evidence of the presence of gene(s) influencing root xylem vessel number, size, and distribution in bread wheat. It was found that root vasculature follows a specific developmental pattern along the length of the tap root and 1RS dosage tends to affect the transitions differentially in different positions. This study indicated that the inherent differences in root morphology and anatomy of different 1RS lines may be advantageous compared to normal bread wheat to survive under stress conditions.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>1RS translocation</kwd>
        <kwd>dosage effect</kwd>
        <kwd>heterosis</kwd>
        <kwd>root anatomy</kwd>
        <kwd>root morphology</kwd>
        <kwd>stress adaptation</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>All higher plants have roots and the root fraction of the plant's total mass varies widely, even within the same species. Although, roots encounter many fluctuations in their external environment<strike>s</strike> that affect their growth, it is their tendency to accommodate and survive these as a whole system that makes them strongly homoeostatic (Barlow, 1986). Knowledge of these modifications in the root system at a morphological and anatomical level, whether due to environmental response or genetic control, is of importance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Weaver, 1926</xref>).</p>
      <p>Root morphological traits and root growth response to the external environment have been studied widely in a number of crop species. In a greenhouse study, drought-stressed <italic>Lolium perenne</italic> L. plants increased the number and growth of lateral roots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Jupp and Newman, 1987</xref>). In barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L.), potassium deficiency was associated with the reduced length of laterals and larger root diameter compared with phosphorus deficiency under greenhouse conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Hackett, 1968</xref>). In wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.), temperature had a profound effect on dry weight and root length under greenhouse environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bowen and Rovira, 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Huang, 1991</xref>). Besides root morphology, anatomical traits are also greatly influenced by the surrounding environment and have been widely studied in different crop species such as maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Hose <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>), rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Uga <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), and other cereals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Aloni and Griffith, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Liljeroth, 1995</xref>). In controlled environmental growth chamber-grown winter and spring wheat, chilling and high temperature decreases the diameter of the central metaxylem vessel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Huang <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Terzioglu and Ekmekci, 1995</xref>).</p>
      <p>There are reports which suggest that specific morphological and anatomical root traits help stress-tolerant plants survive a particular stress condition. In rice, traits such as deep root-to-shoot ratio and deep specific root length were found to contribute to drought avoidance in the field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Yoshida and Hasegawa, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Fukai and Cooper, 1995</xref>). Drought-tolerant wheat cultivars have smaller xylem vessel diameters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). This anatomical adaptation of the tolerant wheat genotypes proved to be an advantage for the survival and higher grain yield under water stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Richards and Passioura, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Huang <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Huang and Taylor, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Ou <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>).</p>
      <p>The genetic control of root characteristics is poorly understood especially in bread wheat. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Robertson <italic>et al.</italic> (1979)</xref> characterized genetic variability for seedling root number within the genus <italic>Triticum</italic> to examine its value in a breeding programme and found this trait to be positively correlated with seed weight. In a field study in winter wheat, post-anthesis root growth was investigated and cultivars were found to be significantly different in root length and mass especially below 30 cm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Ford <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">O'Brien (1979)</xref> examined different wheat genotypes for root development in glass-fronted growth containers in the greenhouse and reported that the variability in seminal roots was sufficient for the root morphology to be altered by hybridization and selection. In bread wheat, xylem vessel diameter was found to have more useful genetic variation and higher heritability than the number of seminal axes in the roots and they showed a significant response to selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Richards and Passioura, 1989</xref>). In a wheat backcross breeding programme, lines selected for reduced xylem vessel diameter yielded 3&#x2013;11% more grain in the driest environments than unselected controls, depending on the genetic background (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Richards and Passioura, 1989</xref>). Besides these findings, there is still no report in bread wheat of the chromosomal localization of genes that affect root anatomy.</p>
      <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Weaver (1926)</xref> compared the root systems of rye and bread wheat under natural field conditions and reported that rye had deeper seminal roots. The spontaneous translocation of the short arm of chromosome 1 of rye (1RS) (<italic>Secale cereale</italic> L.) to the long arm of chromosome 1B (1BL) in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) was first identified in the late 1930s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Kattermann, 1938</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Mettin <italic>et al.</italic>, 1973</xref>). Over the past few decades, there have been several reports of higher grain yield of 1RS translocated wheats over other commonly grown wheat genotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Rajaram <italic>et al.</italic>, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Villareal <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Owuoche <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Kim <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). In other studies, an increase in grain yield among 1RS wheats was found to be positively correlated with higher root biomass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Ehdaie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>) while there were no significant differences found for shoot traits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Kim <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Roots of 1RS.1BL translocation wheats were thinner and there was a higher root length density when grown in acid soils and this enhanced the root surface area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Manske and Vlek, 2002</xref>).</p>
      <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Lukaszewski (1993)</xref> reconstructed the complete chromosomes of 1B and 1R from a 1RS.1BL translocation and, later, produced three new centric translocations namely, 1RS.1AL, 1RS.1BL, and 1RS.1DL in &#x2018;Pavon 76&#x2019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Lukaszewski, 1997</xref>). Each of three translocations had the same 1RS arm but in different locations in the genome and each was mitotically stable. All three translocations had greater root biomass and higher grain yield under irrigated and water-stressed greenhouse conditions and under irrigated field conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Ehdaie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Kumlay <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). These translocation lines were ranked for root biomass as Pavon 1RS.1AL&gt;Pavon 1RS.1DL&gt;Pavon 1RS.1BL&gt;Pavon 76 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Ehdaie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). Recently, a genetic map was generated using 1RS-1BS recombinant breakpoints in Pavon 76 wheat and their genetic analysis indicated the distal 15% of the physical length of chromosome 1RS may carry the gene(s) for better rooting ability and root morphological traits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Sharma <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p>
      <p>The present study was conducted to address the dosage effect of the 1RS translocation in bread wheat. Wheat genotypes were used that differ in their number of the 1RS translocations in a spring bread wheat &#x2018;Pavon 76&#x2019; genetic background. For generating F<sub>1</sub> seeds, Pavon 1RS.1AL was the preferred parent of choice due to its better performance for root biomass than other 1RS lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Ehdaie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). The dosage effect of a 1RS chromosome arm on different root traits including root biomass, root diameter, stele diameter, central metaxylem (CMX) vessel diameter, CMX vessel area, CMX vessel number, and number of xylem poles of wheat roots is reported here. The results from this study may validate previous results of the presence of genes for rooting ability on the 1RS chromosome arm. This study also provides evidence for the presence of genes affecting root anatomy on the 1RS arm.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Plant material</title>
        <p>Five genotypes, Pavon 76, F<sub>1</sub> (Pavon 1RS.1AL&#xD7;Pavon 76), Pavon 1RS.1AL, Pavon 1RS.1DL, and Pavon 1RS.1AL-Pavon 1RS.1DL were used. They were coded as R<sub>0</sub>, RA<sub>1</sub>, RA<sub>2</sub>, RD<sub>2</sub>, and RAD<sub>4</sub>, respectively. Here, &#x2018;R&#x2019; denoted the dosage of chromosome arm 1RS, the second letter A and D denoted the chromosome 1 of the respective genome of wheat to which 1RS is translocated and numbers in the subscripts are dosage number of 1RS chromosome arms present in the genotype. Pavon 76 is a spring bread wheat from the breeding programme of Centro Internacional de Mejoramiento de Ma&#xED;z y Trigo (CIMMYT), Mexico. For a single dose of 1RS, crosses were made between Pavon 1RS.1AL and Pavon 76 and F<sub>1</sub> seed was used as RA<sub>1</sub>. Seeds of RA<sub>2</sub>, RD<sub>2</sub>, and RAD<sub>4</sub> genotypes were provided by Dr AJ Lukaszewski, University of California, Riverside.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Experimental set-up</title>
        <p>To study the effect of different dosages of the 1RS chromosome arm of rye in a wheat background and their effect on root morphology, an experiment was set up in a randomized complete block design with six replicates per genotype during January 2007, April 2007, January 2008, and January 2009. The genotypes were grown under a natural photoperiod in a temperature controlled greenhouse (20&#x2013;30 &#xB0;C and 50&#x2013;90% relative humidity). Anatomy of the primary seminal roots or specifically the primary axile roots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Watt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) was studied for two of these seasons. Seminal roots and primary-axile roots are mentioned from here onwards as tap root in accordance with root nomenclature guidelines (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rootrap.boku.ac.at/index.php?id=28">http://rootrap.boku.ac.at/index.php?id=28</ext-link>). Seeds from the above-mentioned five genotypes were surface-sterilized with 5% commercial bleach for 5&#x2002;min, washed for 10 min in distilled water, soaked in water for 24 h, and then germinated on wet filter paper in Petri dishes. 3&#x2013;5-d-old seedlings were transplanted to 7.5 l cylindrical pots (21&#xD7;21.5 cm diameter), lined with a plastic bag containing 6.5 kg of washed silica sand no. 30 with bulk density of 1.42 g ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> and 24% field capacity (w/w). Small holes were made at the bottom of the plastic bags to allow drainage of excess water. Plants were watered, when necessary, with half-strength Hoagland's solution to ensure that nutrients and water were not limiting.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Phenotypic data</title>
        <p>Plants were harvested 45 d after germination at the mid-to-late tillering stage or Decimal code of 28&#x2013;29 for growth stages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Zadoks <italic>et al.</italic>, 1974</xref>) and pots containing roots in polythene bags were stored at 4 &#xB0;C until processed. Each polythene bag was laid out on a screen frame in a tub half-filled with water and a cut was made on the side of the bag. The frame was moved gently in the tub to separate sand from the roots. Roots were recovered without damage using the floatation technique (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">B&#xF6;hm, 1979</xref>) and attached sand was removed by hand. Different plant characters were measured including plant height (PH), number of tillers (NT), longest leaf length (LLL), maximum width of the longest leaf (LLW), leaf area of the longest leaf (LA), longest root length (LRL), root biomass (RB), shoot biomass (SB), and root biomass to shoot biomass ratio (R/S). Root and shoot biomass was determined from dry matter after drying to constant weight in a forced-air drier for 96 h at 65 &#xB0;C. Leaf area of the longest leaf was calculated by LLL&#xD7;LLW&#xD7;0.78 for each genotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Quarrie and Jones, 1977</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Heterosis</title>
        <p>Mid-parent heterosis (MPH) and best-parent heterosis (BPH) of the F<sub>1</sub> hybrid (RA<sub>1</sub>) over its parents (R<sub>0</sub> and RA<sub>2</sub>) for root biomass and shoot biomass were calculated as:<disp-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="jexboterq097fx1_ht.jpg"/></disp-formula></p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Root anatomy</title>
        <p>After washing, root samples were collected in two different seasons from the tap roots of six plants of each genotype at three different locations, namely root tip, middle of the root, and 1 cm from the base of the root adjacent to the seed. Root samples were immersed in half-strength Karnovosky's fixative (2.5% gluteraldehyde and 4% formaldehyde in 50 mM phosphate buffer, pH 7.2). The roots were left in the fixative at 4 &#xB0;C for 24 h. The roots were dehydrated by passing through a graded ethanol series of 10%, 35%, 50%, and 70% and then left overnight in 70% ethanol followed by another 2 h treatment in 85%, 90%, and 100% and then subsequently overnight in 100% with 1% Erythrosine B (C.I. 11A). Then the samples were transferred through an ethanol/xylene series of 3/1, 1/1, and 1/3 for 30 min to 1 h each. Tissues were then placed in pure xylene for 2 h followed by overnight treatment. Infiltration and embedding was done in paraffin.</p>
        <p>Paraffin blocks containing tissues were sectioned at 10 &#x3BC;m thick using an A/O rotary Microtome and stainless steel knives. Root tips were serially sectioned in the transverse plane starting at the tip of the root cap. Sections were mounted on slides and stained with Safranin O (C.I. 50240) and Fast Green FCF (C.I.# 19) using Sass's procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Ruzin, 1999</xref>). Samples were observed on a Zeiss standard compound brightfield microscope. Digital images were taken using an Infinity 1 digital camera (Luminere Inc, Canada). Data were recorded for the different root anatomical features such as root diameter, stele diameter, central metaxylem (CMX) vessel diameter, CMX vessel area, CMX vessel number, and number of xylem poles from different regions of the roots of all the above-mentioned five genotypes. Data on CMX vessel diameter and area were made on transverse sections of root tips at a distance of 1370 &#x3BC;m from the tip for all genotypes. At this position the CMX vessel was clearly evident and there was no significant difference in the position of its appearance from the root tip between the genotypes. Calibrations and measurements were carried out by camera compliant software &#x2018;Analyse Infinity&#x2019; (Luminere Inc, Canada).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>The morphological data were subjected to analysis of variance (ANOVA) for each year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Steel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). The combined ANOVA across seasons was performed for each measured and calculated trait using a split plot design in time. Season was treated as the main plot and genotype as a sub-plot. In combined ANOVA, all the factors were considered fixed. The anatomical data were also subjected to ANOVA to determine the genetic differences among genotypes. Simple correlation coefficients were calculated to determine the relationship among different anatomical traits. Linear regression analysis was carried out for different anatomical root traits to assess the relationship between dosage of the 1RS chromosome arm and the root anatomical traits in bread wheat. Statistix 8 program (Analytical Software, Tallahassee FL) was used to carry out correlation and regression analysis.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Phenotypic study</title>
        <p>There was lesser total root biomass in Pavon 76 (R<sub>0</sub>) than any of its 1RS sister lines. Among the 1RS lines, F<sub>1</sub> (RA<sub>1</sub>) and RAD<sub>4</sub> had the highest root biomass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). There were significant differences among genotypes for plant height, number of tillers, length of longest leaf, maximum width of longest leaf, root biomass, shoot biomass, and root to shoot ratio (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). For leaf area, differences among genotypes were not significant. All the genotypes showed significant difference for all the phenotypic traits across the seasons (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05). Genotype &#xD7; season interactions (P &lt;0.01) were not significant for leaf area and root-to-shoot ratio. The RAD<sub>4</sub> genotype had the highest number of tillers, longest leaf length, and maximum root-to-shoot ratio but the shortest plant height, minimum width of longest leaf measured at its widest point, and minimum leaf area of the longest leaf. The RA<sub>1</sub> hybrid performed significantly differently from other genotypes for root biomass and shoot biomass (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05). Mean values of RA<sub>2</sub> were higher for maximum width of the longest leaf and leaf area. For root biomass, RA<sub>1</sub> and RAD<sub>4</sub> were significantly different from RA<sub>2</sub>, RD<sub>2</sub>, and check R<sub>0</sub> (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). RA<sub>2</sub> was significantly different from RD<sub>2</sub>, and check R<sub>0</sub> only at P &lt;0.01 data not shown). All the genotypes were significantly similar for shoot biomass except RA<sub>1</sub> which was significantly different from them (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Summary of combined ANOVA and mean values of plant height (PH), number of tillers (NT), longest leaf length (LLL), maximum width of the longest leaf (LLW), leaf area of the longest leaf (LA), root biomass per plant (RB), shoot biomass per plant (SB), and root to shoot biomass ratio (R/S) for bread wheat Pavon 76 (R<sub>0</sub>), F<sub>1</sub>, Pavon 1RS.1AL&#xD7;Pavon 76 (RA<sub>1</sub>), Pavon 1RS.1AL (RA<sub>2</sub>), Pavon 1RS.1DL (RD<sub>2</sub>), and Pavon 1RS.1AL-Pavon 1RS.1DL (RAD<sub>4</sub>) grown in sand pots for 45 d (mid to late tillering stage) averaged across four seasons</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PH<italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">a</xref></italic></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT<italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">a</xref></italic></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LLL<italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">a</xref></italic></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LLW<italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">a</xref></italic></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LA<italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">a</xref></italic></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RB<italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">a</xref></italic></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SB<italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">a</xref></italic></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R/S<italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">a</xref></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(cm)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(no.)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(cm)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(cm)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(cm<sup>2</sup>)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mg)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mg)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sub>0</sub></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 c</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38 ab</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.1 ab</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1073 bc</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3692 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 bc</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RA<sub>1</sub></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.7 ab</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1549 a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4319 a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 ab</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RA<sub>2</sub></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.9 a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1232 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3802 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 ab</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RD<sub>2</sub></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 c</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 bc</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 ab</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.3 ab</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1087 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3637 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 c</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAD<sub>4</sub></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 c</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 c</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.1 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1461 a</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3743 b</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Season</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype&#xD7;Season</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CV (%)<italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">b</xref></italic></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tblfn1">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>Means followed by the same small letter within a column are not significantly different at <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05 according to LSD test; **=significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01); NS=not significant (<italic>P</italic> &gt;0.05).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="tblfn2">
              <label>b</label>
              <p>CV=Coefficient of variation.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <fig id="fig1" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Roots of different wheat genotypes with different number of 1RS translocations in spring bread wheat &#x2018;Pavon 76&#x2019; background harvested 45 d after germination (grown in pots). Pavon 76 (R0)=0 dose of 1RS, Pavon 1RS.1AL&#xD7;Pavon 76 (RA1)=1 dose of 1RS, Pavon 1RS.1AL (RA2)=2 doses of 1RS on 1AL, Pavon 1RS.1DL (RD2)=2 doses of 1RS on 1DL, and Pavon 1RS.1AL- Pavon 1RS.1DL (RAD4) = 4 doses of 1RS on 1AL and 1DL. (This figure is available in colour at <italic>JXB</italic> online.)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq097f01_3c"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Mid-parent and best-parent heterosis</title>
        <p>Mean values of the F<sub>1</sub> hybrid (RA<sub>1</sub>) were significantly different from both of its parents (R<sub>0</sub> and RA<sub>2</sub>) for root biomass and shoot biomass (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). MPH and BPH for root biomass were calculated to be 34.4% and 25.7%, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). For shoot biomass, heterotic gain of F<sub>1</sub> over mid-parent and best-parent was 15.3% and 13.6%, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float">
          <label>Table 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Mid-parent heterosis (MPH) and best-parent heterosis (BPH) for root and shoot biomass (per plant) of bread wheat hybrid F<sub>1</sub> - Pavon 1RS.1AL&#xD7;Pavon 76 (RA<sub>1</sub>) over parents Pavon 1RS.1AL (RA<sub>2</sub>) and Pavon 76 (R<sub>0</sub>) grown in sand pots for 45 d (mid-tillering stage).</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Trait</td>
                <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Mean</td>
                <td rowspan="3" colspan="1">MPH (%)</td>
                <td rowspan="3" colspan="1">BPH (%)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hybrid (RA<sub>1</sub>)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mid-parent</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Best-parent (RA<sub>2</sub>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mg)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mg)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mg)</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root biomass</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1549</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1153</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1232</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.4</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shoot biomass</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4319</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3747</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3802</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>Mean values are averaged across four seasons.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Root anatomy along the root</title>
        <p>To study root anatomy, the two seasons selected were representative of the four seasons used for the study. For most of the phenotypic traits, including root and shoot biomass, genetic differences observed across four years were also statistically significant when the data across the two years (in which the microscopy was done) were analysed separately. The size, number, and arrangement of metaxylem vessels varied along the length of the tap root from the top to the tip region for each genotype. In the top region, there were 3&#x2013;6 large metaxylem vessels that were not necessarily central in position. More of these were present in the transverse sections of R<sub>0</sub>, RA<sub>1</sub>, and RA<sub>2</sub> than in RD<sub>2</sub> and RAD<sub>4</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A&#x2013;E</xref>). In the latter genotypes, especially RAD<sub>4</sub>, there was variation for number and arrangement of CMX vessels in the basal portion transverse sections of the tap root (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A, B, C</xref>). A partial ring of smaller metaxylem vessels surrounding the bigger CMX vessel was observed in some of the tap roots where there was only a single CMX vessel. Similar variation was also observed in RD<sub>2</sub> (data not shown). The diameter of the stele was larger in R<sub>0</sub> and RA<sub>1</sub> than RA<sub>2</sub>, RD<sub>2</sub>, and RAD<sub>4</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A&#x2013;E</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig2" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Stained transverse sections of different regions (A&#x2013;E top, F&#x2013;J middle, K&#x2013;0 tip) of roots of wheat genotypes. (A, F, K) Pavon 76 (R<sub>0</sub>); (B, G, L) F<sub>1</sub> of Pavon 1RS.1AL&#xD7;Pavon 76 (RA<sub>1</sub>); (C, H, M) Pavon 1RS.1AL (RA<sub>2</sub>); (D, I, N) Pavon 1RS.1DL (RD<sub>2</sub>); (E, J, O) Pavon 1RS.1AL-Pavon 1RS.1DL (RAD<sub>4</sub>); (F) is labelled with C, cortex; CMX, central metaxylem vessel; E, endodermis; PX, protoxylem; Scale bar, 100 &#x3BC;m.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq097f02_3c"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="fig3" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>(A, B, C) Examples of patterns seen in the number of CMX vessels in the top region of tap root of the RAD<sub>4</sub> genotype (four doses of 1RS chromosome arm). (B) is labelled with arrowheads, inner xylem vessels; C, cortex; CMX, central metaxylem vessel; E, endodermis; PX, protoxylem; Scale bar, 100 &#x3BC;m.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq097f03_3c"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In the middle region of the root, there were two centrally located metaxylem vessels in the stele of R<sub>0</sub> and RA<sub>1</sub> and a single CMX vessel in RD<sub>2</sub> and RAD<sub>4</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2F&#x2013;J</xref>). The diameter of the stele was smaller in the middle than in the top region of the root for most of the genotypes (data not shown). In the root tip region, there was a single differentiating CMX vessel in all the genotypes which was narrower in RA<sub>2</sub>, RD<sub>2</sub>, and RAD<sub>4</sub> genotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2M, N, O</xref>). There was not much variation for other anatomical traits in the root tip region among the genotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2K&#x2013;O</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Top region of the root (TOP)</title>
        <p>There were significant differences among genotypes for stele diameter, total metaxylem vessel area, number of CMX vessels, and number of xylem poles in the top region of the tap root. Differences among genotypes were not significant for xylem diameter, CMX number, and root diameter but all genotypes showed the same trend in their performance for all the root anatomical traits measured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A&#x2013;F</xref>). Hybrid RA1 was the largest among genotypes, except for root diameter, followed by R<sub>0</sub>, for all the traits in the top region of the tap root while RAD<sub>4</sub> was the smallest.</p>
        <fig id="fig4" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Graphical representation of mean performances of anatomical traits: (A) stele diameter; (B) metaxylem vessel diameter; (C) number of central metaxylem vessels; (D) total metaxylem vessel area; (E) number of xylem poles (protoxylem); and (F) root diameter measured from top region of the roots of each wheat genotype with different number of 1RS translocation arms in the genetic background of spring bread wheat &#x2018;Pavon 76&#x2019;. The same small letters within a graph are not significantly different. <italic>X</italic>-axis, bread wheat genotypes namely Pavon 76 (R0)=0 dose of 1RS, Pavon 1RS.1AL&#xD7;Pavon 76 (RA1)=1 dose of 1RS, Pavon 1RS.1AL (RA2)=2 doses of 1RS on 1AL, Pavon 1RS.1DL (RD2)=2 doses of 1RS on 1DL, and Pavon 1RS.1AL- Pavon 1RS.1DL (RAD4)=4 doses of 1RS on 1AL and 1DL; Y axis, scale for root trait.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq097f04_ht"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The calculation of correlation coefficients (<italic>r</italic>) revealed a strong degree of association among traits of root anatomy in the top region of the root (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). Stele diameter showed a positive correlation with CMX vessel area (0.82), number of xylem poles (0.81), and root diameter (0.84). CMX vessel area was further associated highly with CMX vessel diameter (0.77), number of xylem poles (0.71)), and root diameter (0.86). There was also a high correlation between root diameter and number of xylem poles (0.79) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float">
          <label>Table 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Simple correlation coefficients between different root anatomical traits in different root regions in the genetic background of spring bread wheat &#x2018;Pavon 76&#x2019; with different number of 1RS translocation arms; <italic>n</italic>=20 for TOP and TIP regions, <italic>n</italic>=25 for MID regions</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root traits</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root regions</td>
                <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Root traits<italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn3">a</xref></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stele diameter</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMX vessel area</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMX vessel diameter</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMX vessel number</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xylem poles</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMX vessel area</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOP</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MID</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIP</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMX vessel diameter</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOP</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46*</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MID</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIP</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMX vessel number</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOP</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MID</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIP</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xylem poles</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOP</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53*</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84**</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MID</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIP</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;0.02</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;0.01</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root diameter</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOP</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56*</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MID</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIP</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64**</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;0.08</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tblfn3">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>** Significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x2264;0.01); * significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x2264;0.05 &gt;0.01).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Linear regression analysis showed significant <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> values for all anatomical root traits measured in this study. The number of CMX vessels in the top of the root was the best explained trait (51%) due to 1RS dosage. Forty-seven per cent of the variation of two root traits, CMX area and number of xylem poles, was explained by the linear regression on the number of 1RS dosages in a genotype (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>). The number of 1RS dosages explained 45% and 38% of the variation in stele diameter and root diameter, respectively. The negative slope of the regression equation showed a negative relationship between root anatomical traits in the top region and number of 1RS dosages (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>). This is also evident from the negative trends in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float">
          <label>Table 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Summary of regression analysis</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dependent variable</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intercept</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>R</italic>
                  <sup>2</sup>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>F</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>P</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Root top</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stele diameter (&#x3BC;m)</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">363.4</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;36.5</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.66</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total CMX area (&#x3BC;m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15720.0</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;2540.0</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.01</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMX diameter (&#x3BC;m)</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.0</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;4.2</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.65</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMX (number)</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;1.0</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.63</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xylem pole (number)</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;1.2</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.78</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root diameter (&#x3BC;m)</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">667.7</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;44.5</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Root tip</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stele (&#x3BC;m)</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">250.8</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;5.4</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMX area (&#x3BC;m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6161.4</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;773.5</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.30</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMX diameter (&#x3BC;m)</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.7</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;6.0</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.69</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xylem pole (number)</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root diameter (&#x3BC;m)</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">655.8</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;15.1</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>The independent variable is number of 1RS translocation arms in the spring bread wheat &#x2018;Pavon 76&#x2019; genetic background (<italic>n</italic>=20)</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Mid-region of the root (MID)</title>
        <p>ANOVA showed no significant differences among genotypes for any of the anatomical root traits in the mid-region of the tap root except number of xylem poles (data not shown). However, all the traits showed stronger association among themselves except CMX vessel number (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>). Regression analysis showed a negligible dependence of root traits on the number of 1RS dosages (data not shown).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Tip of the root (TIP)</title>
        <p>In root tips of the tap roots, there were significant differences among genotypes for CMX vessel area and CMX vessel diameter. For both the traits, R<sub>0</sub> and RA<sub>1</sub> showed significantly higher mean values than 1RS double dosage genotypes (RA<sub>2</sub> and RD<sub>2</sub>) and quadruple dosage of 1RS in RAD<sub>4</sub> genotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A, B</xref>). Correlation coefficient values of both the above traits also showed a highly positive association with each other followed by stele and root diameter (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>). Again in the regression analysis, both the traits, CMX vessel area and CMX vessel diameter, were significantly influenced by different 1RS dosages in the genotypes. Their regression equation showed negative slope and the variation explained for CMX vessel area and CMX vessel diameter was 54% and 52%, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig5" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 5.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Graphical representation of mean performances of (A) total metaxylem vessel diameter; and (B) average metaxylem diameter measured in root tips of the roots of different wheat genotypes with different number of 1RS translocation arms in the genetic background of spring bread wheat &#x2018;Pavon 76&#x2019;. The same small letters within a graph are not significantly different. <italic>X</italic>- axis, bread wheat genotypes, namely Pavon 76 (R0)=0 dose of 1RS, Pavon 1RS.1AL&#xD7;Pavon 76 (RA1)=1 dose of 1RS, Pavon 1RS.1AL (RA2)=2 doses of 1RS on 1AL, Pavon 1RS.1DL (RD2)=2 doses of 1RS on 1DL, and Pavon 1RS.1AL - Pavon 1RS.1DL (RAD4)=4 doses of 1RS on 1AL and 1DL; Y -axis, scale for root trait.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq097f05_ht"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>From previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Ehdaie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Sharma <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), it was clear that there was a gene (or genes) present on the 1RS chromosome arm which affects root traits in bread wheat. These authors did not attempt to determine if this chromosomal region affects any root anatomical traits in bread wheat. The purpose of this study was to look for variation in root morphology and anatomy among different wheat genotypes and then to determine how these differences are related to different dosages of 1RS in bread wheat. During this study, we came to some interesting conclusions: (i) F<sub>1</sub> hybrids showed a heterotic effect for root biomass and there was an additive effect of the 1RS arm number on root morphology of bread wheat; (ii) there was a specific development pattern in the root vasculature from top to tip in wheat roots and 1RS dosage tended to affect root anatomy differently in different regions of the tap root. Further, the differences in root biomass, and traits associated with CMX of the different genotypes may have specific bearing on their ability to tolerate water and heat stress.</p>
      <p>The results in this study were obtained at an early stage of growth in the greenhouse environment. Although the positive correlation of higher root biomass of 1RS wheats in the greenhouse and their yield performance in field conditions was demonstrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Ehdaie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>), it may be difficult to translate the observed effects of this study to wheat root systems in the field at later stages, especially the anatomical traits on xylem vessel number, size etc which were observed on only one tap root per plant.</p>
      <sec>
        <title>Effect of 1RS dosage on root morphology</title>
        <p>The effect of number of 1RS translocation arms in bread wheat was clearly evident from their averaged mean values for root biomass. RA<sub>1</sub> and RAD<sub>4</sub> were ranked highest while R<sub>0</sub> ranked at the bottom (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). Genotype RD<sub>2</sub> performed only slightly better than R<sub>0</sub> for root biomass because of its poor performance in one season, otherwise it showed better rooting ability in the other three seasons. Otherwise, all the genotypes with 1RS translocations showed higher root biomass than R<sub>0</sub> which carried a normal 1BS chromosome arm. Data in this study suggested two types of effects of 1RS on wheat roots. First, an additive effect of 1RS, there was increase in root biomass with the increase in 1RS dosage from zero (R<sub>0</sub>) to two (RA<sub>2</sub> and RD<sub>2</sub>) and then to four (RAD<sub>4</sub>).</p>
        <p>A second major effect noted was a heterotic effect of 1RS and 1AS on root biomass and shoot biomass. MPH and BPH of the F<sub>1</sub> hybrid (RA<sub>1</sub>) were higher for root biomass than for shoot biomass (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). This further explained the more pronounced effect of 1RS on root biomass than shoot biomass. Significant positive heterosis was observed for root traits among wheat F<sub>1</sub> hybrids and 27% of the genes were differentially expressed between hybrids and their parents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). The possible role of differential gene expression was suggested to play a role in root heterosis of wheat and other cereal crops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). In a recent molecular study of heterosis, it was speculated that up-regulation of TaARF, an open reading frame (ORF) encoding a putative wheat ARF protein, might be contributing to heterosis observed in wheat root and leaf growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Yao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Root anatomy in three dimensions in different doses of 1RS arms</title>
        <p>There is a large void in root research involving the study of root anatomy in wheat as well as other cereal crops. Most of the anatomical literature is either limited to root anatomy near the base of the root (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Aloni and Griffith, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Watt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) or near the root tip (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Huang <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>) in young seedlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Richards and Passioura, 1989</xref>). There is still a general lack of knowledge about the overall structure and pattern of whole root vasculature during the later stages of growth in cereals, especially in wheat. Recently, a study was conducted on root anatomy of various classes of winter wheat, barley, and triticale roots, including primary axile (tap) roots, scutellar, coleoptile, and leaf node axile roots, as well as branch roots of various orders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Watt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). These authors sampled axile (tap) roots at 3&#x2013;5 cm from the base of young plants grown in the greenhouse and other branch roots from field-grown plants at flowering.</p>
        <p>In the present study, root anatomical traits were studied in the tap roots of different spring wheat genotypes containing different dosages of 1RS translocation arms harvested during the late-tillering stage. Root sections were made from three regions along the length of the root, namely top of the root, middle of the root, and root tip, to get an overview of the complete structure and pattern of root anatomy relative to differences in 1RS dosage. A comparison of the different regions of the root of a genotype showed a transition for CMX vessel number and CMX area from higher in the top region of the root to a single CMX vessel in the root tip. In barley, a similar pattern was reported only in the nodal roots retaining the central pith (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Luxov&#xE1;, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">1991</xref>), but the author also observed a few instances of more than one CMX vessel in the base of the seminal (tap) root. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Watt <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> reported one to three CMX vessels in the primary axile (tap) roots of hexaploid winter wheat and tritcale (<italic>Triticale hexaploid</italic>). The variation that was found along a single tap root of spring wheat spans the differences between different root types in winter wheat observed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Watt <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref>. In the root tip only CMX vessel diameter and area were traceable as other cell types were still differentiating. This developmental pattern was consistent across the different wheat genotypes used in this study. Interestingly, there was variation in timing for the transitions in root anatomy among genotypes and this variation was explained by dosage of the 1RS arm in bread wheat. RD<sub>2</sub> and RAD<sub>4</sub> transitioned earlier, from having multiple metaxylem vessels and a larger stele to a single, CMX vessel and smaller stele, than did R<sub>0</sub> and RA<sub>1</sub>.</p>
        <p>In the top region, all the root traits were significantly different among genotypes except average CMX vessel diameter and CMX vessel number (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A&#x2013;F</xref>). The average CMX diameter was calculated from the average of diameters of all the CMX number of that subsequent genotype and, hence, the number of CMX vessels was different in each genotype and so was the total CMX vessel area. Interestingly, all the root traits in the top region showed negative slope in regression analysis and most of them were significant, especially stele diameter, total CMX vessel area, and peripheral xylem pole number. Variation in all the traits was explained by number of 1RS dosages in wheat genotypes and root anatomical traits were smaller with a higher number of 1RS dosages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A&#x2013;E</xref>). Significant positive correlation among almost all the root traits from the top region and mid-region of the roots (except CMX vessel number) suggested their inter-dependences in growth and development. Root diameter could not be measured for all the replicates of each genotype because of the degeneration and mechanical damage to the cortex and epidermis. Earlier, a study on the rate of cortical death in seminal (tap) roots was investigated in different cereals. It was found that rate of cortical death was faster in hexaploid wheat and was positively associated with root age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Liljeroth, 1995</xref>). Our results suggest there are genes on the 1RS arm that affect xylem anatomy which is further affected by 1RS dosage.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Structural adaptation to stress</title>
        <p>Root morphology and root architecture are responsible for both water and nutrient uptake while in root anatomy, xylem vessels are essential for their transportation to the shoots to allow continued photosynthesis and growth. Variations in xylem anatomy and hydraulic properties occur at interspecific, intraspecific, and intraplant levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Zimmermann, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Sperry and Saliendra, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Jackson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). Variations in xylem vessel diameter can drastically affect the axial flow because of the fourth-power relationship between radius and flow rate through a capillary tube, as described by the Hagen&#x2013;Poiseuille law (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Zimmermann, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Tyree and Ewers, 1991</xref>). Thus, even a small increase in mean vessel diameter would have exponential effects on specific hydraulic conductivity (<italic>K</italic><sub>s</sub>) for the same pressure difference across a segment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">McElrone <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Xylem diameters tend to be narrower in drought-tolerant genotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Ou <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), and at higher temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Huang <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>). Smaller xylem diameters pose higher flow resistance and slower water flow which may help the wheat plant to survive water-stressed conditions. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Richards and Passioura (1989)</xref> reported increased grain yield of two Australian wheat cultivars by selecting for narrow xylem vessels in seminal (tap) roots. Reduced water flow in seminal axile (tap) roots may be most important at the early stages of plant development since they are the first to emerge and seedling survival is often a critical stage, especially in rainfed environments, where seedling survival solely depends on the available sub-soil moisture.</p>
        <p>A model for water and nitrogen capture in cereal root systems predicted greater economic returns from crops with greater partitioning of dry matter to the roots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">King <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). The results in this study generally showed more allocation of dry matter to roots in the 1RS genotypes. It was observed that partitioning of dry matter to roots was incremental with an increase in dosage of the 1RS arm excluding the F<sub>1</sub> hybrid genotype (data not shown). The non-significant difference in <italic>R</italic>/<italic>S</italic> ratio between RD<sub>2</sub> (=0.31) and <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub> (=0.33) may be due to the poor performance of RD<sub>2</sub> during the 2008 season. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Ehdaie <italic>et al.</italic> (2003)</xref> observed a better <italic>R</italic>/<italic>S</italic> ratio in RD<sub>2</sub> genotype than Pavon 76 (R<sub>0</sub>) in a greenhouse experiment grown to maturity. These authors also studied resource capture involving genotypes RA<sub>2</sub> and RD<sub>2</sub> which showed better water use efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Ehdaie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>) and more nutrient uptake with less leachate concentration than check R<sub>0</sub> (B Ehdaie and JG Waines, unpublished data). These authors reported a larger and well-branched root system in 1RS wheats which is further positively correlated with an increase in grain yield and its components (B Ehdaie and JG Waines, unpublished data). The model for resource capture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">King <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>) also predicted maximum returns from crops with smaller specific root weight, i.e. finer roots. It was suggested to be advantageous for the plants to invest in more surface area available for resource capture at lower depths.</p>
        <p>The results of this study also showed that the presence of 1RS arm in bread wheat increased root biomass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>) and reduced the dimensions of some root parameters, especially the CMX vessel area and diameter in the root tips (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A&#x2013;E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A, B</xref>) as well as in the top of the root (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figs 2K&#x2013;O</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4 B, D</xref>). Future experiments warrant inclusion of traits such as root number, extensiveness of root branching, and root surface area along with resource capture studies to address the effect of 1RS wheats. The present study also suggests the possibility of different genes present on the 1RS arm affecting root biomass and anatomy in wheat as dosage of the 1RS arm affects these traits differently. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Manske and Vlek (2002)</xref> reported that wheat genotypes with the 1RS translocated chromosome arm had thinner roots and higher root-length density compared with normal wheat with a 1BS chromosome arm under field conditions. Similar differences were also observed for root length density, diameters of stele and CMX vessel between winter wheat and triticale (genome formula=AABBRR) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Watt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Among 1RS translocation wheats, significant association was observed between root biomass and grain yield under well-watered and droughted environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Ehdaie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). Narrow metaxylem vessels and higher root biomass may provide 1RS translocation wheats with better adaptability to water stress and make them better performers for grain yield.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In a recent study on rice root anatomy, QTL for metaxylem vessels were identified on the distal end of the long arm of chromosome 10 of rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Uga <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) which showed synteny to the 1RS chromosome arm of rye (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Hackauf <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). These reports also support the present findings and may validate the purpose of the current study on wheat root anatomy. This study suggests that the short arm of chromosome 1 of rye carries important genes affecting root morphology and root anatomy in bread wheat. The 1RS arm showed heterotic effect and significant dosage effect on root biomass and root anatomy in bread wheat. Thus, higher root biomass and narrow metaxylem vessels in 1RS wheat strongly advocate their inclusion as a selection criterion in wheat breeding programmes.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This research was supported by United States Department of Agriculture&#x2013;New Mexico State Southwest Consortium on Plant Genetics and Water Resources, New Mexico, USA Project No. 064N09/07R09. SS would like to thank Dr David Carter for providing technical help for microscopy and useful discussions.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aloni</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Griffith</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Functional xylem anatomy in root-shoot junctions of six cereal species</article-title>
          <source>Planta</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>184</volume>
          <fpage>123</fpage>
          <lpage>129</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barlow</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Gregory</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lake</surname>
              <given-names>JV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rose</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The cellular organization of roots and its response to the physical environment</article-title>
          <source>Root development and function</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>26</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>B&#xF6;hm</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Methods of studying root systems</article-title>
          <year>1979</year>
          <comment>Ecological Studies Vol. 33. Wallingford: CAB International</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bowen</surname>
              <given-names>GD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rovira</surname>
              <given-names>AD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relationship between root morphology and nutrient uptake</article-title>
          <source>Recent advances in plant nutrition</source>
          <year>1971</year>
          <volume>Vol. 1</volume>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Gordon and Breach Science Publishers Inc. USA</publisher-name>
          <fpage>293</fpage>
          <lpage>305</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ehdaie</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Whitkus</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waines</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Root biomass, water-use efficiency, and performance of wheat-rye translocations of chromosomes 1 and 2 in spring bread wheat &#x2018;Pavon&#x2019;</article-title>
          <source>Crop Science</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>710</fpage>
          <lpage>717</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ford</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gregory</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gooding</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pepler</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genotype and fungicide effects on late-season root growth of winter wheat</article-title>
          <source>Plant and Soil</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>284</volume>
          <fpage>33</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fukai</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of drought-resistant cultivars using physio-morphological traits in rice</article-title>
          <source>Field Crops Research</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>67</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hackauf</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rudd</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Voort</surname>
              <given-names>JRvd</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miedaner</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wehling</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparative mapping of DNA sequences in rye (<italic>Secale cereale</italic> L.) in relation to the rice genome</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>118</volume>
          <fpage>371</fpage>
          <lpage>384</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18953524</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hackett</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A study of the root system of barley. 1. Effects of nutrition on two varieties</article-title>
          <source>New Phytologist</source>
          <year>1968</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>287</fpage>
          <lpage>299</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hose</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clarkson</surname>
              <given-names>DT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steudle</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schreiber</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hartung</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The exodermis: a variable apoplastic barrier</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>2245</fpage>
          <lpage>2264</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11709575</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wheat root morphology, root anatomy, and hydraulic conductivity as affected by temperature</article-title>
          <source>Dissertation Abstracts International. B, Sciences and Engineering</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>2358B</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>BR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Morphological development and anatomical features of wheat seedlings as influenced by temperature and seeding depth</article-title>
          <source>Crop Science</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>1269</fpage>
          <lpage>1273</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>BR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McMichael</surname>
              <given-names>BL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of temperature on the development of metaxylem in primary wheat roots and its hydraulic consequence</article-title>
          <source>Annals of Botany</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>163</fpage>
          <lpage>166</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jackson</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sperry</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dawson</surname>
              <given-names>TE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Root water uptake and transport: using physiological processes in global predictions</article-title>
          <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>482</fpage>
          <lpage>488</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11077257</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jupp</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Newman</surname>
              <given-names>EI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Morphological and anatomical effects of severe drought on the roots of <italic>Lolium perenne</italic> L</article-title>
          <source>New Phytologist</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>105</volume>
          <fpage>393</fpage>
          <lpage>402</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kattermann</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>On constant strains with pubescent stems from wheat&#x2013;rye crosses with 2<italic>n</italic>=42 chromosomes</article-title>
          <source>Zeitschrift f&#xFC;r induktive Abstammungs- und Vererbungslehre</source>
          <year>1938</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>354</fpage>
          <lpage>375</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baenziger</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lukaszewski</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gaines</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Agronomic effect of wheat&#x2013;rye translocation carrying rye chromatin (1R) from different sources</article-title>
          <source>Crop Science</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>1254</fpage>
          <lpage>1258</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gay</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sylvester-Bradley</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bingham</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Foulkes</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gregory</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Modelling cereal root systems for water and nitrogen capture: towards an economic optimum</article-title>
          <source>Annals of Botany</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>383</fpage>
          <lpage>390</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12547691</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumlay</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baenziger</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shelton</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graybosch</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lukaszewski</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wesenberg</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Understanding the effect of rye chromatin in bread wheat</article-title>
          <source>Crop Science</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>1643</fpage>
          <lpage>1651</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liljeroth</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparisons of early root cortical senescence between barley cultivars, <italic>Triticum</italic> species and other cereals</article-title>
          <source>New Phytologist</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>130</volume>
          <fpage>495</fpage>
          <lpage>501</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lukaszewski</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reconstruction in wheat of complete chromosomes 1B and 1R from the 1RS.1BL translocation of &#x2018;Kavkaz&#x2019; origin</article-title>
          <source>Genome</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>821</fpage>
          <lpage>824</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18470029</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lukaszewski</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Further manipulation by centric misdivision of the 1RS.1BL translocation in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>257</fpage>
          <lpage>261</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Luxov&#xE1;</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The vascular system in the roots of barley and its hydraulic aspects</article-title>
          <source>Structural and functional aspects of transport in roots</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <comment>Third international symposium on structure and function of roots, Nitra, Czechoslovakia, 3&#x2013;7 Aug. 1987, 15&#x2013;20</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Luxov&#xE1;</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mechanisms of reduction of the stelar pattern along barley roots</article-title>
          <source>Botanica Acta</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>104</volume>
          <fpage>163</fpage>
          <lpage>168</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Manske</surname>
              <given-names>GGB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vlek</surname>
              <given-names>PLG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Waisel</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eshel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kafkafi</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Root architecture: wheat as a model plant</article-title>
          <source>Plant roots: the hidden half</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York USA</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Marcel Dekker Inc.</publisher-name>
          <fpage>249</fpage>
          <lpage>259</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McElrone</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pockman</surname>
              <given-names>WT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martinez-Vilalta</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jackson</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Variation in xylem structure and function in stems and roots of trees to 20 m depth</article-title>
          <source>New Phytologist</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>163</volume>
          <fpage>507</fpage>
          <lpage>517</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mettin</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bluthner</surname>
              <given-names>WD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schlegel</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Additional evidence on spontaneous 1B/1R wheat-rye substitutions and translocations. <italic>Proceedings of the fourth international wheat genetics symposium</italic></article-title>
          <source>Alien genetic material</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          <fpage>179</fpage>
          <lpage>184</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O'Brien</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic variability of root growth in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>
          <source>Australian Journal of Agricultural Research</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>587</fpage>
          <lpage>595</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib29">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ou</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ni</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relationship between root xylem vessels and drought resistance in spring wheat</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Triticeae Crops</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>27</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib30">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Owuoche</surname>
              <given-names>JO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sears</surname>
              <given-names>RG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown-Guedira</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fritz</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Heterotic effects of wheat&#x2013;rye chromosomal translocations on agronomic traits of hybrid wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) under an adequate moisture regime</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>132</volume>
          <fpage>67</fpage>
          <lpage>77</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib31">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Quarrie</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>HG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of abscisic acid and water stress on development and morphology of wheat</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>1977</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>192</fpage>
          <lpage>203</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib32">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rajaram</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mann</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ortiz-Ferrara</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mujeeb-Kazi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Sakamoto</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adaptation, stability and high yield potential of certain 1B/1R CIMMYT wheats</article-title>
          <source>Sixth international wheat genetic symposium</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <publisher-loc>Kyoto, Japan</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Plant Germ-Plasm Institute</publisher-name>
          <fpage>613</fpage>
          <lpage>621</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib33">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Richards</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Passioura</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A breeding program to reduce the diameter of the major xylem vessel in the seminal roots of wheat and its effect on grain yield in rain-fed environments</article-title>
          <source>Australian Journal of Agricultural Research</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>943</fpage>
          <lpage>950</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib34">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Robertson</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waines</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic variability for seedling root numbers in wild and domesticated wheats</article-title>
          <source>Crop Science</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>843</fpage>
          <lpage>847</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib35">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ruzin</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Ruzin</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Staining</article-title>
          <source>Plant microtechnique and microscopy</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Oxford University Press Inc.</publisher-name>
          <fpage>87</fpage>
          <lpage>116</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib36">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhat</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ehdaie</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Close</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lukaszewski</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waines</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Integrated genetic map and genetic analysis of a region associated with root traits on the short arm of rye chromosome 1 in bread wheat</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>119</volume>
          <fpage>783</fpage>
          <lpage>793</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19544051</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib37">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sperry</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saliendra</surname>
              <given-names>NZ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intra- and inter-plant variation in xylem cavitation in <italic>Betula occidentalis</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>1233</fpage>
          <lpage>1241</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib38">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Steel</surname>
              <given-names>RGD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Torrie</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dickey</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Principles and procedures of statistics: a biometrical approach</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York, NY USA</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill Inc</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib39">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Terzioglu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ekmekci</surname>
              <given-names>YT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of chilling on seminal root central metaxylem diameter in some wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) cultivars</article-title>
          <source>Turkish Journal of Botany</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib40">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tyree</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ewers</surname>
              <given-names>FW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tansley review No. 34. The hydraulic architecture of trees and other woody plants</article-title>
          <source>New Phytologist</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>119</volume>
          <fpage>345</fpage>
          <lpage>360</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib41">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Uga</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okuno</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yano</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>QTLs underlying natural variation in stele and xylem structures of rice root</article-title>
          <source>Breeding Science</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>7</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib42">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Villareal</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rajaram</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mujeeb-Kazi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toro</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The effect of chromosome 1B/1R translocation on the yield potential of certain spring wheats (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>
          <source>Plant Breeding</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <fpage>77</fpage>
          <lpage>81</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib43">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ni</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nie</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Heterosis in root development and differential gene expression between hybrids and their parental inbreds in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <fpage>1283</fpage>
          <lpage>1294</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16932881</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib44">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Watt</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magee</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McCully</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Types, structure and potential for axial water flow in the deepest roots of field-grown cereals</article-title>
          <source>New Phytologist</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>178</volume>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>146</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18221246</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib45">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weaver</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Root habits of rye</source>
          <year>1926</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill Book Company Inc</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib46">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mu</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relationship between roots hydraulic conductivity and root anatomy of winter wheat (<italic>T. aestivum</italic>)</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Northwest A and F University - Natural Science Edition</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>160</fpage>
          <lpage>164</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib47">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yao</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ni</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Du</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ectopic overexpression of wheat adenosine diphosphate-ribosylation factor, TaARF, increases growth rate in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Integrative Plant Biology</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>35</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19166492</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib48">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yoshida</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hasegawa</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The rice root system: its development and function</article-title>
          <source>Drought resistance in crops with emphasis on rice</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <fpage>97</fpage>
          <lpage>114</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib49">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zadoks</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>TT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Konzak</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A decimal code for the growth stages of cereals</article-title>
          <source>Weed Research</source>
          <year>1974</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>415</fpage>
          <lpage>421</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib50">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zimmermann</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Xylem structure and the ascent of sap</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <publisher-loc>Berlin German Federal Republic</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
