<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2877893</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erq071</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Papers</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Rubisco activities, properties, and regulation in three different C<sub>4</sub> grasses under drought</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carmo-Silva</surname>
            <given-names>A. Elizabete</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Keys</surname>
            <given-names>Alfred J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Andralojc</surname>
            <given-names>P. John</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Powers</surname>
            <given-names>Stephen J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Arraba&#xE7;a</surname>
            <given-names>M. Celeste</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Parry</surname>
            <given-names>Martin A. J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Centro de Engenharia Biol&#xF3;gica and Departamento de Biologia Vegetal, Universidade de Lisboa, Faculdade de Ci&#xEA;ncias, Campo Grande, 1749-016 Lisboa, Portugal</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Plant Sciences, Centre for Crop Genetic Improvement, Rothamsted Research, Harpenden, Hertfordshire AL5 2JQ, UK</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Biomathematics and Bioinformatics, Centre for Mathematical and Computational Biology, Rothamsted Research, Harpenden, Hertfordshire AL5 2JQ, UK</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Present address and to whom correspondence should be sent: USDA-ARS, US Arid-Land Agricultural Research Center, N. Cardon Lane, Maricopa, AZ, 85138, USA. E-mail: <email>elizabete.carmosilva@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>2</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>2</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>61</volume>
      <issue>9</issue>
      <fpage>2355</fpage>
      <lpage>2366</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2010 The Author(s).</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
          <license-p>This paper is available online free of all access charges (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html">http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html</ext-link> for further details)</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>In C<sub>4</sub> plants, water deficit may decrease photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation independently of changes in stomatal conductance, suggesting decreased turnover by ribulose-1,5-<italic>bis</italic>phosphate carboxylase/oxygenase (Rubisco). The activity and biochemistry of Rubisco was studied in three different C<sub>4</sub> grasses: <italic>Paspalum dilatatum</italic>, <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic>, and <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic>. The objectives were to characterize the C<sub>4</sub> Rubisco in these species and to identify factors associated with decreased photosynthetic rates caused by drought. Rubisco isolated from each of the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses was characterized by smaller specificity factors (<italic>S</italic><sub>C/O</sub>), larger Michaelis&#x2013;Menten constants for CO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>K</italic><sub>c</sub>) and O<sub>2</sub> (<italic>K</italic><sub>o</sub>), and larger maximum carboxylation velocities (<italic>V</italic><sub>c</sub>) than Rubisco from wheat, which can be rationalized in terms of the CO<sub>2</sub>-rich environment of C<sub>4</sub> Rubisco in the bundle sheath. During leaf dehydration the quantity and maximum activity of Rubisco remained unchanged but the initial and total activities declined slightly, possibly due to increased inhibition. Tight-binding inhibitors were present in the light but were more abundant in the dark, especially in <italic>Z. japonica</italic>, and increased in quantity with drought stress. The inhibitor from darkened leaves of <italic>Z. japonica</italic> was identified as 2-carboxyarabinitol-1-phosphate (CA1P). Consistent with the presence of CA1P, the total activity of Rubisco was decreased after 12 h darkness in <italic>Z. japonica</italic>. Ribulose-1,5-<italic>bis</italic>phosphate (RuBP) in the leaves decreased with drought stress, to quantities approximating those of Rubisco catalytic sites. The magnitude of the decrease in RuBP suggested that, at least in <italic>C. dactylon</italic> and <italic>Z. japonica</italic>, it could contribute to the drought-induced decrease in photosynthesis.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>CA1P</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>kinetic constants</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Paspalum dilatatum</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>Rubisco</kwd>
        <kwd>RuBP</kwd>
        <kwd>water deficit</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic>
        </kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The presence of a CO<sub>2</sub>-concentrating mechanism in the leaves of C<sub>4</sub> plants results in improved water use efficiency compared to C<sub>3</sub> plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Long, 1999</xref>) and is generally seen as a potential advantage for areas with increased aridity. Stomatal closure is amongst the earliest plant responses to decreasing water availability and, in C<sub>3</sub> plants, constitutes a major limitation to photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation under such conditions. In those plants, metabolic or non-stomatal limitations to photosynthesis may also be observed under mild to moderate water-deficit conditions, concomitantly with stomatal limitation, but their relative contribution to decreased CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation increases with the severity of stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lawlor, 2002</xref>). C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis saturates at much lower CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations and is therefore unlikely to be affected by stomatal closure in the same fashion as C<sub>3</sub> photosynthesis. Increased leakiness of the bundle sheath may cause decreased CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations at the site of carboxylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Saliendra <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Williams <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). However, in several C<sub>4</sub> grasses subjected to water deficit, raising CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations to physiologically high levels&#x2014;which would suppress the effect of decreased stomatal conductance and increased leakiness&#x2014;did not result in the recovery of net photosynthetic rates to those of well-watered plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Carmo-Silva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Ghannoum, 2009</xref>), supporting the presence of non-stomatal limitations of photosynthesis. The limited number of studies with C<sub>4</sub> species suggests higher susceptibility of the C<sub>3</sub> than the C<sub>4</sub> cycle enzymes to impairment by water deficit (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Ghannoum, 2009</xref>).</p>
      <p>Ribulose-1,5-<italic>bis</italic>phosphate (RuBP) carboxylase/oxygenase (Rubisco) is crucial in the regulation of photosynthesis in fully-hydrated leaves of the C<sub>4</sub> species <italic>Flaveria bidentis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Furbank <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>), but the importance of this most abundant of leaf proteins in the limitation of C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis under drought conditions is not well understood. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Flexas and Medrano (2002)</xref> suggested that, in C<sub>3</sub> plants, Rubisco capacity was of little importance in the drought-induced limitation of photosynthesis, whilst decreased capacity for RuBP regeneration&#x2014;possibly as a result of decreased ATP synthesis or impaired Calvin cycle enzyme activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lawlor, 2002</xref>)&#x2014;would constitute a major metabolic limitation. However, decreased activity and/or quantity of Rubisco has been observed in several different C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> species exposed to water deficit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Majumdar <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Du <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lal and Edwards, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Parry <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Tezara <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bota <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Marques da Silva and Arraba&#xE7;a, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Carmo-Silva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Soares-Cordeiro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009)</xref>.</p>
      <p>Rubisco activity is regulated by the extent of carbamylation of a lysyl residue within the catalytic site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Lorimer and Miziorko, 1980</xref>) and is affected by various chloroplast metabolites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hatch and Jensen, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Badger and Lorimer, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jordan <italic>et al.</italic>, 1983</xref>) and by naturally occurring tight-binding inhibitors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Pearce and Andrews, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kim and Portis, 2004</xref>). At night, Rubisco may be inhibited by a specific tight-binding inhibitor, 2-carboxyarabinitol-1-phosphate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Gutteridge <italic>et al.</italic>, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Berry <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Moore <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>), which is present in some species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Vu <italic>et al.</italic>, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Seemann <italic>et al.</italic>, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Servaites <italic>et al.</italic>, 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Holbrook <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sage and Seemann, 1993</xref>). The main contender for the inhibition of Rubisco in the light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Kane <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>), <sc>D</sc>-<italic>glycero</italic>-2,3-diulose-1,5-<italic>bis</italic>phosphate (PDBP), is too labile for detailed study, and the occurrence of inhibitors during daytime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Keys <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>) has become associated with misfire products formed during enolization and oxygenation of RuBP catalysed by Rubisco (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Pearce and Andrews, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kim and Portis, 2004</xref>). It is generally accepted that removal of all these inhibitors requires the ATP-dependent action of Rubisco activase. Tight-binding inhibitors such as CA1P protect Rubisco from proteolytic breakdown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Khan <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>) and may play an important role in regulating the enzyme under stress conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Parry <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), as well as during darkness and at low irradiance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kobza and Seemann, 1989<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33"><italic>b</italic></xref>).</p>
      <p>Photorespiration is initiated by the oxygenase activity of Rubisco and decreases both the rate and efficiency of CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation in C<sub>3</sub> plants. Because CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> are competing substrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bowes and Ogren, 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laing <italic>et al.</italic>, 1974</xref>), the high CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the bundle sheath of C<sub>4</sub> plants means that the oxygenase activity is much decreased. This situation could be compromised under conditions of water deficit since the concomitant reduction in stomatal aperture leads to decreased CO<sub>2</sub> availability. However, photorespiration has been shown neither to increase nor contribute to the limitation of photosynthesis in C<sub>4</sub> grasses under drought stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Carmo-Silva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). From a consideration of the kinetics of the carboxylation and oxygenation of RuBP catalysed by Rubisco, the specificity factor (<italic>S</italic><sub>C/O</sub>) defines the relative reactivity towards the two gaseous substrates and is given by <italic>V</italic><sub>c</sub><italic>K</italic><sub>o</sub>/<italic>V</italic><sub>o</sub><italic>K</italic><sub>c</sub>, where <italic>V</italic><sub>c</sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub>o</sub> represent the maximum velocities of the carboxylase and oxygenase reactions, respectively, and <italic>K</italic><sub>c</sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub>o</sub> the Michaelis&#x2013;Menten constants for CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub>. The individual kinetic constants are known for relatively few types of Rubisco, mostly from C<sub>3</sub> species. Michaelis&#x2013;Menten constants of Rubisco from C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> grasses for CO<sub>2</sub> and RuBP have been reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Yeoh <italic>et al.</italic> (1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">1981)</xref> and the Rubisco kinetic parameters have recently been compared in eudicot plants with the C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> photosynthetic pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kubien <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). In the sequence of studies described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Carmo-Silva <italic>et al.</italic> (2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">2009)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Soares-Cordeiro <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref> on the responses of three different C<sub>4</sub> grasses to water deficit, it became important to add details of the kinetic constants for the Rubiscos peculiar to these three species.</p>
      <p>The objectives of this investigation were to study the biochemistry of Rubisco and to determine the effects of water deficit on the regulation of the enzyme in three C<sub>4</sub> grasses of different metabolic subtypes: <italic>Paspalum dilatatum</italic> Poir. (NADP-malic enzyme, NADP-ME), <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic> (L.) Pers (NAD-malic enzyme, NAD-ME), and <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic> Steudel (phospho<italic>enol</italic>pyruvate carboxykinase, PEPCK). The previous studies showed that net photosynthesis was decreased in these three grasses by both slowly and rapidly induced drought stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Carmo-Silva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">2008</xref>). The purpose of the present study was to investigate the relationship to drought of decreased carboxylation of RuBP (photosynthesis), the activation state of Rubisco due to carbamylation, the presence of inhibitors, and the quantity of RuBP in the leaves.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>General methods</title>
        <p>Rubisco was purified from wheat as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Keys and Parry (1990)</xref>. RuBP prepared as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Wong <italic>et al.</italic> (1980)</xref>, 2-carboxyarabinitol-1,5-<italic>bis</italic>phosphate (CABP) prepared from RuBP by reaction with KCN or [<sup>14</sup>C]-KCN followed by hydrolysis of the cyanohydrins, and CA1P made from CABP by partial dephosphorylation using alkaline phosphatase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Gutteridge <italic>et al.</italic>, 1989</xref>) were all purified by anion-exchange chromatography. Radioactivity of <sup>14</sup>C labelled compounds, typically in a volume of 0.4&#x2013;0.45 ml of aqueous solution, was measured after mixing with 3.6 ml Ultima Gold Scintillation cocktail in a Liquid Scintillation Analyser (Perkin-Elmer, USA). Specific mixtures of N<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> were prepared using a gas divider (Signal Group, UK) and concentrations of O<sub>2</sub> in solution were calculated by taking the solubility at 25 &#xB0;C in water as 257.5 &#x3BC;M in a standard atmosphere at 100% relative humidity and correcting for the atmospheric pressure during measurements [using the formula 257.5&#xD7;(<italic>P</italic>&#x2013;11589)/(101 325&#x2013;11589), where <italic>P</italic> is the observed pressure, 11589 Pa is the saturated H<sub>2</sub>O vapour pressure at 25 &#xB0;C, and 101325 Pa is the standard atmospheric pressure]. Concentrations of CO<sub>2</sub> in solution in equilibrium with HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> were calculated assuming a p<italic>K</italic><sub>a</sub><sup>1</sup> for carbonic acid at 25 &#xB0;C of 6.11 and using accurate measures of the pH of each buffer solution. Values of Michaelis&#x2013;Menten constants and maximum velocities were estimated using EnzFitter (Biosoft: Software for Science, UK).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Plant growth and drought stress induction</title>
        <p>The C<sub>4</sub> grasses <italic>Paspalum dilatatum</italic> Poir. cv. Raki (NADP-ME), <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic> (L.) Pers var. Shangri-L&#xE1; (NAD-ME), and <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic> Steudel &#x2018;Jacklin Sunrise Brand&#x2019; (produced by Jacklin Seed Company, USA) (PEPCK) were grown from seeds in trays or pots with peat-free compost in a greenhouse, as previously described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Carmo-Silva <italic>et al.</italic> (2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">2009)</xref>. Artificial light was provided whenever the natural light was below a photosynthetic photon flux density (<italic>PPFD</italic>) of 500 &#x3BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> during a 16 h photoperiod. The temperature was set not to fall below 25 &#xB0;C during the day or below 18 &#xB0;C during the night. Pots, containing five seedlings each, were well-watered until the beginning of the drought stress treatment and then placed according to a rectangular split-plot design, where each column of pots was a main plot of a particular species and the sampling-days and treatments (control and drought stress) were randomized in the rows (split-plots). Each pot corresponded to one independent sample. When appropriate, the number of samples was duplicated and organized in two blocks to allow the imposition of a light/dark regime, by restricted randomization. Several batches of plants were grown, to obtain samples for the different measurements. Because the growing conditions were not fully controlled, batches of plants varied slightly in the extent of drought stress achieved.</p>
        <p>Water deficit was imposed by ceasing to provide water, consecutively, with 1 d intervals, to the plants of <italic>C. dactylon</italic>, then <italic>Z. japonica</italic> and last <italic>P. dilatatum</italic>. Samples composed of young fully expanded leaves were taken from all three species for four consecutive days at the end of the drought period (after the soil water content in the pots had fallen below 10%; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Carmo-Silva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Five-week-old plants of <italic>P. dilatatum</italic> and <italic>C. dactylon</italic> and 9-week-old plants of the slow-growing <italic>Z. japonica</italic> were analysed simultaneously. On each occasion, two leaf samples were taken from each pot: the first was quickly frozen in liquid nitrogen (LN<sub>2</sub>) and then stored at &#x2013;80 &#xB0;C for biochemical assays and the second was used to determine the leaf relative water content (<italic>RWC</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Catsky, 1960</xref>). The leaf samples were collected in the growth environment under fully illuminated conditions, 4 h after the beginning of the photoperiod, or in the dark, after placing the plants in a dark environment for a period of 12 h (overnight).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Rubisco activity and concentration in leaf crude extracts</title>
        <p>Rubisco was extracted from leaves by grinding frozen samples (0.1&#x2013;0.4 g fresh weight, FW) in a cold mortar with quartz sand, 1% (w/v) insoluble polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP) and 10 (<italic>P. dilatatum</italic> and <italic>C. dactylon</italic>) or 15 vols (<italic>Z. japonica</italic>) of ice-cold extraction medium containing 50 mM Bicine-KOH pH 8.0, 1 mM EDTA, 5% (w/v) PVP<sub>25000</sub>, 6% (w/v) polyethylene glycol 4000 (PEG<sub>4000</sub>), 10 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), 50 mM 2-mercaptoethanol, and 1% (v/v) protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma, USA). After taking aliquots for total chlorophyll determination, the remaining homogenate was centrifuged for 3 min at 16000 <italic>g</italic> and 4 &#xB0;C and the supernatant immediately used for measuring the activities and quantities of Rubisco, with two analytical replicates for each measurement.</p>
        <p>The activities of Rubisco were determined by the incorporation of <sup>14</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> into acid-stable products at 25 &#xB0;C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parry <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). The reaction mixture (final volume 0.5 ml) contained 100 mM Bicine-NaOH pH 8.2, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM NaH<sup>14</sup>CO<sub>3</sub> (18.5 kBq &#x3BC;mol<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>), and 0.4 mM RuBP. The initial activity was determined by adding 25 &#x3BC;l of crude extract and quenching the reaction after 60 s with 0.2 ml 10 M HCOOH. Total activity was measured after incubating 25 &#x3BC;l of the same extract for 3 min with all the components except RuBP, to allow carbamylation of all available Rubisco catalytic sites, and then starting the reaction by adding RuBP. Maximal activity was measured after the removal of Rubisco tight-binding inhibitors by incubating 250 &#x3BC;l of crude extract with 200 mM Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, 10 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, and 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> for 30 min at 4 &#xB0;C. Protein was precipitated with 20% (w/v) PEG<sub>4000</sub> and 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and then washed three times with 20% PEG<sub>4000</sub> in 100 mM Bicine-NaOH pH 8.2, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, and 50 mM 2-mercaptoethanol. The final precipitate was dissolved in extraction buffer and assayed for total activity. The quenched reaction mixtures were completely dried at 100 &#xB0;C and the residues rehydrated before <sup>14</sup>C determination.</p>
        <p>Rubisco in leaf crude or inhibitor-free extracts was quantified by the [<sup>14</sup>C]-CABP binding assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Parry <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). For this purpose, 100 &#x3BC;l of extract was incubated with 100 mM Bicine-NaOH pH 8.0, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 50 mM 2-mercaptoethanol, 100 mM Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, and 75 &#x3BC;M [<sup>14</sup>C]-CABP (37 kBq &#x3BC;mol<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) for 15 min at 4 &#xB0;C. Rubisco was precipitated by the addition of PEG<sub>4000</sub> to a final concentration of 25% and the precipitate washed three times with 20% PEG<sub>4000</sub> in 100 mM Bicine-NaOH pH 8.2, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, and 50 mM 2-mercaptoethanol, and then redissolved in 0.5 ml of 1% (v/v) Triton X-100. A subsample (0.45 ml) was used to measure the radioactivity due to [<sup>14</sup>C]-CABP bound to Rubisco catalytic sites.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Quantities of RuBP and Rubisco tight-binding inhibitors</title>
        <p>RuBP and Rubisco tight-binding inhibitors were extracted by grinding frozen leaf samples (0.1&#x2013;0.4 g FW) to a fine powder in LN<sub>2</sub> and then adding 0.45 M trifluoroacetic acid (TFA; 0.25 ml per 0.1 g FW). The mixture was ground further during thawing. Duplicate subsamples (20 &#x3BC;l) were taken for chlorophyll determination as phaeophytin and the remaining homogenate was centrifuged for 5 min at 16000 <italic>g</italic> and 4 &#xB0;C.</p>
        <p>For the estimation of RuBP, an aliquot (50 &#x3BC;l) of the acid extract was dried in a glass vial under high vacuum over anhydrous CaCl<sub>2</sub> and NaOH pellets. The residue was redissolved in 50 &#x3BC;l H<sub>2</sub>O, dried down, and redissolved in 50 &#x3BC;l H<sub>2</sub>O again. The RuBP contained in each vial was converted to [<sup>14</sup>C]-phosphoglycerate by incubating at room temperature for 45 min in a reaction mixture (0.5 ml) containing 100 mM Bicine-NaOH pH 8.2, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 8 mM NaH<sup>14</sup>CO<sub>3</sub> (18.5 kBq &#x3BC;mol<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>), and 20 &#x3BC;g of pure, activated wheat Rubisco. The reaction was quenched with 0.1 ml 10 M HCOOH. The mixture was dried down and the residue rehydrated for liquid scintillation counting.</p>
        <p>Rubisco inhibitors in 20 &#x3BC;l of the acid extracts were measured by comparison to inhibition of the enzyme by known quantities of CA1P (in 20 &#x3BC;l of 0.45 M TFA). Each standard and sample extract solution was mixed with 230 &#x3BC;l of (final concentrations) 100 mM Bicine-NaOH pH 8.2, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM NaH<sup>12</sup>CO<sub>3</sub>, and 10 &#x3BC;g of activated wheat Rubisco, and incubated for 5 min to hydrolyse lactones of CA1P and allow the binding to Rubisco. Rubisco activity was measured by adding 250 &#x3BC;l of 100 mM Bicine-NaOH pH 8.2, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM NaH<sup>14</sup>CO<sub>3</sub> (18.5 kBq &#x3BC;mol<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) and 0.4 mM RuBP, and the reaction was quenched after 2.5 min with 0.1 ml 10 M HCOOH. The mixture was dried down and the residue rehydrated before scintillation counting.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Identification of CA1P by HPLC</title>
        <p>Frozen leaf samples (0.1&#x2013;0.2 g FW) were ground to a fine powder in LN<sub>2</sub> and extracted with 1.0 ml of 0.45 M TFA after the addition of 490 Bq (240 pmol) [<sup>14</sup>C]-CA1P. After centrifugation, the extracts were purified by passage through 0.5 g Solid Phase Extraction columns (C18-E, Phenomenex, USA). The eluate was evaporated to dryness <italic>in vacuo</italic> over anhydrous CaCl<sub>2</sub> and NaOH pellets. The residue was resuspended in H<sub>2</sub>O, passed through a column of Dowex 50 H<sup>+</sup> (0.5 ml), and the eluate evaporated to dryness as before. The residue was dissolved in 0.25 ml H<sub>2</sub>O and mixed with 50 &#x3BC;l 1 M TRIS base. The resulting, mildly alkaline, solution was stored at &#x2013;20 &#xB0;C before fractionation by HPLC. The fractionation was conducted on a Dionex PA1 column (4&#xD7; 250 mm) using a DX500 chromatography system operated at 1 ml min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. The eluent was 100 mM CO<sub>2</sub>-free NaOH containing varying concentrations of sodium acetate: 100 mM from 0 to 5 min increasing to 800 mM at 30 min, to 900 mM at 35 min, and decreasing back to 100 mM at 40 min. In this system the retention times (min) were 8.9 for glucose 1-phosphate, 15.1 for fructose 6-phosphate, 16.0&#xB1;0.2 for CA1P, and 20.9 for fructose 1,6-<italic>bis</italic>phosphate. Fractions of 0.5 ml were collected and each mixed with 75 &#x3BC;l of 0.2 M Bicine-NaOH pH 8.0 and 1 M HCl. Fractions containing CA1P were identified by the presence of <sup>14</sup>C and frozen at &#x2013;20 &#xB0;C.</p>
        <p>The CA1P was restricted to two HPLC fractions and the total in each sample was obtained by the addition of the quantities estimated for each fraction. CA1P in 100 &#x3BC;l aliquots was measured by the inhibition of Rubisco activity by comparison to CA1P standards, making appropriate allowance for the presence of the small quantity of added [<sup>14</sup>C]-CA1P. Reaction mixtures (0.5 ml) contained 100 mM Bicine-NaOH pH 8.0, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM NaH<sup>14</sup>CO<sub>3</sub> (18.5 kBq &#x3BC;mol<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>), 0.4 mM RuBP, and 10 &#x3BC;g of activated Rubisco. Samples and standard solutions were preincubated with the reaction mixture without RuBP for 7 min before adding the RuBP to start the reaction. The reaction was stopped after a further 7 min by adding 0.1 ml 10 M HCOOH. The acidified reaction mixtures were dried and <sup>14</sup>C measured in the residues after rehydration. Corrections for losses of CA1P during the isolation process were made, based upon the recovery of the added [<sup>14</sup>C]-CA1P.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Total chlorophyll determination</title>
        <p>The total chlorophyll content in the leaf homogenates was determined spectrophotometrically, as either chlorophyll or phaeophytin, after extraction in ethanol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Wintermans and de Mots, 1965</xref>). The total chlorophyll content (relative to the leaf area and turgid mass) remained unchanged with water deficit in the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses (data not shown) and provided a good basis to normalize the data of the different measurements.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Rubisco kinetic constants</title>
        <p>Seedlings of <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L. cv. Riband (C<sub>3</sub> species used as the reference) and of the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses were grown in trays for the determination of Rubisco kinetic parameters using young leaves. Leaf samples (0.5 g FW) were quickly frozen in LN<sub>2</sub> and used within one day. Rubisco was extracted by grinding the leaves in a cold mortar with quartz sand, 2.5% (w/v) insoluble PVP, and 5 vols of ice-cold extraction medium containing 100 mM Bicine-KOH pH 8.2, 0.1 mM EDTA, 6% (w/v) PEG<sub>4000</sub>, 10 mM DTT, 50 mM 2-mercaptoethanol, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 1 mM benzamidine, 1 mM &#x3F5;-aminocaproic acid, and 1% (v/v) protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma, USA). After grinding to produce a fine suspension, the homogenate was centrifuged for 4 min at 16000 <italic>g</italic> and 4 &#xB0;C. Low molecular weight proteins and salts present in the leaf crude extracts were removed by passage of supernatant (1 ml) through a Sephadex G-200 (GE Healthcare, USA) column (20 ml bed volume, 1.5&#xD7;11.5 cm) pre-equilibrated and eluted with desalt buffer (100 mM Bicine-KOH pH 8.2, 0.5 mM EDTA, 1 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 1 mM benzamidine, and 1 mM &#x3F5;-aminocaproic acid). This treatment was introduced to remove potentially interfering enzymes of mass &#x2264;150 kDa. Fractions of 0.5 ml were collected and, after measuring the soluble protein content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bradford, 1976</xref>), the three fractions containing most protein were combined and the protease inhibitor cocktail added to a final concentration of 2.5% (v/v). The mixture was divided into different aliquots, some of which were immediately frozen in LN<sub>2</sub> (for later measurement of Rubisco quantity and for appropriate control assays).</p>
        <p>All measurements for the determination of kinetic parameters were conducted at 25 &#xB0;C. The Michaelis&#x2013;Menten constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub>) for CO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>K</italic><sub>c</sub>) was measured essentially as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bird <italic>et al.</italic> (1982)</xref>, but <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> for O<sub>2</sub> (<italic>K</italic><sub>o</sub>) was estimated by measuring <italic>K</italic><sub>c apparent</sub> at several O<sub>2</sub> concentrations (0, 21, 60, and 100%, balanced with N<sub>2</sub>). The carboxylation activity of Rubisco was determined at several CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations for each gas mixture. The assay buffer was pretreated by sparging with the appropriate gas mixture. Septum-sealed vials with stirring magnets were connected in series through the septa using butyl rubber transfer tubes fitted at each end with hypodermic needles and flushed with the appropriate CO<sub>2</sub>-free gas mixtures at 20 ml min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> for at least 30 min. Flushing of the vials was discontinued after the addition of the appropriate buffer but before the addition of NaH<sup>14</sup>CO<sub>3</sub>. The reaction mixtures (1 ml) contained (final concentrations) 100 mM Bicine-NaOH pH 8.2, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 &#x3BC;g ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> carbonic anhydrase (freshly dissolved), 0.4 mM RuBP, and six different concentrations of NaH<sup>14</sup>CO<sub>3</sub> (0&#x2013;10 mM; 37 kBq &#x3BC;mol<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>). The reactions were started at 30 s intervals by adding 20 &#x3BC;l of the partially purified leaf extract previously activated by incubation with 10 mM NaH<sup>14</sup>CO<sub>3</sub> (37 kBq &#x3BC;mol<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) for 30 min. The reactions were quenched after 2 min with 0.1 ml 10 M HCOOH. Changes in the activity of Rubisco through the course of the assays were monitored by the use of replicates of the same vial at staggered time points. The acidified mixtures were dried down and the residues rehydrated for scintillation counting.</p>
        <p>Several control assays were performed in order to ensure that <sup>14</sup>C incorporation by Rubisco occurred in the conditions of the assay at saturating CO<sub>2</sub> and low O<sub>2</sub> concentrations (positive control), and that <sup>14</sup>C incorporation did not occur (a) in the absence of the substrate RuBP; (b) when RuBP had been replaced by phosphoglycerate; or (c) when the Rubisco preparation had been preincubated with CABP to block the catalytic sites (negative controls). The quantity of Rubisco in the partially purified extracts was determined essentially as described above, using [<sup>14</sup>C]-CABP.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Rubisco specificity factor</title>
        <p>Rubisco was purified from fresh and young leaves of each of the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses to determine the specificity factor (<italic>S</italic><sub>C/O</sub>) by total consumption of RuBP in the oxygen electrode (Hansatech Instruments, UK) as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Parry <italic>et al.</italic> (1989)</xref>. The purification was essentially as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Haslam <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> and consisted of precipitation of Rubisco from the leaf extracts with 20% PEG<sub>4000</sub>, step-elution from an anion-exchange column, and desalting.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>All the analyses were made using GenStat<sup>&#xAE;</sup> 9.2, 2005 (Lawes Agricultural Trust, UK). Regression analysis was applied to model the variation of the different measurements with <italic>RWC</italic>. Non-significantly different parameters (<italic>t</italic> tests, <italic>P</italic> &gt;0.05) in the significant model terms of the regression (<italic>F</italic>-tests, <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05) were amalgamated in order to attain parsimony. The residuals were checked and found to conform to the assumptions of the analysis. The resulting best regression models were plotted and the parameter estimates (intercepts and slopes) with their respective standard errors (se), the percentage of variance accounted for by the model (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>), the residuals mean square (<italic>s</italic><sup>2</sup>), and the degrees of freedom (df) are given with the figures.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Rubisco activities</title>
        <p>The initial and total activities of Rubisco declined slightly with decreasing <italic>RWC</italic> but maximal activities of the enzyme were not significantly affected (<italic>P</italic> &gt;0.05) by leaf dehydration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). Initial activities were approximately 60% of maximal activities for <italic>P. dilatatum</italic> and about 40% of maximal activities for <italic>C. dactylon</italic> and <italic>Z. japonica</italic>, indicating that Rubisco activity was down-regulated by the lack of carbamylation of many catalytic sites under the growing conditions. Total activities were also less than maximal activities, especially at decreased <italic>RWC</italic>, consistent with further down-regulation by the presence of inhibitors in all three species.</p>
        <fig id="fig1" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Rubisco initial, total and maximal carboxylation activities (&#x3BC;mol CO<sub>2</sub> min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> chlorophyll) as a function of the relative water content (<italic>RWC</italic>, %) in the leaves of <italic>Paspalum dilatatum</italic> (A, D), <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic> (B, E), and <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic> (C, F). Initial activities (A&#x2013;C, black symbols) were determined immediately after extraction, total activities (A&#x2013;C, grey symbols) after activation in the presence of CO<sub>2</sub> and Mg<sup>2+</sup>, and maximal activities (D&#x2013;F, open symbols) after removal of tight-binding inhibitors with sulphate. Each data point corresponds to one sample, with seven (<italic>P. dilatatum</italic> and <italic>Z. japonica</italic>) or eight (<italic>C. dactylon</italic>) control (well-watered) and 12 non-watered samples per species. Regression lines were fitted when the <italic>RWC</italic> effect was significant (<italic>F</italic>-test; Initials: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=50.5%, <italic>s</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.033, df=55, <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001; Totals: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=32.5%, <italic>s</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.052, df=56, <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001; Maximals: no regression on <italic>RWC</italic>, <italic>P</italic> &gt;0.05).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq071f01_ht"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Quantities of Rubisco and RuBP</title>
        <p>The concentration of Rubisco catalytic sites mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> chlorophyll in leaves of the three species was not significantly affected (<italic>P</italic> &gt;0.05) by water deficit and the average values for <italic>P. dilatatum</italic>, <italic>C. dactylon</italic>, and <italic>Z. japonica</italic> were 26.6&#xB1;0.8, 24.4&#xB1;0.8, and 21.0&#xB1;0.8 nmol mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> Chl, respectively. In all three species, as the <italic>RWC</italic> fell, the quantities of RuBP decreased to values approaching the catalytic site concentration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>), suggesting that the rate of carboxylation could become increasingly limited by the availability of the CO<sub>2</sub> acceptor substrate as the leaves suffered water deficit. The quantities of RuBP present in the fully-hydrated leaves of <italic>C. dactylon</italic> and <italic>Z. japonica</italic> were greater, but the decrease with water deficit was more marked than in <italic>P. dilatatum</italic>.</p>
        <fig id="fig2" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Quantities of RuBP (<italic>R</italic><sub>t</sub>, filled symbols) and Rubisco catalytic sites (<italic>E</italic><sub>t</sub>, open symbols) (nmol mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> chlorophyll) as a function of the relative water content (<italic>RWC</italic>, %) in the leaves of <italic>Paspalum dilatatum</italic> (A), <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic> (B), and <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic> (C). Each data point corresponds to one sample, with seven or eight samples from control (well-watered) and 12 samples from non-watered plants per species. The insert in (A) represents a scale-up of the plot. Regression lines were fitted when the <italic>RWC</italic> effect was significant (<italic>F</italic>-tests; RuBP: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=75.6%, <italic>s</italic><sup>2</sup>=216.7, df=54; <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001; Rubisco catalytic sites: no regression on <italic>RWC</italic>, <italic>P</italic> &gt;0.05).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq071f02_ht"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In order to compare the effects of water deficit on RuBP quantities (this study) and on net CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Carmo-Silva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), values obtained for drought-stressed plants of each of the three species were expressed as a percentage of average values for the corresponding control plants. Both the relative rates of net CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation and RuBP quantities declined with decreasing <italic>RWC</italic> in the leaves of the three species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). Notably, in <italic>C. dactylon</italic> and <italic>Z. japonica</italic>, but not in <italic>P. dilatatum</italic>, the decrease in RuBP was apparently more marked than the decrease in the net photosynthetic rates.</p>
        <fig id="fig3" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Effect of leaf dehydration on the quantity of RuBP (black squares) and net CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation rate (A, grey circles) of <italic>Paspalum dilatatum</italic>, <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic>, and <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic>. The RuBP quantities (&#x3BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>) and rates of photosynthesis (&#x3BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>; measured at 25&#xB1;2 &#xB0;C, a <italic>PPFD</italic> of 850&#xB1;50 &#x3BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, and ambient concentrations of CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Carmo-Silva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) obtained for non-watered plants were expressed as a percentage of average values for corresponding control (well-watered) plants, to allow a comparison of drought effects in two independent batches of plants of the three species grown under identical conditions. The relative values of RuBP and photosynthesis were plotted against the corresponding <italic>RWC</italic> of each drought-stressed sample (also expressed as a percentage of average control values). Each data point corresponds to one sample. Regression lines were fitted when the <italic>RWC</italic> effect was significant (<italic>F</italic>-tests; RuBP: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=65.5%, <italic>s</italic><sup>2</sup>=220.4, df=30; <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001; A: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=59.2%, <italic>s</italic><sup>2</sup>=198.6, df=105; <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq071f03_ht"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Evidence for tight-binding inhibitors</title>
        <p>Tight-binding inhibitors were quantified by the inhibition of purified Rubisco by acid extracts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). In illuminated leaves these inhibitors were present in very low quantities and appeared to increase only marginally with leaf dehydration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>), up to the equivalent of &#x223C;5% of the Rubisco catalytic sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). Due to a non-significant interaction between species and treatment (<italic>P</italic> &gt;0.05), the same regression with <italic>RWC</italic> fitted the data for the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses in the light (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Larger quantities of tight-binding inhibitors were found in dark-adapted than in illuminated leaves, especially in <italic>Z. japonica</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Because <italic>RWC</italic> was partly re-established during the night, through decreased evaporation from the leaves and continued water absorption from the soil, samples collected from non-watered pots at the end of the 12 h dark period had higher <italic>RWC</italic> values, and corresponded to a narrower <italic>RWC</italic> range, than samples collected in the light period (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref> with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Even so, and despite the large scatter, a significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001) increase in the quantity of inhibitor with increasing water deficit was observed. In the dark, the inhibitor content increased with decreasing <italic>RWC</italic> to the equivalent of &#x223C;8% of the Rubisco catalytic sites in <italic>P. dilatatum</italic> and <italic>C. dactylon</italic> and to &#x223C;28% of the catalytic sites in <italic>Z. japonica</italic>.</p>
        <fig id="fig4" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Quantities of tight-binding inhibitor(s) of Rubisco activity (nmol mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> chlorophyll) in leaf acid extracts of <italic>Paspalum dilatatum</italic> (black symbols), <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic> (grey symbols), and <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic> (open symbols) as a function of the leaf relative water content (<italic>RWC</italic>, %). Samples were either harvested after 12 h of darkness (<italic>Dark</italic>, A) or from illuminated plants (<italic>Light</italic>, B). Each data point corresponds to one sample, with seven or eight samples from control (well-watered) and 12 samples from non-watered plants for each species for each light regime. Regression lines were fitted when the <italic>RWC</italic> effect was significant (<italic>F</italic>-test; Dark: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=79.1%, <italic>s</italic><sup>2</sup>=1.138, df=56, <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.001; Light: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=15.0%, <italic>s</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.0805, df=56, <italic>P</italic>=0.002).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexboterq071f04_ht"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Further studies attempted to characterize the inhibitor in <italic>Z. japonica</italic>. A component was isolated from acid extracts of the dark-adapted leaves of this species, which inhibited purified Rubisco and had a retention time in HPLC identical to that of authentic CA1P. Quantification of this inhibitory component utilized a trace of [<sup>14</sup>C]-CA1P&#x2014;added at the time of tissue homogenization&#x2014;to correct for losses during extraction and HPLC separation. Leaves of plants not subjected to drought were used to establish the occurrence of CA1P after a prolonged period of darkness. The quantities of CA1P estimated after HPLC (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>) were in the range of values obtained by the direct estimates of inhibitor in crude acid extracts shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>. Therefore, it is likely that CA1P is the predominant inhibitor present in the dark in <italic>Z. japonica</italic>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Quantity of CA1P (nmol mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> chlorophyll) in light- and dark-adapted leaves of <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-treatment</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Z. japonica</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CA1P (nmol mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> Chl)</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dark</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.97&#xB1;1.76</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Light</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53&#xB1;0.39</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>Samples were taken from well-watered plants after a period of 12 h in darkness (Dark) or 4 h after the beginning of the subsequent photoperiod (Light). The inhibitor was extracted with trifluoroacetic acid and measured after HPLC separation. Extracts were spiked with tracer quantities of [<sup>14</sup>C]-CA1P to allow correction for losses in processing the samples (average 56.4%). The retention time in the chromatographic system was the same as authentic CA1P and consistent with the radioactive spike. Values are means of four biological replicates &#xB1;standard errors.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>In agreement with the presence of a tight-binding inhibitor in the dark in <italic>Z. japonica</italic>, the total activities of Rubisco in dark-adapted leaves of this species (after the 12 h dark period) were &#x223C;74% of the total activities in leaves harvested in the light (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>), meaning that inhibitors were bound to &#x223C;26% of the catalytic sites in the dark. This result was independent of water deficit and was observed only for <italic>Z. japonica</italic>. No significant (<italic>P</italic> &gt;0.05) differences in Rubisco total activities were observed between the light- and dark-adapted leaves of <italic>P. dilatatum</italic> and <italic>C. dactylon</italic> and therefore no evidence was shown of a bound inhibitor for these two species. In neither light nor dark was there evidence of an increase in tight-binding inhibitor with drought stress, so these data did not support the slight trend shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4</xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float">
          <label>Table 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Total activity of Rubisco (&#x3BC;mol min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> Rubisco) extracted from light- or dark-adapted leaves of well watered (control, C) and non-watered (drought stress, S) plants of <italic>Paspalum dilatatum</italic>, <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic>, and <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Treatment<hr/></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>P. dilatatum</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>C. dactylon</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Z. japonica</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Rubisco total activity (mmol min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> Rubisco)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dark</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03&#xB1;0.06</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83&#xB1;0.10</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74&#xB1;0.07</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96&#xB1;0.08</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81&#xB1;0.10</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74&#xB1;0.03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Light</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11&#xB1;0.02</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73&#xB1;0.25</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36&#xB1;0.04</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14&#xB1;0.16</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79&#xB1;0.07</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39&#xB1;0.05</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RWC</italic> (%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dark</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.2&#xB1;0.4</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.1&#xB1;0.3</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5&#xB1;0.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.4&#xB1;0.4</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.7&#xB1;0.6</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.8&#xB1;3.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Light</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.6&#xB1;0.1</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.0&#xB1;1.2</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.9&#xB1;1.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.2&#xB1;4.6</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.9&#xB1;4.1</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.1&#xB1;0.3</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>Samples were taken after a period of 12 h in darkness (Dark) or 4 h after the beginning of the photoperiod (Light). Corresponding leaf relative water contents (<italic>RWC</italic>, %) are also given. Values are means of three biological replicates &#xB1;standard errors.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Rubisco kinetic parameters</title>
        <p>Rubisco purified from each of the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses, <italic>P. dilatatum</italic>, <italic>C. dactylon</italic>, and <italic>Z. japonica</italic>, was characterized by lower <italic>S</italic><sub>C/O</sub> than in wheat (C<sub>3</sub> species used as reference) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>). The Michaelis&#x2013;Menten constants of Rubisco for CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> (<italic>K</italic><sub>c</sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub>o</sub>) estimated for each of the C<sub>4</sub> species were in the same range and were higher than the corresponding values estimated for wheat. The maximum Rubisco carboxylation activity (<italic>V</italic><sub>c</sub>) was also higher in the C<sub>4</sub> than in the C<sub>3</sub> species, and among the grasses <italic>V</italic><sub>c</sub> was higher in <italic>Z. japonica</italic> than in <italic>C. dactylon</italic> and lowest in <italic>P. dilatatum</italic>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float">
          <label>Table 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Kinetic parameters of Rubisco from wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) and from the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses (<italic>Paspalum dilatatum</italic>, <italic>Cynodon dactylo</italic><italic>n</italic>, and <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic>) at 25 &#xB0;C</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S</italic><sub>C/O</sub> (<italic>V</italic><sub>c</sub><italic>K</italic><sub>o</sub>/<italic>V</italic><sub>o</sub><italic>K</italic><sub>c</sub>)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>c</sub> (&#x3BC;M)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>o</sub> (&#x3BC;M)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>V</italic><sub>c</sub> (&#x3BC;mol min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> Rubisco)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>V</italic><sub>o</sub> (&#x3BC;mol min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> Rubisco)</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>T. aestivum</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0&#xB1;9.2</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9&#xB1;0.9</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">341&#xB1;33</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.54&#xB1;0.07</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79&#xB1;0.03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>P. dilatatum</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.0&#xB1;7.1</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9&#xB1;0.8</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">415&#xB1;5</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.11&#xB1;0.04</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71&#xB1;0.03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>C. dactylon</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.2&#xB1;9.0</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0&#xB1;1.3</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">402&#xB1;27</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41&#xB1;0.18</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73&#xB1;0.06</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Z. japonica</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.1&#xB1;7.7</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5&#xB1;1.2</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">403&#xB1;27</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78&#xB1;0.08</td>
                <td align="char" char="plusmn" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98&#xB1;0.08</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>For the Michaelis&#x2013;Menten constants of Rubisco for CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> (<italic>K</italic><sub>c</sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub>o</sub>, &#x3BC;M) and the maximum Rubisco carboxylation and oxygenation activities (<italic>V</italic><sub>c</sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub>o</sub>, &#x3BC;mol min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> Rubisco) the mean values and respective standard errors were calculated from measurements taken with three biological and three analytical replicates. The specificity factor (<italic>S</italic><sub>C/O</sub>) was determined in Rubisco purified from each species using a minimum of five analytical replicates.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Attempts were made to measure both <italic>V</italic><sub>c</sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub>o</sub> by an HPLC method based on that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Yaguchi <italic>et al.</italic> (1996)</xref> using partially purified extracts of leaves from wheat and each of the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses. These attempts failed and <italic>V</italic><sub>o</sub> was subsequently determined indirectly by solving the equation <italic>S</italic><sub>C/O</sub>=<italic>V<sub>c</sub>K<sub>o</sub>/V<sub>o</sub>K<sub>c.</sub></italic> However, the variation in the measurements of <italic>S</italic><sub>C/O</sub> is too high to allow much precision in the estimation of <italic>V</italic><sub>o</sub>. The estimated <italic>V</italic><sub>o</sub> was highest in <italic>Z. japonica</italic>, the species with lowest specificity towards CO<sub>2</sub>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses, <italic>Paspalum dilatatum</italic>, <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic>, and <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic>, Rubisco initial and total activities decreased slightly with water deficit, but maximal activity and Rubisco quantity remained unchanged, consistent with commonly observed drought effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Ghannoum, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Lawlor and Tezara, 2009</xref>). In all three species, Rubisco initial activity was lower than total activity and both initial and total activities were lower than maximal activity, and suggested increasing down-regulation with leaf dehydration (decreasing <italic>RWC</italic>). Rubisco down-regulation can be explained by a combination of decreased carbamylation of the active site lysine and the presence of competitive and tight-binding inhibitors. Carbamylation may be impeded by negative effectors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hatch and Jensen, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Badger and Lorimer, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jordan <italic>et al.</italic>, 1983</xref>) or by RuBP bound into the non-carbamylated sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brooks and Portis, 1988</xref>), but these effects will not necessarily affect the activity in extracts because of dilution. The proportion of initial to total activity was not affected by leaf dehydration (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq071/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online), whereas both initial and total activities showed a similar decrease in relation to maximal activity with increasing water deficit, suggesting a possible increase in Rubisco tight-binding inhibitors.</p>
      <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Parry <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref> showed that Rubisco activity was inhibited in tobacco under drought stress. In that study, the inhibitory component in acid extracts of illuminated leaves was assumed to be <sc>D</sc>-<italic>glycero</italic>-2,3-diulose-1,5-<italic>bis</italic>phosphate (PDBP). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> shows that the quantities of tight-binding inhibitors in the leaves of <italic>P. dilatatum</italic>, <italic>C. dactylon</italic>, and <italic>Z. japonica</italic> were only marginally increased with water deficit. The maximum quantities in the light were estimated to be, at the most, &#x223C;5% of the Rubisco catalytic sites and, therefore, insufficient to explain entirely the decrease in total activity with respect to maximal activity. It can be argued that some Rubisco inhibitors are unstable in the acid extracts and this merits further investigation.</p>
      <p>The quantity of Rubisco inhibitor in the acid extracts from leaves after 12 h in the dark was most in <italic>Z. japonica</italic> and least in <italic>P. dilatatum</italic>. The first evidence of CA1P in leaves was the observed modulation of Rubisco activity by light and dark transitions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Vu <italic>et al.</italic>, 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Besford, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Servaites <italic>et al.</italic>, 1984</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sage and Seemann (1993)</xref> reported regulation of Rubisco in <italic>Z. japonica</italic> by darkness and considered that this might be due to the accumulation of CA1P. The removal of CA1P from Rubisco catalytic sites in the light depends on the action of Rubisco activase and the inhibitor is then degraded by CA1P phosphatase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Robinson and Portis, 1988</xref>). The effects of CA1P may continue at the beginning of the light period, at low light intensities, and in long periods of low light intensity due either to dense cloud coverage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Sage <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>) or to shading by neighbouring leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kobza and Seemann, 1989<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33"><italic>b</italic></xref>).</p>
      <p>The concentration of inhibitor in acid extracts from dark-adapted leaves was approximately 28%, in <italic>Z. japonica</italic>, and 5%, in <italic>P. dilatatum</italic> and <italic>C. dactylon</italic>, of the quantity of Rubisco catalytic sites in each species. For <italic>Z. japonica</italic>, the difference in the total Rubisco activity between extracts of leaves harvested in the light and after 12 h in the dark was consistent with the quantity of inhibitor measured, but there were no consistent differences between total Rubisco activity in the light- and dark-adapted leaves for <italic>P. dilatatum</italic> and <italic>C. dactylon</italic>. These results corroborate the observations of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sage and Seemann (1993)</xref>, suggesting the presence of CA1P in <italic>Z. japonica</italic>, but are not conclusive about the presence/absence of this inhibitor in <italic>P. dilatatum</italic> and <italic>C. dactylon</italic>. To confirm the identity of the inhibitor occurring in <italic>Z. japonica</italic> in the dark, the putative CA1P was analysed by HPLC after isolation from light- and dark-adapted (12 h dark period) leaves. Rubisco activity was inhibited by components in the acid extracts that were recovered in the same HPLC fractions as authentic CA1P and the quantities of inhibitor estimated by this method were in the range found by the direct estimates on crude leaf acid extracts, thus providing definitive evidence for the presence of CA1P in the leaves of <italic>Z. japonica</italic>. The presence of inhibitors is likely to protect Rubisco from proteolysis, especially in stressed leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Parry <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>).</p>
      <p>The RuBP content was greater in fully hydrated leaves of <italic>C. dactylon</italic> and <italic>Z. japonica</italic> than in <italic>P. dilatatum</italic>. <italic>In vivo</italic>, this potential disadvantage for <italic>P. dilatatum</italic> may be partly counter-balanced by a greater Rubisco activation state, as indicated by the higher initial activity in this species than in <italic>C. dactylon</italic> or <italic>Z. japonica</italic>. Leaf dehydration caused a much larger decrease in the quantity of RuBP in <italic>C. dactylon</italic> and <italic>Z. japonica</italic> than in <italic>P. dilatatum</italic>. Decreased RuBP availability with water deficit has been observed in several studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Gimenez <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gunasekera and Berkowitz, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Tezara <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Wingler <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Parry <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bota <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Because RuBP consumption and production are interdependent, it is difficult to assess whether decreased RuBP availability may constitute a limitation to or be a consequence of decreased CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation. Comparison of relative effects of drought stress revealed a more marked decrease in RuBP quantities than in net photosynthetic rates by <italic>C. dactylon</italic> and <italic>Z. japonica</italic>, suggesting that the decline in substrate availability could constitute a factor contributing to limit carboxylation in these two C<sub>4</sub> grasses. In <italic>P. dilatatum</italic> the moderate relative decrease in RuBP with water deficit is more likely to represent a consequence of decreased CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation (and thus decreased 3-phosphoglycerate production), rather than constitute a limiting factor <italic>per se</italic>.</p>
      <p>Decreased capacity for RuBP regeneration may be a consequence of impairment of ATP synthesis, of Calvin cycle enzymes activity, or both. Whilst some studies on tobacco and barley indicate decreased activity of Calvin cycle enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gunasekera and Berkowitz, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Wingler <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>), in sunflower, although the decrease in ATP was less dramatic than the decrease in RuBP, it was concluded that the latter was a consequence of decreased ATP synthesis through its effect on RuBP regeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Tezara <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lawlor, 2002</xref>). Decreased ATP synthesis, due to impaired photophosphorylation by chloroplastic ATP synthase, in association with increased concentrations of Mg<sup>2+</sup>, has been suggested as a major metabolic limitation to photosynthesis under water deficit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lawlor, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Lawlor and Tezara, 2009</xref>). An alternative view is that ATP availability may decrease as a result of increased consumption by alternative sinks under drought stress. For instance, increased bundle sheath leakage, as observed in sorghum and sugarcane when subjected to drought (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Saliendra <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Williams <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>), decreases the efficiency of the C<sub>4</sub> cycle, and accumulation of compounds associated with drought tolerance, such as proline, as observed for the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses under study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Carmo-Silva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), would increase the usage of ATP.</p>
      <p>The quantities, on a chlorophyll basis, of both RuBP (<italic>R</italic><sub>t</sub>) and Rubisco catalytic sites (<italic>E</italic><sub>t</sub>) were included in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref> to allow easy comparison. In <italic>P. dilatatum</italic>, <italic>R</italic><sub>t</sub> was only marginally above <italic>E</italic><sub>t</sub>, even in well-watered plants. Even though only some 60&#x2013;70% of the catalytic sites were active in this species, the ratio <italic>R</italic><sub>t</sub>/<italic>E</italic><sub>t</sub> was less than 2 and so approaching the range where RuBP becomes limiting in C<sub>3</sub> species (below &#x223C;1.5&#x2013;1.8; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">von Caemmerer, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lawlor, 2002</xref>). The modelling of the situation where the substrate concentration is similar to the catalytic site concentration is described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">von Caemmerer (2000)</xref>. The <italic>R</italic><sub>t</sub> in <italic>C. dactylon</italic> and <italic>Z. japonica</italic> was much higher in control plants, corresponding to <italic>R</italic><sub>t</sub>/<italic>E</italic><sub>t</sub> ratios of 3.5 and 2.9, respectively, but the values fell steeply as <italic>RWC</italic> decreased, giving ratios similar to those in <italic>P. dilatatum</italic> at about 85% <italic>RWC</italic>. Thus, the quantities of RuBP in the leaves of all three species under drought stress were close to the critical value for RuBP-dependence of C<sub>3</sub> photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lawlor, 2002</xref>).</p>
      <p>Rubisco activase removes inhibitors from carbamylated catalytic sites and facilitates the removal of RuBP bound to non-carbamylated sites. Rubisco activase requires ATP for activation of Rubisco but is inhibited by ADP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Portis, 2003</xref>). If the decreased capacity for regeneration of RuBP under drought is a consequence of decreased ATP synthesis, a further consequence could be more Rubisco-bound inhibitors and fewer carbamylated Rubisco catalytic sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lawlor, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Lawlor and Tezara, 2009</xref>) &#x2013; both resulting from the decline in activase activity caused by a fall in the ratio ATP/ADP. Inactivation of Rubisco catalytic sites with increasing water deficit will decrease both carboxylation and oxygenation and, therefore, photosynthesis and photorespiration, as previously predicted by the modelling of carbon assimilation under drought (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Carmo-Silva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>).</p>
      <p>Rubiscos isolated from leaves of the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses had lower specificity factors (<italic>S</italic><sub>C/O</sub>), higher Michaelis&#x2013;Menten constants for CO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>K</italic><sub>c</sub>) and higher maximum carboxylase activities (<italic>V</italic><sub>c</sub>) than wheat Rubisco, which is in agreement with previous reports on the kinetics of Rubisco from C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Yeoh <italic>et al.</italic>, 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Tcherkez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kubien <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). The lower specificity for CO<sub>2</sub> of Rubisco from C<sub>4</sub> compared with C<sub>3</sub> monocots is associated with specific differences in the large subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Christin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) and may be a consequence of diminished selection pressure resulting from increased CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations in the vicinity of the enzyme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Jordan and Ogren, 1981</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Tcherkez <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> suggested evolutionary optimization of Rubiscos from different species to the subcellular environment in which the enzyme functions. In the present study, the relatively high <italic>V</italic><sub>c</sub> would support rapid assimilation in the CO<sub>2</sub>-rich environment of the bundle sheath, consistent with the high photosynthetic performance of the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Carmo-Silva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>).</p>
      <p>The Michaelis&#x2013;Menten constant for oxygen (<italic>K</italic><sub>o</sub>) of Rubisco from different photosynthetic organisms is largely unknown. The few values published (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">von Caemmerer, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kubien <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) suggest that <italic>K</italic><sub>o</sub> may be highly variable between different species, even when they are closely related and represent the same photosynthetic pathway. The need to determine <italic>K</italic><sub>o</sub> for each species is therefore justified. The estimates of <italic>K</italic><sub>o</sub> obtained here for the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses were similar and provide a valuable contribution for future modelling of photosynthesis.</p>
      <p>In view of the effects of drought on the quantities of RuBP in the leaves, a measure of the Michaelis&#x2013;Menten constant for RuBP (<italic>K</italic><sub>RuBP</sub>) would be a valuable addition to the kinetic constants determined for the three grasses. Values for <italic>K</italic><sub>RuBP</sub> for several C<sub>4</sub> species have been published (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Yeoh <italic>et al.</italic>, 1981</xref>) and ranged from 15 &#x3BC;M to 100 &#x3BC;M which also suggests that measurements are needed for each species for which the objective is the mechanistic modelling of photosynthesis. The much lower concentration of RuBP in fully-hydrated leaves of <italic>P. dilatatum</italic> (NADP-ME) than in <italic>C. dactylon</italic> (NAD-ME) may be associated with a lower average <italic>K</italic><sub>RuBP</sub> in NADP-ME than in NAD-ME C<sub>4</sub> grasses (calculated from data in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Yeoh <italic>et al.</italic>, 1981</xref>). Estimation of the effective concentration of RuBP at the catalytic site of Rubisco is problematic because of the presence of competitive inhibitors and the formation of complexes with Mg<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">von Caemmerer, 2000</xref>).</p>
      <p>The results presented here show that the decline in the quantity of RuBP in the leaves as water deficit increased was of the same order of magnitude as the decline in photosynthetic rates reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Carmo-Silva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Concomitant measurements of ATP and potential competitive inhibitors of RuBP binding to Rubisco, including intermediate metabolites of the Calvin cycle, particularly 3-phosphoglycerate, would improve understanding of factors limiting C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis under water deficit. The marginal increase in Rubisco tight-binding inhibitors under water deficit is unlikely to have a relevant contribution to the decreased photosynthetic rates. The presence of CA1P in dark-adapted leaves of <italic>Z. japonica</italic> may confer protection against degradation of Rubisco by proteolysis, but the mechanism by which Rubisco is down-regulated in the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses under water deficit merits further study.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Supplementary data</title>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq071/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link> are available at <italic>JXB</italic> online.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/erq071/DC1"><bold>Supplementary Fig. S1.</bold></ext-link> Rubisco activation state in relation to <italic>RWC</italic> in the three C<sub>4</sub> grasses</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>[Supplementary Data]</title>
        </caption>
        <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="erq071_index.html"/>
        <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="erq071_1.pdf"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>AE Carmo-Silva acknowledges <italic>Funda&#xE7;&#xE3;o para a Ci&#xEA;ncia e a Tecnologia</italic>, Portugal, for financial support (PhD grant SFRH/BD/13730/2003). Rothamsted Research is a grant-aided institute of The Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council, UK. The authors thank AgResearch, Margot Forde Forage Germplasm Centre, New Zealand, and Al&#xED;pio Dias &amp; Irm&#xE3;o, Lda, Portugal, for providing grass seeds; and Dr Michael E Salvucci, US Arid-Land Agricultural Research Center, USA, for helpful comments on the manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Badger</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lorimer</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Interaction of sugar phosphates with the catalytic site of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase</article-title>
          <source>Biochemistry</source>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>2219</fpage>
          <lpage>2225</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7236594</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berry</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lorimer</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pierce</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seemann</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meek</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Freas</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isolation, identification, and synthesis of 2-carboxyarabinitol 1-phosphate, a diurnal regulator of ribulose-bisphosphate carboxylase activity</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>734</fpage>
          <lpage>738</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Besford</surname>
              <given-names>RT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Some properties of ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase from tomato leaves</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>153</volume>
          <fpage>495</fpage>
          <lpage>504</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bird</surname>
              <given-names>IF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cornelius</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Affinity of RuBP carboxylases for carbon dioxide and inhibition of the enzymes by oxygen</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>1004</fpage>
          <lpage>1013</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bota</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Medrano</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Flexas</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Is photosynthesis limited by decreased Rubisco activity and RuBP content under progressive water stress?</article-title>
          <source>New Phytologist</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>162</volume>
          <fpage>671</fpage>
          <lpage>681</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bowes</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogren</surname>
              <given-names>WL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Oxygen inhibition and other properties of soybean ribulose 1,5-diphosphate carboxylase</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source>
          <year>1972</year>
          <volume>247</volume>
          <fpage>2171</fpage>
          <lpage>2176</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5062819</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bradford</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein&#x2013;dye binding</article-title>
          <source>Analytical Biochemistry</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <fpage>248</fpage>
          <lpage>254</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brooks</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Portis</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Protein-bound ribulose bisphosphate correlates with deactivation of ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase in leaves</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>244</fpage>
          <lpage>249</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16666111</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carmo-Silva</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Francisco</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Powers</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lia</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>MAJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arraba&#xE7;a</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Grasses of different C<sub>4</sub> subtypes reveal leaf traits related to drought tolerance in their natural habitats: changes in structure, water potential and amino acid content</article-title>
          <source>American Journal of Botany</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>96</volume>
          <fpage>1222</fpage>
          <lpage>1235</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carmo-Silva</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Powers</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arraba&#xE7;a</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>MAJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Photorespiration in C<sub>4</sub> grasses remains slow under drought conditions</article-title>
          <source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>925</fpage>
          <lpage>940</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carmo-Silva</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soares</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marques</surname>
              <given-names>da Silva J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bernardes</surname>
              <given-names>da Silva A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arraba&#xE7;a</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Photosynthetic responses of three C<sub>4</sub> grasses of different metabolic subtypes to water deficit</article-title>
          <source>Functional Plant Biology</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>204</fpage>
          <lpage>213</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Catsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Determination of water deficit in discs cut out from leaf blades</article-title>
          <source>Biologia Plantarum</source>
          <year>1960</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>76</fpage>
          <lpage>77</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Christin</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salamin</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muasya</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roalson</surname>
              <given-names>EH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Russier</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Besnard</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evolutionary switch and genetic convergence on <italic>rbcL</italic> following the evolution of C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>2361</fpage>
          <lpage>2368</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18695049</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Du</surname>
              <given-names>YC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kawamitsu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nose</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hiyane</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murayama</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wasano</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uchida</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of water stress on carbon exchange rate and activities of photosynthetic enzymes in leaves of sugarcane (<italic>Saccharum</italic> sp.)</article-title>
          <source>Australian Journal of Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>719</fpage>
          <lpage>726</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Flexas</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Medrano</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Drought-inhibition of photosynthesis in C<sub>3</sub> plants: stomatal and non-stomatal limitations revisited</article-title>
          <source>Annals of Botany</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>183</fpage>
          <lpage>189</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12099349</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Furbank</surname>
              <given-names>RT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chitty</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jenkins</surname>
              <given-names>CLD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trevanion</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>von Caemmerer</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ashton</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic manipulation of key photosynthetic enzymes in the C<sub>4</sub> plant</article-title>
          <source>Flaveria bidentis. Australian Journal of Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>477</fpage>
          <lpage>485</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ghannoum</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis and water stress</article-title>
          <source>Annals of Botany</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>635</fpage>
          <lpage>644</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18552367</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gimenez</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitchell</surname>
              <given-names>VJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lawlor</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of photosynthetic rate of two sunflower hybrids under water stress</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <fpage>516</fpage>
          <lpage>524</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16668670</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gunasekera</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berkowitz</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Use of transgenic plants with ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase oxygenase antisense DNA to evaluate the rate limitation of photosynthesis under water stress</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>629</fpage>
          <lpage>635</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12231969</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gutteridge</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>MAJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burton</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mudd</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feeney</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Servaites</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pierce</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A nocturnal inhibitor of carboxylation in leaves</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>324</volume>
          <fpage>274</fpage>
          <lpage>276</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gutteridge</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reddy</surname>
              <given-names>GS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lorimer</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The synthesis and purification of 2&#x2019;-carboxy-D-arabinitol 1-phosphate, a natural inhibitor of ribulose 1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase, investigated by <sup>31</sup>P NMR</article-title>
          <source>Biochemical Journal</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>260</volume>
          <fpage>711</fpage>
          <lpage>716</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2764899</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haslam</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andralojc</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Madgwick</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andersson</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grimsrud</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eilertsen</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>MAJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Omasa</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nouchi</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>DeKok</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Specificity of diatom Rubisco</article-title>
          <source>Plant responses to air pollution and global change</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
          <fpage>157</fpage>
          <lpage>164</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hatch</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jensen</surname>
              <given-names>RG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase from tobacco: changes in pH response and affinity for CO<sub>2</sub> and Mg<sup>2+</sup> induced by chloroplast intermediates</article-title>
          <source>Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>205</volume>
          <fpage>587</fpage>
          <lpage>594</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6781414</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Holbrook</surname>
              <given-names>GP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turner</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Polans</surname>
              <given-names>NO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dark inhibition of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase oxygenase in legumes: a biosystematic study</article-title>
          <source>Photosynthesis Research</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jordan</surname>
              <given-names>DB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chollet</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogren</surname>
              <given-names>WL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Binding of phosphorylated effectors by active and inactive forms of ribulose-1,5-bisphoaphate carboxylase</article-title>
          <source>Biochemistry</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>3410</fpage>
          <lpage>3418</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jordan</surname>
              <given-names>DB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogren</surname>
              <given-names>WL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Species variation in the specificity of ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volume>291</volume>
          <fpage>513</fpage>
          <lpage>515</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kane</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilkin</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Portis</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrews</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Potent inhibition of ribulose-bisphosphate carboxylase by an oxidised impurity in ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>1059</fpage>
          <lpage>1069</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9662549</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Major</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>MAJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Is there another player in the game of Rubisco regulation?</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>1245</fpage>
          <lpage>1251</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib29">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>MAJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Lea</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase and carbonic anhydrase</article-title>
          <source>Enzymes of primary metabolism</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib30">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andralojc</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lea</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>MAJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>2'-Carboxy-<sc>D</sc>-arabitinol 1-phosphate protects ribulose 1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase against proteolytic breakdown</article-title>
          <source>European Journal of Biochemistry</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>266</volume>
          <fpage>840</fpage>
          <lpage>847</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10583377</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib31">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Portis</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Oxygen dependent H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production by Rubisco</article-title>
          <source>FEBS Letters</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>571</volume>
          <fpage>124</fpage>
          <lpage>128</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15280029</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib32">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kobza</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seemann</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Light-dependent kinetics of 2-carboxyarabinitol 1-phosphate metabolism and ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase activity</article-title>
          <source>in vivo. Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1989a</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>174</fpage>
          <lpage>179</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib33">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kobza</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seemann</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase activity in response to diurnal changes in irradiance</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1989b</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>918</fpage>
          <lpage>924</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16666642</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib34">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kubien</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Whitney</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>PV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jesson</surname>
              <given-names>LK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The biochemistry of Rubisco in <italic>Flaveria</italic></article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>1767</fpage>
          <lpage>1777</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18227079</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib35">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Laing</surname>
              <given-names>WA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogren</surname>
              <given-names>WL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hageman</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of soybean net photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub> fixation by interaction of CO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>2</sub> and ribulose 1,5-diphosphate carboxylase</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1974</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>678</fpage>
          <lpage>685</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16658951</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib36">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lal</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edwards</surname>
              <given-names>GE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysis of inhibition of photosynthesis under water stress in the C<sub>4</sub> species <italic>Amaranthus cruentus</italic> and <italic>Zea mays</italic>: electron transport, CO<sub>2</sub>-fixation and carboxylation capacity</article-title>
          <source>Australian Journal of Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>403</fpage>
          <lpage>412</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib37">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lawlor</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Limitation to photosynthesis in water-stressed leaves: stomata vs. metabolism and the role of ATP</article-title>
          <source>Annals of Botany</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>871</fpage>
          <lpage>885</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12102513</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib38">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lawlor</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tezara</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Causes of decreased photosynthetic rate and metabolic capacity in water-deficient leaf cells: a critical evaluation of mechanisms and integration of processes</article-title>
          <source>Annals of Botany</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>561</fpage>
          <lpage>579</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19155221</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib39">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Long</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Sage</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Monson</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Environmental responses</article-title>
          <source>C<sub>4</sub> plant biology</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>215</fpage>
          <lpage>249</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib40">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lorimer</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miziorko</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Carbamate formation on the amino group of a lysine residue as the basis for the activation of RuBP carboxylase</article-title>
          <source>Biochemistry</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>5321</fpage>
          <lpage>5328</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6778504</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib41">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Majumdar</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghosh</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glick</surname>
              <given-names>BR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dumbroff</surname>
              <given-names>EB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Activities of chlorophyllase, phospho<italic>enol</italic>pyruvate carboxylase and ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase in the primary leaves of soybean during senescence and drought</article-title>
          <source>Physiologia Plantarum</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <fpage>473</fpage>
          <lpage>480</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib42">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marques</surname>
              <given-names>da Silva J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arraba&#xE7;a</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Photosynthetic enzymes of the C<sub>4</sub> grass <italic>Setaria sphacelata</italic> under water stress: a comparison between rapidly and slowly imposed water deficit</article-title>
          <source>Photosynthetica</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          <lpage>47</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib43">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>BD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharkey</surname>
              <given-names>TD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobza</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seemann</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification and levels of 2'-carboxyarabinitol in leaves</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>1546</fpage>
          <lpage>1550</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16669072</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib44">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>MAJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andralojc</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lea</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rubisco activity: effects of drought stress</article-title>
          <source>Annals of Botany</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>833</fpage>
          <lpage>839</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12102509</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib45">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>MAJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andralojc</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parmar</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Habash</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paul</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alred</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quick</surname>
              <given-names>WP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Servaites</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of Rubisco by inhibitors in the light</article-title>
          <source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>528</fpage>
          <lpage>534</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib46">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>MAJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gutteridge</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Variation in the specificity factor of C<sub>3</sub> higher plant Rubisco determined by the total consumption of ribulose-P<sub>2</sub></article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>317</fpage>
          <lpage>320</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib47">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>MAJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Madgwick</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carmo-Silva</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andralojc</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rubisco regulation: a role for inhibitors</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>1569</fpage>
          <lpage>1580</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18436543</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib48">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pearce</surname>
              <given-names>FG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrews</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The relationship between side reactions and the slow inhibition of ribulose-bisphosphate carboxylase revealed by a loop 6 mutant of the tobacco enzyme</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>278</volume>
          <fpage>32526</fpage>
          <lpage>32536</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12783874</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib49">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Portis</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rubisco activase: Rubisco's catalytic chaperone</article-title>
          <source>Photosynthesis Research</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          <lpage>27</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16245090</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib50">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Portis</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Release of the nocturnal inhibitor, carboxyarabinitol-1-phosphate, from ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase by Rubisco activase</article-title>
          <source>FEBS Letters</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>233</volume>
          <fpage>413</fpage>
          <lpage>416</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib51">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sage</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reid</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>Bd</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seemann</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Long-term kinetics of the light-dependent regulation of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase activity in plants with and without 2-carboxyarabinitol 1-phosphate</article-title>
          <source>Planta</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>191</volume>
          <fpage>222</fpage>
          <lpage>230</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib52">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sage</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seemann</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase oxygenase activity in response to reduced light-intensity in C<sub>4</sub> plants</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>21</fpage>
          <lpage>28</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12231795</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib53">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saliendra</surname>
              <given-names>NZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meinzer</surname>
              <given-names>FC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perry</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thom</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Associations between partitioning of carboxylase activity and bundle sheath leakiness to CO<sub>2</sub>, carbon isotope discrimination, photosynthesis, and growth in sugarcane</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>907</fpage>
          <lpage>914</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib54">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seemann</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berry</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Freas</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krump</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase activity <italic>in vivo</italic> by a light modulated inhibitor of catalysis</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>8024</fpage>
          <lpage>8028</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib55">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Servaites</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>MAJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gutteridge</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Species variation in the predawn inhibition of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase oxygenase</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>1161</fpage>
          <lpage>1163</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16665155</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib56">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Servaites</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Torisky</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chao</surname>
              <given-names>SF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diurnal changes in ribulose 1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase activity and activation state in leaves of field-grown soybeans</article-title>
          <source>Plant Science Letters</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>115</fpage>
          <lpage>121</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib57">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Soares-Cordeiro</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carmo-Silva</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bernardes</surname>
              <given-names>da Silva A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marques</surname>
              <given-names>da Silva J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arraba&#xE7;a</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of rapidly imposed water deficit on photosynthetic parameters of three C<sub>4</sub> grasses</article-title>
          <source>Photosynthetica</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>304</fpage>
          <lpage>308</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib58">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tcherkez</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farquhar</surname>
              <given-names>GD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrews</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Despite slow catalysis and confused substrate specificity, all ribulose bisphosphate carboxylases may be nearly perfectly optimized</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>7246</fpage>
          <lpage>7251</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib59">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tezara</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitchell</surname>
              <given-names>VJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Driscoll</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lawlor</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Water stress inhibits plant photosynthesis by decreasing coupling factor and ATP</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>401</volume>
          <fpage>914</fpage>
          <lpage>917</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib60">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tezara</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitchell</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Driscoll</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lawlor</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of water deficit and its interaction with CO<sub>2</sub> supply on the biochemistry and physiology of photosynthesis in sunflower</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>1781</fpage>
          <lpage>1791</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12147728</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib61">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>von Caemmerer</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Biochemical models of leaf photosynthesis</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <publisher-loc>Collingwood</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>CSIRO Publishing</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib62">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vu</surname>
              <given-names>CV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allen</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bowes</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of light and elevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> on the ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase activity and ribulose bisphosphate level of soybean leaves</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>729</fpage>
          <lpage>734</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16663291</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib63">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vu</surname>
              <given-names>CV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allen</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bowes</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dark/light modulation of ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase activity in plants from different photosynthetic categories</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <fpage>843</fpage>
          <lpage>845</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16663937</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib64">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gempko</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fravolini</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leavitt</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wall</surname>
              <given-names>GW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kimball</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pinter</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>LaMorte</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ottman</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Carbon isotope discrimination by <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> under CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment and drought</article-title>
          <source>New Phytologist</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>150</volume>
          <fpage>285</fpage>
          <lpage>293</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib65">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wingler</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quick</surname>
              <given-names>WP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bungard</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bailey</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lea</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leegood</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of photorespiration during drought stress: an analysis utilizing barley mutants with reduced activities of photorespiratory enzymes</article-title>
          <source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>361</fpage>
          <lpage>373</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib66">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wintermans</surname>
              <given-names>JFGM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Mots</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spectrophotometric characteristics of chlorophylls <italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic> and their phaeophytins in ethanol</article-title>
          <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source>
          <year>1965</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>448</fpage>
          <lpage>453</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5867546</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib67">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>C-H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McCurry</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Whitesides</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Practical enzymatic syntheses of ribulose 1,5-bisphosphate and ribose 5-phosphate</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the American Chemical Society</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>7938</fpage>
          <lpage>7939</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib68">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yaguchi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oguni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ouchiyama</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Igarashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kodama</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A non-radioisotopic anion-exchange chromatographic method to measure the CO<sub>2</sub>/O<sub>2</sub> specificity factor for ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase</article-title>
          <source>Bioscience, Biotechnology, and Biochemistry</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>942</fpage>
          <lpage>944</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib69">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yeoh</surname>
              <given-names>H-H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Badger</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watson</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Variations in <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub>(CO<sub>2</sub>) of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase among grasses</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>1110</fpage>
          <lpage>1112</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16661586</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib70">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yeoh</surname>
              <given-names>H-H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Badger</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watson</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Variations in kinetic properties of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylases among plants</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>1151</fpage>
          <lpage>1155</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16661826</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
