<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4714848</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-28714</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Novel Structural and Functional Motifs in <italic>cellulose synthase</italic> (<italic>CesA</italic>) Genes of Bread Wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>, L.)</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>cellulose synthase</italic> (<italic>CesA</italic>) Genes in Hexaploid Wheat</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kaur</surname>
            <given-names>Simerjeet</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dhugga</surname>
            <given-names>Kanwarpal S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="currentaff001">
            <sup>&#xA4;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gill</surname>
            <given-names>Kulvinder</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <given-names>Jaswinder</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff001">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Plant Science, McGill University, Sainte Anne de Bellevue, QC, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff002">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Genetic Discovery, DuPont Pioneer, 7300 NW 62nd Avenue, Johnston, IA, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff003">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Crop and Soil Science, Washington State University, Pullman, WA, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Cantu</surname>
            <given-names>Dario</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>University of California Davis, UNITED STATES</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JS KD KG. Performed the experiments: SK. Analyzed the data: SK. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JS. Wrote the paper: SK.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="currentaff001">
          <label>&#xA4;</label>
          <p>Current address: International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT), El Bat&#xE1;n, Texcoco, Estado de M&#xE9;xico</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>jaswinder.singh@mcgill.ca</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <elocation-id>e0147046</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2016 Kaur et al</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Kaur et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0147046.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cellulose is the primary determinant of mechanical strength in plant tissues. Late-season lodging is inversely related to the amount of cellulose in a unit length of the stem. Wheat is the most widely grown of all the crops globally, yet information on its <italic>CesA</italic> gene family is limited. We have identified 22 <italic>CesA</italic> genes from bread wheat, which include homoeologs from each of the three genomes, and named them as <italic>TaCesAXA</italic>, <italic>TaCesAXB</italic> or <italic>TaCesAXD</italic>, where X denotes the gene number and the last suffix stands for the respective genome. Sequence analyses of the CESA proteins from wheat and their orthologs from barley, maize, rice, and several dicot species (Arabidopsis, beet, cotton, poplar, potato, rose gum and soybean) revealed motifs unique to monocots (Poales) or dicots. Novel structural motifs CQIC and SVICEXWFA were identified, which distinguished the CESAs involved in the formation of primary and secondary cell wall (PCW and SCW) in all the species. We also identified several new motifs specific to monocots or dicots. The conserved motifs identified in this study possibly play functional roles specific to PCW or SCW formation. The new insights from this study advance our knowledge about the structure, function and evolution of the <italic>CesA</italic> family in plants in general and wheat in particular. This information will be useful in improving culm strength to reduce lodging or alter wall composition to improve biofuel production.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This study was supported by BIOFUEL NET CANADA (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biofuelnet.ca/">http://www.biofuelnet.ca/</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="10"/>
        <table-count count="3"/>
        <page-count count="18"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta id="data-availability">
          <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
          <meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability</title>
      <p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Cellulose is the primary determinant of mechanical strength in plants [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. It is also the world's most abundant renewable carbon source [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In plants, the secondary cell wall is deposited inside the primary wall and, because of its greater thickness, it generally constitutes majority of the vegetative biomass [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Primary cell wall is deposited during cell division and expansion stages, whereas the secondary cell wall begins to form as cell expansion approaches cessation [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Cellulose in plants is synthesized by multimeric protein complexes, which consist of hexameric, rosette-like structures in the plasma membrane [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Individual members of each of the hexameric components are referred to as <italic>cellulose synthase A</italic> (<italic>CesA</italic>), where the letter <italic>A</italic> stands for the catalytic subunit [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) genome contains at least 10 <italic>CesA</italic> genes, which cluster into six groups [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Mutational genetics established that six of the ten genes each had a nonredundant function in primary or secondary cell wall (PCW or SCW) formation. Three of the genes, <italic>AtCesA1</italic>, <italic>AtCesA3</italic>, and <italic>AtCesA6</italic>, are involved in PCW formation and another three, <italic>AtCesA4</italic>, <italic>AtCesA7</italic> and <italic>AtCesA8</italic> in SCW formation [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The remaining genes, <italic>AtCesA2</italic>, <italic>5</italic> and <italic>9</italic>, are partially redundant with <italic>AtCesA6</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. <italic>AtCesA10</italic> remains uncharacterized. Maize and rice possess 13 and 11 <italic>CesA</italic> genes, respectively [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Barley has nine genes, of which <italic>HvCesA1</italic>, <italic>HvCesA2</italic>, <italic>and HvCesA6</italic> make PCW, and <italic>HvCesA4</italic>, <italic>HvCesA7</italic>, and <italic>HvCesA8</italic> form SCW [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. <italic>HvCesA3</italic>, <italic>5</italic> and <italic>9</italic> are different from both the groups because of their unique tissue-specific transcript levels [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Mapping studies from Arabidopsis, maize and rice revealed that the members of the <italic>CesA</italic> gene family were spread across the genome although some genes were clustered together [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p>
      <p>Plant CESAs belong to family 2 of glycosyl transferases (GT2), which catalyze beta linkage between the glycosyl residues. CESAs are intrinsic plasma membrane proteins with their catalytic domains extending into the cytoplasm [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Each of the six subunits of a cellulose synthase complex (CSC) is believed to be composed of 6 enzymatically active CESAproteins. Each of the CESA proteins catalyzes the synthesis of an individual beta-1,4-linked chain [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Multiple chains extruded from the CSC then polymerize through hydrogen bond formation into a microfibril outside the plasma membrane.</p>
      <p>A CESA protein of higher plants possesses eight transmembrane domains (TMDs), which are believed to form a pore in the plasma membrane to allow extrusion of the newly synthesised glucan chain. Two zinc-finger domains (ZnF), which are highly homologous to the RING-finger motif, are present on the cytoplasmic face close to the amino terminus [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The central or the catalytic domain, is located between the second and third TMDs [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Three aspartyl residues (referred to as D1, D2, and D3) and a QXXRW motif in the catalytic domain of the CESA proteins are conserved across all the species studied thus far. The D1 and D2 residues are believed to coordinate UDP binding while D3 provides a catalytic base for glucan chain extension [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] The QXXRW motif acts as a binding site for the terminal disaccharide of the glucan [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p>
      <p>Motifs are the conserved groups of residues in proteins, which can be associated with structural and functional variability across species. A highly conserved motif, CXXC, which is located within the ZnF, distnguishes CESAs from the CSL (cellulose synthase-like) proteins [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Crystal structure of the cellulose synthase subunit A (BcsA) and accessory protein BcsB of <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> demonstrated the involvement of a single catalytic site in the formation of beta-1,4-glycosidic bond of the glucan chain [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Computationally predicted model of GhCESA1 revealed two class-specific regions (C-SR-I and C-SR-II), which distinguished different CESAs, and two plant-conserved regions (P-CR), which were absent in the bacterial BcsA but highly conserved in all the plant CESAs [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The P-CR might be potentially involved in the multimerization of the plant CESA polypeptides, leading to the formation of rosettes. C-SRs are probably responsible for regulating cellulose synthesis at different developmental stages.</p>
      <p>The <italic>CesA</italic> gene family has not yet been compiled from wheat, the most widely grown crop in global agriculture. Functional classification of the <italic>CesA</italic> genes in cereal crops has proved helpful in associating various genes with culm or stalk strength [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In this report, we present the <italic>CesA</italic> gene family from wheat. To understand the involvement of the different <italic>CesAs</italic> in primary or secondary wall formation in grasses or dicot plants, we have identified unique sequence motifs. Sequence comparisons of the PCW and SCW <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes were performed at both the DNA and protein levels. Phases of intron evolution were predicted and compared between the groups of the <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes involved in the formation of PCW or SCW. Unique motifs were identified among the representative monocot and dicot species. RNA-seq expression profiling of the <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes revealed unique, homoeolog-specific expression patterns in different tissues.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002">
      <title>Methods and Materials</title>
      <sec id="sec003">
        <title>Identification of <italic>CesA</italic>s in wheat and their true orthologs from different species</title>
        <p>The conserved cellulose synthase domains from barley CESA proteins was used as query to perform tBLASTn search with Chromosome Survey Sequence (CSS) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plants.ensembl.org/Triticum_aestivum/Info/Index">http://plants.ensembl.org/Triticum_aestivum/Info/Index</ext-link>) generated by the International Wheat Genome Sequencing Consortium (IWGSC) [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Availability of whole genome sequence of barley (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://webblast.ipk-gatersleben.de/barley/">http://webblast.ipk-gatersleben.de/barley/</ext-link>) made it possible to isolate full-length barley <italic>CesA</italic> sequences [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Genome databases of <italic>Triticum urartu</italic> and <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>, A and D genome progenitors of wheat, respectively, were also explored to identify full-length <italic>CesA</italic> genes for the sequences missing in hexaploid wheat. The homoeologs were first identified from Ensembl Plant database followed by amino acid sequence alignment for the presence of conserved motifs and domains. Highly variable class-specific regions (C-SRs) present in different <italic>CesAs</italic> were used to differentiate the homoeologous genes from each other (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0147046.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046.g001</object-id>
          <label>Fig 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Predicted protein features of wheat cellulose synthase genes.</title>
            <p>The numbers 1 to 8 in the purple rectangles refers to the transmembrane domains (TMDs). Black triangles localize the conserved motifs. The newly identified motifs CXXC and SXXCEXWF are highlighted in blue and previously reported motifs in black.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0147046.g001"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Orthologs of various <italic>CesA</italic> genes were identified through alignment of the wheat <italic>CesA</italic>s with those from Arabidopsis, barley, rice and maize. The ortholog of each gene was selected based on the sequence identity and query coverage, presence of all domains and motifs similar to the query sequence, Amino acid content/size and distance among various new motifs identified in this study relative to the query sequence. Arabidopsis, rice and maize <italic>CesA</italic> sequences were retrieved from Phytozome v9.1: Home (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phytozome.net/">http://www.phytozome.net/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec004">
        <title>Gene structure analysis</title>
        <p>Although in this study we identified 22 <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes, comparative studies for gene structure were performed only for the genes that were specific for PCW and SCW cellulose synthesis. Based on analysis of the orthologs, <italic>TaCesA4</italic>, <italic>7</italic> and <italic>8</italic> were characterized as one-to-one orthologs of SCW-specific, <italic>TaCesA1</italic>, <italic>2</italic>, and <italic>6</italic> as PCW-specific, and <italic>TaCesA3</italic>, <italic>5</italic> and <italic>9</italic> as partially redundant to the PCW <italic>CesAs</italic>. The homoeologous copies of each gene shared 95&#x2013;99% sequence identity in addition to all the motifs and domains. Therefore only one copy among the three homoeologs was used for comparative analysis. Intron-exon boundaries and translation start and stop sites were predicted through alignments of full-length genomic copies of <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes with their corresponding cDNA sequences. The introns and exons were drawn to scale for all the genes as indicated by the cDNA-genomic sequence comparisons. Phases of intron evolution were predicted using Plant Intron Exon Comparison and Evolution database (PIECE) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/piece/">http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/piece/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec005">
        <title>Protein structure and motif identification</title>
        <p>Amino acid sequence similarity of TaCESA protein sequences was determined by multiple sequence alignment (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/tools/clustalw/">http://www.genome.jp/tools/clustalw/</ext-link>). Color Align Conservation tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.org/sms2/color_align_cons.html">http://www.bioinformatics.org/sms2/color_align_cons.html</ext-link>) was used to differentiate the conserved patterns of aligned sequences. Conserved domains and motifs were identified by manual search in the aligned sequences.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec006">
        <title>Phylogenetic analysis</title>
        <p>22 newly identified wheat CESA proteins were used to deduce their phylogenetic relationships. Protein sequences for <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (AtCESA), <italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> (BvCESA), <italic>Eucalyptus grandis</italic> (EgCESA), <italic>Glycine max</italic> (GmCESA), <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> (GhCESA), <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> (HvCESA), <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> (OsCESA), <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic> (PtCESA), <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> (StCESA), <italic>Zea mays</italic> (ZmCESA) were retrieved from NCBI (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. An unrooted phylogenetic tree was constructed with bootstrap analysis over 1000 replicates, using the Neighbor-Joining method using the MEGA6 program [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Evolutionary distances were computed using Poisson correction method [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. All positions containing gaps and missing data were eliminated.</p>
        <p>GenBank accession numbers for CESA amino acid sequences used to generate the phylogenetic tree are: AtCESA1, AF027172; AtCESA2, AF027173; AtCESA3, AF027174; AtCESA4, AB006703; AtCESA5, AB016893; AtCESA6, AF062485; AtCESA7, AF088917; AtCESA8, AL035526; AtCESA9, AC007019; AtCESA10, At2G25540; ZmCESA1, AF200525; ZmCESA2, AF200526; ZmCESA3, NP_001292792.1; ZmCESA4, AF200528; ZmCESA5, AF200529; ZmCESA6, AF200530; ZmCESA7, AF200531; ZmCESA8, AF200532; ZmCESA9, AF200533; ZmCESA10, AY372244; ZmCESA11, AY372245; ZmCESA12, AY372246; ZmCESA13, KJ874174; OsCESA1, AF030052; OsCESA2, D48636, OsCESA3, BAD30574; OsCESA4, AK100475; OsCESA5, BAD30574; OsCESA6, XM_477282; OsCESA7, XM_477282; OsCESA8, XM_477093; OsCESA9, XM_477093; OsCESA10, LOC_O<italic>-4</italic>2g29300; OsCESA11, LOC_OS06g39970; HvCESA1, AY483150; HvCESA2, AY483152; HvCESA3, AY483151; HvCESA4, AY483154; HvCESA5/7, AY483153; HvCESA6, AY483155; HvCESA8, AY483156; HvCESA9, AK367031; PtCESA6, XP_002319002; EgCESA5, XP_010063196; StCESA3, XP_006354075; GmCESA2, XP_003531396; GhCESA5, AFB18634 and BvCESA2, XP_010678670.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec007">
        <title>RNA-seq expression profiling of <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes</title>
        <p>Gene expression profiling for 21 of the wheat <italic>CesA</italic> genes was performed using publicly available RNA-seq data from two different databases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wheat-urgi.versailles.inra.fr/Seq-Repository/RNA-Seq">http://wheat-urgi.versailles.inra.fr/Seq-Repository/RNA-Seq</ext-link>) at McGill University and Genome Quebec Innovation Center. First dataset was a non-oriented library with five wheat organs analysed in duplicates at three development stages for each of the organs. The five organs taken into consideration with respect to developmental stages were root (at seedling, three leaves, and meiosis stages), leaf (seedling, three tillers, and 2 days after anthesis), stem (spike at 1 cm, 2 nodes, and anthesis), spike (2 nodes, meiosis, and anthesis) and grain (2, 14, and 30 days after anthesis). The second dataset was the oriented library with five wheat organs (root, leaf, stem, spike, and grain) with five conditions pooled for 4 lines per organ [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</p>
        <p>The abundance of transcripts from RNA-Seq data was reported using the estimated counts quantified by a programme Kallisto (v0.42.1) [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Counts-per-million reads were obtained using Bioconductor's edgeR [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Ward&#x2019;s linkage method was applied to the matrix of Pearson's correlation distances for cluster analysis. Heat map of the candidate transcripts was reported by log2 counts per million (CPM) standard deviation [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="sec008">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="sec009">
        <title>Identification and mapping of <italic>CesA</italic> gene family in wheat</title>
        <p>We queried the Chromosome Survey Sequence (CSS) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plants.ensembl.org/Triticum_aestivum/Info/Index">http://plants.ensembl.org/Triticum_ aestivum/Info/Index</ext-link>) generated by the International Wheat Genome Sequencing Consortium to identify the orthologs of various <italic>CesA</italic> genes from bread wheat corresponding to the barley <italic>CesA</italic> sequences [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Twenty-two <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes were isolated, six of which were partial (<xref rid="pone.0147046.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Text</xref>). The identified genes were named following the nomenclature of barley, which shares synteny with wheat. To simplify the nomenclature, we attached a suffix corresponding to the specific wheat genome identifier (A, B, or D) at the end of the gene number. For example, <italic>CesA1</italic> in genomes A, B, and D is named as <italic>TaCesA1A</italic>, <italic>TaCesA1B</italic>, and <italic>TaCesA1D</italic>, respectively. As expected, we found three copies for majority of the nine <italic>CesA</italic> orthologs corresponding to the barley genes. For <italic>CesA6</italic>, <italic>7</italic>, and <italic>8</italic> we were able to find only two <italic>CesA</italic> homoeologs. Only one copy was identified for <italic>TaCesA9</italic>. The missing homoeolog of <italic>CesA6</italic> belonged to the D genome but we obtained it from the D genome progenitor <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>. The <italic>TaCesA7</italic> homoeolog, which was absent in the A genome, was recovered from the A genome progenitor <italic>Triticum urartu</italic>. We were unable to find the A genome copy of <italic>TaCesA8</italic> from bread wheat as well as the A genome donor, <italic>Triticum urartu</italic>. The three homoeologous copies of each of the <italic>CesA</italic> genes shared 95&#x2013;99% sequence identity. Different <italic>CesA</italic> genes within a species possessed two highly variable class-specific regions (C-SR-I and C-SR-II) that differentiated them from each other. The wheat orthologs of the CESA proteins of other species exhibited a similarity of 70&#x2013;80% at the amino acid level with Arabidopsis and 90&#x2013;95% with rice and barley. The <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes ranged from 4044 to 5251 bp in length and contained 9&#x2013;13 introns. The ensembl IDs of all the newly identified wheat <italic>CesA</italic> genes are given in <xref rid="pone.0147046.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0147046.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>CesA</italic> genes and their chromosomal locations in hexaploid wheat.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0147046.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0147046.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA</italic> gene</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Map position (MB)</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ensembl ID</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA1A</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_2AS_665AF9500.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA1B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.50</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_2BS_064B02A89.3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA1D</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.70</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_2DS_C80293002.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA2A</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176.7</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_4AL_941C0E3EF.2</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA2B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262.70</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_5BL_3A1A752B7.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA2D</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151.78</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_5DL_3B0E69498.2</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA3A</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.80</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_5AL_E176291CC.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA3B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247.07</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_5BL_CFCBFDA99.2</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA3D</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.92</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_5DL_BBFD06D43.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA4A</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.16</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_1AL_F420A1BBE.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA4B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.70</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_1BL_B34FCB150.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA4D</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_1DL_129574E44.1/ EMT11949</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA5A</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.31</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_1AS_10C467127.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA5B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.00</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_1BS_64E9CC6E0.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA5D</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_1DS_65C1FDCD8.2</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA6A</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.23</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_6AS_CF6D8CD28.2</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA6B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.84</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_6BS_8DA635027.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA7B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">514.04</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRAES3BF028900030CFD_t1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA7D</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.80</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_3DL_B2FD2FBFA</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA8B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163.48</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_5BL_51C858A97.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA8D</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.35</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_5DL_E82D6D246.2</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA9B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traes_2BS_9B34A7A43.2</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t001fn001">
              <p>NA- Precise location of these genes on the respective chromosomes is not known because of the incomplete assembly of the wheat genome.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>The newly identified wheat <italic>CesA</italic> genes were mapped to respective chromosomes based on the physical mapping information available in the wheat IWGSC survey sequence annotation database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wheatgenome.org/">http://www.wheatgenome.org/</ext-link>). As expected the chromosomal locations of different <italic>CesA</italic> genes followed the trend reported earlier in the syntenic species barley [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. <italic>TaCesA4A</italic>, <italic>B</italic>, and <italic>D</italic> mapped in respective genomes to chromosome 1; <italic>TaCesA7B</italic> and <italic>D</italic> to chromosome 3; and <italic>TaCesA8B</italic> and <italic>D</italic> to chromosome 5. Similarly, the homoeologs of <italic>TaCesA1</italic>, <italic>2</italic>, <italic>3</italic>, <italic>5</italic>, and <italic>6</italic> mapped to chromosomes 2, 5, 5, 1 and 6 of the respective genomes. However, <italic>TaCesa9B</italic> mapped to chromosome 2B, unlike its ortholog from barley, which is located on chromosome 6. The approximate location of <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes and their homoeologs is presented in <xref rid="pone.0147046.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec010">
        <title>DNA sequence comparison of primary and secondary cell wall <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes</title>
        <p>On average, a PCW forming gene was longer than the one involved in SCW formation. The longest gene, <italic>TaCesA6</italic>, was 5251 base pairs (bp) and the shortest, <italic>TaCesA4</italic>, was 3923 bp in length. The size variations among different <italic>CesA</italic> genes arose mainly from the number and length of introns (<xref rid="pone.0147046.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). <italic>TaCesA1</italic>, <italic>2</italic>, and <italic>6</italic> had 13 introns each, whereas <italic>TaCesA4</italic>, 7 and <italic>8</italic> had 7, 12, and 9 introns, respectively (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0147046.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046.g002</object-id>
          <label>Fig 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Structural features of the <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes.</title>
            <p>Drawn to scale, exons are represented by black boxes and introns by grey lines. Intron lengths are presented on top of each intron. PCW and SCW <italic>CesA</italic> genes are shown in blue and red colors, respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0147046.g002"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0147046.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Structures of the <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes for PCW and SCW synthesis.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0147046.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0147046.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA</italic> gene</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCW or SCW</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene length (nt)</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introns (#)</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ORF length (AA)</th>
                  <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Map to Chromosome</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA1</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCW</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5175</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1080</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA2</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCW</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5005</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1091</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA3</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCW</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5127</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1105</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA4</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCW</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3923</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1044</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA5</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCW</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,085</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1078</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA6</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCW</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5251</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1075</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA7</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCW</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5072</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">991</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA8</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCW</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4044</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1055</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic>TaCesA9</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCW</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2184</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">537</td>
                  <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>The introns in PCW <italic>TaCesA1</italic>, <italic>2</italic>, and <italic>6</italic> accounted for 1732&#x2013;2026 bp of the genes, approximately double that of the 791 and 879 bp for the SCW <italic>TaCesA4</italic> and <italic>8</italic> genes. One of the SCW genes, <italic>TaCesA7</italic>, possessed a large total intronic region of 2095 bp, which was similar to the PCW <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes. Exonic regions in all the PCW forming genes (~3.2 kb) were similar in length to those of the SCW forming genes (2.9&#x2013;3.2kb). Exon-intron boundaries were random in all the genes studied, which was in contrast to the conserved boundaries reported in other species [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The PCW and SCW genes, across groups, were 45&#x2013;52% similar. Sequence similarity within the PCW and SCW groups was 54&#x2013;56% and 46&#x2013;63% respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec011">
        <title>Evolution of introns in <italic>TaCesA</italic> gene family</title>
        <p>Three different phases of intron evolution were predicted. Phase 0, 1, or 2 referred to the insertion of an intron between two consecutive codons, between the first and the second base or second and the third base of a codon, respectively [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In PCW <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes, all of the introns had identical phase distributions: introns 1, 3, 7, 8, 9, 10, 12, and 13 occurred in 0 phase, introns 2, 4, and 11 were in phase 1, and introns 5 and 6 occurred in phase 2. In contract, SCW <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes exhibited variable patterns of intron phase distribution. Introns 2, 5, 6, and 7 in <italic>CesA4</italic> had 0 phase distribution, introns 1 and 3 had 1, and intron 4 had a phase distribution of 2. <italic>TaCesA7</italic> also had introns with all three types of phase distribution; introns 2, 6, 7, 8, 9, 11, 12 were in phase 0, introns 1, 3, and 10 in phase 1, and introns 4 and 5 in phase 2. <italic>CesA8</italic> similarly had introns 1, 4, 5, 6, 8, and 9 in phase 0, introns 2 and 7 in phase 1, and intron 3 in phase 2 (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). The largest proportion of introns (57&#x2013;66%) in all the studied genes was found to be in phase 0, followed by phase 1 (22&#x2013;28%) and phase 2 (11&#x2013;16%).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0147046.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046.g003</object-id>
          <label>Fig 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Amino acid sequence alignment of wheat CESA proteins.</title>
            <p>Drawn to scale with solid lines representing conserved amino acid sequences and the gaps representing the mismatches and deletions. Corresponding phases of intron evolution (0, 1, 2) for the CESA proteins are shown on the top of the solid lines. Primary and secondary cell wall CESAs are shown in blue and red color, respectively.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0147046.g003"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec012">
        <title>Amino acid variability of predicted TaCESA proteins</title>
        <p>The predicted size of PCW and SCW TaCESAs ranged between 1075&#x2013;1091 and 991&#x2013;1055 amino acids (AA), respectively. To identify group-specific changes in primary and secondary cell wall CESA proteins, AA sequences from all TaCESAs were aligned. All the complete CESA proteins possessed the already known, specific CESA domains, such as a ZnF (CX2-CX14-ACX2-CX4-CX2-CX7-GX3-CX2-C) near the N-terminus of the derived amino acid sequence (<xref rid="pone.0147046.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Text</xref>). All the TaCESAs possessed eight TMDs; two towards the N-terminus and six near the C-terminus, as well as the conserved D, DXD, D, QXXRW signatures (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>).</p>
        <p>Major differences among TaCESAs resulted from the deletion of up to 45 AAs in hypervariable regions. The N-terminii of the PCW TaCESAs possessed more highly conserved motifs and fewer deletions in comparison to the SCW TaCESAs. ZnF consisted of 46 AAs in the predicted TaCESAs, with the exception of an 8 AAs deletion in TaCESA7 and its homoeologs, resulting in the following domain: CX2-CX6-ACX2-CX4-CX2-CX7-GX3-CX2-C as compared to the known domain (CX2-CX12-FXACX2-CX2PXCX2-CXEX5-GX3-CX2C), where X is any amino acid [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Four of the TaCESAs out of 22 were missing the ZnF as did TaCESA9 because they were incomplete on the N-terminal end.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec013">
        <title>New motifs distinguishing PCW CESAs from SCW CESAs</title>
        <p>A new motif distinguishing the PCW CESAs from the SCW CESAs was found within the ZnF. The motif, CQIC, was identified within the small motif, CXXC, reported earlier for differentiating CESAs from the CSL genes [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This motif was present in all the PCW TaCESAs. Although SCW TaCESAs also possessed a "CXXC" motif, the two middle amino acids in these proteins were variable. In the SCW TaCESA4, the polar amino acid glutamine was replaced by the negatively charged amino acid, glutamate; in TaCESA7, both the amino acids were replaced by the marginally hydrophobic amino acid alanine; and in TaCESA8, glutamine was replaced by a highly basic (positively charged) amino acid, arginine, and isoleucine was replaced by a relatively conservative substitution of alanine (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). Another conserved motif, SVICEXWFA, was located within the second transmembrane domain in all the PCW CESAs. In the SCW-specific CESAs, TaCESA4, 7, and 8 this motif was variable but all the amino acid replacements were conservative. For example, isoleucine, a hydrophobic amino acid next to glutamate was replaced by an iso-amino acid, leucine, in CESA4; alanine was replaced by glycine, both somewhat hydrophobic, in CESA7; and valine and isoleucine, both hydrophobic amino acids, switched places in CESA8.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0147046.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046.g004</object-id>
          <label>Fig 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Motifs differentiating PCW and SCW CESA orthologs from different species.</title>
            <p>Amino acid changes in the motifs are shown in blue.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0147046.g004"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec014">
        <title>Conservation of motifs in monocots and dicots</title>
        <p>The two motifs, CQIC and SVICEXWFA, distinguished the PCW from the SCW CESAs (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). That these motifs were conserved was confirmed by analysing the CESA proteins in the PCW and SCW groups from dicot (Arabidopsis) and monocot (barley, maize, rice, and wheat) species. Alignment results demonstrated that the CQIC and SVICEXWFA motifs were completely conserved only in the PCW-specific CESAs in all the plant species studied. The completely conserved amino acid residues in each motif across all the CESA proteins were CXXC and SXXCEXWF (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec015">
        <title>Unique motifs conserved among the CESA orthologs from different species</title>
        <p>Motif analysis was performed by aligning CESA proteins from Arabidopsis, barley, maize, rice and wheat. Arabidopsis CESA4 and its orthologs from wheat, barley, maize, and rice exhibited 73&#x2013;74% sequence similarity. In the case of SCW, nine motifs ranging from 2&#x2013;15 amino acid residues in length provided ortholog-specific identity to the SCW CESAs from different species (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>). These motifs were highly conserved among the orthologs from the five species analysed in this study. Only one gene from each species, with the exception of maize which had two closely related copies for one of the three SCW genes (CESA12 and 13), shared these motifs including a dicot, Arabidopsis. This suggests that the genes for SCW had already duplicated before the separation of monocots and dicots. The number of amino acid residues among most of these motifs was also conserved among different species (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>). CESA7 and 8 from wheat showed 71&#x2013;75% and 77&#x2013;79% sequence similarity with the corresponding orthologs from different species, respectively. Although the motifs were unique for CESA4, 7 and 8, they were highly conserved among the orthologs form different species (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0147046.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046.g005</object-id>
          <label>Fig 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Conserved motifs differentiating the orthologs of SCW CESAs from <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> (TaCESA), <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (AtCESA), <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> (HvCESA), <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> (OsCESA), and <italic>Zea mays</italic> (ZmCESA).</title>
            <p>Amino acid changes in the motifs are shown in blue.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0147046.g005"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Two PCW CESAs, AtCESA1, 3 and their orthologs from other species differed from AtCESA6 and its orthologs in structural features. AtCESA1 and 3 were highly similar (77&#x2013;79%) to the corresponding orthologs from barley, maize, rice and wheat. Four motifs in TaCESA6 and three in TaCESA1 orthologs differentiated them from each other and all other CESAs (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0147046.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046.g006</object-id>
          <label>Fig 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Conserved motifs differentiating the orthologs of PCW CESAs from <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> (TaCESA), <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (AtCESA), <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> (HvCESA), <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> (OsCESA), and <italic>Zea mays</italic> (ZmCESA).</title>
            <p>Amino acid changes in the motifs are shown in blue.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0147046.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec016">
        <title>Motifs differentiating CESAs from monocots and dicots</title>
        <p>Arabidopsis CESA6 and its orthologs from other species in this study exhibited 68&#x2013;70% sequence similarity but lacked any specific patterns that could differentiate them from the other CESAs. However, this group possessed motifs that were only conserved in the orthologs from monocots (grasses) but not in Arabidopsis. To confirm the specificity of these motifs for grasses, we retrieved the sequences of TaCESA2 orthologs from seven dicot species: <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (AtCESA6), <italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> (BvCESA2), <italic>Eucalyptus grandis</italic> (EgCESA5), <italic>Glycine max</italic> (GmCESA2), <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> (GhCESA5), <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic> (PtCESA6) and <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> (StCESA3). The CESA2 and its orthologs from grasses were compared with its orthologs from dicot species. For this particular gene nine motifs were highly conserved in the orthologs from grasses (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref>). But in dicots, these motifs were replaced by variable amino acid residues.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0147046.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046.g007</object-id>
          <label>Fig 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Motifs of CESA orthologs from <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> (TaCESA), <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (AtCESA), <italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> (BvCESA), <italic>Eucalyptus grandis</italic> (EgCESA), <italic>Glycine max</italic> (GmCESA), <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> (GhCESA), <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> (HvCESA), <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> (OsCESA), <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic> (PtCESA), <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> (StCESA) and <italic>Zea mays</italic> (ZmCESA).</title>
            <p>Conserved and non-conserved amino acids residues are highlighted in red and green respectively. Amino acid changes in the motifs are highlighted in blue.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0147046.g007"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec017">
        <title>Phylogenetic analysis</title>
        <p>The evolutionary history of the CESAs was inferred from the analysis involving 70 CESA protein sequences from different species. An unrooted phylogenetic tree revealed that the orthologs from Arabidopsis, barley, beet, cotton, maize, poplar, potato, rice, rose gum, soybean and wheat were grouped together. Branch lengths, which are indicative of the evolutionary distances were used to interpret the phylogenetic tree (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>). The paralogs from various species were grouped in different clades from those of the orthologs. This suggests, again, that divergence of the <italic>CesA</italic> genes had occurred prior to the separation of monocots and dicots.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0147046.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046.g008</object-id>
          <label>Fig 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Unrooted phylogenetic tree of the CESAs from <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> (TaCESA), <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (AtCESA), <italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> (BvCESA), <italic>Eucalyptus grandis</italic> (EgCESA), <italic>Glycine max</italic> (GmCESA), <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> (GhCESA), <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> (HvCESA), <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> (OsCESA), <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic> (PtCESA), <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> (StCESA) and <italic>Zea mays</italic> (ZmCESA).</title>
            <p>The bar provides a scale for the branch length in the horizonal dimension. The line segment with the number '0.1' means that an equal length of the branch between the CESA proteins represents a change of 0.1 AA. Color codes for different species: Red&#x2014;TaCESA, blue&#x2013;AtCESA, purple&#x2014;HvCESA, yellow&#x2014;ZmCESA, green&#x2014;OsCESA, and grey&#x2013;BvCESA, EgCESA, GmCESA, GhCESA, PtCESA, StCESA.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0147046.g008"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec018">
        <title>RNA-seq analysis of <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes</title>
        <p>Gene expression of 21 of the 22 <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes was studied in five organs at three development stages. We left out the <italic>TaCesA9</italic> gene because it was represented by a highly truncated cDNA. A heat map displaying transcript abundance of the <italic>CesA</italic> genes from different wheat tissues is shown in <xref rid="pone.0147046.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0147046.g009" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046.g009</object-id>
          <label>Fig 9</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Heat map of 21 <italic>TaCesA</italic> transcripts expressed as deviation of log2 counts per million (CPM) standard deviation in hexaploid wheat.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0147046.g009"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Transcript abundance data revealed the presence of two distinct groups. Group I consisted of <italic>TaCesA4A</italic>, <italic>B</italic>, <italic>D</italic>, <italic>TaCesA7B</italic>, <italic>D</italic> and <italic>TaCesA8B</italic>, <italic>D</italic> genes, all involved in SCW synthesis. These genes were highly expressed in the mature tissues, for example, stem collected soon after anthesis, and at very low levels in the PCW formation (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>). For example, <italic>TaCesA7B</italic>, <italic>D</italic> and <italic>TaCesA8B</italic>, <italic>D</italic> genes were expressed at extremely low levels in the spike and grain tissues (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>).</p>
        <p>Group II comprised the PCW <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes: <italic>TaCesA1</italic>, <italic>2</italic>, <italic>3</italic>, <italic>5</italic> and <italic>6</italic> along with their homoeologs from A, B and D genomes. These genes were expressed at lower levels in the mature tissues and at relatively high levels in the PCW forming cells (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>). For example, all three homoeologous copies of the <italic>TaCesA3</italic> gene were expressed in the grain and the leaf tissues. These genes were expressed moderately in the developing grain, which agrees with grain having a relatively low cell wall fraction. The expression of the <italic>TaCesA5A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> genes was highest in the grain tissues from 14 and 30 DAAs, whereas the <italic>TaCesA5D</italic> was moderately expressed in these tissues. The expression of <italic>TaCesA5D</italic> homoeolog was dramatically lower in the leaf tissues at 2 days after anthesis (DAA), whereas <italic>TaCesA1D</italic> was expressed at higher level. The transcript abundance of <italic>TaCesA1A</italic> was highest in the grain tissues at 2DAAs whereas <italic>TaCesA6B</italic> homoeolog was moderately expressed. The expression level of <italic>TaCesA1B</italic> was moderate in the root and grain tissues.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec019">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Cellulose consists of paracrystalline microfibrils of multiple, unbranched beta-1,4-glucan chains, which are synthesized by the individual CESA polypeptides in the plasma membrane-localized rosette. <italic>CesA</italic> is a multigene family consisting of more than eight members in higher plants [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Structure and function of the <italic>CesA</italic> genes in wheat remains undocumented. Most studies about structural and functional characterization of <italic>CesAs</italic> have been performed in Arabidopsis [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], maize [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and rice [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Bread wheat, an allohexaploid, has a complex genome, ~17 Gb in size, ~80&#x2013;90% of which consists of repetitive DNA [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The availability of large-scale genomic sequence information and conserved synteny between barley and wheat is valuable in exploring wheat gene function and structure [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. In barley, the <italic>CesA</italic> gene family consists of nine genes (<italic>HvCesA1</italic> to <italic>HvCesA9</italic>. Three genes, <italic>HvCesA1</italic>, <italic>HvCesA2</italic>, and <italic>HvCesA6</italic>, are expressed during primary wall formation, and another three, <italic>HvCesA4</italic>, <italic>HvCesA7</italic>, and <italic>HvCesA8</italic>, during secondary wall formation [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In this report, we document 22 <italic>CesA</italic> genes from wheat, which we identified using a comparative genomics approach using barley sequences as anchors. As expected, most of the <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes each have three paralogs in the homoeologous genomes A, B and D. Four of the 22 genes deviated from this pattern: only one paralog was identified for <italic>TaCesA9</italic>, and two each for <italic>TaCesA6</italic>, <italic>7</italic>, and <italic>8</italic>. One of the genes, <italic>TaCesA2</italic>, had two paralogous copies on chromosomes 5B and 5D but the third on chromosome 4A, which was most likely because of a translocation between chromosomes 5A and 4A (<xref rid="pone.0147046.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].</p>
      <p>All the CESAs possess domains known to be highly conserved among all the plant species studied thus far [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Sequences in the non-conserved domains, however, are useful for the identification of the orthologs of individual <italic>CesA</italic> genes (<xref rid="pone.0147046.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). In the case of gene families, it is often difficult to determine true orthology among different species solely based on sequence similarity. Many previous studies reported <italic>CesA</italic> orthologs based on phylogenetic analyses [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. We supplemented the phylogenetic analysis as a tool for the identification of the <italic>CesA</italic> orthologs by searching for the conserved motifs in addition to the ones already known [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone.0147046.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046.t003</object-id>
        <label>Table 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title><italic>TaCesA</italic> genes and their orthologs from Arabidopsis, barley, maize, and rice involved in the formation of primary cell wall (PCW) or secondary cell wall (SCW).</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone.0147046.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0147046.t003"/>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Function</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barley</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maize</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rice</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arabidopsis</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA5</italic>, <italic>6</italic> and <italic>9</italic></td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA6</italic> and <italic>9</italic></td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA1</italic>, <italic>2</italic> and <italic>3</italic></td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA1</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA1</italic>and <italic>10</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA1</italic>and <italic>3</italic></td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA1</italic>and <italic>3</italic></td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA4</italic>, <italic>5</italic>, and <italic>9</italic></td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA2</italic>, <italic>8</italic>,<italic>10</italic> and <italic>11</italic></td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA3</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA2</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA2</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA6</italic>, <italic>7</italic>, and <italic>8</italic></td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA3</italic>, <italic>5</italic>, and <italic>6</italic></td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA2</italic>, <italic>5</italic>, <italic>6</italic>, and <italic>9</italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCW</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA4</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA4</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA10</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA7</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA4</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA8</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA8</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA12</italic> and <italic>13</italic></td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA9</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA7</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA7</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CesA5</italic> and <italic>7</italic></td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA11</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA4</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CesA8</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Knowledge about the conserved structural motifs that can distinguish <italic>CesA</italic> genes involved in PCW and SCW formation as well as <italic>CesAs</italic> between monocots and dicots is limited. Distinct patterns of intron placement, removal, and the phases of insertion in <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes suggested that the phases of intron insertion remained conserved during the evolution of these genes [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Deviation of phase distribution from the expected 33% suggested a bias in intron insertions towards the 0 phase, that is, between the codons rather than within the codons [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p>
      <p>The motif CQIC in ZnF distinguishes the PCW and SCW CESAs from both the monocots and dicots. Distinct CSCs for the synthesis of primary and secondary cell walls have been reported [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The high level of conservation of the CQIC motif suggests that it is possibly related to cellulose synthesis. This concurs with the observation in other major gene families, where domains and motifs were conserved during the evolution [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</p>
      <p>A similar trend of intron phase distribution and motif conservation was observed when we compared CESA1 of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> with its orthologs from angiosperms (<italic>Arabidopsis lyrata</italic>, <italic>Aquilegia coerulea</italic>, <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>, <italic>Carica papaya</italic>, <italic>Citrus clementina</italic>, <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic>, <italic>Cucumis sativus</italic>, <italic>Eucalyptus grandis</italic>, <italic>Glycine max</italic>, <italic>Manihot esculenta</italic>, <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic>, <italic>Mimulus guttatus</italic>, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>, <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic>, <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic>, <italic>Prunus persica</italic>, <italic>Ricinus communis</italic>, <italic>Setaria italica</italic>, <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic>, <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>, <italic>Zea mays</italic>), Chlorophytes (<italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic>, <italic>Volvox carteri)</italic>, and pteridophyte (<italic>Selaginella moellendorffii</italic>).</p>
      <p>We also identified new, highly conserved motifs among the CESA orthologs of five species (Arabidopsis, barley, maize, rice and wheat). Despite the variable protein sequence of each member of the CESA family among the orthologs from various species, the organization of the motifs remained conserved.</p>
      <p>RNA-seq expression profiling revealed that the three SCW genes (<italic>TaCesA4</italic>, <italic>7</italic>, <italic>8</italic>) and their homoeologs were co-expressed in the mature stem tissues (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>). This observation provided support for these genes being functionally orthologous to the secondary wall-forming genes from other species, for example, Arabidopsis [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], barley [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], maize [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and rice [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Five genes (<italic>TaCesA1</italic>, <italic>2</italic>, <italic>3</italic>, <italic>5</italic>, <italic>6</italic>) and their homoeologs from the A, B and D genomes of wheat constituted a second group involved in PCW synthesis.</p>
      <p>Most of the <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes were differential expressed among three different genomes of bread wheat, which is a common phenomenon in hexaploid wheat [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. This differential expression pattern is attributable to the genetic divergence of paralogous genes during the evolution [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes are distributed across the wheat genome (<xref rid="pone.0147046.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig 10</xref>). Similar distribution patterns were observed in Arabidopsis, barley and maize [<xref rid="pone.0147046.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147046.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p>
      <fig id="pone.0147046.g010" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147046.g010</object-id>
        <label>Fig 10</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Map positions of <italic>TaCesA</italic> genes in the wheat genome.</title>
          <p>The exact locations are shown in <xref rid="pone.0147046.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pone.0147046.g010"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Our study compiles a list of the <italic>CesA</italic> genes in bread wheat, classified them into PCW and SCW formation, and maps them to the chromosomes. This information will be useful in breeding wheat for culm strength and biofuel-related traits.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec020">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>We have identified 22 <italic>CesA</italic> genes from bread wheat and compared them with their orthologs from Arabidopsis, barley, maize, and rice. New structural motifs were identified, which allowed differentiation of the CESA proteins for their roles in primary or secondary wall (PCW or SCW) formation in higher plants. Further characterization of the motifs would be needed, however, to establish their respective biological roles. Several new motifs identified in this study would be useful as signatures for the identification of orthologs of the <italic>CesA</italic> genes from various species. The compilation of the <italic>CesA</italic> gene family in bread wheat along with the expression patterns and genomic map positions of individual members will be helpful in improving culm strength for reduced lodging as well as improving the straw for biofuels.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec021">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0147046.s001">
        <label>S1 Text</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Amino acid sequences of wheat <italic>CesA</italic> genes.</title>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0147046.s001.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0147046.s002">
        <label>S2 Text</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Amino acid alignments of wheat, barley, rice and maize <italic>CesA</italic> genes.</title>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0147046.s002.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref001">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dhugga</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Appenzeller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meeley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bourett</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Brittle stalk 2 encodes a putative glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchored protein that affects mechanical strength of maize tissues by altering the composition and structure of secondary cell walls</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>224</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1174</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>84</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00425-006-0299-8">10.1007/s00425-006-0299-8</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 16752131?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16752131</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref002">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Appenzeller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doblin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barreiro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kollipara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Cellulose synthesis in maize: isolation and expression analysis of the cellulose synthase (CesA) gene family</article-title>. <source>Cellulose</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3&#x2013;4</issue>):<fpage>287</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref003">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dhugga</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Building the wall: genes and enzyme complexes for polysaccharide synthases</article-title>. <source>Current opinion in plant biology</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>488</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11641063?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11641063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref004">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dhugga</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Maize biomass yield and composition for biofuels</article-title>. <source>Crop Science</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2211</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref005">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Single-nucleotide polymorphisms in PtoCesA7 and their association with growth and wood properties in Populus tomentosa</article-title>. <source>Molecular Genetics and Genomics</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>289</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>439</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00438-014-0824-6">10.1007/s00438-014-0824-6</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid WOS:000336728600016?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24549852</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref006">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mansoori</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vernhettes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Complexes with mixed primary and secondary cellulose synthases are functional in Arabidopsis plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>160</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>726</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.112.199208">10.1104/pp.112.199208</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3461551.<?supplied-pmid 22926318?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22926318</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref007">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McFarlane</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doring</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>The cell biology of cellulose synthesis</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>94</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev-arplant-050213-040240">10.1146/annurev-arplant-050213-040240</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 24579997?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24579997</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref008">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hamann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Youngs</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Misson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nussaume</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Global expression analysis of CESA and CSL genes in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Cellulose</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3&#x2013;4</issue>):<fpage>279</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref009">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Higher plant cellulose synthases</article-title>. <source>Genome biology</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):REVIEWS3001-REVIEWS. .<?supplied-pmid MEDLINE:11178255?></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref010">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>. <article-title>The cellulose synthase superfamily</article-title>. <source>Plant physiology</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>124</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>495</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11027699?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11027699</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref011">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Endler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cellulose synthases and synthesis in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>199</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>211</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/mp/ssq079">10.1093/mp/ssq079</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 21307367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21307367</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref012">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hill JL, Hammudi MB, Tien M. The Arabidopsis Cellulose Synthase Complex: A Proposed Hexamer of CESA Trimers in an Equimolar Stoichiometry. The Plant Cell Online. 2014:tpc. 114.131193.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref013">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paredez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palsdottir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doblin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poindexter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Genetic evidence for three unique components in primary cell-wall cellulose synthase complexes in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>39</issue>):<fpage>15566</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0706592104">10.1073/pnas.0706592104</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2000526.<?supplied-pmid 17878302?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17878302</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref014">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Desprez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Juraniec</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crowell</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jouy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pochylova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parcy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Organization of cellulose synthase complexes involved in primary cell wall synthesis in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>39</issue>):<fpage>15572</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0706569104">10.1073/pnas.0706569104</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2000492.<?supplied-pmid 17878303?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17878303</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref015">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheetamun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dhugga</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rafalski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tingey</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shirley</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Spatial gradients in cell wall composition and transcriptional profiles along elongating maize internodes</article-title>. <source>BMC plant biology</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24423166</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref016">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Expression profiling and integrative analysis of the CESA/CSL superfamily in rice</article-title>. <source>BMC plant biology</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>282</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21167079</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref017">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sznajder</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rafalski</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dhugga</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mather</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A Genome-Wide Association Study for Culm Cellulose Content in Barley Reveals Candidate Genes Co-Expressed with Members of the CELLULOSE SYNTHASE A Gene Family</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>. <year>2015</year>;<fpage>10</fpage>(7).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref018">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shirley</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>King</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fincher</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>. <article-title>The CesA gene family of barley. Quantitative analysis of transcripts reveals two groups of co-expressed genes</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>224</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>36</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.103.032904">10.1104/pp.103.032904</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC316302.<?supplied-pmid 14701917?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14701917</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref019">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Helentjaris</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dhugga</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xoconostle-Cazares</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delmer</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>. <article-title>A comparative analysis of the plant cellulose synthase (CesA) gene family</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1313</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.123.4.1313">10.1104/pp.123.4.1313</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid WOS:000088792200018?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10938350</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref020">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Rayon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olek</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carpita</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Towards Redesigning Cellulose Biosynthesis for Improved Bioenergy Feedstocks</chapter-title><source>Plants and BioEnergy</source>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year> p. <fpage>183</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref021">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strumillo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Crystallographic snapshot of cellulose synthesis and membrane translocation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>493</volume>(<issue>7431</issue>):<fpage>181</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature11744">10.1038/nature11744</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23222542?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23222542</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref022">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slabaugh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haigler</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yingling</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cellulose synthases: new insights from crystallography and modeling</article-title>. <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>99</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>106</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tplants.2013.09.009">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tplants.2013.09.009</ext-link>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tplants.2013.09.009">10.1016/j.tplants.2013.09.009</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 24139443?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24139443</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref023">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kurek</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawagoe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacob-Wilk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doblin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delmer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dimerization of cotton fiber cellulose synthase catalytic subunits occurs via oxidation of the zinc-binding domains</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>11109</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref024">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bashline</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cellulose synthesis and its regulation</article-title>. <source>Arabidopsis Book</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0169</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1199/tab.0169">10.1199/tab.0169</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3894906.<?supplied-pmid 24465174?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24465174</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref025">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RM</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Fevre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geremia</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Multidomain architecture of beta-glycosyl transferases: implications for mechanism of action</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>177</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1419</fpage><?supplied-pmid 7883697?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7883697</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref026">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sethaphong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haigler</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kubicki</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bonetta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DeBolt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Tertiary model of a plant cellulose synthase</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>7512</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref027">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>Y-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z-Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>F-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>J-D</given-names></name>. <article-title>cDNA cloning and molecular characterization of five cellulose synthase A genes from Eucalyptus camaldulensis</article-title>. <source>Journal of plant biochemistry and biotechnology</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>199</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>210</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref028">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ranik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Myburg</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Six new cellulose synthase genes from Eucalyptus are associated with primary and secondary cell wall biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Tree physiology</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>545</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>56</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16452068?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16452068</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref029">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dole&#x17E;el</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pozniak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eversole</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feuillet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A chromosome-based draft sequence of the hexaploid bread wheat (Triticum aestivum) genome</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>345</volume>(<issue>6194</issue>):<fpage>1251788</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1251788">10.1126/science.1251788</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 25035500?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25035500</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref030">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goodstein</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neupane</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fazo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Phytozome: a comparative platform for green plant genomics</article-title>. <source>Nucleic acids research</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D1178</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>D86</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22110026</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref031">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>You</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lazo</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thilmony</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>PIECE: a database for plant gene structure comparison and evolution</article-title>. <source>Nucleic acids research</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D1159</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>D66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23180792</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref032">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>A root-specific wall-associated kinase gene, HvWAK1, regulates root growth and is highly divergent in barley and other cereals</article-title>. <source>Functional &amp; integrative genomics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>167</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23443578</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref033">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Filipski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>MEGA6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0</article-title>. <source>Molecular biology and evolution</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2725</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mst197">10.1093/molbev/mst197</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 24132122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132122</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref034">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saitou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>The neighbor-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Molecular biology and evolution</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>406</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 3447015?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3447015</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref035">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zuckerkandl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pauling</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolutionary divergence and convergence in proteins</article-title>. <source>Evolving genes and proteins</source>. <year>1965</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>166</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref036">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pingault</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choulet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alberti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wincker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feuillet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Deep transcriptome sequencing provides new insights into the structural and functional organization of the wheat genome</article-title>. <source>Genome biology</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25853487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref037">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bray N, Pimentel H, Melsted P, Pachter L. Near-optimal RNA-Seq quantification. arXiv preprint arXiv:150502710. 2015.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref038">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>. <article-title>edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>139</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>40</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 19910308?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref039">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Usadel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2014</year>:btu170.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref040">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fedorov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Do introns favor or avoid regions of amino acid conservation</article-title>? <source>Molecular biology and evolution</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>521</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>252</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11919293?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11919293</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref041">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Csuros</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rogozin</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>. <article-title>A detailed history of intron-rich eukaryotic ancestors inferred from a global survey of 100 complete genomes</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e1002150</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002150">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002150</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3174169.<?supplied-pmid 21935348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21935348</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref042">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Growth of the plant cell wall</article-title>. <source>Nature reviews molecular cell biology</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>850</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16261190?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16261190</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref043">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>. <article-title>The cellulose synthase gene superfamily and biochemical functions of xylem-specific cellulose synthase-like genes in Populus trichocarpa</article-title>. <source>Plant physiology</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>142</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1233</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>45</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16950861?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16950861</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref044">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howells</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huttly</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Interactions among three distinct CesA proteins essential for cellulose synthesis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1450</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0337628100">10.1073/pnas.0337628100</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC298793.<?supplied-pmid 12538856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12538856</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref045">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arioli</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Betzner</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wittke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herth</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Molecular analysis of cellulose biosynthesis in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>279</volume>(<issue>5351</issue>):<fpage>717</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 9445479?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9445479</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref046">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Onosato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miyao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirochika</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Three distinct rice cellulose synthase catalytic subunit genes required for cellulose synthesis in the secondary wall</article-title>. <source>Plant physiology</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>133</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>73</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>83</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12970476?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12970476</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref047">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A missense mutation in the transmembrane domain of CESA9 affects cell wall biosynthesis and plant growth in rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Science</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>196</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.plantsci.2012.08.002">10.1016/j.plantsci.2012.08.002</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid WOS:000310044500014?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23017906</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref048">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mochida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Unlocking Triticeae genomics to sustainably feed the future</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1931</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/pcp/pct163">10.1093/pcp/pct163</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3856857.<?supplied-pmid 24204022?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24204022</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref049">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stiller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berkman</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feuillet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Sequence-based analysis of translocations and inversions in bread wheat (Triticum aestivum L.)</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e79329</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0079329">10.1371/journal.pone.0079329</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 24260197?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24260197</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref050">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trapp</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genomic organization of plant terpene synthases and molecular evolutionary implications</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>158</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>811</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11404343?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11404343</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref051">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mochida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ogihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Discrimination of homoeologous gene expression in hexaploid wheat by SNP analysis of contigs grouped from a large number of expressed sequence tags</article-title>. <source>Molecular Genetics and Genomics</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>270</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>371</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14595557</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0147046.ref052">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Expression divergence of cellulose synthase (CesA) genes after a recent whole genome duplication event in Populus</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>241</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00425-014-2217-9">10.1007/s00425-014-2217-9</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 25486888?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25486888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
