<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Braz J Microbiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Braz. J. Microbiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bjm</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Brazilian Journal of Microbiology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1517-8382</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-4405</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Microbiologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4704640</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26691455</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1517-838246420140024</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Environmental Microbiology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Screening and characterization of endophytic <italic>Bacillus</italic>and <italic>Paenibacillus</italic> strains from medicinal plant <italic>Lonicera
japonica</italic> for use as potential plant growth promoters</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Longfei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>Yajun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lai</surname>
            <given-names>Xin-He</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shan</surname>
            <given-names>Changjuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>Zhenshan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ji</surname>
            <given-names>Yuliang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Key Laboratory of Plant-Microbe Interactions of Henan, Shangqiu
Normal University, PR China</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Institute of Translational Medicine, Wenzhou Medical University, PR
China</aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>School of Science and Technology, Henan Institute of Science and
Technology PR China</aff>
        <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>College of Life Sciences, Yan'an University, PR China</aff>
        <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Biological and Medical Engineering Department, Shangluo University,
PR China</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="equal" id="fn1">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="c1">Send correspondence to L. Zhao. Shangqiu Normal University, Shangqiu,
476000 Henan, PR China. E-mail: <email>hnzhaolongfei@163.com</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn2">
          <p>Associate Editor: Lara Dur&#xE3;es Sette</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <season>Oct-Dec</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>01</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>46</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>977</fpage>
      <lpage>989</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2015, Sociedade Brasileira de
Microbiologia</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
          <license-p>All the content of the journal, except where otherwise noted, is licensed
under a Creative Commons License CC BY-NC.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p>A total of 48 endophytic bacteria were isolated from surface-sterilized tissues of
the medicinal plant <italic>Lonicera japonica</italic>, which is grown in eastern
China; six strains were selected for further study based on their potential ability
to promote plant growth in vitro (siderophore and indoleacetic acid production). The
bacteria were characterized by phylogenetically analyzing their 16S rRNA gene
similarity, by examining their effect on the mycelial development of pathogenic
fungi, by testing their potential plant growth-promoting characteristics, and by
measuring wheat growth parameters after inoculation. Results showed that the number
of endophytic bacteria in <italic>L. japonica</italic> varied among different
tissues, but it remained relatively stable in the same tissues from four different
plantation locations. Among the three endophytic strains, strains 122 and 124 both
had high siderophore production, with the latter showing the highest phosphate
solubilization activity (45.6 mg/L) and aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid deaminase
activity (47.3 nmol/mg/h). Strain 170 had the highest indoleacetic acid (IAA)
production (49.2 mg/L) and cellulase and pectinase activities. After inoculation,
most of the six selected isolates showed a strong capacity to promote wheat growth.
Compared with the controls, the increase in the shoot length, root length, fresh
weight, dry weight, and chlorophyll content was most remarkable in wheat seedlings
inoculated with strain 130. The positive correlation between enzyme (cellulose and
pectinase) activity and inhibition rate on <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic>, the
IAA production, and the root length of wheat seedlings inoculated with each tested
endophytic strain was significant in regression analysis. Deformity of pathogenic
fungal mycelia was observed under a microscope after the interaction with the
endophytic isolates. Such deformity may be directly related to the production of
hydrolytic bacterial enzymes (cellulose and pectinase). The six endophytic bacterial
strains were identified to be <italic>Paenibacillus</italic> and
<italic>Bacillus</italic> strains based on the results of 16S rRNA gene sequencing
analysis and their physiological and biochemical characteristics. Results indicate
the promising application of endophytic bacteria to the biological control of
pathogenic fungi and the improvement of wheat crop growth.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Key words:</title>
        <kwd>Lonicera japonica</kwd>
        <kwd>Bacillus</kwd>
        <kwd>Paenibacillus</kwd>
        <kwd>plant growth-promoting characteristics</kwd>
        <kwd>endophytic bacterium</kwd>
        <kwd>wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>)</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="5"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <equation-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="48"/>
        <page-count count="13"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Endophytes are important constituents of the plant microecosystem. These organisms have
formed a mutually beneficial relationship with their host plants during long-term
evolutionary processes. Endophytic bacteria reside intercellularly or intracellularly
within the host tissues and do not cause visible damage or morphological changes in
their hosts. Therefore, these bacteria may be more advantageous for plant survival as
protection from environmental stress and microbial competition (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Geetha <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Some endophytes benefit the
host plants, <italic>i.e.</italic>, they increase soil porosity, produce indoleacetic
acid (IAA, a phytohormone), siderophores, and antibiotic compounds, function in
phosphate solubilization and nitrogen fixation, suppress phytopathogens via competition
for colonization sites and nutrients, and act as antagonists of nematodes (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Khan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Furthermore,
endophytes may help symbiotic rhizobia form nodules with non-specific hosts and promote
plant growth (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Zhao <italic>et al.</italic>,
2011</xref>). Therefore, endophytic bacteria are important microbial resources and have
gradually become a multidisciplinary research hotspot in different fields, including
botany, microbiology, plant protection, and plant breeding. Microorganisms associated
with medicinal plants are of interest as producers of compounds responsible for plant
bioactivity. A recent study has highlighted the potential use of endophytes for
synthesis of bioactive compounds, promotion of plant growth, and enhanced resistance to
various pathogens and drought (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Miller <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2012a</xref>). Conceivably, endophyte-derived metabolites may be
related to the observed bioactivity and beneficial health claims of the host plants in
traditional Chinese medicine (TCM). As a perennial semi-evergreen winding woody liana of
the genus <italic>Lonicera</italic> in Caprifoliaceae, <italic>Lonicerae
japonica</italic> (commonly known as honeysuckle or <italic>Jinyinhua</italic> in
Chinese) is an herb used in TCM as <italic>Flos Lonicerae</italic>; the plant is widely
grown in the Henan, Hebei, and Shandong Provinces of China. Given its latent
fever-clearing, antibacterial, antifungal, antiviral, and anti-inflammatory effects, the
herb has been prescribed to treat &#x201C;fever syndrome&#x201D; (a TCM term; an aspect of the common
cold), febrile diseases, dysentery, carbuncles, and virulent swellings (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Mphprc 2000</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Li
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Wu
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).</p>
      <p>Bacteria has been isolated from the rhizosphere of wheat (<italic>Triticum
aestivum</italic>), which is a major staple crop being cultivated worldwide and the
largest annual crop (24.4 Mha, 2012) in China. These bacterial isolates mainly include
<italic>Azospirillum brasilense, Pantoea agglomerans, Arthrobacter</italic> spp.,
<italic>Achromobacter xylosoxidans, Herbaspirillum hiltneri, Stenotrophomonas
maltophilia, Pseudomonas</italic> spp., <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp.,
<italic>Rahnella aquatilis, Paenibacillus riograndensis</italic>, and <italic>P.
polymyxa</italic> (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Venieraki <italic>et al.</italic>,
2011</xref>). <italic>Bacillus</italic> and <italic>Paenibacillus</italic> strains
are prominent members of the endophyte population in healthy tissues of medicinal plants
and function as prolific producers of bioactive compounds, including antimicrobials,
siderophores, and phytotoxins (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Miller <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2012b</xref>). For example, <italic>P. polymyxa</italic> benefits
plants by reducing disease severity, inducing defense mechanisms, promoting growth, and
producing several hydrolytic enzymes (&#x3B2;-1,3-glucanases and chitinases) and antifungal or
antibacterial metabolites (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Deng <italic>et al.</italic>,
2011</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Raza <italic>et al.</italic>,
2009</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Lai <italic>et al.</italic>,
2012</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Raza <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).
In addition, <italic>Bacillus</italic> sp. is involved in the biosynthesis of a broad
spectrum of antibiotics (<italic>e.g.</italic>, surfactant lichenysin) and can
effectively reduce disease incidence in diverse plant hosts by inducing systemic disease
resistance (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Bianco <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>),
forming biofilms on root surfaces and endospores, suppressing root phytopathogens, and
promoting heat and desiccation tolerance by colonizing the rhizosphere (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p>
      <p>Phytopathogens cause a variety of plant diseases and are useful model microorganisms for
studying various aspects of host-pathogen interactions. <italic>Alternaria</italic> and
<italic>Fusarium</italic> species can be found as pre-harvest fungal contaminants in
wheat (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mar&#xED;a <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).
<italic>Alternaria</italic> sp. is the predominant genus found in wheat grown in
different agroecological regions, with <italic>A. alternata</italic> being the most
prevalent species (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Gonz&#xE1;lez <italic>et al.</italic>,
1996</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Broggi <italic>et al.</italic>,
2007</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Ramirez <italic>et al.</italic>,
2005</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mar&#xED;a <italic>et al.</italic>,
2013</xref>). <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic> causes rice blast disease, which is
one of the most serious plant fungal diseases, whereas <italic>Fusarium
oxysporum</italic> may cause diseases in various crops, such as rice and wheat.</p>
      <p>The endophytes present in various plants and the antibacterial activity of endophytic
fungi isolated from <italic>Flos Lonicerae</italic> have been investigated (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). However, only a
few studies have reported the effect of endophytic bacteria from <italic>Flos
Lonicerae</italic> on phytopathogens (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Xu <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2013</xref>), and information is limited on the use of endophytes
isolated from tissues of the medicinal plant <italic>L. japonica</italic> in wheat
production. Moreover, the role of endophytic bacteria in plant growth and their
antagonistic potential against phytopathogens are unclear.</p>
      <p>The objectives of our study were as follows: (1) to isolate and screen endophytic
bacteria from tissues of the medicinal plant <italic>L. japonica</italic>; (2) to
characterize the plant growth-promoting characteristics (PGPC) of endophytic bacteria;
and (3) to detect the antifungal activities and effects of endophytic bacteria on wheat
seedlings.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Collection of <italic>L. japonica</italic> samples</title>
        <p>Root, stem, and leaf samples were collected from the medicinal plant <italic>L.
japonica</italic> (traditional variety Damaohua, 2<italic>n</italic> = 18) growing
in four different locations in the Henan and Shandong Provinces from July 2011 to
July 2012. Samples were collected during the plant's flowering and growth stages,
when active metabolism facilitated plant identification. The four sampling sites were
the medicinal botanical garden of Shangqiu Normal University, the Huaxian County of
Henan Province, and the Pingyi County and Juye County of Shangdong Province. The
distance between sampling sites was more than 50 km; each sampling site included at
least three subsites that were more than 1 km apart. From each subsite, 5 plants that
were separated at least by 30 m were randomly chosen and uprooted. Upon collection,
samples were placed in sterile bags and stored in the dark at 4 &#xB0;C until further
processing, usually within 24 h of collection.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Isolation of endophytic bacteria</title>
        <p>Briefly, 5 g each of root, stem, or leaf were carefully weighed from a pooled mixture
of healthy <italic>L. japonica</italic> plants, washed with sterile water to remove
remaining soil particles and attached epiphytic bacteria, and cut into 1-2 cm small
portions with sterile scissors. These portions were further surface-sterilized by
sequential immersion in 95% ethanol for 30 s then in 5% sodium hypochlorite for 3 min
before the samples were finally rinsed eight times in sterile distilled water. A
total of 5 plants were used from each subsite to form a mixture sample from the same
tissue, such that 15 plants were used for each site. Strain isolation was performed
from a pooled replicate of the same tissue from five plants in each subsite, such
that each site had three replicates. The surface-sterilized portions were placed into
sterile metal mortar, ground to slurry with 0.85% sterile saline, and shaken with a
vortex for 1 min. In the stationary state, the supernatant was collected and diluted
in different concentrations of the bacterial suspension. Subsequently, 100 &#x3BC;L of each
processed sample suspension was plated (with three replicates per sample) on nutrient
agar (NA) plates (5.0 g peptone, 1.5 g yeast extract, 1.5 g beef extract, 5.0 g NaCl,
20 g agar, and 1 L distilled water; pH 7.2) (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Deng
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). The cultures were incubated at 28 &#xB0;C for
3 d. A single colony of each isolate was re-streaked on fresh plates of the same
media and microscopically examined. The pure cultures were preserved on plates at 4
&#xB0;C for temporary storage or in sterile vials with 30% (v/v) glycerol for long-term
storage at &#x2212;80 &#xB0;C.</p>
        <p>To confirm the successful surface sterilization process, the surface sterilized
portions were rolled over the NA plates or aliquots of water from the final rinse
solutions. These portions were plated onto fresh NA plates and examined for
contaminants. Plates with no contaminants were effectively surface sterilized and
were used for the isolation of endophytes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Characterization of plant growth-promoting characteristics (PGPC) of endophytic
bacteria</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Examination of siderophore production</title>
          <p>Bacteria were cultured in lysogeny broth (LB; 10 g NaCl/L) for 72 h under
iron-restricted conditions. Aliquots of each bacterial culture were inoculated in
plates (three plates per strain) containing agar Chrome Azurol S (CAS) and
incubated at 30 &#xB0;C. Plates were observed daily for 7 d to detect the appearance of
an orange halo around the colonies (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Schwyn
<italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>). The siderophore levels produced by
the isolates corresponded to the diameter of the orange halo. The presence of
catechol and hydroxamate siderophores in the culture supernatants obtained from
bacteria grown in iron-restricted conditions in casamino acid (CAA) medium was
quantitatively determined by the colorimetric assay, as previously described
(<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Ma <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Phosphate solubilization</title>
          <p>To determine the phosphate-solubilizing activity, the isolates were cultured in
triplicate in modified Pikovskayas medium (0.5% tricalcium phosphate) (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Sundara-Rao <italic>et al.</italic>, 1963</xref>) at
30 &#xB0;C for 7 d at 200 rpm. The solubilized phosphate in the culture supernatant was
quantified as described by <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Fiske and Subbarow
(1925)</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Indole acetic acid (IAA) production</title>
          <p>IAA production was examined as previously described (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Gordon <italic>et al.</italic>, 1951</xref>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">In&#xE9;s <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Briefly, each bacterial
suspension (1 &#xD7; 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/mL) was inoculated in 10 mL LB broth containing
L-TRYPTOPHAN (100 &#x3BC;G/ML) AND INCUBATED AT 28 &#xB0;C for 72 h at 200 rpm. Bacterial
cells were removed by centrifugation at 8,000 rpm for 15 min, and the collected
supernatant was incubated at room temperature in the dark for 30 min. Pure IAA
(Sigma, USA) was used as a standard. The IAA concentration in the culture
supernatant was calculated according to the optical density of the culture, which
was measured at 530 nm with Salkowski's reagent (12 g/L FeCl<sub>3</sub> in 7.9 M
H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>). Each experiment was performed thrice.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC) deaminase activity</title>
          <p>The selective SMC medium supplemented with ACC was used to isolate bacteria that
could utilize ACC as an energy source with &#x3B1;-ketobutyrate as a precursor of
branched chain amino acids. The ACC deaminase activity in endophytic cells was
determined by monitoring the amount of &#x3B1;-ketobutyrate generated by the enzymatic
hydrolysis of ACC. The endophytes were grown in test tubes containing 10 mL of the
liquid SMC medium (containing per liter: KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.4 g;
K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 2 g; MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.2 g; CaCl<sub>2</sub>,
0.1 g; FeSO<sub>4</sub>, 5 mg; H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3</sub>, 2 mg;
ZnSO<sub>4</sub>, 5 mg; Na<sub>2</sub>MoO<sub>4</sub>, 1 mg; MnSO<sub>4</sub>, 3
mg; CoSO<sub>4</sub>, 1 mg; CuSO<sub>4</sub>, 1 mg; NiSO<sub>4</sub>, 1 mg; ACC,
0.5 g; NH<sub>4</sub>NO<sub>3</sub>, 0.3 g; and H<sub>2</sub>O, 1 L; pH 6.4) for
24 h at 30 &#xB0;C (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Belimov <italic>et al.</italic>,
2005</xref>). The cells were harvested by centrifugation at 12000 rpm for 10
min at room temperature. The cell pellets were washed twice with sterile deionized
distilled water and resuspended in 1 mL of 0.1 M Tris-HCl buffer. The cells were
disrupted by vigorous vortexing with 30 &#x3BC;L of toluene. A mixture of 100 &#x3BC;L of the
cell suspension with 10 &#x3BC;L of 0.5 M ACC and 100 &#x3BC;L of 0.1 M Tris-HCl buffer (pH
8.5) was incubated for 30 min at 30 &#xB0;C before adding with 1 mL of 0.56 M HCl. The
mixture was centrifuged at 12000 rpm for 5 min to obtain the supernatant.
Subsequently, 400 &#x3BC;L of 0.56 M HCl and 150 mL of 0.2% 2,4-dinitrophenylhydrazine
in 2 M HCl were added to 500 &#x3BC;L of the supernatant. The mixture was incubated for
30 min at 30 &#xB0;C before adding 1 mL of 2 M NaOH. The amount of &#x3B1;-ketobutyrate was
measured by determining the optical density at 600 nm with mixtures without the
cell suspension or ACC as the controls.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Cellulase and pectinase activity</title>
          <p>The activities of cellulase and pectinase were assayed on indicator plates. For
the cellulase assay, nitrogen-freebase (NFB) plates supplemented with 0.2%
carboxymethyl cellulose and 0.5% tryptone were spotted with bacterial cells. After
incubation for 48 h at 30 &#xB0;C, the plates were coated with a Congo Red (1 mg/mL)
solution for 30 min. The excess stain was discarded, and the agar was destained
with 1 M of a NaCl solution. Plates were kept overnight at 4 &#xB0;C and examined on
the following day for clearing zones around the points of inoculation.</p>
          <p>For the pectinase assay, the bacterial isolates were spotted on NA medium
supplemented with 0.5% pectin, and the plates were incubated at 30 &#xB0;C. On the
fifth day of incubation, a 2% cetyltrimethyl ammonium bromide (CTAB) solution was
added to the plate surface for 30 min and then discarded. The plates were washed
with 1 M NaCl to visualize the zone around the bacterial growth (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Ma <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>In vitro detection of antifungal activity</title>
          <p>The interaction of endophytes with pathogenic fungi (<italic>F. oxysporum, M.
grisea</italic>, and <italic>A. alternata</italic>) was performed via the point
inoculation method as previously described (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Zhao
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Briefly, a small block of agar with
fungal growth was cut from potato dextrose agar (PDA) plates (extract of 200 g
potato with 20 g glucose, 18 g agar, and 1 L distilled water) by a sterile puncher
(&#xD8; = 4 mm). Each block was placed in the center of a fresh PDA plate. Test strains
were spot-inoculated on the edge of PDA plate (approximately 25 mm from the
center), incubated at 28 &#xB1; 2 &#xB0;C for 7 d, and observed for zones of inhibition,
with fungal mycelia cultivated for 7 d without spot inoculation as control (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Geetha <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>).
Experiments were performed in triplicate for each bacterial isolate.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Microscopy of fungal mycelia</title>
          <p>The morphological changes caused by endophytes on the mycelia of each pathogenic
fungal species after culturing for 4 d on PDA plates were directly examined,
photographed under an optical fluorescence microscope (BX50 Olympus; under 200x
magnification), and compared with the structures of the control groups.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Effects of endophyte inoculation on plant growth</title>
          <p>Wheat seeds (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> cv. &#x2018;Zhoumai 18&#x2019;, a national
authorized wheat variety of China) were surface sterilized with 100% alcohol for 1
min, 5% sodium hypochlorite for 3 min, and finally rinsed six times with sterile
distilled water. Surface-sterilized seeds were allowed to germinate axenically in
Petri dishes filled with moist filter paper at 28 &#xB0;C. The surface-sterilized seeds
were immersed for 3 h in a thick suspension of the exponential phase bacteria
(approximately 10<sup>9</sup>-10<sup>10</sup> cfu/mL) cultured in 5 mL of YM
broth. The germinated seeds were grown in pots filled with sterilized vermiculite,
which was moistened with sterile water, as described by <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Vincent (1970)</xref>. Seeds were cultured under greenhouse
conditions programmed for a 14 h/d photoperiod at a constant temperature of 28 &#xB0;C
during the day and 20 &#xB0;C at night at approximately 50% relative humidity. All pot
experiments were incubated with isolates 122, 124, 130, 132, 135, or 170 in three
repetitions with 30 seedlings per pot. Seedlings without bacteria were used as the
controls. The wheat plants were harvested after 7 weeks when seedling roots were
well developed. Parameters such as the fresh weight, dry weight, shoot length,
root length, and the chlorophyll content of experimental plants were measured and
compared with those of the control plants (plants that were not inoculated with
endophyte).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Estimation of chlorophyll content</title>
          <p>The greenest leaves were collected from 20-day-old wheat plants without the dry
leaves, plant diseases, and insect pests and were then kept in the dark. A total
of 90 plants were used in the replicates, and 3 repetitions were performed. From
each plant, three leaves were collected, cut into smaller pieces, and mixed.
Subsequently, 1 g of leaf tissue was crushed in a mixture of ethanol and acetone
(v/v, 1:1) and maintained at 40 &#xB0;C for 24 h. The chlorophyll content was
spectrophotometrically measured with the specific absorption coefficients for
chlorophyll a and b at 645 and 663 nm, respectively. The chlorophyll content was
calculated according to <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Geetha <italic>et
al.</italic> (2008)</xref>, with the mixture of ethanol and acetone as the
control.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Identification of endophytic bacterial strains</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Strain morphology, physiological characteristics, and biochemical
tests</title>
          <p>The physiological and biochemical characteristics of our isolated strains were
determined according to Bergey's Manual of Determinative Bacteriology (VIIIth
edition). The main assays were: catalase activity; V-P test; growth in
Luria-Bertani broth (pH 5.0) with 0%, 2%, 5%, 7%, and 10% of NaCl at 4 &#xB0;C, 10 &#xB0;C,
30 &#xB0;C, 40 &#xB0;C, and 50 &#xB0;C; acid production from D-GLUCOSE, D-arabinose, xylose, and
D-mannitol; starch hydrolysis; citrate utilization; nitrate reduction;
phenylalanine deamination; and casein decomposition. Gram staining, spore
production, cellular size, cell shape, and colony characteristics were also
examined.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Sequencing and phylogenetic analysis</title>
          <p>The phylogeny of the 16S rRNA genes has been used as one of the main criteria for
differentiating species, genera, and higher taxa in current bacterial taxonomy. To
identify the potential endophytic bacteria, total genomic DNA was extracted from
the isolates as previously described (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Moulin
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). The 16S rRNA gene was selectively
amplified from genomic DNA by PCR with the universal forward primer P1
(5&#x2032;-CGGGATCCAGAGTTTGATCCTGGCTCAGAACGAACGCT-3&#x2032;) and reverse primer P6
(5&#x2032;-CGGGATCCTACGGCTACCTTGTTACGACTTCACCCC-3&#x2032;), which corresponded to the positions
8-37 bp and 1479-1506 bp, respectively, in the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>
16S rRNA gene (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">van Berkum <italic>et al.</italic>,
1996</xref>). An aliquot of PCR products of isolates was directly sequenced by
the Sangon Biotech (Shanghai) Co., Ltd. with the same primers mentioned above. The
acquired and related sequences were matched with the ClustalX 1.81 software and
manually corrected with Bioedit 4.8.4. A phylogenetic tree was constructed with
the Jukes-Cantor model and the neighbor-joining method (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Saitou <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>) by the TREECON software
package (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">van de Peer <italic>et al.</italic>,
1997</xref>). The computation of the similarity of each strain tested was
performed by the DNAMAN application (version 6.0.3.40; Lynnon Corporation). The
obtained 16S rRNA gene sequences were deposited in the NCBI GenBank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>) under the accession numbers KC208613
through KC208618.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>Data on the density of endophytic bacteria in different tissues of <italic>Lonicera
japonica</italic>, growth promotion, and endophytic inoculation experiments were
treated with ANOVA (analysis of variance), and mean comparisons were performed with
Tukey's test (p = 0.05). Regression analysis was performed with the IBM SPSS 17.0
package (by the Data Theory Scaling System Group, Faculty of Social and Behavioral
Sciences, Leiden University, The Netherlands).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Isolation of endophytic bacteria from <italic>L. japonica</italic>
</title>
        <p>Endophytic bacteria (48 strains) with different colony morphology
(<italic>e.g.</italic>, shape, size, and color) were isolated from the healthy
root, stem, and leaf tissues of <italic>L. japonica</italic> plants. By contrast, no
colonies appeared on the NA plates upon incubation at 28 &#xB0;C for 2 d to 3 d, either by
rolling over with the sterilized surface portions of this medicinal plant or plating
aliquots of water from final rinse solutions, thereby indicating successful surface
sterilization. The amount of endophytic bacteria significantly varied between the
different tissues, as follows: 3.62 &#xD7; 10<sup>4</sup> cfu/g in roots, 0.88 &#xD7;
10<sup>4</sup> cfu/g in stems, and 2.73 &#xD7; 10<sup>4</sup> cfu/g in leaves (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). No significant differences were
observed in the bacterial density between the same tissues among different plants
from all four plantation locations (p = 0.05).</p>
        <table-wrap id="t1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Density of endophytic bacteria isolated from different tissues of
<italic>L. japonica</italic> (&#xD7; 10<sup>4</sup> cfu/g).</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup width="25%" span="1">
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead style="border-top: thin solid; border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Origin sites</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Roots</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stems</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaves</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shangqiu, Henan Province</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.56 &#xB1; 0.0038<sup>a,</sup>
<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN2">&#xA7;</xref>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 &#xB1; 0.0048<sup>a</sup>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98 &#xB1; 0.0051<sup>a</sup>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Huaxian, Henan Province</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.89 &#xB1; 0.0038<sup>b</sup>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 &#xB1; 0.0089<sup>b</sup>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.61 &#xB1; 0.0029<sup>b</sup>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pingyi, Shangdong Province</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.67 &#xB1; 0.0092<sup>c</sup>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 &#xB1; 0.0060<sup>c</sup>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87 &#xB1; 0.0062<sup>c</sup>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Juye, Shangdong Province</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37 &#xB1; 0.0142<sup>d</sup>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 &#xB1; 0.0021<sup>a</sup>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45 &#xB1; 0.0092<sup>d</sup>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62 &#xB1; 0.0078</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 &#xB1; 0.0055</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.73 &#xB1; 0.0059</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="TFN1">
              <p>Notes: Data are the mean of three samples. &#xB1; represents the standard errors
of the mean.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="TFN2">
              <label>&#xA7;</label>
              <p>The same letter indicates no significant differences between treatments at
0.05 levels.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Characterization of endophytic bacteria for factors with plant growth-promoting
potential</title>
        <p>All 48 strains were studied for their siderophore production. Six of these strains
showed remarkable performance as evidenced by the orange halo around the colony. The
color change is attributed to iron removal by the bacteria from the blue CAS-Fe (III)
complex in the CAS agar medium with the dark blue background. Only 5 of the 6 strains
except strain 132 produced a siderophore concentration in the range of 1.8-87.2 mg/L
for catecholate and 0.90-76.3 mg/L for hydroxymate (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>) in the quantitative analysis. Strains 122 and 124 showed the most
significant siderophore production after 24 h of incubation.</p>
        <table-wrap id="t2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>PGPC of endophytic bacteria.</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup width="12%" span="1">
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead style="border-top: thin solid; border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strains</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sid. (C) (mg/L)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN4">*</xref>
</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sid. (H) (mg/L)</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pho. (mg/L)</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IAA production (mg/L)</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACC deaminase (nmol/mg/h)</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellulase activity (D/d)</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pectinase activity (D/d)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.6 &#xB1; 0.17a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN5">&#xA7;</xref>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.3 &#xB1; 0.56a</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3 &#xB1; 0.26a</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.3 &#xB1; 0.12a</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.2 &#xB1; 0.36a</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#xB1; 0.08a</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 &#xB1; 0.01a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.2 &#xB1; 0.36b</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.1 &#xB1; 0.26b</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.6 &#xB1; 0.46b</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5 &#xB1; 0.12b</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.3 &#xB1; 0.26b</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 &#xB1; 0.05a</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#xB1; 0.06b</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7 &#xB1; 0.53c</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5 &#xB1; 0.53c</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9 &#xB1; 0.72c</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.3 &#xB1; 0.35c</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.6 &#xB1; 031c</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 &#xB1; 0.03c</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 &#xB1; 0.05c</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87 &#xB1; 0.07d</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9 &#xB1; 0.14d</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 &#xB1; 0.03d</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 &#xB1; 0.01d</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 &#xB1; 0.06d</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#xB1; 0.09d</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6 &#xB1; 0.17e</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3 &#xB1; 0.39d</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 &#xB1; 0.03b</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43 &#xB1; 0.02a</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.9 &#xB1; 0.36e</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4 &#xB1; 0.26e</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.2 &#xB1; 0.46f</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.58 &#xB1; 0.06e</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64 &#xB1; 0.04e</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="TFN3">
              <p>Note: Sid. (C), Siderophore production (Catechol-type); Sid. (H),
Siderophore production (Hydroxamate-type); Pho phosphate solubilization;
IAA, indoleacetic acid; ACC, 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid, activity
(nmol &#x3B1;-ketobutyrate/mg biomass/h. D/d indicates the ability to produce
siderophores, cellulose, and pectinase. D, diameter of colony and halo; d -
colony diameter.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="TFN4">
              <label>*</label>
              <p>Average (&#xB1;, standard deviation), the data in columns is average values of
three repetitions.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="TFN5">
              <label>&#xA7;</label>
              <p>The same letter means no significant differences between treatments at 0.01
level; negative action, blank; control for IAA assay was LB (10 g NaCl/L)
without inoculated bacterial suspension under the same incubation
condition.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>The phosphate solubilization potential was studied for all 48 isolates, only 6
isolates showed a zone of phosphate solubilization on the Pikovskayas agar medium
with tricalcium phosphate. These 6 strains were further quantified for phosphate
solubilization in a liquid medium; 4 of which were within the range of 1.87-45.6 mg/L
(<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). Isolated strain 124 had the
highest level of phosphate solubilization, whereas isolates 135 and 170 showed levels
that were under the detection limit.</p>
        <p>IAA production was measured for all the 48 endophytic bacteria in the range of
11.5-49.2 mg/L after 72 h of incubation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table
2</xref>). The IAA levels of the strains in the culture supernatant matched their
anti-fungal activity. Isolate 170 produced significantly higher IAA levels than the
other isolates.</p>
        <p>Among the tested 48 isolates, only 4 strains could utilize ACC as the sole carbon
source (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>), which is an indication of
the ACC deaminase activity. Among these 4 strains, strains 124 and 122 were the top
two strains that utilize ACC as the sole carbon source. Based on the development of a
yellow-color zone on the NFB and NA plates, all six strains exhibited cellulase and
pectinase activities, with isolate 170 showing the highest levels (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). The statistical differences between
strains were shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref> in terms of the
activities of ACC deaminase, cellulase, and pectinase, as well as phosphate
solubilization and IAA/siderophore production.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Detection of <italic>in vitro</italic> antifungal activity</title>
        <p>The inhibitory activity of the 48 endophytic bacterial strains against pathogenic
fungi (<italic>M. grisea, F. oxysporum</italic>, and <italic>A. alternata</italic>)
was measured. All six selected strains (12.5%) strongly inhibited pathogenic fungi
compared with the control. Based on the inhibition of mycelial growth, strain 124
showed the strongest effect against <italic>F. oxysporum</italic> (74.39%), followed
by strain 132 against <italic>A. alternata</italic> (70.93%), and strain 130 against
<italic>M. grisea</italic> (73.75%), respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>). Compared with the controls, the correlation was positive and
significant between the activities of hydrolytic enzymes (cellulose and pectinase)
and the inhibition rate of <italic>F. oxysporum</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1A-C</xref>) for each strain tested.</p>
        <table-wrap id="t3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Inhibition of endophytic bacteria by pathogenic fungi.</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup width="12%" span="1">
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead style="border-top: thin solid; border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strains</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th>
                <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>F. oxysporum</italic>
                </th>
                <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>A. alternata</italic>
                </th>
                <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>M. grisea</italic>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.63<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN8">*</xref>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.51<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN8">*</xref>
</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.50<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN8">*</xref>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.39</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.89</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.25</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stem</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.51</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.63</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.75</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.73</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.93</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.50</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.76</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.95</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.75</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stem</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.85</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.95</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.75</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="TFN6">
              <p>Notes: Data are the mean of three samples.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="TFN7">
              <p>Colony diameter, cm.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="TFN8">
              <label>*</label>
              <p>Inhibition ratio of pathogenic fungus (%) = (Control colony
diameter-treatment colony diameter)100/ Control colony diameter.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="TFN9">
              <p>Controls for antifungal activity assays were fungal mycelia cultivated for 7
d on PDA plates without the tested strains under the same incubation
condition.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Regression analysis of the effect of endophytic bacteria on root length and
the pathogenic fungus <italic>F. oxysporum</italic>. (A) Regression analysis of
bacterial IAA and root lengths of seedlings inoculated with endopyhtic
bacteria. (B) Regression analysis of bacterial cellulase activity and
inhibition rate of <italic>F. oxysporum</italic>. (C) Regression analysis of
bacterial pectinase activity and inhibition rate of <italic>F.
oxysporum</italic>. Names of strains are shown on different data
dots.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1678-4405-bjm-46-04-0977-gf01"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Microscopy of pathogenic fungi mycelia</title>
        <p>Compared with the nearly straight and even mycelia of the control under laboratory
condition and cultured on PDA medium for 4 d (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure
2A-C</xref>; also shown in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="suppl1">Supplementary figure</xref>), the colonies of the pathogenic fungi
shrunk upon interaction with endophytic bacteria, and their mycelia underwent
considerable morphological changes, as follows: becoming coralline (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2Da</xref>), fractured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2Fd, f</xref>), swollen, globular, or atrophied (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2Fd-f</xref>); forming a bending knot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2Eb-c</xref>); and undergoing autolysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2Fe</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Morphological changes of the mycelia of plant pathogenic fungi upon
interaction with <italic>Lonicera japonica</italic> endophytes. Images in A, B,
and C were representative of normal mycelia of <italic>M. grisea</italic> MG01,
<italic>F. oxysporum</italic> FO02, and <italic>A. alternata</italic> AA03.
Images in D, E, F were the atrophy and deformity of <italic>M. grisea</italic>
MG01 mycelia (by strain 130), bending knot of <italic>F. oxysporum</italic>
FO02 mycelia (by strain 124), autolysis, fracture, and atrophy of <italic>A.
alternata</italic> AA03 mycelia (by strain 132).</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1678-4405-bjm-46-04-0977-gf02"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Wheat growth promotion after endophyte inoculation</title>
        <p>The six bacterial isolates with plant growth-promoting potential and antagonistic
activity against pathogenic fungi <italic>in vitro</italic> were further evaluated
because of their effectiveness in promoting wheat growth upon <italic>in
vivo</italic> inoculation. Compared with the control, strain 130 significantly
increased its shoot length by 14.57% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure
3A</xref>), whereas all six strains promoted root length to a different extent. Root
length promotion was more pronounced with strains 130, 132, and 170 (10.87%, 8.42%,
and 10.27%, respectively as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref>).
Strains 130 and 135 significantly increased wheat fresh weight (16.48% and 15.78%,
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3C</xref>) and dry weight (20.07% and 19.65%,
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3D</xref>). Regression analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1A</xref>) showed a significant positive
correlation between IAA production and increase in root length of the wheat seedlings
inoculated with endophytic bacteria.</p>
        <fig id="f3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effect of six endophytic bacteria on shoot length (A), root length (B),
fresh weight (C), and dry weight (D) of wheat seedlings. Each value is the mean
of ten replicates. Bars represent the standard deviations of mean. Statistical
significance was determined at p &lt; 0.05 according to the Tukey's test. The
asterisk represents significant differences.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1678-4405-bjm-46-04-0977-gf03"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Compared with the uninoculated control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure
4</xref>), the chlorophyll content of the endopyhte-inoculated wheat increased to a
range of 8.4% to 33.98%, with the strain 130-treated group showing the highest
content (33.98%). The inoculation of strain 130 induced the highest increase in shoot
length, root length, fresh weight, dry weight, and chlorophyll content of wheat.</p>
        <fig id="f4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effect of six endophytic bacteria on the chlorophyll content of wheat
seedlings. Each value is the mean of three replicates. Bars represent the
standard deviations of the mean. Statistical significance was determined at p
&lt; 0.05 according to the Tukey's test. The asterisk represents significant
differences.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1678-4405-bjm-46-04-0977-gf04"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Identification of the six plant growth-promoting endophytic bacteria</title>
        <p>Physiological and biochemical tests were conducted, including measurements of
catalase, V-P test, utilization of carbohydrate, the production of enzymes, growth
temperature, salt tolerance, and bacterial morphology (<italic>i.e.</italic>, size,
shape, and Gram staining; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="suppl2">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). Based on these results and the sequencing of 16S
rRNA gene and phylogeny analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref> and
<xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>), our endophytic isolates belonged
to two genera, namely, <italic>Bacillus</italic> and <italic>Paenibacillus</italic>.
Strains 122 and 130 showed high identity with <italic>Paenibacillus</italic> and were
most closely related to <italic>P. polymyxa</italic> IAM 13419<sup>T</sup> (D16276)
and <italic>P. ehimensis</italic> KCTC3748 (AY116665) with 98.7% and 100% similarity,
respectively. Therefore, a <italic>Paenibacillus</italic> sub-clade was formed.
Strains 170, 124, 132, and 135 had high sequence similarities to <italic>B.
atrophaeus</italic> NRRLNRS-213<sup>T</sup> (EU138516) (99.6%), <italic>B.
megaterium</italic> IAM13418<sup>T</sup> (D16273) (99.1%), and <italic>B.
subtilis</italic> FL (EU221673) with a similarity of 99.6% and 99.7%.</p>
        <fig id="f5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Neighbor-joining tree based on the alignment of nucleotide sequences of the
16S rRNA gene from the tested strains (shown in bold) and reference strains.
GenBank accession numbers were placed in parentheses. Bootstrap values greater
than 50% were indicated. Scale bar represents the number of substitutions per
site.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1678-4405-bjm-46-04-0977-gf05"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="t4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Identification and classification of the tested strains.</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup width="20%" span="1">
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
              <col span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead style="border-top: thin solid; border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strains</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus affiliation</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accession No. of the 16S rDNA
sequence</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Best closest match</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Similarity (%)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody style="border-bottom: thin solid; border-color: #000000">
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Paenibacillus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KC208613</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Paenibacillus polymyxa</italic> IAM 13419<sup>T</sup>
(D16276)</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Bacillus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KC208614</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic> IAM13418<sup>T</sup> (D16273)</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Paenibacillus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KC208617</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Paenibacillus ehimensis</italic> IFO15659<sup>T</sup>
(AB021184)</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Bacillus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KC208615</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> FL (EU221673)</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Bacillus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KC208616</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> FL (EU221673)</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Bacillus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KC208618</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus atrophaeus</italic> NRRLNRS-213<sup>T</sup>
(EU138516)</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This work is the first report on the isolation and population density of endophytic
bacteria from the medicinal plant <italic>L. japonica</italic>, which is widely planted
in the Henan and Shandong provinces in eastern China. As summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>, the endophytic bacterial load varied
significantly in different tissues, but it remained relatively stable without
significant differences in the same tissues of different plants from different planting
locations (p = 0.05), thereby implying that the prevalence of endophytic bacteria
depended on the plant tissues being colonized and the microenvironment they lived in.
The endophytic bacterial number in roots is the highest probably because the root soil
environment is fairly complex under the effect of both biotic and abiotic factors.
Previous studies have reported that the population of endophytic <italic>B.
subtilis</italic> E1R-j in roots increases when the bacterial cell number reisolated
from the leaf tissue distinctly decreases from the second to fourth leaf stage, thereby
indicating that <italic>B. subtilis</italic> E1R-j can relocate from the root to the
aerial parts of a wheat plant (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Our results are in line with those obtained in a
recent report (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Gao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>)
that endophytic bacterial density varies in different parts of the plant, with the
highest value in roots and the lowest value in stems. Similar patterns of bacterial
population levels in the root and stem tissues have been widely reported in cabbage
(<italic>B. subtilis</italic> BB), cacao (<italic>B. subtilis</italic>), rose, and
crops such as maize, wheat, rice (<italic>B. subtilis</italic> strain NR-64), soybean,
sweet corn, sugar beet, and potato, or in various medicinal plants such as
<italic>Glycyrrhiza</italic> spp., <italic>Pinellia ternate, Lycium chinense,
Digitalis purpurae, Leonurus heterophyllus, Bletilla striata, Belamcanda chinases, P.
pedatisecta</italic>, and <italic>Taxus yunnanensis</italic> (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Venieraki <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Gao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Wulff <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Bahig
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Li
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Miller
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2012a</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Leite
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).</p>
      <p>Siderophore production could confer competitive advantages in bacteria for colonizing
plant tissues, excluding other microorganisms from the same ecological niche (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Loaces <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), competing for
nutrients, and protecting plant from phytopathogens (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Compant <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Metagenomic analysis (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Sessitsch <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) revealed
that the presence of a high number of genes involved in siderophore production in an
endophyte community that colonizes rice roots indicates a strong biocontrol capacity
because endophytes compete with other pathogens for iron. Among the 6 endophytic
bacteria (3 strains from roots, 2 strains from stems, and 1 strain from leaves; 4
<italic>Bacillus</italic> and 2 <italic>Paenibacillus</italic> strains), strains 122
and 124 showed a higher capacity for siderophore production.</p>
      <p>Several phosphate-solubilizing microorganisms are able to convert insoluble phosphorus
to a soluble form through acidification, secretion of organic acids or protons (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Richardson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), or
chelation and exchange reactions (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Hameeda <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bhattacharyya <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), thereby representing a possible mechanism of direct
plant growth promotion under field conditions (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Verma
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). These microorganisms are important for
plant nutrition because they increase phosphate uptake and act as biofertilization
promoters of wheat crops. <italic>Bacillus</italic> is reportedly one of the most
significant phosphate-solubilizing bacteria (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Mehnaz
<italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Four of our six strains are capable of
phosphate solubilization. Strains 124 (<italic>Bacillus</italic>) and 122
(<italic>Paenibacillus</italic>) showed relatively higher phosphate solubilization
than the others, and these strains significantly increased the dry weight and fresh
weight of the inoculated wheat, respectively.</p>
      <p>In this report, six endophytic strains from the medicinal plant <italic>L.
japonica</italic> exhibited inhibitory activity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>) against phytopathogenic fungi (<italic>F. oxysporum, M. grisea, A.
alternata</italic>), which are useful model organisms for studying various aspects of
host-pathogen interactions. These pathogens are chosen as test targets in the antifungal
activity experiment because of their capacity to cause epiphytic disease and major
damage in crops and plants, including <italic>L. japonica</italic> and wheat. Previous
works have verified that promoting plant growth and inhibiting phytopathogen growth may
involve a large number of bacterial endophytes. A recent report also suggests that the
cellulase and pectinase produced by <italic>Klebsiella oxytoca</italic> GR-3 might play
an important role in plant-microbe interactions and the intercellular colonization of
roots (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Ma <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Our
findings revealed that all 6 of the selected strains (<italic>Bacillus</italic> and
<italic>Paenibacillus</italic>) exhibited cellulose and pectinase activities.</p>
      <p>Growth-promoting agents can enhance plant growth and have the potential to replace the
use of chemical fertilizers, pesticides, and other supplements (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Kim <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bhattacharyya <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Endophytes that are associated
with medicinal plants are of interest as producers of compounds responsible for the
observed plant bioactivity with biosynthetic potential (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Miller <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012b</xref>). This finding is in agreement with our
result, <italic>i.e.</italic>, strain 130 induced the largest increase in root length,
stem length, flesh weight, dry weight, and the chlorophyll content of wheat <italic>in
vivo</italic>, although its <italic>in vitro</italic> ACC deaminase activity is lower
than that of strains 122 and 124. One explanation for this phenomenon is that strain 130
contains ACC deaminase but its activity was not induced very much in the <italic>in
vitro</italic> study. Alternatively, strain 130 showed a higher IAA production,
thereby directly promoting wheat growth via hormonal stimulation. Furthermore, plant
growth is the overall result of all growth-promoting molecules produced by root
endophytes and ectophytes (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Patten <italic>et
al.</italic>, 2002</xref>).</p>
      <p>In summary, our work showed that some of the endophytic bacteria (strains 130, 135, and
170) isolated from the medicinal plant <italic>L. japonica</italic> can produce wheat
growth-promoting molecules <italic>in vitro</italic> and increase wheat growth
(<italic>i.e.</italic>, root length, stem length, flesh weight, dry weight, and
chlorophyll content) <italic>in vivo</italic>. Therefore, these endophytic bacteria have
the potential to be used as plant growth-promoting agents in agriculture to increase
crop growth.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>This work was supported by projects from the National Science Foundation of China
(U1204301), the Henan Provincial Education Department of Science and Technology Research
Key Research Project (12A210019), and the Foundation for University Key Teacher by the
Ministry of Education of Henan Province (2012GGJS166). The Authors are grateful to Dr.
Guihong Yin for providing the wheat seeds (cv. &#x2018;Zhoumai18&#x2019;). We thank Prof. Yi Ren of
the Department of Biomedical Sciences, Florida State University College of Medicine,
Tallahassee, FL, USA, Dr. Jane Kelly, of the Medical Research Service, RD-33, Department
of Veterans Affairs Medical Center, 3710 SW U.S. Veterans Hospital Road, Portland, OR,
USA, and an anonymous reviewer from the USA for proofreading and polishing the final
draft of our manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <app-group>
      <app id="app1">
        <title>Supplementary Material</title>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="suppl1">
          <label>Figure S1</label>
          <media xlink:href="bjm-46-977-s001.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
          <p>Antagonistic activity of endophytes against phytopathogenic fungi after 3 d. (A)
Inhibition of <italic>M. grisea</italic> MG01 by endophyte strain 130; (B0
inhibition of <italic>F. oxysporum</italic> FO02 by endophyte strain 124; C.
inhibition of <italic>A. alternata</italic> AA03 by endophyte strain 132. A&#x2019;, B&#x2019;,
and C&#x2019; were control pathogenic fungusfungal colonies without endophytes.</p>
        </supplementary-material>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="suppl2">
          <label>Table S1</label>
          <media xlink:href="bjm-46-977-s002.pdf">
            <caption>
              <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
          <p>A Physiological and biochemical test results and cell characteristics of strains
122, 124, 130, 132, 135, and 170.</p>
        </supplementary-material>
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bahig</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salih</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Youssuf</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2012</year>
          <article-title>Characterization of endophytic bacteria associated with rose plant
(<italic>Rosa damascena trigintipeta</italic>) during flowering stage and their
plant growth promoting traits</article-title>
          <source>J Plant Interact</source>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>248</fpage>
          <lpage>225</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Belimov</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hontzeas</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Safronova</surname>
              <given-names>VI</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Cadmium-tolerant plant growth-promoting bacteria associated with the
roots of Indian mustard (<italic>Brassica juncea</italic> L.
Czern.)</article-title>
          <source>Soil Biol Biochem</source>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>241</fpage>
          <lpage>250</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bhattacharyya</surname>
              <given-names>PN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jha</surname>
              <given-names>DK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2012</year>
          <article-title>Plant growth-promoting rhizobacteria (PGPR): emergence in
agriculture</article-title>
          <source>World J Microb Biot</source>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>1327</fpage>
          <lpage>1350</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bianco</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daffonchio</surname>
              <given-names>FQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lorenzo</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Restructuring of Endophytic Bacterial Communities in Grapevine
Yellows-Diseased and Recovered <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L.
Plants</article-title>
          <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <fpage>5018</fpage>
          <lpage>5022</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21622794</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Broggi</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonz&#xE1;lez</surname>
              <given-names>HHL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Resnik</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title><italic>Alternaria alternata</italic> prevalence in cereal grains and soybean
seeds from Entre R&#xED;os, Argentina</article-title>
          <source>Rev Iberoam Micol</source>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          <lpage>51</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17592893</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chai</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <article-title>Biocontrol of tomato wilt disease by <italic>Bacillus
subtilis</italic> isolates from natural environments depends on conserved genes
mediating biofilm formation</article-title>
          <source>Environ Microbiol</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>916</fpage>
          <lpage>927</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23320867</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Compant</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duffy</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nowak</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Use of plant growth-promoting bacteria for biocontrol of plant
diseases: principles, mechanisms of action, and future prospects</article-title>
          <source>Appl Environ Microb</source>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <fpage>4951</fpage>
          <lpage>4959</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Deng</surname>
              <given-names>ZS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kong</surname>
              <given-names>ZY</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Diversity of endophytic bacteria within nodules of the
<italic>Sphaerophysa salsula</italic> in different regions of Loess Plateau in
China</article-title>
          <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <fpage>463</fpage>
          <lpage>475</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21303396</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fiske</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Subbarow</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1925</year>
          <article-title>A colorimetric determination of phosphorus</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>375</fpage>
          <lpage>400</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gao</surname>
              <given-names>LL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>XL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jian</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2012</year>
          <article-title>Isolation and identification of endophytic nitrogen-fixing bacteria in
rice with antipathogenic functions</article-title>
          <source>J Huazhong Agri University</source>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>553</fpage>
          <lpage>557</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geetha</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Falguni</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anjana</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Enhanced growth and nodulation of pigeon pea by co-inoculation of
<italic>Bacillus</italic> strains with <italic>Rhizobium</italic>
spp</article-title>
          <source>Biores Technol</source>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>4544</fpage>
          <lpage>4550</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gonz&#xE1;lez</surname>
              <given-names>HHL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pacin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Resnik</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>1996</year>
          <article-title>Deoxynivalenol and contaminant mycoflora in freshly harvested
Argentinean wheat in 1993</article-title>
          <source>Mycopathologia</source>
          <volume>135</volume>
          <fpage>129</fpage>
          <lpage>134</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9091829</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gordon</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weber</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1951</year>
          <article-title>Colorimetric estimation of indoleacetic acid</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>192</fpage>
          <lpage>195</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16654351</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hameeda</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harini</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rupela</surname>
              <given-names>OP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Growth promotion of maize by phosphate-solubilizing bacteria isolated
from composts and macrofauna</article-title>
          <source>Microbiol Res</source>
          <volume>163</volume>
          <fpage>234</fpage>
          <lpage>242</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16831538</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>In&#xE9;s</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luc&#xED;a</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ana Fern&#xE1;ndez</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Dynamics, diversity and function of endophytic Siderophore-producing
bacteria in rice</article-title>
          <source>Microb Ecol</source>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>606</fpage>
          <lpage>618</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21128071</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeon</surname>
              <given-names>YH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>A plant growth promoting <italic>Paenibacillus polymyxa</italic>
strain GBR-1, suppresses root-knot nematode</article-title>
          <source>Biores Technol</source>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>3016</fpage>
          <lpage>3023</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>YC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brian</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>The multifactorial basis for plant health promotion by plant-
associated bacteria</article-title>
          <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <fpage>1548</fpage>
          <lpage>1555</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21216911</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lai</surname>
              <given-names>KP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>MY</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2012</year>
          <article-title>Control of postharvest green mold of citrus fruit by application of
endophytic <italic>Paenibacillus polymyxa</italic> strain SG-6</article-title>
          <source>Postharv Biol Technol</source>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <fpage>40</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Leite</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>AB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gomes</surname>
              <given-names>FP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <article-title><italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> and <italic>Enterobacter cloacae</italic>
endophytes from healthy <italic>Theobroma cacao</italic> L. trees can systemically
colonize seedlings and promote growth</article-title>
          <source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>2639</fpage>
          <lpage>2651</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23212670</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ye</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Determination of five major iridoid glucosides in Flos Lonicerae by
high-performance liquid chromatography coupled with evaporative light scattering
detection</article-title>
          <source>J Chromatogr A</source>
          <volume>1008</volume>
          <fpage>167</fpage>
          <lpage>172</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12967181</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>NY</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2010</year>
          <article-title>Study on isolation and identification endophytic fungi and
antibacterial activity of <italic>Flos Lonicerae</italic>
</article-title>
          <source>Chin J Antibiot</source>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>236</fpage>
          <lpage>238</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sinkko</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Montonen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2012</year>
          <article-title>Biogeography of symbiotic and other endophytic bacteria isolated from
medicinal <italic>Glycyrrhiza</italic> species in China</article-title>
          <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>46</fpage>
          <lpage>68</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22066910</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qiao</surname>
              <given-names>HP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>LL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Biological control of take-all in wheat by endophytic <italic>Bacillus
subtilis</italic> E1R-j and potential mode of action</article-title>
          <source>Biol Control</source>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>277</fpage>
          <lpage>285</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Loaces</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luc&#xED;a</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ana</surname>
              <given-names>FS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Dynamics, diversity and function of endophytic siderophore-producing
bacteria in rice</article-title>
          <source>Microb Ecol</source>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>606</fpage>
          <lpage>618</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21128071</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mani</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>YM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Inoculation of endophytic bacteria on host and non-host plants-effects
on plant growth and Ni uptake</article-title>
          <source>J Hazard Mater</source>
          <volume>195</volume>
          <fpage>230</fpage>
          <lpage>237</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21872991</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mar&#xED;a</surname>
              <given-names>SO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mar&#xED;a</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mar&#xED;a</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <article-title>Toxigenic profile and AFLP variability of <italic>Alternaria
alternata</italic> and <italic>Alternaria infectoria</italic> occurring on
wheat</article-title>
          <source>Braz J Microbiol</source>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>447</fpage>
          <lpage>455</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24294236</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mehnaz</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lazarovits</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Inoculation effects of <italic>Pseudomonas putida, Gluconacetobacter
azotocaptans</italic>, and <italic>Azospirillum lipoferum</italic> on corn
plant growth under greenhouse conditions</article-title>
          <source>Microb Ecol</source>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>326</fpage>
          <lpage>335</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16598630</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miller</surname>
              <given-names>KI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qing</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sze</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2012a</year>
          <article-title>Culturable endophytes of medicinal plants and the genetic basis for
their bioactivity</article-title>
          <source>Microb Ecol</source>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <fpage>431</fpage>
          <lpage>449</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22430508</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miller</surname>
              <given-names>KI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qing</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sze</surname>
              <given-names>DMY</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2012b</year>
          <article-title>Investigation of the biosynthetic potential of endophytes in
traditional Chinese anticancer herbs</article-title>
          <source>Plos One</source>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <elocation-id/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moulin</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>B&#xE9;na</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boivin-Masson</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Phylogenetic analyses of symbiotic nodulation genes support vertical
and lateral gene co-transfer within the <italic>Bradyrhizobium</italic>
genus</article-title>
          <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>720</fpage>
          <lpage>732</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012950</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <collab>Mphprc</collab>
          </person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <source>Pharmacopoeia of the People's Republic of China</source>
          <publisher-name>Chemical Industry Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>
          <fpage>177</fpage>
          <lpage>177</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Patten</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glick</surname>
              <given-names>BR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>The role of bacterial indoleacetic acid in the development of the host
plant root system</article-title>
          <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>3795</fpage>
          <lpage>3801</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12147474</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <element-citation publication-type="confproc">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ramirez</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sturm</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oviedo</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <source>Alternaria species isolated from wheat in Argentina</source>
          <conf-name>Proceeding of Myco-Globe: Reducing Impact of Mycotoxins in Tropical
Agriculture</conf-name>
          <conf-loc>Acra, Ghana</conf-loc>
          <fpage>35</fpage>
          <lpage>35</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Raza</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>XM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Isolation and characterization of fusaricidin-type compound-producing
strain of <italic>Paenibacillu polymyxa</italic> SQR-21 active against
<italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f. sp. <italic>nevium</italic>
</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Plant Pathol</source>
          <volume>125</volume>
          <fpage>471</fpage>
          <lpage>483</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Richardson</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barea</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McNeill</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2009</year>
          <article-title>Acquisition of phosphorus and nitrogen in the rhizosphere and plant
growth promotion by microorganisms</article-title>
          <source>Plant Soil</source>
          <volume>321</volume>
          <fpage>305</fpage>
          <lpage>339</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saitou</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nei</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1987</year>
          <article-title>The neighbor-joining method: a new method for reconstructing
phylogenetic trees</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>406</fpage>
          <lpage>425</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3447015</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schwyn</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neilands</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1987</year>
          <article-title>Universal chemical assay for the detection and determination of
siderophores</article-title>
          <source>Anal Biochem</source>
          <volume>160</volume>
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          <lpage>56</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2952030</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sessitsch</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hardoim</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D&#xF6;ring</surname>
              <given-names>WA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2012</year>
          <article-title>Functional characteristics of an endophyte community colonizing rice
roots as revealed by metagenomic analysis</article-title>
          <source>MPMI</source>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>28</fpage>
          <lpage>36</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21970692</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sundara-Rao</surname>
              <given-names>WVB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sinha</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1963</year>
          <article-title>Phosphate dissolving microorganisms in the soil and
rhizosphere</article-title>
          <source>Indian J Agr Sci</source>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>272</fpage>
          <lpage>278</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Van Berkum</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beyene</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eardly</surname>
              <given-names>BD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1996</year>
          <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships among <italic>Rhizobium</italic> species
nodulating the common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>
L.)</article-title>
          <source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>240</fpage>
          <lpage>244</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Van de Peer</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wachter</surname>
              <given-names>YDR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1997</year>
          <article-title>Construction of evolutionary distance trees with TREECON for Windows:
accounting for variation in nucleotide substitution rate among
sites</article-title>
          <source>Comput Appl Biosci</source>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>227</fpage>
          <lpage>230</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9183524</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Venieraki</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dimou</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pergalis</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>The genetic diversity of culturable nitrogen-fixing bacteria in the
rhizosphere of wheat</article-title>
          <source>Microb Ecol</source>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>277</fpage>
          <lpage>285</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20857096</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Verma</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ladha</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tripathi</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>Evaluation of plant growth promoting and colonization ability of
endophytic diazotrophs from deep water rice</article-title>
          <source>J Biotechnol</source>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>127</fpage>
          <lpage>141</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11566385</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vincent</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1970</year>
          <source>The cultivation, isolation and maintenance of Rhizobia. A
Manual for the practical study of the root-nodule bacteria international
biological programme handbook</source>
          <publisher-name>Blackwell Scientific</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>13</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B45">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Effect of chlorogenic acid on antioxidant activity of Flos Lonicerae
extracts</article-title>
          <source>J Zhejiang Univ Sci B</source>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>673</fpage>
          <lpage>679</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17726749</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B46">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wulff</surname>
              <given-names>EG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Vuurde</surname>
              <given-names>JWL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hockenhull</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>The ability of the biological control agent <italic>Bacillus
subtilis</italic>, strain BB, to colonise vegetable brassicas endophytically
following seed inoculation</article-title>
          <source>Plant and Soil</source>
          <volume>255</volume>
          <fpage>463</fpage>
          <lpage>474</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B47">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dai</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2013</year>
          <article-title>Isolation and characteristic of endophytic bacteria in medicinal plant
<italic>Flos Lonicerae</italic>
</article-title>
          <source>Guandong Agr Sci</source>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>121</fpage>
          <lpage>124</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B48">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2011</year>
          <article-title>Identification and characterization of the endophytic plant growth
prompter <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> strain MQ23 isolated from
<italic>Sophora alopecuroides</italic> root nodules</article-title>
          <source>Braz J Microbiol</source>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>567</fpage>
          <lpage>575</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24031669</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
