<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4021350</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2229-14-107</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24766773</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-14-107</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Homologous haplotypes, expression, genetic effects and geographic distribution of the wheat yield gene <italic>TaGW2</italic></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Qin</surname>
            <given-names>Lin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>qinlin1115@163.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>Chenyang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>haochy74@163.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Hou</surname>
            <given-names>Jian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>windtalker.127@163.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Yuquan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>wyq315705686@126.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Tian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>ltlt9869@163.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Lanfen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>wanglanfen@caas.cn</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7">
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>Zhengqiang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>zqm2@njau.edu.cn</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A8">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Xueyong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>zhangxueyong@caas.cn</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Key Laboratory of Crop Gene Resources and Germplasm Enhancment, Ministry of Agriculture/The National Key Facility for Crop Gene Resources and Genetic Improvement/Institute of Crop Science, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing 100081, China</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Crop Genomics and Bioinformatics Center and National Key Lab of Crop Genetics and Germplasm Enhancement, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing 210095, Jiangsu, China</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>107</fpage>
      <lpage>107</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>9</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2014 Qin et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Qin et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2229/14/107"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p><italic>TaGW2-6A</italic>, cloned in earlier research, strongly influences wheat grain width and TKW. Here, we mainly analyzed haplotypes of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and their effects on TKW and interaction with haplotypes at <italic>TaGW2-6A.</italic></p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>About 2.9&#xA0;kb of the promoter sequences of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> were cloned in 34 bread wheat cultivars. Eleven SNPs were detected in the promoter region of <italic>TaGW2-6B,</italic> forming 4 haplotypes, but no divergence was detected in the <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> promoter or coding region. Three molecular markers including CAPS, dCAPS and ACAS, were developed to distinguish the <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotypes. Haplotype association analysis indicated that <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> has a stronger influence than <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> on TKW, and <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> was a favored haplotype increasing grain width and weight that had undergone strong positive selection in global wheat breeding. However, clear geographic distribution differences for <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> haplotypes were found; <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> was favored in Chinese, Australian and Russian cultivars, whereas <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic> was preferred in European, American and CIMMYT cultivars. This difference might be caused by a flowering and maturity time difference between the two haplotypes. <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> is the earlier type. Haplotype interaction analysis between <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> showed additive effects between the favored haplotypes. <italic>Hap-6A-A/Hap-6B-1</italic> was the best combination to increase TKW. Relative expression analysis of the three <italic>TaGW2</italic> homoeologous genes in 22 cultivars revealed that <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> underwent the highest expression. <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> was the least expressed during grain development and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> was intermediate. Diversity of the three genes was negatively correlated with their effect on TKW.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>Genetic effects, expression patterns and historic changes of haplotypes at three homoeologous genes of <italic>TaGW2</italic> influencing yield were dissected in wheat cultivars. Strong and constant selection to favored haplotypes has been found in global wheat breeding during the past century. This research also provides a valuable case for understanding interaction of genes that control complex traits in polyploid species.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>TaGW2</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>Grain weight</kwd>
        <kwd>Gene expression</kwd>
        <kwd>Haplotype interaction</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Common wheat is a hexaploid species (AABBDD) with a large genome size (17.9&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>9</sup>&#xA0;bp) and abundant repeat sequences (&gt;80%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Comparative genomics proved the existence of genomic colinearity among cereal crops [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. As a model plant of cereals, the rice genomic sequence completed in 2002 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], and several yield-related genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], such as <italic>GS3</italic>, <italic>GW2</italic>, <italic>GW5</italic>, <italic>GW8</italic>, <italic>TGW6</italic>, <italic>Ghd7</italic> and <italic>GIF1</italic>, have been isolated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], providing opportunities for homology-based cloning of yield-related genes in other cereals. The availability of a draft wheat genome sequence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] will promote genome-based research of this extremely important crop. Cloning yield-related genes, exploring the favored alleles and developing functional markers will be important for yield improvement in that crop. This will be the next major focus of wheat genetics and genomics.</p>
      <p>Among yield-related genes, current studies on gene function and allele discovery of <italic>GW2</italic> are the most in-depth and extensive in cereal crops. Firstly, Song <italic>et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] isolated a major yield QTL from rice, which was mapped on short arm of chromosome 2 and designated as <italic>OsGW2</italic>. It encoded a RING-type protein with E3 ubiquitin ligase activity that negatively regulated grain width, and loss-of-function mutations enhanced grain weight and yield. In maize, Li <italic>et al.</italic> (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] found two homologs of <italic>OsGW2</italic>, viz. <italic>ZmGW2-CHR4</italic> and <italic>ZmGW2-CHR5</italic>, and a SNP in the promoter region of <italic>ZmGW2-CHR4</italic> was significantly associated with kernel width (KW) and hundred kernel weight (HKW) in maize. We cloned <italic>TaGW2</italic> from chromosome 6A of wheat, and found SNPs in its promoter region, that were significantly associated with KW and TKW. A CAPS marker was developed based on the -593 A/G polymorphism and association analysis indicated that <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> increased TKW by more than 3.1&#xA0;g [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Recently, a <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic>-CAPS marker was used to detect variation in a BC<sub>2</sub>F<sub>4</sub> RIL population, as well as a natural population, further demonstrating that <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> was significantly associated with grain weight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Yang <italic>et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] identified a single-base insertion in the eighth exon of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> causing premature termination in landrace Lankaodali, which ultimately led to increased grain width and grain weight. However, Bednarek <italic>et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] showed that the patterns of <italic>TaGW2</italic> regulation of grain development might be more complex after studies on RNA interference (RNAi) of expression of <italic>TaGW2</italic> in wheat. In consideration of the characteristics of the wheat genome, further dissection of the regulation and expression patterns of the three <italic>TaGW2</italic> homoeologous genes on grain weight could have important biological and breeding implications.</p>
      <p>In this study, further research focused on sequencing and diversity studies of the promoter regions of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic>, functional marker development, and an expression pattern comparison of the three homoeologous <italic>TaGW2</italic> loci. Hence, the major objectives were to (1) reveal sequence diversity and distribution characteristics of the three <italic>GW2</italic> homoeologous genes by sequence alignment of their ~2.9&#xA0;kb promoter regions; (2) develop functional markers for <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> to distinguish various haplotypes, and discover favored haplotypes for yield improvement through association analysis; (3) evaluate the distributions of different haplotypes in global wheat major production regions, including North America, Europe, Australia, Russia, Mexico and China, and understand the selection intensity and geographical distribution of <italic>TaGW2s</italic> in different wheat ecological regions; (4) assess the relationships between the expression levels of the three <italic>TaGW2</italic> homoeologues and grain size by real-time PCR analysis, and preliminarily evaluate the genetic effects of <italic>TaGW2s</italic> based on phenotypic variation (<italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>) for grain traits; and (5) examine interactions among the three <italic>TaGW2</italic> loci on chromosomes 6A, 6B and 6D through haplotype combination analysis. It was expected that the study would identify important genes and functional markers for wheat yield improvement.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Major variations in <italic>TaGW2s</italic> occur in the promoter regions</title>
        <p>In the coding sequence of <italic>TaGW2</italic> homoeologous genes, 34 wheat accessions (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S3) were used to study the nucleotide polymorphism and no divergence was found. Genome walking was used to clone the sequences of the promoter regions of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic>, and ~2.9&#xA0;kb upstream sequences from the ATG start codons were obtained. The core elements of the promoters were predicted with the TSSP program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.softberry.com">http://www.softberry.com</ext-link>), and the TATA box and STS (Start Transcription Site) were identified at -159&#xA0;bp and -127&#xA0;bp upstream from the ATG codon of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic>. For <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic>, the corresponding locations were located at -162&#xA0;bp and -130&#xA0;bp, respectively. Generally, more variations in <italic>TaGW2s</italic> occurred in the promoter regions, but the diversity of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> was higher than that of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic>, in which eight SNPs forming two haplotypes were found earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. No divergence was detected in the <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> promoter region (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Four haplotypes were formed by 11 SNPs within the 2.9&#xA0;kb upstream sequence of <italic>TaGW2-6B;</italic> these were designated <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic>, <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic>, <italic>Hap-6B-3</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="F1" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Gene structures of </bold><bold><italic>TaGW2-6A, -6B </italic></bold><bold>and </bold><bold><italic>-6D.</italic></bold> Variations mainly occurred in the promoter regions.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-1"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F2" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Haplotypes and predicted </bold><bold><italic>cis</italic></bold><bold>-acting regulatory elements in the promoter regions of </bold><bold><italic>TaGW2-6A </italic></bold><bold>and </bold><bold><italic>TaGW2-6B. </italic></bold><bold>A</bold>, two haplotypes were formed by 8 SNPs in the <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> promoter region. <bold>B</bold>, four haplotypes were formed by 11 SNPs in the <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> promoter region. The ellipses mean the polymorphic sites where markers were developed. The rectangles mean cis-acting regulatory elements. ABRE, abscisic acid-responsive element; GCN4_motif, endosperm tissue-specific expression; GT1-motif, light responsive element; WUN-motif, wound responsive element; AuxRR-core, auxin responsive element; G-box, light responsive element.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-2"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Haplotypes in promoter region of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> have strong effects on TKW</title>
        <sec>
          <title>
            <italic>TaGW2-6B marker development</italic>
          </title>
          <p>In the 11 SNPs detected in the <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> promoter region (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>), the nucleotide polymorphism at -1709&#xA0;bp created a restriction enzyme recognition site for <italic>BstNI</italic> (CCWGG) (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>A). This was employed to develop a cleaved amplified polymorphism sequence (CAPS) marker to distinguish <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> from the other three haplotypes. No restriction enzyme recognition site was found in <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> (-1709A), whereas it existed in the other three haplotypes (-1709C). In addition, ACAS-PCR primer sets designed for SNP-83&#xA0;T/C worked well and were co-dominant (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>B). The forward primer for ACAS-PCR was genome-specific, and the reverse was allele-specific with artificial mismatches in the 3&#x2032;-end. <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic> amplified a fragment of 626&#xA0;bp, whereas <italic>Hap-6B-3</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> amplified a 464&#xA0;bp fragment. Thus, the ACAS-PCR primer sets reliably discriminated <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic> and the other two haplotypes. Finally, only one SNP difference was found at -721&#xA0;bp for discriminating <italic>Hap-6B-3</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic>. The dCAPS marker was designed with a specific mismatch in the primer to introduce a restriction enzyme Hpy166II recognition site (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>C) using an available program dCAPS Finder 2.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://helix.wustl.edu/dcaps/dcaps.html">http://helix.wustl.edu/dcaps/dcaps.html</ext-link>). This marker effectively discriminated <italic>Hap-6B-3</italic> (263&#xA0;bp) and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> (240&#xA0;bp). Thus, three markers, <italic>TaGW2</italic>-6B-CAPS, <italic>TaGW2</italic>-6B-dCAPS and <italic>TaGW2</italic>-6B-ACAS, were developed to distinguish these haplotypes.</p>
          <fig id="F3" position="float">
            <label>Figure 3</label>
            <caption>
              <p><bold>Marker development and genetic mapping of </bold><bold><italic>TaGW2-6B. </italic></bold><bold>A</bold>, CAPS marker was developed using nucleotide polymorphism at -1709&#xA0;bp; <bold>B</bold>, ACAS-PCR marker was designed for SNP-83&#xA0;T/C; <bold>C</bold>, dCAPS marker was based on one SNP difference at -721&#xA0;bp; <bold>D</bold>, All of the markers based on polymorphisms in the upstream region of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> were mapped on chromosome 6B in common wheat. All wheat accessions used in this study for developing markers were listed in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S3.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-3"/>
          </fig>
          <p>Tests on a set of Chinese Spring (CS) nullisomic-tetrasomic lines confirmed that the three markers were chromosome 6B-specific (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>D). The <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> gene was mapped between the markers <italic>Xmag359</italic> and <italic>Xwmc341</italic> on chromosome 6B in the recombinant inbred line (RIL) population derived from Nanda 2419 and Wangshuibai (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1). Based on the wheat consensus SSR genetic map [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> was very close to the 6B centromere.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Strong differences in TKW and heading date exist between <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotypes</title>
        <p>All three molecular markers, distinguishing the four <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> promoter haplotypes were used for genotyping the 265 entries in the Chinese wheat mini-core collection. Previous studies had demonstrated that these accessions were clustered into two sub-populations comprising 151 landraces and 114 modern cultivars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] by Structure v2.1 software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Therefore, association analysis between haplotypes of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and grain traits took population structure into account.</p>
        <p>There were significant differences in TKW between <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> in the landraces (<italic>P &lt;0.01</italic> in 2002, <italic>P &lt;0.05</italic> in 2006), and phenotypic differences between them were 6.38&#xA0;g and 4.68&#xA0;g in 2002 and 2006, respectively (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). This might be caused by differences in KL between <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> (0.43&#xA0;mm in 2002, 0.49&#xA0;mm in 2006). Among modern cultivars, significant differences were again detected in TKW between <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> (<italic>P &lt;0.01</italic> in 2002 and 2006), and the mean TKW differences of <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> were 16.68&#xA0;g and 15.25&#xA0;g. These differences were due to large differences in KW and KT (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). KW differences between the two groups were 0.45&#xA0;mm and 0.39&#xA0;mm, the KT differences were 0.45&#xA0;mm and 0.33&#xA0;mm, respectively. The significant negative effect of <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> may be the major reason for its elimination in breeding. Compared with the other three haplotypes, <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> was the favored one that increased grain weight. It was noteworthy that <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic> was quite close to <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> in effect on grain weight in modern Chinese cultivars.</p>
        <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
              <bold>
                <italic>TaGW2-6B </italic>
              </bold>
              <bold>haplotype associations with grain traits in two environments</bold>
            </p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
            <colgroup>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead valign="top">
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">
                  <bold>Trait/genotype</bold>
                </th>
                <th colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>02LY</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </th>
                <th colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>06LY</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Hap-6B-3</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Hap-6B-3</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody valign="top">
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>Overall</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.77&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06a (A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.58&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06ab (AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.40&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05bc(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.27&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.09c(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.73&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.56&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06a(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.35&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06b(BC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.15&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08b(C)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KW (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.23&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.15&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.04&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02b(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.91&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04c(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.29&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.19&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02b(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.11&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02c(BC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.05&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03c(C)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KT(mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.90&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.84&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.79&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02b(BC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.67&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04c(C)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.93&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.86&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02b(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.80&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02bc(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.74&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03c(B)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL/KW ratio<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.10&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.09&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.11&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.16&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.05&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.05&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.02&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">TKW (g)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">40.39&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.71a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">36.72&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.88b(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">33.89&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.72c(BC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">29.35&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.89d(C)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">40.99&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.72a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">36.94&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.83b(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">33.88&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.60c(BC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">31.20&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.82c(C)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>Landraces</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.70&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.16a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.38&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.36&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06b<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.27&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.10b<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.64&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.13a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.38&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.33&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.15&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.09b(B)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KW (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.01&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.01&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.01&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.92&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.13&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.11&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.10&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KT (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.79&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.77&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.77&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.69&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.83&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.79&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.78&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.75&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL/KW ratio<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.23&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.12&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.12&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.16&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.13&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.05&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.01&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">TKW (g)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">36.08&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.03a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">32.44&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.02ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">33.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.70ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">29.70&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.90b(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">36.21&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.76a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">32.50&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.79b<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">33.29&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.60ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">31.53&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.81b<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>Modern cultivars</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.79&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.80&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.63&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.09a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.22&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.76&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.76&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.10a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.48&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.15a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.13&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KW (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.30&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.30&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.23&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06a(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.85&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.10b(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.34&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.29&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.21&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.95&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.15b<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KT (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.94&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.90&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.91&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.49&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.11b(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.96&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.94&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.91&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.63&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.13b<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL/KW ratio<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.19&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.03&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.02&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.09&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.12a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">TKW (g)</td>
                <td align="left">41.77&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.59a(A)</td>
                <td align="left">41.32&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.08a(A)</td>
                <td align="left">39.71&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.16a(A)</td>
                <td align="left">25.09&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.62b(B)</td>
                <td align="left">42.52&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.67a(A)</td>
                <td align="left">41.70&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.09a(A)</td>
                <td align="left">37.98&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.81ab(AB)</td>
                <td align="left">27.27&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.39b(B)</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <p>02LY, Luoyang (2002); 06LY, Luoyang (2006).</p>
            <p>Different capital and small letters within groups indicate significance differences between haplotypes at <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01 and <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05 for each trait, respectively.</p>
            <p>*<italic>Hap-6B-1</italic>, landraces, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;20; Modern cultivars, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;62.</p>
            <p>*<italic>Hap-6B-2</italic>, landraces, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;44; Modern cultivars, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;41.</p>
            <p>*<italic>Hap-6B-3</italic>, landraces, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;63; Modern cultivars, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;9.</p>
            <p>*<italic>Hap-6B-4</italic>, landraces, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;24; Modern cultivars, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;2.</p>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>In addition to kernel weight, haplotype association analyses of heading and maturity dates were also performed (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>: Figure S2). There were no significant differences between <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> among the landraces for the two traits, but among modern cultivars heading and maturity date differences between <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> in both growing seasons were significant. The heading dates in 2002 and 2006 differed by 13 and 9&#xA0;days and the corresponding differences for maturity date were 15 and 6&#xA0;days, respectively. Similarly, <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic> was also 11 and 6&#xA0;days earlier than <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> in heading in the two seasons. For maturity, <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic> was 13 and 4&#xA0;days earlier than <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> in the two seasons respectively. Therefore, it seemed that <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic> were associated not only with larger grain, but also earlier maturity.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Geographic distribution and frequency changes among haplotypes of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic>, and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> in global wheat breeding</title>
        <sec>
          <title>
            <italic>Geographic distribution of TaGW2-6B haplotypes in Chinese wheats</italic>
          </title>
          <p>Wheat production in China is divided into ten ecological zones based on cultivar ecotypes, growing season, and cultivar response to temperature and photoperiod [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. The distribution of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotypes was evaluated in both landraces and modern cultivars from each zone (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Among landraces, selection pressure on haplotypes in the different zones was not as strong as expected, and the frequency of the favored haplotype <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> was generally low. In the winter wheat zones III, IV, V and IX, the frequency of <italic>Hap-6B-3</italic> was highest, whereas in spring wheat zones VI and X, <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic> was more frequent, and <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> was relatively frequent only in zone VII. However, in modern cultivars, <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> frequencies were higher across all zones (up to 90%), indicating it had undergone strong positive selection during wheat improvement. In detail, <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> was the most frequent haplotype in zones II, V, VI and VII, whereas <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic> was most frequent in IV, VIII, IX and X. Association analysis showed that grain size and component parameters of <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic> were significantly higher than those of <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic>, although they were lower than those of <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Compared with landraces, <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic> frequencies were higher across the ecological zones, presumably due to selective breeding, hence becoming the most frequent haplotypes. In contrast, the frequencies of <italic>Hap-6B-3</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> significantly decreased and even disappeared in zones IX, VI and VII (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>).</p>
          <fig id="F4" position="float">
            <label>Figure 4</label>
            <caption>
              <p><bold><italic>TaGW2-6B </italic></bold><bold>haplotype distribution in ten Chinese wheat ecological regions. A</bold>, <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotype distribution in 151 Chinese landraces; <bold>B</bold>, <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotype distribution in 320 modern cultivars. I, Northern winter wheat region; II, Yellow and Huai River valley winter wheat region; III, Low and middle Yangtze River valley winter wheat region; IV, Southwestern winter wheat region; V, Southern winter wheat region; VI, Northeastern spring wheat region; VII, Northern spring wheat region; VIII, Northwestern spring wheat region; IX, Qinghai-Tibet spring-winter wheat region; X, Xinjiang winter-spring wheat region.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-4"/>
          </fig>
          <p>Further evidence showing that <italic>TaGW2</italic>-6B underwent strong selection in Chinese wheat breeding is provided in Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>. The frequency of <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> showed an increasing trend, especially in the 2000s (frequencies higher than 90%). Thus this haplotype tended towards fixation during modern breeding. In contrast, <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-3</italic> disappeared from cultivars released after the 1980s.</p>
          <fig id="F5" position="float">
            <label>Figure 5</label>
            <caption>
              <p>
                <bold>Haplotype frequencies of </bold>
                <bold>
                  <italic>TaGW2-6B </italic>
                </bold>
                <bold>in 151 landraces and 320 modern cultivars released in different periods in China.</bold>
              </p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-5"/>
          </fig>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Global distributions of haplotypes for <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic></title>
        <p>Previous study showed that <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> was favored in China, whereas <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic> was favored in Europe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. In order to evaluate the distribution of all <italic>TaGW2</italic> haplotypes in global wheat cultivars, the frequencies of haplotypes at the <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> loci were determined in cultivar collections from North America, Australia, China, CIMMYT, Europe and Russia (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="F6" position="float">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Geographic distribution of haplotypes at </bold><bold><italic>TaGW2-6A </italic></bold><bold>haplotypes and </bold><bold><italic>TaGW2-6B </italic></bold><bold>in global wheat cultivars. A</bold>, Geographic distribution of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> haplotypes in 320 Chinese, 374 European, 471 American, 51 Australian, 53 CIMMYT and 83 Russian accessions; <bold>B</bold>, Geographic distribution of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotypes. North America; II, CIMMYT; III, Europe; IV, Former USSR; V, China; VI, Australia.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-6"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Obvious geographic differences in haplotype frequencies for <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> were found among the different groups. <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> was more frequent in Australian, Chinese and Russian cultivars, whereas <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic> predominated in U.S., CIMMYT and European collections (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>: Figure S3). At <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic>, the superior haplotype <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> was more frequent in all regions, and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> was virtually absent in all groups. Selection pressure on <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> in North America and Europe was apparently very low, in contrast to China, and <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic> tended to dominate (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>: Figure S3A-B). The favored haplotype <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> at <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> showed a slow growth trend, while <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> gradually decreased or disappeared in all continents (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>: Figure S3C-D). Therefore, an obvious consistency of globally favored haplotypes was detected at <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic>, but not at <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title><italic>TaGW2</italic> genes negatively regulate wheat grain weight</title>
        <p>The average expression level of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> reached a peak at 15 dpf and was significantly higher than that of either <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> or <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> in all six sampling stages of seed development (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>A). The average relative expression of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> peaked at 10 dpf, and that of <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> was 15 dpf. The average relative expression level of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> was higher than that of <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> in all six stages except 15 dpf.</p>
        <fig id="F7" position="float">
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Mean relative expression levels of </bold><bold><italic>TaGW2 </italic></bold><bold>in 22 wheat accessions at different stages of grain development. A</bold>, Mean relative expression levels of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic>, <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic>; <bold>B</bold>, Mean relative expression levels of haplotypes of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic>. First Y-axis means relative expression levels of <italic>TaGW2</italic>. Secondary Y-axis means average Ct values of actin and <italic>Ta2776</italic> genes in cultivars at different stages of grain development. As endogenous control, the actin and Ta2776 genes were not varying too much at different stages. Normalized values of <italic>TaGW2</italic> relative expression to actin were given as Mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-7"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Differences in average relative expression of <italic>TaGW2 genes</italic> were detected between the 10 higher-TKW cultivars and 12 lower-TKW genotypes. Relative expression of all <italic>TaGW2</italic>s in the lower-TKW group peaked at 15 dpf. In the other group, <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> also peaked at 15 dpf, but <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> peaked at 10 dpf (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>: Figure S4). Interestingly, the average relative expression level of the three <italic>TaGW2</italic> homoeologous genes in cultivars with lower TKW was higher than that of higher-TKW genotypes in developing seeds, whereas only small differences occurred in mature seeds (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>: Figure S4). This further confirmed that all three <italic>TaGW2</italic> homoeologous genes negatively regulated grain weight.</p>
        <p>Association analysis showed that haplotypes <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic> at <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> were significantly associated with higher TKW, whereas <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> were associated with lower TKW [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The same set of 22 cultivars was used for further analysis of the relationship between relative expression levels of various <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotypes and kernel traits (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>: Figure S5, Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>B). As shown in (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>: Figure S5), the average relative expression level of <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic> was higher than that of <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> at all periods except 25 dpf, and was also very obvious at 15 dpf (approximately 1.8 times higher). The average relative expression of <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> was lower than other haplotypes (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>B), especially at 15 dpf. All of these results further suggested that <italic>TaGW2s</italic> negatively regulate grain weight by controlling the gene expression level during seed development.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Additive genetic effects between favored haplotypes at <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic></title>
        <p>To reveal combination effects between haplotypes at <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic>, an analysis was carried out on the 265 accessions mainly coming from the Chinese wheat mini core collection (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>: Figure S6, Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Eight combinations of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotypes were detected in landraces, but there were only seven in modern cultivars, the exception was <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic>/<italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> (<italic>A/4</italic>). No significant phenotypic differences were detected among these combination types in landraces (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). In modern cultivars, there were significant differences between <italic>A/1</italic> (<italic>Hap-6A-A</italic>/<italic>Hap-6B-1</italic>) and <italic>G/4</italic> (<italic>Hap-6A-G</italic>/<italic>Hap-6B-4</italic>) on KT, KW and TKW, and combination <italic>A/1</italic> was a favored type, consistent with the earlier results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). Combination <italic>A/2</italic> (<italic>Hap-6A-A</italic>/<italic>Hap-6B-2</italic>) was close to <italic>A/1</italic>, and much higher in TKW than <italic>G/4</italic>. Comparative analysis of phenotypic effects among the favored combination and superior single and other haplotypes (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>) further revealed that these homoeologous genes had a strong additive effect on KW and TKW. Moreover, the favored haplotype combination <italic>A/1</italic> occurred at a higher frequency in the modern cultivars than in landraces, whereas small grained G/4 was the opposite (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S8">8</xref>: Figure S7). These results indicate that combination <italic>A/1</italic> had undergone strong positive selection in wheat breeding due to its positive effect on grain size.</p>
        <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
              <bold>Effects of </bold>
              <bold>
                <italic>TaGW2-6A </italic>
              </bold>
              <bold>and </bold>
              <bold>
                <italic>TaGW2-6B </italic>
              </bold>
              <bold>haplotype interaction on grain traits in two environments</bold>
            </p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
            <colgroup>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead valign="top">
              <tr>
                <th align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>Trait/genotype</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </th>
                <th colspan="8" align="center" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>02LY</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">&#xA0;</th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>A/1</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>A/2</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>A/3</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>A/4</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>G/1</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>G/2</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>G/3</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>G/4</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody valign="top">
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>Overall</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.79&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.66&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08abc(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.36&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06bc(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.11&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.17abc(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.73&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.11&#xA0;ac(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.51&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.09abc(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.44&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08abc(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.31&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.10c(B)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KW (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.28&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.25&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.05&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03b(BC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.05&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03abc(ABC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.15&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03b(BC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.03&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03bc(BC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.88&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04c(C)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KT (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.91&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.89&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.78&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03b(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.86&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05abc(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.89&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.79&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03b(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.80&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.63&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04c(B)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL/KW ratio<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.08&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.05&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.09&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.00&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.15&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.13&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.13&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.20&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05b<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">TKW (g)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">41.33&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.80a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">39.35&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.25a(ACD)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">33.57&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.91bc(BE)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">33.34&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.64abc(ABE)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">38.98&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.28ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">34.59&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.16b(BCE)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">34.35&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.17b(BDE)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">28.39&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.93c(E)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>Landraces</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.71&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.21a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.40&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.11a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.33&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.11&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.17a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.70&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.23a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.37&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.10a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.41&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.09a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.32&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.12a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KW (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.02&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.11&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.01&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.05&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.01&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.97&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.01&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.88&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04b(B)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KT (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.67&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.79&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.76&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.86&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.87&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.76&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.79&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.64&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05b<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL/KW ratio<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.23&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.11&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.00&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.23&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.15&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.13&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.20&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">TKW(g)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">34.38&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.55ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">34.33&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.76ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">32.63&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.84ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">33.34&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.64ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">37.22&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.96a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">31.64&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.24ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">33.68&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.22ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">28.74&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.95b(B)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>Modern cultivars</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.81&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.79&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.10a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.59&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.16a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.75&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.11a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.80&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.15a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.68&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.22&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KW (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.33&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.33&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.29&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.23&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.24&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.15&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.09ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.85&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.10b(B)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KT (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.96&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.95&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.94&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.90&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.84&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.88&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.11ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.49&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.11b(B)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL/KW ratio<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.05&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.04&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.00&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.10&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.10&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.13&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.19&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">TKW(g)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">42.68&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.65a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">41.97&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.41a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">40.53&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.09a(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">39.99&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.11a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">40.30&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.69a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">38.69&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.37ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">25.09&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.62b(B)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td colspan="8" align="center" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>06LY</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>A/1</italic>
                  </bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>A/2</italic>
                  </bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>A/3</italic>
                  </bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>A/4</italic>
                  </bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>G/1</italic>
                  </bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>G/2</italic>
                  </bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>G/3</italic>
                  </bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>G/4</italic>
                  </bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>Overall</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.71&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.60&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.10ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.30&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07bc(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.05&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.13abc(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.75&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.09a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.53&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08abc(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.42&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.10abc(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.17&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.09c(B)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KW (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.34&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.24&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03acd(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.12&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03bf(BC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.12&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07abf(ABC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.20&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04bc(ABC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.15&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03bdf(BC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.10&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02bef(BC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.03&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03f(C)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KT(mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.93&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.86&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.76&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02bc(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.83&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04abc(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.93&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.85&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03abc(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.85&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02abc(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.72&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03c(B)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL/KW ratio<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.01&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.04&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.02&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">1.95&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.11&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.08&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.07&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.04&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">TKW (g)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">41.85&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.84a(A)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">39.09&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.25acde(AC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">33.38&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.83b(B)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">32.48&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.09cb(AB)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">39.70&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.28&#xA0;ac(AC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">35.19&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.05bd(BC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">34.57&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.83be(BC)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">30.89&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.90bf(BD)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>Landraces</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.52&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.20a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.33&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.11a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.26&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.05&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.13a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.72&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.18a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.40&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.09a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.42&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.11a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.18&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.10a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KW (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.13&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.12&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.10&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.12&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.13&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.10&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.10&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.04&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KT (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.74&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.73&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.74&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.83&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.88&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.81&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.83&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.73&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL/KW ratio<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.09&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.03&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.03&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">1.95&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.15&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.07&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.08&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.03&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">TKW (g)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">34.22&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.28ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">33.24&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.21ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">32.69&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.83ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">32.48&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.09ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">37.55&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.51a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">32.19&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.00ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">34.15&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.83ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">31.27&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.89b<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>Modern cultivars</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.75&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.74&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.13a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.53&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.16a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.77&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.09a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.79&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.15a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.41&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.29a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.13&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KW (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.38&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.31&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.28&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.24&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.25&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">3.11&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.95&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.15b<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KT (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.97&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.93&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.89&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.07ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.95&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.03ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.95&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.94&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.06ab<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.63&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.13b<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL/KW ratio<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.00&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.02a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.04&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">1.99&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.05a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.09&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.09&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.08a<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.09&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.12a<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">TKW (g)</td>
                <td align="left">43.34&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.70a(A)</td>
                <td align="left">42.14&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.47a(AB)</td>
                <td align="left">38.47&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.49ab(AB)</td>
                <td align="left">&#xA0;</td>
                <td align="left">40.93&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.39a(AB)</td>
                <td align="left">41.01&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.65a(AB)</td>
                <td align="left">37.36&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.02ab(AB)</td>
                <td align="left">27.27&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.39b(B)</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <p>02LY, Luoyang (2002); 06LY, Luoyang (2006).</p>
            <p>Different capital and small letters indicate significant between haplotypes at <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01 and <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05.</p>
            <p>*<italic>A/1</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-A/Hap-6B-1</italic>; landraces, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;8; Modern cultivars, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;41.</p>
            <p>*<italic>A/2</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-A/Hap-6B-2</italic>; landraces, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;13; Modern cultivars, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;25.</p>
            <p>*<italic>A/3</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-A/Hap-6B-3</italic>; landraces, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;37; Modern cultivars, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;5.</p>
            <p>*<italic>A/4</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-A/Hap-6B-4</italic>; landraces, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;5; Modern cultivars, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.</p>
            <p>*<italic>G/1</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-G/Hap-6B-1</italic>; landraces, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;12; Modern cultivars, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;21.</p>
            <p>*<italic>G/2</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-G/Hap-6B-2</italic>; landraces, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;31; Modern cultivars, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;16.</p>
            <p>*<italic>G/3</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-G/Hap-6B-3</italic>; landraces, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;26; Modern cultivar, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;4.</p>
            <p>*<italic>G/4</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-G/Hap-6B-4</italic>; landraces, N&#x2009;=&#x2009;19; Modern cultivars, N&#x2009;=&#x2009;2.</p>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <fig id="F8" position="float">
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>TKWs and kernel widths for the </bold><bold><italic>Hap-6A-A/Hap-6B-1 </italic></bold><bold>combination and for single haplotypes. A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>: landraces; <bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>: modern cultivars. The bars represent the standard deviation.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-8"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title><italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> has a stronger effect than <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> on TKW</title>
        <p>Based on the haplotype polymorphisms of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic>, the phenotypic explanation rates (<italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>) for grain traits was calculated in the same set of 265 accessions (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). In landraces, <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> for grain traits in <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> was higher than that in <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic>, and the value of the combination of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic>/<italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> was higher than that of either <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> or <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> alone in both growing seasons (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). As for modern cultivars, the <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> of the combination of these two genes was still the highest, <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> followed and <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> was the lowest. Although they had the similar <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> trends in these two subpopulations, <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> of these haplotypes in the modern cultivars was significantly higher than in landraces, especially for KW and TKW. This further indicated that these grain trait-related genes had undergone strong positive selection in modern breeding, and that <italic>TaGW2</italic> controlled grain weight in terms of regulating grain width during development. In addition, the <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> values of the <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic>/<italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> combination were higher than those of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> plus <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> for all grain traits in two environments in the landraces. However, in modern cultivars, the phenotypic effect of the combination of these two haplotypes was less than that of their simple sum.</p>
        <table-wrap position="float" id="T3">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
              <bold>Phenotypic explanation rates (</bold>
              <bold>
                <italic>R</italic>
              </bold>
              <sup>
                <bold>
                  <italic>2</italic>
                </bold>
              </sup>
              <bold>) of </bold>
              <bold>
                <italic>TaGW2-6A, TaGW2-6B </italic>
              </bold>
              <bold>and their combinations for grain traits in landrace and modern cultivar subpopulations in two environments</bold>
            </p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
            <colgroup>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="center"/>
              <col align="center"/>
              <col align="center"/>
              <col align="center"/>
              <col align="center"/>
              <col align="center"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead valign="top">
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">
                  <bold>Item</bold>
                </th>
                <th colspan="3" align="center" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>02LY</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </th>
                <th colspan="3" align="center" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>06LY</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th align="center">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="center">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="center">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>TaGW2-6A/TaGW2-6B</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="center">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="center">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
                <th align="center">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>TaGW2-6A/TaGW2-6B</italic>
                  </bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody valign="top">
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Landraces<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">TKW (g)<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">0.44<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">7.17<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">10.40<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">0.09<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">6.19<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">8.52<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">0.13<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">5.77<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">6.41<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">1.12<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">6.81<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">8.57<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KW (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">3.58<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">3.76<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">9.76<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">0.27<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">1.58<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">2.33<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KT (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">0.01<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">2.71<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">9.57<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">3.47<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">1.62<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">9.52<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Modern cultivars<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">TKW (g)<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">5.79<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">13.54<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">16.82<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">3.94<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">12.88<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">14.99<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KL (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">0.26<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">3.23<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">3.49<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">0.03<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">4.84<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">5.04<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">KW (mm)<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">9.73<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">10.51<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">17.36<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">10.55<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">9.73<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">18.38<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">KT (mm)</td>
                <td align="center">8.31</td>
                <td align="center">12.08</td>
                <td align="center">17.79</td>
                <td align="center">0.36</td>
                <td align="center">8.55</td>
                <td align="center">8.97</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <p>02LY, Luoyang (2002); 06LY, Luoyang (2006).</p>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Natural diversity in cereal yield genes usually occurs in promoter and intron regions that influence gene expression levels</title>
        <p>The isolation of genes controlling grain weight in wheat and development of functional markers are desirable for marker-assisted-selection (MAS) breeding. On the basis of genetic information, several successful examples of MAS combined with phenotypic measurement have been accomplished, and these have mainly focused on improvement of discontinuous traits such as resistance to pests/disease, stress tolerance, and grain quality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. Liu <italic>et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>] recently reviewed progress in functional marker development in wheat, including the 97 markers associated with processing quality, agronomic traits and disease resistance. In this review, three markers for wheat grain weight genes were also mentioned; they were <italic>TaSus2-2B</italic>, <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaCwi-A1</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>], respectively. Among them, the CAPS marker of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> distinguished <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> and <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic> with higher accuracy and repeatability, making it an effective marker for selection of kernel weight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>].</p>
        <p>In some cereal yield genes, natural diversity usually occurred in promoter or intron regions, which influenced gene expression levels. For example, the differences in expression levels of <italic>GS5</italic> in rice are attributable to polymorphisms in the promoter region, leading to grain width variation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. Another good example is that one polymorphism in the promoter region of <italic>ZmGS3</italic> was found to affect HKW in two environments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. It is also found that one SNP in the promoter region of <italic>ZmGW2-CHR4</italic> was significantly associated with KW and HKW, and the expression level of this gene was negatively correlated with KW [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Further analysis of polymorphism in the <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> diversity in this study showed that most of the diversity existed in the promoter region of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic>, with no diversity in <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). This is consistant with findings for yield gene diversity in rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] and maize [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. In addition, the diversity of wheat yield gene <italic>TaDep1</italic> and <italic>TaSUS1-7B</italic> were also found in intron regions, which influenced gene expression levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>].</p>
        <p>Association analysis of grain traits suggested that <italic>Hap-6B-1 and Hap-6B-2</italic> were favored haplotypes (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>), and the <italic>TaGW2</italic>-6B-CAPS markers could distinguish the favored haplotypes from other haplotypes, indicating that they could be used as diagnostic markers in MAS for increased grain weight.</p>
        <p>The average TKW of <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> was about 3.1&#xA0;g higher than that of <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic> in Chinese modern cultivars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Moreover, genotypes with the <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> allele had earlier heading and maturity dates of about 3.5 and 2.5&#xA0;days than <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic> genotypes. In this study, the favored haplotype <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> also affected wheat maturity, with earlier heading and maturity dates compared to other haplotypes (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>: Figure S2). This may be caused by: (1) a hitchhiking effect of a developmentally-related gene during selection of <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> in domestication and breeding; genes affecting maturity have been mapped near the chromosome group 6 centromere regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>], or (2) a pleiotropic effect of <italic>TaGW2</italic>. The additive effect of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> combined with <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> showed that <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic>/<italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> was a superior combination conferring high TKW in modern cultivars (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>), although is effect in landraces was not. The combination effect of the two favored haplotypes was significantly higher than that of any single haplotype (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>), indicating an obvious additive effect.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Strong selection of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotypes occurred in global wheat breeding</title>
        <p>In most domesticated crops, genetic diversity differs under conditions of continuous natural and artificial selection. In this process, about 2 to 4% of maize genes (a minimum of 1,200) throughout the genome were targeted for selection during domestication and improvement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>], and many genes, such as the <italic>Waxy</italic> gene in rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>], height-reduction genes <italic>Rht-B1</italic> and <italic>Rht-D1</italic> in wheat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>], and the tomato fruit size gene <italic>fw2.2</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>] had retained a selection trace. Grain weight is a quantitative trait controlled by multiple genes and is also positively selected during domestication and breeding. In modern wheat breeding, genes controlling yield traits have undergone strong artificial selection and the frequency distributions of their variations are extremely uneven, and the alleles associated with ecological adaptation and favored agronomic traits are present at high frequency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>].</p>
        <p>Our previous study investigated the distribution of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> haplotypes in Chinese and European wheat cultivars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. In this study, the distribution of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotypes are systematically described for six major regional wheat production regions worldwide, viz. China, US, Canada, Russia, Australia, Europe and Mexico (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Haplotype <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> at <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> was favored in cultivars released in China, Australia and Russia, whereas <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic> was frequent in other areas. In addition, <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> was mainly distributed in spring and weak-winter wheat cultivars with early maturity, which was favorable to increasing the multi-cropping index, whereas in winter and strong-winter wheat cultivars <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic> was more frequent. This geographic difference in <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> haplotypes may be related to the breeding and planting environment. In contrast, the distribution of favored <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotypes tended to be more consistent across global wheat cultivars, and favored haplotypes <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic> have undergone strong positive selection and accumulation in breeding programs.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title><italic>TaGW2</italic> negatively regulates grain weight, genotypes with lower expression were positively selected in breeding</title>
        <p>In recent years scientists have been searching for key genes controlling kernel weight in cereals because it is a major component of yield. In rice, <italic>GS3</italic>, <italic>GW2</italic> and <italic>qSW5</italic> negatively regulate grain size [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. In contrast, <italic>GW8</italic> and <italic>GS5</italic> were isolated as positive regulators of grain size, and their higher expression levels could be involved in promoting cell division and ultimately increasing grain yield [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. A comparative genomics study found that the expression level of the <italic>ZmGW2-CHR4</italic> gene was negatively correlated with grain weight in maize [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>], and shared the same regulation pattern as <italic>GW2</italic> in rice. Gene <italic>TaGW2</italic> regulated grain size in wheat through variation in expression level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. SNPs in the <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> promoter region may be related to expression of different alleles, such as <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> and <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic>. The regulation pattern of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> was consistent with <italic>OsGW2</italic>, both of which negatively regulated grain width and weight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Yang <italic>et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] identified a 1&#xA0;bp insertion at the 977th base pair of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> in cultivar Lankaodali and a derived SNP marker was used to genotype an F<sub>2</sub> population derived from a cross of Lankaodali (TT) and Chinese Spring (tt). Compared with the tt genotype, the average increase in TT genotypes was 0.18&#xA0;mm for KW and 3.94&#xA0;g for TKW, indicating that <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> regulated grain width and grain weight. However, Bednarek <italic>et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] showed that RNAi resulted in down-regulation of <italic>TaGW2</italic> expression in wheat, inducing significant decreases in grain parameters (viz. final grain fresh, dry and irrigation masses, and grain volume, width, and thickness). They concluded that <italic>TaGW2</italic> positively regulated grain size in wheat. For relative expression analysis RT-PCR was performed at different seed development periods after flowering in the present study (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>: Figure S5), in order to objectively evaluate the relationship between gene expression and grain size/weight. Our results showed that the relative expression levels of the <italic>TaGW2-A/B/D</italic> orthologs in developing seeds were all negatively correlated with grain width/weight.</p>
        <p>The <italic>cis</italic>-elements in promoter regions of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> were predicted by Plantcare. More <italic>cis</italic>-elements were found on <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic> than on <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic>. Due to the SNP at -2070&#xA0;bp, there is an endosperm tissue-specific expression element GCN4_motif in <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic>, but in corresponding region of <italic>Hap-6A-G,</italic> it is an ABA response element, ABRE (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). For <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> locus<italic>,</italic> at -929&#xA0;bp, a G-box was detected in <italic>Hap-6B-3</italic> and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic>, an auxin responsive element (AuxRR-core) was found in <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> at -1709&#xA0;bp, an ABRE was detected in <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic>, <italic>Hap-6B-3</italic> and Hap-6B-4 (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The influence of these <italic>cis</italic>-elements on <italic>TaGW2</italic> expression need to be further elucidated in the future.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the average relative expression level of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> was higher than that of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic>, and the phenotypic explanation rate (<italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>) for grain traits explained by <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> was higher than that of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> in both landraces and modern cultivars (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Therefore, the lower the relative expression level of a <italic>TaGW2</italic> gene, the higher its <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> value, indicating that grain size is negatively regulated by <italic>TaGW2</italic> genes. Thus among the three <italic>TaGW2</italic> homoeologous genes, the average expression of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> during the grain development was the highest, but its <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> was the lowest. <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> gene was the most conservative with the lowest mean expression among the three homoeologous genes, and its <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> was estimated to be the highest. There are three possible reasons for lack of diversity at <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> locus. Firstly, during evolution from tetraploid to hexaploid wheat, the increase in KW was larger than that in KL. Secondly, the D genome has much lower diversity than the A- or B- genomes in common wheat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>]. Thirdly, <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> has the strongest effect on TKW, and it underwent strong positive selection and fixation in early domestication of hexaploid wheat (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Haplotypes, expression, genetic effects and geographic distribution of wheat yield gene <italic>TaGW2</italic> were analyzed. Major variations occurred at their promoter regions in the three homoeologous genes. Expression levels of <italic>TaGW2</italic>s were negatively correlated with TKW, which further supported earlier conclusion that the <italic>GW2</italic> negatively regulates grain size in cereals. Haplotype interaction analysis exhibited the additive effects between favored haplotypes at <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic>. We also found that haplotypes at <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> underwent strong selection in one century of global wheat breeding. Therefore, there are major genes even though yield is a complex quantitative trait. It illustrated that association based on haplotypes is more effective than single marker in dissection of complex traits. This study provided important genes and functional markers for MAS in wheat yield improvement.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Plant materials</title>
        <p>Four hundred and seventy one Chinese wheat accessions including 151 landraces and 320 modern cultivars were used for functional validation of the <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> markers (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S9">9</xref>: Table S1), among which 265 accessions (151 landraces and 114 modern cultivars) were mainly from the Chinese wheat mini-core collection (MCC) representing more than 70% of the genetic diversity of the total Chinese germplasm collection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Association analysis between <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> markers and grain traits earlier confirmed that these materials provided good representation and effectiveness when used as a population for association analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. In addition, 1,032 introduced wheat cultivars comprising 374 European, 471 American, 51 Australian, 53 CIMMYT and 83 Russian accessions were used for haplotype distribution analysis of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> in global wheat cultivars (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S10">10</xref>: Table S2).</p>
        <p>Chinese Spring was used to clone the promoter sequences of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic>. A set of Chinese Spring (CS) nullisomic-tetrasomic lines was used for chromosome location of <italic>TaGW2</italic>. Thirty-four accessions with large variations in grain weight, including 22 modern cultivars and 12 landraces (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S3), were used for sequencing to detect single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and haplotypes in the promoter regions of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic>.</p>
        <p>A recombinant inbred line (RIL) population derived from Nanda 2419 and Wangshuibai was used for fine mapping of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Measurement of grain weight related traits</title>
        <p>During the 2001-2002 and 2005-2006 wheat-growing seasons, cultivars used in this study were planted at the CAAS-Luoyang Experiment Station in Henan province (111.6&#xB0;E, 33.8&#xB0;N). Each cultivar was planted in 2&#xA0;m double rows spaced 25&#xA0;cm apart, with 40 seeds planted in each row. The field management followed local practices.</p>
        <p>After harvest, 20 grains were randomly selected from each genotype and lined up length-wise along a ruler to measure average kernel length (KL), and then arranged breadth-wise to measure kernel width (KW). The middle parts of ten grains were measured with vernier calipers to estimate average kernel thickness (KT). Two independent samples of 500 grains were weighted and the means were converted to one thousand-kernel weight (TKW).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Cloning the promoters of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic></title>
        <p>Genomic DNA was extracted from young leaves of 10-day-old seedlings using a modified CTAB method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>]. Primers were designed by the software Primer Premier Version 5.0 (Premier Biosoft International, Palo Alto, CA), and all primers were synthesized by Shanghai Sangon Biological Technology Co., Ltd (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sangon.com/">http://www.sangon.com/</ext-link>).</p>
        <p>Primers pF147 and pR1481 were designed to amplify the 1.5&#xA0;kb promoter regions of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> according to the <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> promoter sequence. PCR were performed in total volumes of 15&#xA0;&#x3BC;l, including 3 pmol of each primer, 120&#xA0;&#x3BC;M of each dNTP, 80&#xA0;ng genomic DNA, 0.75 unit La-Taq and 7.5&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of 2&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;GC Buffer (TaKaRa Biotechnology (Dalian) Co. Ltd, Product Code: DRR20AG). PCR were performed as follows: 95&#xB0;C for 4&#xA0;min; followed by 35&#xA0;cycles of 95&#xB0;C for 30&#xA0;s, annealing (60-64&#xB0;C) for 30&#xA0;s, and extension at 72&#xB0;C (30&#xA0;s to 3&#xA0;min), and 72&#xB0;C for 30&#xA0;s, with a final extension of 72&#xB0;C for 10&#xA0;min. The annealing temperatures and extension times depended on the primer sets and the lengths of the expected PCR products. The PCR products were separated by electrophoresis in agarose gels, and the target bands were extracted and cloned into the pEASY-T1 simple vector and transformed to DH5&#x3B1; competent <italic>E. coli</italic> cells by the heat shock method (Beijing Trans Gen Biotech Co., Ltd, Product Code: CT111). Positive clones were selected for sequencing by ABI 3730XI DNA Analyzer. To guarantee sequence accuracy, the PCR and DNA sequencing were repeated at least three times.</p>
        <p>A Genome Walking Kit (TaKaRa Biotechnology (Dalian) Co. Ltd, Product Code No. 6108) was used to obtain the 5&#x2032; flanking promoter sequence of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic>. The kit was based primarily on the known genomic DNA sequence, utilizing the annealing temperature difference between degenerate primers and specific primers for thermal asymmetric PCR, and flanking sequences were obtained by three nested PCR. Three specific primers TaGW2-SP1, TaGW2-SP2 and TaGW2-SP3 (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S11">11</xref>: Table S4) were designed according to the promoter sequence to amplify the sequences in the unknown regions. Here, TaGW2-SP2 was designed on the inside of TaGW2-SP1, and TaGW2-SP3 was located on the inside of TaGW2-SP2. Each distance between the two primers was 60-100&#xA0;bp. Three PCR were performed in total volumes of 25&#xA0;&#x3BC;l, including 80&#xA0;ng genomic DNA, 4&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of 2.5&#xA0;mM dNTP mixture, 2.5&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of 10&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;LA PCR Buffer II (Mg<sup>2+</sup> plus), 1.25 U of TaKaRa LA Taq, 0.5&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of AP Primer (100 pmol/&#x3BC;l), 0.5&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of SP Primer (10 pmol/&#x3BC;l). The first PCR was as follows: Taking Chinese Spring DNA as the template, AP Primer as the upstream primer, and TaGW2-SP1 as downstream primer for the first PCR. PCR were performed as follows: 94&#xB0;C for 1&#xA0;min, 98&#xB0;C for 1&#xA0;min; followed by 5&#xA0;cycles of 94&#xB0;C for 30&#xA0;s, 62&#xB0;C for 1&#xA0;min, 72&#xB0;C for 2&#xA0;min; 94&#xB0;C for 30&#xA0;s, 25&#xB0;C for 3&#xA0;min, 72&#xB0;C for 2&#xA0;min; followed by 15&#xA0;cycles of 94&#xB0;C for 30&#xA0;s, 62&#xB0;C for 1&#xA0;min, 72&#xB0;C for 2&#xA0;min, 94&#xB0;C for 30&#xA0;s, 62&#xB0;C for 1&#xA0;min, 72&#xB0;C for 2&#xA0;min, 94&#xB0;C for 30&#xA0;s, 44&#xB0;C for 1&#xA0;min, 72&#xB0;C for 2&#xA0;min; and 72&#xB0;C for 10&#xA0;min. The second PCR was performed as follows: the first PCR solution was diluted 100 times, taking 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;l as template for the second PCR, AP primer as the upstream, and TaGW2-SP2 as the downstream primer. PCR were performed as follows: 15&#xA0;cycles of 94&#xB0;C for 30&#xA0;s, 63&#xB0;C for 1&#xA0;min, 72&#xB0;C for 2&#xA0;min, 94&#xB0;C for 30&#xA0;s, 63&#xB0;C for 1&#xA0;min, 72&#xB0;C for 2&#xA0;min, 94&#xB0;C for 30&#xA0;s, 44&#xB0;C for 1&#xA0;min, 72&#xB0;C for 2&#xA0;min; and 72&#xB0;C for 10&#xA0;min. For the third PCR, the second PCR solution was diluted 100 times, then taking 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;l as the template, AP primer as the upstream primer, and TaGW2-SP3 as the downstream primer. PCR were performed as for the second PCR. The three PCR products were separated by electrophoresis in 1% agarose gels; the target bands were extracted and PCR products were selected for sequencing using the primer TaGW2-SP3. A sequence of about 700&#xA0;bp was obtained by genome walking, taking this sequence as a reference to continue amplifying upstream sequences. Through this method of genome walking, ~2.9 Kb of promoter sequences of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> were obtained.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>SNP identification and functional marker development</title>
        <p>Thirty-four cultivars were initially chosen for detecting sequence variation in the promoter regions of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic>. SNPs were identified using DNA Star software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dnastar.com/">http://www.dnastar.com/</ext-link>). The core elements of the promoters were identified using the TSSP program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.softberry.com">http://www.softberry.com</ext-link>). The cis-acting regulatory elements of the promoter were predicted by Plantcare (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.psb.ugent.be/webtools/plantcare/html/">http://bioinformatics.psb.ugent.be/webtools/plantcare/html/</ext-link>).</p>
        <p>Four haplotypes formed by 11 SNPs were found in <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> and three markers were developed to distinguish them. Genome-specific primers were designed for these three markers, respectively (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S11">11</xref>: Table S4). Basically, the three systems of PCR and digestion were similar. PCR were performed in total volumes of 15&#xA0;&#x3BC;l, including 80&#xA0;ng genomic DNA, 1.5&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of 10&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;PCR Buffer, 1.5&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of MgCl<sub>2</sub> (25&#xA0;mM), 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M of each primer, 0.16&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of dNTP (25&#xA0;&#x3BC;M), 0.75 U of Taq (Fermentas). PCR were performed as follows: 95&#xB0;C for 4&#xA0;min; followed by 35&#xA0;cycles of 95&#xB0;C for 30&#xA0;s, annealing (60-64&#xB0;C) for 30&#xA0;s, and extension at 72&#xB0;C (30 - 90&#xA0;s), and 72&#xB0;C for 30&#xA0;s, with a final extension of 72&#xB0;C for 10&#xA0;min. The annealing temperatures and extension times depended on the primer sets and the lengths of expected PCR products (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S11">11</xref>: Table S4). Digestions were performed in total volumes of 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;l, including 5&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of PCR products, 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of 10&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;Buffer, 0.1&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of BSA, 0.25&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of restriction enzyme, and 3.65&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of ddH<sub>2</sub>O.</p>
        <p>The <italic>TaGW2</italic>-6B-CAPS marker amplified a 1.4 Kb genome-specific fragment, which was digested with BstNI (NEB) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions, and the digested segments were separated on 1.5% agarose gels with EB. This marker effectively distinguished <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> and three other haplotypes. <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic> (no restriction sites) was represented by a single 1.4&#xA0;kb band, whereas the other three were digested into 1.0 Kb and 400&#xA0;bp bands.</p>
        <p>The <italic>TaGW2</italic>-6B-ACAS marker needs two PCR amplifications, the <italic>TaGW2</italic>-6B-ACAS-1 primer amplified a 464&#xA0;bp fragment and the <italic>TaGW2</italic>-6B-ACAS-2 primer amplified a 626&#xA0;bp fragment. The two fragments represent <italic>Hap-6B-2</italic> and other two haplotypes, respectively; they were easily distinguished in 1.5% agarose gels.</p>
        <p>The <italic>TaGW2</italic>-6B-dCAPS marker amplified a 263&#xA0;bp genome-specific fragment; the products were then digested with Hpy166II (NEB) at 65&#xB0;C for 20&#xA0;min, and the digested segments were separated on 8% non-denaturing polyacrylamide gels. The marker distinguished <italic>Hap-6B-3</italic> (263&#xA0;bp) and <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic> (240&#xA0;bp).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>RNA extraction, reverse transcription and real-time quantitative PCR</title>
        <p>For each cultivar, spikes from all tillers of each individual were tagged at anthesis when the first spikelets on the head flowered, and the date was recorded. Grains were harvested at 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 and 30&#xA0;days post-flowering (dpf) as well as mature seeds. Genome-specific primers were designed according to cDNA sequence differences of the <italic>GW2</italic> homoeologues from chromosomes 6A, 6B and 6D to evaluate the correlation of gene expression levels of <italic>TaGW2-6A/6B/6D</italic> and grain weight. To investigate the temporal expression profiles of the <italic>TaGW2s</italic> during grain development, RT-PCR was conducted using developing seeds at 5, 10, 15, 20, 25, and 30&#xA0;days post-flowering (dpf) and mature seeds from 22 wheat cultivars including 12 small grained and 10 large grained genotypes. mRNA was extracted using TIANGENRNA Plant Plus Reagent. cDNA was synthesized with the SuperScript II System (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. DNA was removed by digestion with DNaseI (Fermentas) before reverse transcription. The expression analysis of <italic>TaGW2</italic> was performed with SYBR Premix Ex-Taq [TaKaRa Biotechnology (Dalian) Co. Ltd, Product Code: DRR041A]. RT-PCR were performed in total volumes of 2 0&#xA0;&#x3BC;l, including 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;L cDNA, 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of 2&#xD7; SYBR Premix Ex-Taq, 0.4&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of each primer (10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M) and 0.4&#xA0;&#x3BC;l of ROX Reference Dye (50&#xD7;). The primer sets of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic>, <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic>, <italic>TaGW2-6D</italic> and Actin (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S11">11</xref>: Table S4) were used for amplification of <italic>TaGW2</italic> and actin genes, respectively. Three replications were performed to obtain average values and standard deviations of expression level for each gene. Cts were exported and averaged from technical triplicates. Relative expression was determined using the <italic>&#x394;Ct</italic> method corrected for primer efficiencies. Actin gene was used as endogenous control, which was not changed too much in different tissues and developmental stages of wheat under our experiment. This housekeeping gene was assayed on our experimental samples and data were normalized to the expression of actin. To compare <italic>TaGW2</italic> homoeologous expression, the relative expression values of <italic>TaGW2s</italic> were calculated using the <italic>2-&#x394;&#x394;Ct</italic> method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>], with the 5 dpf stage of Chinese Spring as a reference sample for <italic>&#x394;&#x394;Ct</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Statistical analyses</title>
        <p>Statistical analyses were based on phenotypic data of average grain size and grain weight in two environments. Variance analyses were performed on the SPSS System for Windows version 12.0 to determine phenotypic differences between the four haplotypes individually and in haplotype combinations, based on analysis of variance (One-Way ANOVA) according to Tukey test at the significance level of 5% (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&#x2264;&#x2009;0.05). <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> was mapped using data from recombinant inbred lines derived from the cross between Nanda 2419 and Wangshuibai using MAPMAKER/EXP 3.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>]. Phenotypic explanation rate (<italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>) of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> was the ratio between the sum of squares between groups and total squares for the various haplotypes.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>L: Landraces; M: Modern cultivars; TKW: One-thousand kernel weight (g); KL: Kernel length (mm); KW: Kernel width (mm); KT: Kernel thickness (mm); MCC: Chinese mini core collection.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>QL carried out the molecular genetic studies, participated in the sequence alignment and drafted the manuscript. HCY participated in the design of the study, performed data analysis and participated in tables and figures. ZXY, MZQ supervised the study and revised the manuscript critically. HJ, WYQ, LT, WLF collected data and measured grain weight related traits<italic>.</italic> All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 1: Table S3</title>
          <p>Wheat accessions used for obtaining of promoter sequences. TKW, One-thousand kernel weight (g), KL, kernel length (mm), KW, kernel width (mm), KT, kernel thickness (mm). *: accessions used for real-time PCR analysis of <italic>TaGW2s</italic>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-S1.xls">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 2: Figure S1</title>
          <p>Genetic mapping of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> in a Nanda2419&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;Wangshuibai recombinant inbred line (RIL) population. <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> gene (red marker) was mapped between <italic>Xmag359</italic> and <italic>Xwmc341</italic> on chromosome 6B. The left side of the map was map distance/cM, the right side was SSR markers.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-S2.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 3: Figure S2</title>
          <p>Differences on heading and maturity dates among <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotypes in landraces and modern cultivars based on two years of field data. A, Heading dates differences among <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotypes in 2002 and 2006. B, Maturity dates differences among <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotypes. The bars represent the standard deviation.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-S3.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 4: Figure S3</title>
          <p>Haplotype frequencies (%) of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> in wheat cultivars released since the 1950s in China, Europe and America. A, the frequency of <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic>; B, the frequency of <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic>; C, the frequency of <italic>Hap-6B-1</italic>; D, the frequency of <italic>Hap-6B-4</italic>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-S4.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S5">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 5: Figure S4</title>
          <p>Mean relative expressions of <italic>TaGW2-6A, -6B, -6D</italic> in two subgroups. Red lines represent the subgroup with higher TKWs (10 accessions, mean TKW 47.2 g) and blue lines represent the subgroup with lower TKWs (12 accessions, mean 28.5 g). A, mean relative expressions of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic>; B, mean relative expressions of <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic>; C, mean relative expressions of <italic>TaGW2-6D. TaGW2</italic> genes negatively regulate grain size. Normalized values of <italic>TaGW2</italic> (relative expression) are given as Mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-S5.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S6">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 6: Figure S5</title>
          <p>Mean relative expressions of haplotypes in <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> at different grain development stages based on 22 wheat accessions. Normalized values of <italic>TaGW2</italic> (relative expression) are given as Mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-S6.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S7">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 7: Figure S6</title>
          <p>TKW and KW for eight haplotype combinations of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> in landraces and modern cultivars grown in two environments. A, TKW for eight haplotype combinations in landraces; B, KW for eight haplotype combinations in landraces; C, TKW for eight haplotype combinations in modern cultivars; D, KW for eight haplotype combinations in modern cultivars; <italic>A</italic>/<italic>1</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic>/<italic>Hap-6B-1</italic>; <italic>A</italic>/<italic>2</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic>/<italic>Hap-6B-2</italic>; <italic>A</italic>/<italic>3</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic>/<italic>Hap-6B-3</italic>; <italic>A</italic>/<italic>4</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-A</italic>/<italic>Hap-6B-4</italic>; <italic>G</italic>/<italic>1</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic>/<italic>Hap-6B-1</italic>; <italic>G</italic>/<italic>2</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic>/<italic>Hap-6B-2</italic>; <italic>G</italic>/<italic>3</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic>/<italic>Hap-6B-3</italic>; <italic>G</italic>/<italic>4</italic>, <italic>Hap-6A-G</italic>/<italic>Hap-6B-4</italic>.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-S7.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S8">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 8: Figure S7</title>
          <p>Frequencies of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> haplotype combinations in Chinese wheat landraces and modern cultivars.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-S8.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S9">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 9: Table S1</title>
          <p>Accessions used for association analysis and haplotype distribution studies in Chinese wheat collections. L, landraces; M, modern cultivars; TKW, One-thousand kernel weight (g); KL, kernel length (mm); KW, kernel width (mm); KT, kernel thickness (mm); *, Chinese mini core collection; I, Northern winter wheat region; II, Yellow and Huai River valley winter wheat region; III, low and middle Yangtze River valley winter wheat region; IV, southwestern winter wheat region; V, southern winter wheat region; VI, northeastern spring wheat region; VII, northern spring wheat region; VIII, northwestern spring wheat region; IX, Qinghai-Tibet spring-winter wheat region; X, Xinjiang winter-spring wheat region.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-S9.xls">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S10">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 10: Table S2</title>
          <p>Accessions used for geographic distribution analysis of haplotypes in global wheat cultivars.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-S10.xls">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S11">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 11: Table S4</title>
          <p>Primer sequences used in this study.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2229-14-107-S11.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank Dr. SL Xue, Nanjing Agricultural University, for help with the fine mapping of the <italic>TaGW2-6B</italic> gene, and gratefully acknowledge help from Prof. Robert A McIntosh, University of Sydney, with English editing. We are grateful to the China Natural Science Foundation (31270036), Chinese Ministry of Science and Technology (2010CB125902), Ministry of Agriculture (2008ZX08009) and CAAS-Innovation Team Project for supporting this research.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Varshney</surname>
            <given-names>RK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hoisington</surname>
            <given-names>DA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tyagi</surname>
            <given-names>AK</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Advances in cereal genomics and applications in crop breeding</article-title>
          <source>Trends Biotechnol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>490</fpage>
          <lpage>499</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibtech.2006.08.006</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16956681?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16956681</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Gale</surname>
            <given-names>MD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Devos</surname>
            <given-names>KM</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Comparative genetics in the grasses</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <fpage>1971</fpage>
          <lpage>1974</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.5.1971</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 9482816?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9482816</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>SN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>SG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>YJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dai</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cao</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ye</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tong</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cong</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Geng</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Han</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
          <article-title>A draft sequence of the rice genome (Oryza sativa L. ssp. indica)</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>296</volume>
          <issue>5565</issue>
          <fpage>79</fpage>
          <lpage>92</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1068037</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 11935017?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11935017</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Goff</surname>
            <given-names>SA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ricke</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lan</surname>
            <given-names>TH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Presting</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dunn</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Glazebrook</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sessions</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oeller</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Varma</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hadley</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hutchison</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Martin</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Katagiri</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lange</surname>
            <given-names>BM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Moughamer</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xia</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Budworth</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhong</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miguel</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Paszkowski</surname>
            <given-names>U</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Colbert</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>WL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cooper</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wood</surname>
            <given-names>TC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mao</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Quail</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
          <article-title>A draft sequence of the rice genome (Oryza sativa L. ssp. japonica)</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>296</volume>
          <issue>5565</issue>
          <fpage>92</fpage>
          <lpage>100</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1068275</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 11935018?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11935018</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Xing</surname>
            <given-names>YZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>QF</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Genetic and molecular bases of rice yield</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>421</fpage>
          <lpage>442</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042809-112209</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20192739?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20192739</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Bai</surname>
            <given-names>XF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xing</surname>
            <given-names>YZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Yield-related QTLs and their applications in rice genetic improvement</article-title>
          <source>J Integr Plant Biol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>300</fpage>
          <lpage>311</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7909.2012.01117.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22463712?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22463712</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Fan</surname>
            <given-names>CC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xing</surname>
            <given-names>YZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mao</surname>
            <given-names>HL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>TT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Han</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>CG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>XH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>QF</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title><italic>GS3</italic>, a major QTL for grain length and weight and minor QTL for grain width and thickness in rice, encodes a putative transmembrane protein</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>1164</fpage>
          <lpage>1171</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-006-0218-1</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16453132?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16453132</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Song</surname>
            <given-names>XJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shi</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>MZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>HQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A QTL for rice grain width and weight lll encodes a previously unknown RING-type E3 ubiquitin ligase</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>623</fpage>
          <lpage>630</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng2014</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17417637?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17417637</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Weng</surname>
            <given-names>JF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
            <given-names>SH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wan</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gao</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Su</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lei</surname>
            <given-names>CL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cheng</surname>
            <given-names>ZJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>XP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhai</surname>
            <given-names>HQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wan</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Isolation and initial characterization of <italic>GW5</italic>, a major QTL associated with rice kernel width and weight</article-title>
          <source>Cell Res</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>1199</fpage>
          <lpage>1209</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2008.307</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19015668?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015668</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>SK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yuan</surname>
            <given-names>QB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>ZB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zeng</surname>
            <given-names>RZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>HT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>GJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Qian</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>GQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fu</surname>
            <given-names>XD</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Control of grain size, shape and quality by <italic>OsSPL16</italic> in rice</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>950</fpage>
          <lpage>954</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2327</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22729225?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22729225</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Ishimaru</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hirotsu</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Madoka</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Murakami</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hara</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Onodera</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kashiwagi</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ujiie</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shimizu</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Onishi</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miyagawa</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Katoh</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Loss of function of the IAA-glucose hydrolase gene TGW6 enhances rice grain weight and increases yield</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>707</fpage>
          <lpage>711</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2612</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23583977?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23583977</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Xue</surname>
            <given-names>WY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xing</surname>
            <given-names>YZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Weng</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>WJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>HJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>SB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>CG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>XH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>QF</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Natural variation in <italic>Ghd7</italic> is an important regulator of heading date and yield potential in rice</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>761</fpage>
          <lpage>767</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.143</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 18454147?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18454147</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>ET</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>XD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>LY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>LX</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>BR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>HX</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>GQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>ZH</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Control of rice kernel filling and yield by a gene with a potential signature of domestication</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>1370</fpage>
          <lpage>1374</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.220</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 18820698?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18820698</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Brenchley</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Spannagl</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pfeifer</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barker</surname>
            <given-names>GL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>D&#x2019;Amore</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Allen</surname>
            <given-names>AM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McKenzie</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kramer</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kerhornou</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bolser</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kay</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Waite</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Trick</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bancroft</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huo</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>MC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sehgal</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gill</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kianian</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kersey</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dvorak</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McCombie</surname>
            <given-names>WR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hall</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mayer</surname>
            <given-names>KF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Edwards</surname>
            <given-names>KJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bevan</surname>
            <given-names>MW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hall</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Analysis of the bread wheat genome using whole-genome shotgun sequencing</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>491</volume>
          <issue>7426</issue>
          <fpage>705</fpage>
          <lpage>710</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11650</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23192148?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23192148</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Jia</surname>
            <given-names>JZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>SC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kong</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>YR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>GY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>WM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Appels</surname>
            <given-names>RD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pfeifer</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tao</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jing</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gao</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gao</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Spannagl</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mayer</surname>
            <given-names>KF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pan</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xia</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wicker</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gou</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kuang</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
          <article-title><italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> draft genome sequence reveals a gene repertoire for wheat adaptation</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>496</volume>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <lpage>95</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12028</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23535592?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23535592</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Ling</surname>
            <given-names>HQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>SC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>DC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>LY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fan</surname>
            <given-names>HJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>LL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tao</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gao</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cui</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lou</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jian</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sha</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
          <article-title>Draft genome of the wheat A-genome progenitor <italic>Triticum urartu</italic></article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>496</volume>
          <fpage>87</fpage>
          <lpage>90</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11997</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23535596?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23535596</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>MC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
            <given-names>YQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>You</surname>
            <given-names>FM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Deal</surname>
            <given-names>KR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>YQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>YQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huo</surname>
            <given-names>NX</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jorgensen</surname>
            <given-names>CM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McGuire</surname>
            <given-names>PE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pasternak</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stein</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ware</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kramer</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McCombie</surname>
            <given-names>WR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kianian</surname>
            <given-names>SF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Martis</surname>
            <given-names>MM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mayer</surname>
            <given-names>KF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sehgal</surname>
            <given-names>SK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gill</surname>
            <given-names>BS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bevan</surname>
            <given-names>MW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Simkov&#xE1;</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dolezel</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Weining</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lazo</surname>
            <given-names>GR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>OD</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
          <article-title>A 4-gigabase physical map unlocks the structure and evolution of the complex genome of <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>, the wheat D-genome progenitor</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>7940</fpage>
          <lpage>7945</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1219082110</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23610408?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23610408</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>XH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Warburton</surname>
            <given-names>ML</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bai</surname>
            <given-names>GH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dai</surname>
            <given-names>JR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>JS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            <given-names>JB</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Relationship, evolutionary fate and function of two maize co-orthologs of rice <italic>GW2</italic> associated with kernel size and weight</article-title>
          <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>143</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-10-143</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20626916?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20626916</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Su</surname>
            <given-names>ZQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>CY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>LF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>YC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Identification and development of a functional marker of <italic>TaGW2</italic> associated with grain weight in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>211</fpage>
          <lpage>223</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-010-1437-z</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20838758?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20838758</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>JS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shi</surname>
            <given-names>CL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>JN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <given-names>FF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tian</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Function of <italic>TaGW2-6A</italic> and its effect on grain weight in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>
          <source>Euphytica</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>192</volume>
          <fpage>347</fpage>
          <lpage>357</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-012-0858-y</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>ZB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bai</surname>
            <given-names>ZY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>XL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>QX</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>LQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>XJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>SNP identification and allelic-specific PCR markers development for <italic>TaGW2</italic>, a gene linked to wheat kernel weight</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>125</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>1057</fpage>
          <lpage>1068</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-012-1895-6</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22643902?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22643902</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Bednarek</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Boulaflous</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Girousse</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ravel</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tassy</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barret</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bouzidi</surname>
            <given-names>MF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mouzeyar</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Down-regulation of the <italic>TaGW2</italic> gene by RNA interference results in decreased grain size and weight in wheat</article-title>
          <source>J Exp Bot</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <issue>16</issue>
          <fpage>5945</fpage>
          <lpage>5955</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ers249</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22996678?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22996678</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Somers</surname>
            <given-names>DJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Isaac</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Edwards</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A high density microsatellite consensus map for bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>1105</fpage>
          <lpage>1114</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-004-1740-7</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 15490101?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15490101</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>CY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>YC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>LY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>You</surname>
            <given-names>GX</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>HN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ge</surname>
            <given-names>HM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jia</surname>
            <given-names>JZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Genetic diversity and construction of core collection in Chinese wheat genetic resources</article-title>
          <source>Chin Sci Bull</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>1518</fpage>
          <lpage>1526</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11434-008-0212-x</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>CW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>LF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>HM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>You</surname>
            <given-names>GX</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>YS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>An estimation of the minimum number of SSR alleles needed to reveal genetic relationships in wheat cultivars I. Information from large-scale planted cultivars and cornerstone breeding parents in Chinese wheat improvement and production</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <fpage>112</fpage>
          <lpage>117</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 12582878?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12582878</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Pritchard</surname>
            <given-names>JK</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Deconstructing maize population structure</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <lpage>204</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/90026</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 11431683?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11431683</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhuang</surname>
            <given-names>QS</given-names>
          </name>
          <source>Chinese Wheat Improvement and Pedigree Analysis</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <publisher-name>Beijing: Agricultural Press</publisher-name>
          <comment>(in Chinese)</comment>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Davierwala</surname>
            <given-names>AP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reddy</surname>
            <given-names>AP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lagu</surname>
            <given-names>MD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ranjekar</surname>
            <given-names>PK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gupta</surname>
            <given-names>VS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Marker assisted selection of bacterial blight resistance genes in rice</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Genet</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <issue>7&#x2013;8</issue>
          <fpage>261</fpage>
          <lpage>278</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 11590832?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11590832</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Koebner</surname>
            <given-names>RM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Summers</surname>
            <given-names>RW</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>21st century wheat breeding, plot selection or plate detection?</article-title>
          <source>Trends Biotechnol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>59</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-7799(02)00036-7</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12573853?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12573853</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>PH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tan</surname>
            <given-names>YF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>YQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>CG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Simultaneous improvement for four quality traits of Zhenshan 97, an elite parent of hybrid rice, by molecular marker-assisted selection</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>326</fpage>
          <lpage>331</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 12582859?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12582859</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>XW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>SG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>YQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>HY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>KD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>LH</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Marker-assisted selection and pyramiding for three blast resistance genes, <italic>Pi-d(t)1</italic>, <italic>Pi-b</italic>, <italic>Pi-ta2,</italic> in rice (in Chinese with English abstract)</article-title>
          <source>Chin J Biotechnol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>708</fpage>
          <lpage>714</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>GM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>CQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fu</surname>
            <given-names>YC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fu</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>KJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>CL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ling</surname>
            <given-names>ZZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>XK</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Pyramiding of senescence inhibition <italic>IPT</italic> gene and <italic>Xa23</italic> for resistance to bacterial blight in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa L</italic>.)</article-title>
          <source>Acta Genet Sin</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>836</fpage>
          <lpage>841</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 15481540?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15481540</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Joseph</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gopalakrishnan</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sharma</surname>
            <given-names>RK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <given-names>VP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <given-names>AK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <given-names>NK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mohapatra</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Combining bacterial blight resistance and basmati quality characteristics by phenotypic and molecular marker-assisted selection in rice</article-title>
          <source>Mol Breed</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>377</fpage>
          <lpage>387</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Sharma</surname>
            <given-names>PN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Torii</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Takumi</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mori</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakamura</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Marker-assisted pyramiding of brown planthopper (<italic>Nilaparvata lugens</italic> St&#xE5;l) resistance genes <italic>Bph1</italic> and <italic>Bph2</italic> on rice chromosome 12</article-title>
          <source>Hereditas</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>140</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>61</fpage>
          <lpage>69</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1601-5223.2004.01726.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 15032948?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15032948</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Yi</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>SK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hong</surname>
            <given-names>YK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cho</surname>
            <given-names>YC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nam</surname>
            <given-names>MH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>SC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Han</surname>
            <given-names>SS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>GL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hahn</surname>
            <given-names>TR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ronald</surname>
            <given-names>PC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jeon</surname>
            <given-names>JS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Use of <italic>Pi5(t)</italic> markers in marker-assisted selection to screen for cultivars with resistance to Magnaporthe grisea</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>978</fpage>
          <lpage>985</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-004-1707-8</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 15141293?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15141293</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Tan</surname>
            <given-names>CX</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ji</surname>
            <given-names>XM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pan</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zuo</surname>
            <given-names>SM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>YF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zou</surname>
            <given-names>JH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>ZX</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>LH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pan</surname>
            <given-names>XB</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Identification and marker-assisted selection of two major quantitative genes controlling rice sheath blight resistance in backcross generations</article-title>
          <source>Acta Genet Sin</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>399</fpage>
          <lpage>405</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 16011032?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16011032</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>YH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>SJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ji</surname>
            <given-names>SL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>WW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>CM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wan</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Fine mapping and marker-assisted selection (MAS) of a low glutelin content gene in rice</article-title>
          <source>Cell Res</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>622</fpage>
          <lpage>630</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.cr.7290332</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16117852?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16117852</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>QQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>QF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cai</surname>
            <given-names>XL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>HM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>SZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>HX</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>ZY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
            <given-names>MH</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Molecular marker-assisted selection for improved cooking and eating quality of two elite parents of hybrid rice</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>2354</fpage>
          <lpage>2360</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2006.03.0180</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Miyata</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Komori</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nitta</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Marker-assisted selection and evaluation of the QTL for stigma exsertion under japonica rice genetic background</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>539</fpage>
          <lpage>548</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-006-0454-4</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17131105?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17131105</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>YN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>ZH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Appels</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xia</surname>
            <given-names>XC</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Functional markers in wheat, current status and future prospects</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>125</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>10</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-012-1829-3</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22366867?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22366867</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>QY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hou</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>CY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>LF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ge</surname>
            <given-names>HM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>YC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The wheat (T. <italic>aestivum</italic>) sucrose synthase 2 gene (<italic>TaSus2</italic>) active in endosperm development is associated with yield traits</article-title>
          <source>Funct Integr Genom</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>49</fpage>
          <lpage>61</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10142-010-0188-x</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>DY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>ZH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xia</surname>
            <given-names>XC</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Characterization of a cell wall invertase gene <italic>TaCwi-A1</italic> on common wheat chromosome 2A and development of functional markers</article-title>
          <source>Mol Breed</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-010-9524-z</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Han</surname>
            <given-names>LM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>FP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xia</surname>
            <given-names>XC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Qu</surname>
            <given-names>YY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>ZW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>ZH</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Distribution of genes related to plant height, kernel weight and disease resistance among wheat cultivars from major countries (in Chinese with English abstract)</article-title>
          <source>J Triticeae Crops</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>824</fpage>
          <lpage>831</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>YB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fan</surname>
            <given-names>CC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xing</surname>
            <given-names>YZ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>YH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>LJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shao</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>XH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xiao</surname>
            <given-names>JH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>YQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>QF</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Natural variation in <italic>GS5</italic> plays an important role in regulating grain size and yield in rice</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>1266</fpage>
          <lpage>1269</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.977</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22019783?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22019783</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B45">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Q</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>XH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bai</surname>
            <given-names>GH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Warburton</surname>
            <given-names>ML</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mahuku</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gore</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dai</surname>
            <given-names>JR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>JS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            <given-names>JB</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Cloning and characterization of a putative <italic>GS3</italic> ortholog involved in maize kernel development</article-title>
          <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <fpage>753</fpage>
          <lpage>763</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-009-1196-x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19898828?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19898828</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B46">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hou</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>QY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>CY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>YQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>HN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Global selection on sucrose synthase haplotypes during a century of wheat breeding</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>164</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>1918</fpage>
          <lpage>1929</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.232454</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24402050?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24402050</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B47">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>YN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xia</surname>
            <given-names>XC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>ZH</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Characterization of dense and erect panicle 1 gene (<italic>TaDep1</italic>) located on common wheat group 5 chromosomes and development of allele-specific markers (in Chinese with English abstract)</article-title>
          <source>Acta Agron Sin</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>589</fpage>
          <lpage>598</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B48">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>LF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Balfourier</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>CY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Exbrayat-Vinson</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>YC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ge</surname>
            <given-names>HM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Comparison of genetic diversity level between European and East-Asian wheat collections using SSR markers (in Chinese with English abstract)</article-title>
          <source>Sci Agric Sin</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>2667</fpage>
          <lpage>2678</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B49">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Wright</surname>
            <given-names>SI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vroh</surname>
            <given-names>BI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schroeder</surname>
            <given-names>SG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yamasaki</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Doebley</surname>
            <given-names>JF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McMullen</surname>
            <given-names>MD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gaut</surname>
            <given-names>BS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The effects of artificial selection on the maize genome</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>308</volume>
          <fpage>1310</fpage>
          <lpage>1314</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15919994</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B50">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Olsen</surname>
            <given-names>KM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Purugganan</surname>
            <given-names>MD</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Molecular evidence on the origin and evolution of glutinous rice</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>162</volume>
          <fpage>941</fpage>
          <lpage>950</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 12399401?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12399401</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B51">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Peng</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Richards</surname>
            <given-names>DE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hartley</surname>
            <given-names>NM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Murphy</surname>
            <given-names>GP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Devos</surname>
            <given-names>KM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Flintham</surname>
            <given-names>JE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beales</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fish</surname>
            <given-names>LJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Worland</surname>
            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pelica</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sudhakar</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Christou</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Snape</surname>
            <given-names>JW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gale</surname>
            <given-names>MD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harberd</surname>
            <given-names>NP</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>&#x2018;Green revolution&#x2019; genes encode mutant gibberellin response modulators</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>400</volume>
          <fpage>256</fpage>
          <lpage>261</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/22307</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 10421366?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10421366</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B52">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Frary</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nesbitt</surname>
            <given-names>TC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Grandillo</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knaap</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cong</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Meller</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Elber</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alpert</surname>
            <given-names>KB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tanksley</surname>
            <given-names>SD</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>fw2.2: a quantitative trait locus key to the evolution of tomato fruit size</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>289</volume>
          <issue>5476</issue>
          <fpage>85</fpage>
          <lpage>88</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.289.5476.85</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 10884229?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10884229</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B53">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Fay</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>CI</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Hitchhiking under positive Darwinian selection</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>155</volume>
          <fpage>1405</fpage>
          <lpage>1413</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 10880498?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10880498</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B54">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tong</surname>
            <given-names>YP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>You</surname>
            <given-names>GX</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>CY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ge</surname>
            <given-names>HM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>LF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>YC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>ZS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Hitchhiking effect mapping, a new approach for discovering agronomic important genes</article-title>
          <source>Agric Sci China</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>255</fpage>
          <lpage>264</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1671-2927(07)60043-1</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B55">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Barrero</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bellgard</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Diverse approaches to achieving grain yield in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Funct Integr Genom</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10142-010-0208-x</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B56">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Shomura</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Izawa</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ebana</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ebitani</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kanegae</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Konishi</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yano</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Deletion in a gene associated with grain size increased yields during rice domestication</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>1023</fpage>
          <lpage>1028</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.169</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 18604208?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18604208</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B57">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>CY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>LF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ge</surname>
            <given-names>HM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>YC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Genetic diversity and linkage disequilibrium in Chinese bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) revealed by SSR markers</article-title>
          <source>PLoS One</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>e17279</fpage>
          <comment>10.1371/journal.pone.0017279</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017279</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21365016?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21365016</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B58">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Cavanagha</surname>
            <given-names>CR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chao</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>SC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>BE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stephen</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kiani</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Forrest</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Saintenac</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brown-Guedira</surname>
            <given-names>GL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Akhunova</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bai</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pumphrey</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tomar</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wong</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kong</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reynolds</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>da Silva</surname>
            <given-names>ML</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bockelman</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Talbert</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dreisigacker</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Baenziger</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carter</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Korzun</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Morrell</surname>
            <given-names>PL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Morell</surname>
            <given-names>MK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sorrells</surname>
            <given-names>ME</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hayden</surname>
            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
          <article-title>Genome-wide comparative diversity uncovers multiple targets of selection for improvement in hexaploid wheat landraces and cultivars</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>8057</fpage>
          <lpage>8062</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1217133110</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23630259?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23630259</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B59">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Heun</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sch&#xE4;fer-Pregl</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Klawan</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Castagna</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Accerbi</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Borghi</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Salamini</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Site of einkorn wheat domestication identified by DNA fingerprinting</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>278</volume>
          <fpage>1312</fpage>
          <lpage>1314</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.278.5341.1312</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B60">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>LF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ge</surname>
            <given-names>HM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>CY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
            <given-names>YC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Identifying loci influencing 1,000-kernel weight in wheat by microsatellite screening for evidence of selection during breeding</article-title>
          <source>PLoS One</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>e29432</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029432</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22328917?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22328917</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B61">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>DL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>CY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>LF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>XY</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Identifying loci influencing grain number by microsatellite screening in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>
          <source>Planta</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>236</volume>
          <fpage>1507</fpage>
          <lpage>1517</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-012-1708-9</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22820969?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22820969</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B62">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>DH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ronald</surname>
            <given-names>PC</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A rapid DNA minipreparation method suitable for AFLP and other PCR applications</article-title>
          <source>Plant Mol Biol Report</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>53</fpage>
          <lpage>57</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1007585532036</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B63">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Livak</surname>
            <given-names>KJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schmittgen</surname>
            <given-names>TD</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2 <sup>-&#x394;&#x394;CT</sup> method</article-title>
          <source>Methods</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>402</fpage>
          <lpage>408</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 11846609?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B64">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Lander</surname>
            <given-names>ES</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Botstein</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Mapping Mendelian factors underlying quantitative traits using RFLP linkage maps</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>185</fpage>
          <lpage>199</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2563713</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
