<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Toxins (Basel)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">toxins</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Toxins</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2072-6651</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3210464</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins3101294</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">toxins-03-01294</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Genetic Diversity in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> from a Major Wheat-Producing Region of Argentina</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alvarez</surname>
            <given-names>Cora Lilia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-toxins-03-01294">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-toxins-03-01294">&#x2020;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Somma</surname>
            <given-names>Stefania</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-toxins-03-01294">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-toxins-03-01294">&#x2020;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Proctor</surname>
            <given-names>Robert H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-toxins-03-01294">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Stea</surname>
            <given-names>Gaetano</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-toxins-03-01294">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mul&#xE8;</surname>
            <given-names>Giuseppina</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-toxins-03-01294">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Logrieco</surname>
            <given-names>Antonio F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-toxins-03-01294">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pinto</surname>
            <given-names>Virginia Fernandez</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-toxins-03-01294">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Moretti</surname>
            <given-names>Antonio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-toxins-03-01294">2</xref>
          <xref rid="c1-toxins-03-01294" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="af1-toxins-03-01294"><label>1</label> Departamento de Biodiversidad y Biolog&#xED;a Experimental, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, Argentina; Email: <email>cora@bg.fcen.uba.ar</email> (C.L.A.); <email>virginia@qo.fcen.uba.ar</email> (V.F.P.)</aff>
      <aff id="af2-toxins-03-01294"><label>2</label> Institute of Sciences of Food Production, CNR, Via Amendola 122/0, 70126 Bari, Italy; Email: <email>stefania.somma@ispa.cnr.it</email> (S.S.);  <email>gaetano.stea@ispa.cnr.it</email> (G.S.); <email>giuseppina.mule@ispa.cnr.it</email> (G.M.); <email>antonio.logrieco@ispa.cnr.it</email> (A.F.L.)</aff>
      <aff id="af3-toxins-03-01294"><label>3</label> Bacterial Foodborne Pathogen and Mycology Research Unit, National Center for Agricultural Utilization Research, ARS, USDA, Peoria, IL 61604, USA; Email: <email>robert.proctor@ars.usda.gov</email></aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn id="fn1-toxins-03-01294">
          <label>&#x2020;</label>
          <p> These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="c1-toxins-03-01294"><label>*</label> Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; Email: <email>antonio.moretti@ispa.cnr.it</email>; Tel.: +39-080-5929326; Fax:  +39-080-5929374. </corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>10</issue>
      <fpage>1294</fpage>
      <lpage>1309</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;  2011 by the authors; licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This article is an open-access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> species complex (FGSC) is a group of mycotoxigenic fungi that are the primary cause of Fusarium head blight (FHB) of wheat worldwide. The distribution, frequency of occurrence, and genetic diversity of FGSC species in cereal crops in South America is not well understood compared to some regions of Asia, Europe and North America. Therefore, we examined the frequency and genetic diversity of a collection of 183 FGSC isolates recovered from wheat grown during multiple growing seasons and across a large area of eastern Argentina, a major wheat producing region in South America. Sequence analysis of the translation elongation factor 1&#x2212;&#x3B1; and &#x3B2;-tubulin genes as well as Amplified Fragment Length Polymorphism (AFLP) analyses indicated that all isolates were the FGSC species <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic>. AFLP analysis resolved at least 11 subgroups, and all the isolates represented different AFLP haplotypes. AFLP profile and geographic origin were not correlated. Previously obtained trichothecene production profiles of the isolates revealed that the 15-acetyldeoxynivalenol chemotype was slightly more frequent than the 3-acetyldeoxynivalenol chemotype among the isolates. These data extend the current understanding of FGSC diversity and provide further evidence that <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> is the predominant cause of FHB in the temperate main wheat-growing area of Argentina. Moreover, two isolates of <italic>F. crookwellense</italic> and four of <italic>F. pseudograminearum</italic> were also recovered from wheat samples and sequenced. The results also suggest that, although <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> was the only FGSC species recovered in this study, the high level of genetic diversity within this species should be considered in plant breeding efforts and development of other disease management strategies aimed at reducing FHB.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd> Fusarium Head Blight</kwd>
        <kwd>AFLP</kwd>
        <kwd>translation elongation factor 1&#x2212;&#x3B1;</kwd>
        <kwd> &#x3B2;-tubulin</kwd>
        <kwd>deoxynivalenol</kwd>
        <kwd>3-acetyldeoxynivalenol</kwd>
        <kwd>15-acetyldeoxynivalenol</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p><italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> (Schwabe) (teleomorph <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic> (Schwein.)) is considered the main cause of Fusarium Head Blight (FHB) worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-toxins-03-01294">1</xref>]. The disease is of significance because it reduces yield and quality of grains and also results in mycotoxin contamination of wheat kernels, primarily with trichothecenes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2-toxins-03-01294">2</xref>], that have adverse effects on animal and human health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3-toxins-03-01294">3</xref>]. The most common trichothecenes produced by <italic>F. graminearum</italic> are deoxynivalenol (DON), its acetylated derivatives 3-acetyldeoxynivalenol (3ADON) and 15-acetyldeoxynivalenol (15ADON), and nivalenol (NIV), and its acetylated derivative 4-acetyl-nivalenol (4ANIV or fusarenone X) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2-toxins-03-01294">2</xref>]. Three trichothecene production profiles (chemotypes) predominate in this species: the production of NIV and 4ANIV (NIV chemotype); the production of DON and 3ADON (3ADON chemotype); and the production of DON and 15ADON (15ADON chemotype) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4-toxins-03-01294">4</xref>]. Surveys of trichothecenes in wheat grains infected with <italic>F. graminearum</italic> indicate that the 3ADON and 15ADON chemotypes predominate in North America, South America and Europe. The NIV chemotype is more common in Europe than America [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5-toxins-03-01294">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6-toxins-03-01294">6</xref>], however, NIV strains have recently been found in North America [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7-toxins-03-01294">7</xref>]. Previous reports from Argentinean strains of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> isolated from wheat have shown controversial results: Ramirez <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8-toxins-03-01294">8</xref>] reported that all the strains produced DON and a few of them produced 3ADON; Lori <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9-toxins-03-01294">9</xref>] reported that the strains produced DON, 3ADON and NIV; finally Fernandez Pinto <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10-toxins-03-01294">10</xref>] reported the production of DON, 3ADON, NIV and mainly 15ADON. A recent report of the mycotoxin production in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains from different regions in the great production area of wheat in Argentina has shown that strains producing DON and 15ADON are as frequent as those producing DON and both acetylated derivatives, 3ADON and 15ADON. In addition, NIV and DON were produced simultaneously by 23.6% of the isolates, although DON was always produced in higher quantities in these isolates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11-toxins-03-01294">11</xref>]. The co-occurrence of DON and NIV in the same isolates is surprising since the genetic basis of DON and NIV chemotypes has been established to be due to differences in <italic>TRI13</italic> and <italic>TRI7</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12-toxins-03-01294">12</xref>]. These genes are non-functional in DON-producing isolates so it is unclear how DON and NIV could both be produced by a single isolate. Similarly, the co-occurrence of 3ADON and 15ADON in the same isolates is surprising since the genetic basis of 3ADON and 15ADON chemotypes is due to different forms of <italic>TRI8</italic> in 3ADON and 15ADON-producing strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13-toxins-03-01294">13</xref>].</p>
      <p>Recognition by morphological characters sometimes is not enough for accurate identification of fungal isolates at the species level. In the last decade, genealogical concordance phylogenetic species recognition (GCPSR) was used to investigate genetic diversity and species limits within <italic>F. graminearum</italic> species complex (FGSC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14-toxins-03-01294">14</xref>]. Based on DNA sequences of 13 genes, FGSC was resolved in 13 species: <italic>Fusarium acacia-mearnsii</italic>, <italic>Fusarium aethiopicum</italic>, <italic>Fusarium asiaticum</italic>, <italic>Fusarium austroamericanum</italic>, <italic>Fusarium boothii</italic>, <italic>Fusarium brasilicum</italic>, <italic>Fusarium cortaderiae</italic>, <italic>Fusarium gerlachii</italic>, <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic>, <italic>Fusarium meridionale</italic>, <italic>Fusarium mesoamericanum</italic>, <italic>Fusarium ussurianum,</italic> and <italic>Fusarium vorosii</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15-toxins-03-01294">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16-toxins-03-01294">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17-toxins-03-01294">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18-toxins-03-01294">18</xref>]. Therefore, a correct identification of FGSC species is a critical point in order to correctly predict and evaluate the potential mycotoxigenic risk related to the occurrence of each species on wheat. The most geographically widespread species of the FGSC is <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic>, which predominates on wheat in North and South America and in Europe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19-toxins-03-01294">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20-toxins-03-01294">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21-toxins-03-01294">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22-toxins-03-01294">22</xref>]. On other hand, a recent report from South America has shown the occurrence on wheat also of another species of FGSC, <italic>F. meridionale</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23-toxins-03-01294">23</xref>]. </p>
      <p>In Argentina, wheat is cultivated in a 6,000,000 ha area that is divided into five regions (designated I to V, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="toxins-03-01294-f001">Figure 1</xref>) according to agrometeorological conditions. </p>
      <fig id="toxins-03-01294-f001" position="anchor">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Map showing the sample fields in the main wheat cultivation area in Argentina. Arabic numerals represent the locations of the 37 fields from which wheat was harvested and isolates were recovered. Wheat cropping area is distributed according to agrometeorological conditions into five regions (I to V, with region II and V divided in two subregions named North (N) and South (S)). </p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="toxins-03-01294-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Regions II and V are further divided into North (N) and South (S) based on differing climatic conditions in each. The regions/sub-regions IIS, IV and VS are considered the main production area because in these regions the production area is the widest in Argentina, the wheat cultivation is more intense and yields are greatest. Sub-region IIS covers almost the entire northern half of the province of Buenos Aires and the extreme South of the province of Santa Fe; region IV covers the south east of the province of Buenos Aires; and sub-region VS covers the far east of the province of La Pampa and the east and south east of the province of Buenos Aires. The temperature and humidity decrease along subregions IIS, IV and VS, with more extreme conditions in region VS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24-toxins-03-01294">24</xref>]. Within these extended areas, where FHB epidemics occur often due mainly to favourable weather conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25-toxins-03-01294">25</xref>], <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> has been reported to be the main cause of FHB only in two localities of Buenos Aires province [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20-toxins-03-01294">20</xref>]. However, the results, reported by Sampietro <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26-toxins-03-01294">26</xref>], demonstrated that the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> complex diversity in Argentina is greater than previously assessed since <italic>F. meridionale</italic> and <italic>F. boothi</italic> were isolated at a high concentration from maize grains cultivated in a wide area in northwest Argentina. </p>
      <p>The main objectives of this study were:</p>
      <list list-type="alpha-lower">
        <list-item>
          <p>deepen and broaden the genetic characterization of strains of the FGSC isolated in multiple seasons from wheat kernels in a wider wheat cropping area from Buenos Aires Province in Argentina than previously studied, by using Amplified Fragment Length Polymorphism (AFLP) and sequence analyses of translation elongation factor 1&#x2212;&#x3B1; (<italic>TEF1</italic>) and &#x3B2;-tubulin (<italic>TUB2</italic>) genes;</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>evaluate the genetic variability of a wide population of FGSC by using AFLP;</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>assess the main FGSC species occurring on wheat in Argentina, comparing it to the contradictory data previously reported from different cereals.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>2. Material and Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>2.1. Isolation and Identification</title>
        <p>Thirty-seven wheat samples from the main wheat production area of Argentina were analyzed. Each sample was from different localities selected over all the Buenos Aires province area and randomly collected from wheat harvested in 2001, 2003 and 2004 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="toxins-03-01294-f001">Figure 1</xref>). Samples were at least 1 kg in size and not sorted by grain quality (all grades included). For the isolation of the internal mycoflora, 100 kernels from each sample were surface disinfested in a 10% sodium hypochlorite for 1 minute, rinsed in sterile distilled water, then in 70% ethyl alcohol, and dried on a filter paper. The kernels were plated on a <italic>Fusarium</italic>-selective medium composed of potato dextrose agar (PDA) containing 0.2 g/L of pentachloronitrobenzene (PCNB) and incubated for 5 days at 25 &#xB0;C under fluorescent light (12 h photoperiod) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27-toxins-03-01294">27</xref>]. Putative <italic>Fusarium</italic> isolates recovered from the wheat kernels were purified by single-spore isolation. Morphological identification was determined with cultures grown on the low nutrient medium SNA (Spezieller Nahrstoffarmer Agar) with filter paper as described by Leslie and Summerell [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27-toxins-03-01294">27</xref>]. </p>
        <p>The 189 fungal isolates used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="toxins-03-01294-t001">Table 1</xref> together with data on their geographic origin and the year in which the corresponding wheat samples were harvested. </p>
        <table-wrap id="toxins-03-01294-t001" position="anchor">
          <object-id pub-id-type="pii">toxins-03-01294-t001_Table 1</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Locality and year of isolation of 189 <italic>Fusarium</italic> strains from Buenos Aires regions of Argentina used in this study. </p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample Fields *</th>
                <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographical Region</th>
                <th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">Year</th>
                <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strains ITEM Number **</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27-Pergamino</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIN</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2001</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8544-8545-8546-8547-8548</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-Arrecifes</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2001</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8310-8311</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-Coronel Villegas</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2001</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8386-8387</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24-Nueve de Julio</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2001</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8467-8468-8471-8473-8475-8476-8477-8478-8479-8480-8481-8482-8483-8485-8486-8487-8488-8492-8493-8497-8502-8504-8505-8510-8512-8513-8514-8516-8517-8526-8531-8538</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29-Saladillo</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2001</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8552</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31-San Pedro</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2001</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8559-8560-8561-8562-8563</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35-Salto</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2001</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8602-8603-8604</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-Belgrano</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2003</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8325-8327-8329-8330-8334-8335</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8-Cardales</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2003</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8339-8340-8341</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25-Pehuajo</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2003</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8540</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-Areco</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8308</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-Bolivar</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8337</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-Bragado</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8338</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10-Carlos Casares</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8357-8361-8362-8363</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11-25 de Mayo</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8364-8365-8366-8367-8368-8369-8370-8371-8372-8373-8374-8375-8376-8377-8379-8380-8381-8382-8589</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15-General Pinto</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8412-8413</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17-General Viamonte</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8417</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19-H Yrigoyen</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8420</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21-Lincoln</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8425-8426</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33-Trenque Lauquen</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8583-8585</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37-Suipacha</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIS</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8564 ***</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16-General Pueyrredon</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2001</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8414-8415-8416</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22-Loberia</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2003</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8427-8428-8429-8430-8432-8433</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-Azul</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8313-8314-8315-8316-8318-8319-8320-8321</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-Balcarce</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8322-8323-8324</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9-Cardenau</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8342-8343-8344-8345-8346-8347-8348-8349-8350-8351-8352-8353-8354-8355-8356</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13-General Alvarado</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8388-8393-8394-8395-8396-8397-8398-8399-8401-8402-8404-8405-8406-8407</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14-General Lamadrid</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8408-8409-8410</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20-Laprida</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8421-8422-8423-8424</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23-Necochea</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8435-8436-8438-8439-8440-8441-8444-8446-8447-8448-8453-8454-8456-8458-8460-8461-8462-8463-8464</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30-San Cayetano</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8555-8556-8558</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32-Tandil</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">2004</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8574-8576-8581-8582-8566 ***-8567 ***-8569 ***</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36-Coronel Suarez</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VS</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2003</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">8383 ****-8384 ****</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-Guamini</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VS</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">8418-8419</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26-Pellegrini</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VS</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">8542</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28-Saavedra</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VS</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">8549</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34-Conhello</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VS</td>
                <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004</td>
                <td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">8591-8600-8601</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>* The numbers show the location of the sample fields in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="toxins-03-01294-f001">Figure 1</xref>; ** Reference number of the Fungal Collection of Institute of Sciences of Food Production, Research National Council (ISPA-CNR), Bari, Italy; *** <italic>F. pseudograminearum</italic>; **** <italic>F. crookwellense</italic>.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>To aid in FGSC species identifications, we employed the following reference strains used as out-group in AFLP analyses, which were kindly provided by D. Geiser (The Penn State University): NRRL 2903 for <italic>F. austroamericanum</italic> (syn. Lineage 1); NRRL 26916 for <italic>F. boothi</italic> (syn. Lineage 3); NRRL 25797 for <italic>F. mesoamericanum</italic> (syn. Lineage 4); NRRL 26754 for <italic>F. acaciae-mearnsii</italic> (syn. Lineage 5); NRRL 13818 for <italic>F. asiaticum</italic> (syn. Lineage 6); NRRL 28336 and NRRL 5883 for <italic>F. graminearum</italic> (syn. Lineage 7); NRRL 29297 for <italic>F. cortaderiae</italic> (syn. Lineage 8) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14-toxins-03-01294">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15-toxins-03-01294">15</xref>]. All strains were deposited in the culture collection of the Institute of Sciences of Food Production, Bari, Italy (ITEM) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28-toxins-03-01294">28</xref>]. All 189 strains from wheat kernels in Argentina (53 isolated in 2001, 18 in 2003, and 118 strains isolated in 2004) were subjected to gene sequencing and AFLP analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>2.2. DNA Extraction</title>
        <p>Fungal isolates were grown for 48 h in shake cultures (125 rpm) at 25 &#xB0;C in 100 mL of Wikerham&#x2019;s medium (4% D-glucose, 0.5% peptone, 0.3% yeast extract, 0.3% malt extract). The resulting mycelium was vacuum-filtered on Whatman N&#xB0; 4 filter paper, washed with distilled water, frozen, and lyophilised. About 25-30 mg of lyophilised mycelium was ground and used to prepare genomic DNA with the E.Z.N.A. Fungal DNA Miniprep Kit (Omega Bio-tek, Doraville, GA). Extracted DNA was dissolved in 100 &#x3BC;L of sterile water and stored at &#x2212;20 &#xB0;C. DNA concentrations were estimated by comparison with a known concentration of a DNA ladder following agarose gel electrophoresis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>2.3. Mating Type Analysis</title>
        <p>A multiplex PCR was used to detect the mating type genes of the isolates. The primers used to amplify the Mating type 1 (MAT1-1) idiomorph were M12-1: 5'-ATGGATACCTCCTTCAGTTTC-3' and M12-2: 5'-GATCATCCGGCTCCTCAGGGT C-3'; and the primers used to amplify the Mating type 2 (MAT1-2) idiomorph were M21-1: 5'-ATGAGCACCCTTATGTTGATG-3' and M21-2: 5'-TCAGACGTTGTTTTTGCTGAGC-3' [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14-toxins-03-01294">14</xref>]. PCR was performed in a final volume of 20 &#x3BC;L, using 5 ng of DNA, 0.3 &#x3BC;L of each primer (10 mM), 0.4 &#x3BC;L of dNTPs (10 mM) and 0.1 &#x3BC;L of Taq DNA Polymerase (Hot Master, 5 U/&#x3BC;L). The thermal cycler parameters were: initial denaturation for 5 min at 94 &#xB0;C; 40 cycles of 35 s at 94 &#xB0;C, 55 s at 54 &#xB0;C, 2 min at 72 &#xB0;C; and a final extension for 7 min at 72 &#xB0;C. The expected amplicon sizes were 1500 bp and 800 bp for MAT1-1 and MAT1-2, respectively. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>2.4. DNA Sequencing</title>
        <p>Sequence analysis of <italic>TEF1</italic> and <italic>TUB2</italic> genes employed PCR conditions and primers described by O&#x2019;Donnell <italic>et al.</italic>  [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14-toxins-03-01294">14</xref>]. PCR products were analyzed by agarose gel electrophoresis to confirm that a ~700 bp fragment was amplified for <italic>TEF1</italic> and a ~1300 bp fragment was amplified for <italic>TUB2</italic>. Fragments were purified by filtration through Shepadex G-50 (Sigma) prior to DNA sequencing. Sequence analysis was carried out with the Big Dye Terminator Cycle Sequencing Ready Reaction Kit (Applied Biosystems). Sequences were aligned in ClustalW [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29-toxins-03-01294">29</xref>] by using default settings with MEGA software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30-toxins-03-01294">30</xref>]. Aligned sequence data were subjected to maximum-parsimony (MP) analysis by using the Close-Neighbor-Interchange algorithm with 10 random-addition replicates with the MEGA 4 software. Clade validation was assessed by bootstrap analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31-toxins-03-01294">31</xref>], using heuristic searches with 1000 replicates. Previously generated <italic>TEF1</italic> and <italic>TUB2</italic> sequences obtained from the National Center for Bioechnology Information (NCBI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32-toxins-03-01294">32</xref>] were also included to allow comparative analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>2.5. AFLP Analysis</title>
        <p>AFLP analysis was performed with the AFLP<sup>TM</sup> Microbial Fingerprint Kit (Applied Biosystems, Fostercity, CA). Restriction enzymes <italic>EcoRI</italic> and <italic>MseI</italic> (New England Biolabs, Hitchin, Hertfordshire, United Kingdom) were used to digest 10 ng of genomic DNA from each isolate, and DNA fragments were ligated with T4 DNA ligase (New England Biolabs, Hitchin, Hertfordshire, United Kingdom) to double-stranded restriction site-specific adaptors supplied by the kit (AFLP<sup>TM</sup> Microbial Fingerprint). The selective reactions used three primer combinations: <italic>EcoRI</italic>+AC/<italic>MseI</italic>+CC, <italic>EcoRI</italic>+AT/<italic>MseI</italic>+CG and <italic>EcoRI</italic>+G/<italic>MseI</italic>+CT, where the <italic>EcoRI</italic> primers were labeled with FAM, NED and JOE fluorescent dyes (Applied Biosystems), respectively. After amplification, the products were mixed with deionized formamide and the GeneScan-500 (Rox) size standard (Applied Biosystems), and then separated by capillary electrophoresis on ABI PRISM 310 Genetic Analyzer. Raw data were analyzed using GeneScan Collection software (version 3.1.2, Applied Biosystems), and AFLP patterns were analyzed with Genotyper software (Applied Biosystems). AFLP peaks ranging from 150 to 500 bp in length and with peak height limit of at least 200. Bands of the same size in different samples were assumed to be homologous and to represent the same allele. Bands of different sizes were considered independent loci with two alleles (present and absent). AFLP data of 183 <italic>Fusarium</italic> Argentinean isolates and 8 reference strains of the FGSC were exported in a binary matrix, in which &#x201C;1&#x201D; represented the presence of the peak and &#x201C;0&#x201D; its absence. Statistical software NTSYS (version 2.02, Exeter software, Setauket, NY) was used for cluster analysis by using DICE similarity coefficient and the un-weighted pair group method (UPGMA). The trees were generated by using the sequential agglomerative hierarchical nested clustering program (SAHN; Exeter software, Setauket, NY). Each DNA sample was subjected to AFLP analysis in at least two independent experiments and yielded the same AFLP profile each time it was run. Strains with &gt;98 AFLP band similarity were considered to belong to the same haplotype.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>3. Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>3.1. Strain Isolation and Identification</title>
        <p>One hundred eighty-nine isolates of <italic>Fusarium</italic> were recovered from wheat kernels that were harvested from across the major wheat-producing region of Argentina during the 2001, 2003 and 2004 growing seasons. All isolates were subjected to PCR to analyze for the presence of the <italic>MAT-1</italic> and <italic>MAT-2</italic> idiomorphs. The PCR yielded amplicons for both idiomorphs from 183 isolates and an amplicon for only the <italic>MAT-2</italic> idiomorph from the remaining six isolates (ITEM 8364, 8366, 8367, 8369, 8383 and 8384). To identify the species to which each isolate belongs, fragments of the <italic>TEF1</italic> and <italic>TUB2</italic> genes were also amplified and sequenced and then subjected to BLAST analysis against the Fusarium-ID database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33-toxins-03-01294">33</xref>]. This analysis indicated that the isolates with <italic>MAT-2</italic> only were either <italic>F. crookwellense</italic> (ITEM 8383 and 8384) or <italic>F. pseudograminearum</italic> (ITEM 8364, 8366, 8367 and 8369), whereas isolates with both idiomorphs were <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="toxins-03-01294-t001">Table 1</xref>). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>3.2. DNA Sequence-Base Phylogenetic Analysis</title>
        <p>The <italic>TEF1</italic> and <italic>TUB2</italic> sequences from a subset of isolates were also subjected to phylogenetic analysis. This analysis employed sequences from 72 randomly selected isolates identified as <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="toxins-03-01294-t001">Table 1</xref>) as well as two isolates identified as <italic>F. pseudograminearum</italic> (ITEM 8366 and 8367), and one identified as <italic>F. crookwellense</italic> (ITEM 8384). In addition, as reference, sequences for FGSC species were downloaded from NCBI and included in the analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13-toxins-03-01294">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15-toxins-03-01294">15</xref>]. One-thousand-four-hundred-sixty-five phylogenetic trees were formed with <italic>TEF1</italic> (Consistency index, Ci: 0.88 and Retention Index, Ri: 0.96) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="toxins-03-01294-f002">Figure 2</xref>). Similar phylogram was obtained with <italic>TUB2</italic> sequences. The 72 <italic>F. graminearum</italic> wheat isolates from Argentina formed a distinct clade with reference strains of <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> that was distinct from the other FGSC species included in the analysis. These results further support the identity of the majority of isolates from Argentinean wheat as <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic>.</p>
        <fig id="toxins-03-01294-f002" position="anchor">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>One of the 1465 most-parsimonious phylograms inferred from translation elongation factor gene sequences. The phylogenetic tree is composed by 72 randomly selected sequences of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> Argentinean strains, 2 of <italic>F. pseudograminearum</italic>, 1 of <italic>F. croockwellense</italic> and the strains used to define species inside FGSC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15-toxins-03-01294">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17-toxins-03-01294">17</xref>], combined with sequences of the eleven species of the FGSC complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17-toxins-03-01294">17</xref>] registered in NCBI database. Branches that received &gt;50% bootstrap values were indicated.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="toxins-03-01294-g002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>3.3. Nucleotide Sequence Accession Numbers</title>
        <p>DNA sequence data generated in the present study for phylogenetic analysis belonging to the 75 strains of <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> (72), <italic>F. pseudograminearum</italic> (2), and <italic>F. crookwellense</italic> (1) have been deposited in GenBank under accession numbers from JN687849 to JN687923.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>3.4. AFLP Analysis</title>
        <p>Isolates identified as <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> were also subjected to AFLP analysis. The AFLP protocol generated a total of 232 reproducible loci ranging in size from 150 to 500 bp; 57 loci were generated with the <italic>EcoRI</italic>-AC/<italic>MseI</italic>-CC primer combination, 52 loci with the <italic>EcoRI</italic>-AT/<italic>MseI</italic>-CG combination, and 123 loci with the <italic>EcoRI</italic>-G/<italic>MseI</italic>-CT combination. Twelve loci were uninformative and were excluded from the UPGMA analysis and determination of DICE similarity coefficient. Based on the UPGMA-generated dendrogram, the isolates of <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> isolated from wheat as well as the reference strains for this species formed a cluster that was distinct from the other six FGSC species included in the analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="toxins-03-01294-f003">Figure 3</xref>a,b). </p>
        <fig id="toxins-03-01294-f003" position="anchor">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Dendrogram generated with AFLP data of 183 <italic>F. graminearum</italic> Argentinean strains and <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> complex standard isolates, generated by NTSYS software with DICE similarity index. Strains are signed with the ITEM number preceded by the field number. Subclusters from A1 to A11 are reported in the figure.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="toxins-03-01294-g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The analysis also indicated that 152 (83%) of the <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> isolates were highly similar to one another and to reference strains NRRL 28336 and NRRL 5883 for this species; the DICE similarity coefficients for the 152 isolates and two reference strains were &gt;0.85 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="toxins-03-01294-f003">Figure 3</xref>a,b). Although Argentinean isolates were grouped in one main cluster, the dendrogram indicates that most of isolates could be grouped in at least 11 sub-clusters, named in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="toxins-03-01294-f003">Figure 3</xref>a,b from A1 to A11. Among them, 10 isolates branched as a single member. A clear cluster made of 10 strains, mainly isolated from the fields, numbers 3 and 4 of the IV region, was formed. The resolved sub-clusters were not correlated with geographical origin, year of harvest or chemotype. No isolate with the same haplotype was found; therefore no isolate was a clonal one. The other 17 isolates of <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> analyzed were less similar to one another as well as the other 152 isolates; they exhibited similarity coefficients of &lt;0.84. In particular, among this group of strains, ITEM 8428 branched at a similarity value of 0.70, being the most distant from all the other strains (DICE similarity coefficient &gt;0.77). This relatively low level of similarity among the 17 isolates was comparable to levels of similarity among some FGSC species; <italic>i.e</italic>., the DICE similarity coefficient for <italic>F. austroamericanum versus F. cortaderiae</italic> and for <italic>F. acaciae-mearnsii versus F. asiaticum</italic> were ~0.79 and ~0.75 respectively. </p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>4. Discussion</title>
      <p>Previous studies on the genetic diversity of <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> from wheat in Argentina have been limited. In one study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20-toxins-03-01294">20</xref>], the genetic diversity of 113 isolates recovered from wheat from two locations and during one growing season was examined by AFLP analysis. However, the profile of trichothecene production was not determined. In a second study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11-toxins-03-01294">11</xref>], trichothecene production profiles were examined for 144 isolates from multiple locations across a large area of the major wheat-producing region of Argentina. However, the genetic diversity of the strains was not examined. In the current study, we examined the species identity and genetic diversity (via AFLP analysis) of the collection of 144 isolates noted above, plus 39 additional isolates, for which trichothecene production was previously determined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11-toxins-03-01294">11</xref>]. Our analysis provides further evidence that <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> is the predominant species of the FGSC in the temperate wheat production region of Argentina. This is the same species that predominates in North America and Europe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15-toxins-03-01294">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21-toxins-03-01294">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22-toxins-03-01294">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34-toxins-03-01294">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35-toxins-03-01294">35</xref>] and that has been reported elsewhere in South America [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20-toxins-03-01294">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23-toxins-03-01294">23</xref>]. However, many reports have also shown that other FGSC species can often co-occur with <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> in the same geographical areas, as it was reported in New Zealand and China [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36-toxins-03-01294">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37-toxins-03-01294">37</xref>]. Recent reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26-toxins-03-01294">26</xref>] indicated that the FGSC species <italic>F. meridionale</italic> and <italic>F. bothii</italic> predominate on maize in north western, subtropical Argentina, whereas <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> predominates on maize and wheat in the temperate regions of Argentina. The co-occurrence of potentially interfertile but phylogenetically distinct FGSC species could promote interbreeding between the species and, therefore, formation of new genotypes that could affect pathogenicity, host range, or toxin production. The homogeneity of the Argentinean population of FGSC from wheat reported here and previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20-toxins-03-01294">20</xref>] could provide an advantage with respect to disease management, plant breeding strategies and quarantine regulations. However, the occurrence of other FGSC species in Argentina should be verified by analyzing other potential host plants, such as maize, barley, and other small cereals. In particular, the occurrence of <italic>F. cortaderiae</italic>, considered by O&#x2019;Donnell <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15-toxins-03-01294">15</xref>] to have a South American origin, should be evaluated.</p>
      <p>From the preliminary AFLP analysis, the high number of polymorphic loci estimated within the 183 field isolates of <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> from Argentina, indicate that the genetic diversity within this species is relatively high. Moreover, the high percentage of haplotypes occurring within the field population of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> highlighted a high degree of genotypic diversity. In particular, the occurrence of two strains, ITEM 8432 and 8428, provided of a low level of similarity with respect to the whole set of strains, due to both unique loci and relatively unique combinations of some loci, increased the genetic/genotypic diversity of the population here investigated. However, these data agree with the data shown by Ramirez <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20-toxins-03-01294">20</xref>] that found a high level of genetic exchange between two populations of <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> isolated from two different localities in Argentina and considered them potentially part of a larger randomly mating population. Moreover, this genotypic variability could be explained by out-crossing, which appears to be common in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> in South and North America [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8-toxins-03-01294">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22-toxins-03-01294">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38-toxins-03-01294">38</xref>] and by gene flow, since the potential long distance dispersal of spores of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> has been well documented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39-toxins-03-01294">39</xref>]. In this study, we utilized two different approaches, AFLP analysis and analysis of DNA sequence of two genes, to gain insight into evolutionary relationships within a population of FGSC isolated from wheat in Argentina. Phylogenetic analysis based on comparisons of <italic>TEF1</italic> and <italic>TUB2</italic> sequences assigned all strains analyzed to <italic>F. graminaerum sensu stricto</italic>. The sequence data are consistent with AFLP data that grouped the Argentinean isolates with the two <italic>ex type</italic> strains of <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> and delineated them from <italic>ex-type</italic> strains of six other FGSC species. Our AFLP data indicate that the level of diversity among some <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> isolates was greater than the level of diversity between the two FGSC species <italic>F. austroamaricanum</italic> and <italic>F. cortaderiae</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="toxins-03-01294-f003">Figure 3</xref>a,b). However, since phenetic criteria such as percent identity of AFLP are considered less reliable and biologically meaningful than GCPSR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15-toxins-03-01294">15</xref>], these data must be evaluated carefully. </p>
      <p>The mycotoxin production of 115 out of the 183 strains, was the object of a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11-toxins-03-01294">11</xref>] that showed that DON was produced by most of the isolates. Isolates producing 15ADON were more common than those producing 3ADON. It is interesting to underline that both 3ADON and 15ADON strains of <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> here reported do not seem to be genetically distinct entities since they occur along the entire length of the AFLP-generated dendrogram. Although this is in contrast with O&#x2019;Donnell <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16-toxins-03-01294">16</xref>] that showed 3ADON and 15ADON isolates of <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> from USA as genetically distinct populations, our data agree with previous studies based on AFLP that could not resolve into separate clades 3ADON and 15ADON isolates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20-toxins-03-01294">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21-toxins-03-01294">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39-toxins-03-01294">39</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>5. Conclusions</title>
      <p>This report contributes to an improved understanding of the genetic diversity within <italic>F. graminearum sensu stricto</italic> across an extended wheat-cropping area of Argentina. This information will be useful for monitoring any future changes in the pathogen related to trichothecene production and for adopting strategies to control Fusarium Head Blight in Argentina. Finally, although only a few strains were isolated, our results provide the first report of <italic>F. pseudograminearum</italic> and <italic>F. crookwellense</italic> on wheat in Argentina.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank Vincenzo Ricci for its valuable technical assistance. We thank Instituto Italo-LatinoAmericano for supporting Cora L Alvarez studies at ISPA-CNR, Bari, Italy. </p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>X.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berrie</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epidemiology of mycotoxigenic fungi associated with <italic>Fusarium</italic> ear blight and apple blue mould: A review.</article-title>
          <source>Food Addit. Contam.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>290</fpage>
          <lpage>301</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02652030500058353</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16019798</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Desjardins</surname>
              <given-names>A.E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Fusarium mycotoxins. Chemistry, Genetics and Biology</source>
          <publisher-name>American Phythopathological Society Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>St. Paul, MN, USA</publisher-loc>
          <year>2006</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klich</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mycotoxins.</article-title>
          <source>Clin. Microbiol. Rev.</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>497</fpage>
          <lpage>516</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12857779</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miller</surname>
              <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greenhalgh</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Y.Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Trichothecene chemotype of three <italic>Fusarium</italic> species.</article-title>
          <source>Mycologia</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <fpage>121</fpage>
          <lpage>130</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3759927</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yli-Mattila</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ecology, and evolution of toxigenic <italic>Fusarium</italic> species in cereals in northern Europe and Asia.</article-title>
          <source>J. Plant Pathol.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>7</fpage>
          <lpage>18</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schmale</surname>
              <given-names>D.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wood-Jones</surname>
              <given-names>A.K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cowger</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bergstrom</surname>
              <given-names>G.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arellano</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Trichothecene genotypes of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic> from winter wheat fields in the eastern USA.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Pathol.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>909</fpage>
          <lpage>917</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3059.2011.02443.x</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gale</surname>
              <given-names>L.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harrison</surname>
              <given-names>S.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Milus</surname>
              <given-names>E.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gale</surname>
              <given-names>S.W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kistler</surname>
              <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nivalenol-type populations of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> and <italic>F. asiaticum</italic> are prevalent on wheat in southern Louisiana</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>124</fpage>
          <lpage>134</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20822434</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-03-10-0067</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ram&#xED;rez</surname>
              <given-names>M.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reynoso</surname>
              <given-names>M.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farnochi</surname>
              <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chulze</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Vegetative compatibility and mycotoxin chemotypes among <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> (<italic>Gibberella zeae</italic>) isolates from wheat in Argentina.</article-title>
          <source>Eur. J. Plant Pathol.</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>115</volume>
          <fpage>139</fpage>
          <lpage>148</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10658-006-0009-1</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lori</surname>
              <given-names>G.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carranza</surname>
              <given-names>M.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Violante</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rizzo</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alippi</surname>
              <given-names>H.E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Fusarium</italic> spp. en trigo, capacidad toxicogenica y quimiotaxonomia de las cepas aisladas en la Argentina</article-title>
          <source>Agronomie </source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>459</fpage>
          <lpage>467</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/agro:19920604</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fern&#xE1;ndez Pinto</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Terminiello</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Basilico</surname>
              <given-names>J.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ritieni</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Natural occurrence of nivalenol and mycotoxigenic potential of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> strains in wheat affected by Head Blight in Argentina.</article-title>
          <source>Braz. J.Microbiol.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>157</fpage>
          <lpage>162</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1517-83822008000100031</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alvarez</surname>
              <given-names>C.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azcarate</surname>
              <given-names>P.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fern&#xE1;ndez Pinto</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Toxigenic potential of <italic>Fusarium graminearum sensu stricto</italic> isolates from wheat in Argentina.</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Food Microbiol.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>135</volume>
          <fpage>131</fpage>
          <lpage>135</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19717200</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2009.07.037</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>Y.-K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>K.-H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yun</surname>
              <given-names>S.-H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>Y.-W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Tri13</italic> and <italic>Tri7</italic> determine deoxynivalenol- and nivalenol-producing chemotypes of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic>.</article-title>
          <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>2148</fpage>
          <lpage>2154</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11976083</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.68.5.2148-2154.2002</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alexander</surname>
              <given-names>N.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McCormick</surname>
              <given-names>S.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waalwijk</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van der Lee</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Proctor</surname>
              <given-names>R.H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The genetic basis for 3-ADON and 15-ADON trichothecene chemotypes in <italic>Fusarium</italic>.</article-title>
          <source>Fungal Genet. Biol.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>485</fpage>
          <lpage>495</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21216300</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fgb.2011.01.003</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kistler</surname>
              <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tacke</surname>
              <given-names>B.K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caspar</surname>
              <given-names>H.H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gene genealogies reveal global phylogeographic structure and reproductive isolation among lineages of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>, the fungus causing wheat scab.</article-title>
          <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>7905</fpage>
          <lpage>7910</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10869425</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geiser</surname>
              <given-names>D.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kistler</surname>
              <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aoki</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genealogical concordance between the mating type locus and seven other nuclear genes supports formal recognition of nine phylogenetically distinct species within the <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> clade.</article-title>
          <source>Fungal Genet. Biol.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>600</fpage>
          <lpage>623</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15121083</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fgb.2004.03.003</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aberra</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kistler</surname>
              <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aoki</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orwig</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kimura</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bj&#xF8;rnstad</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klemsdal</surname>
              <given-names>S.S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multilocus genotyping and molecular phylogenetics resolve a novel head blight pathogen within the <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> species complex from Ethiopia.</article-title>
          <source>Fungal Genet. Biol.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>1514</fpage>
          <lpage>1522</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18824240</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fgb.2008.09.002</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Starkey</surname>
              <given-names>D.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aoki</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gale</surname>
              <given-names>L.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kistler</surname>
              <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geiser</surname>
              <given-names>D.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suga</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>T&#xF3;th</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Varga</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Global molecular surveillance reveals novel <italic>Fusarium</italic> head blight species and trichothecene toxin diversity.</article-title>
          <source>Fungal Genet. Biol.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>1745</fpage>
          <lpage>1776</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yli-Mattila</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gagkaeva</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aoki</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kistler</surname>
              <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel Asian clade within the <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> species complex includes a newly discovered cereal head blight pathogen from the Russian Far East.</article-title>
          <source>Mycologia</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>841</fpage>
          <lpage>852</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19927749</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3852/08-217</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Laday</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Juh&#xE0;sz</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mul&#xE8;</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moretti</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sz&#xE8;csi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Logrieco</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA diversity and lineage determination of European isolates of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> (<italic>Gibberella zeae</italic>).</article-title>
          <source>Eur. J. Plant Pathol.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>545</fpage>
          <lpage>550</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:EJPP.0000032394.39130.2c</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ramirez</surname>
              <given-names>M.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reynoso</surname>
              <given-names>M.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farnochi</surname>
              <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Torres</surname>
              <given-names>A.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leslie</surname>
              <given-names>J.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chulze</surname>
              <given-names>S.N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Population genetic structure of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic> isolated from wheat in Argentina.</article-title>
          <source>Food Addit. Contam.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>1115</fpage>
          <lpage>1120</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17886183</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02652030701546487</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zeller</surname>
              <given-names>K.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bowden</surname>
              <given-names>R.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leslie</surname>
              <given-names>J.F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diversity of epidemic populations of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic> from small quadrats in Kansas and North Dakota.</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>874</fpage>
          <lpage>880</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18943169</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO.2003.93.7.874</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zeller</surname>
              <given-names>K.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bowden</surname>
              <given-names>R.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leslie</surname>
              <given-names>J.F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Population differentiation and recombination in wheat scab populations of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic> from the United States.</article-title>
          <source>Mol. Ecol.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>563</fpage>
          <lpage>571</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14871361</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-294X.2004.02098.x</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scoz</surname>
              <given-names>L.B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Astolfi</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reartes</surname>
              <given-names>D.S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmale</surname>
              <given-names>D.G.</given-names>
              <suffix>III</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moraes</surname>
              <given-names>M.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Del Ponte</surname>
              <given-names>E.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Trichothecene mycotoxin genotypes of Fusarium graminearum sensu stricto and Fusarium meridionale in wheat from southern Brazil</article-title>
          <source>Plant Pathol. </source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>344</fpage>
          <lpage>351</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3059.2008.01949.x</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Trigo Argentino Home Page</article-title>
          <date-in-citation>(accessed on 20 October 2011)</date-in-citation>
          <comment>Available online:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.trigoargentino.com.ar">www.trigoargentino.com.ar</ext-link></comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moschini</surname>
              <given-names>R.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pioli</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carmona</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sacchi</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Empirical predictions of wheat head blight in the Northern Argentinean Pampas Region.</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci.</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>1541</fpage>
          <lpage>1545</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sampietro</surname>
              <given-names>D.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D&#xED;az</surname>
              <given-names>C.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonzalez</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vattuone</surname>
              <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ploper</surname>
              <given-names>L.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Catalan</surname>
              <given-names>C.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Species diversity and toxigenic potential of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> complex isolates from maize fields in northwest Argentina.</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Food Microbiol.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>145</volume>
          <fpage>359</fpage>
          <lpage>364</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21277035</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2010.12.021</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Leslie</surname>
              <given-names>J.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Summerell</surname>
              <given-names>B.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The Fusarium Laboratory Manual</source>
          <publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Ames, IA, USA</publisher-loc>
          <year>2006</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <collab>ITEM Collection</collab>
          <article-title>Agri-Food Toxigenic Fungi Culture Collection</article-title>
          <date-in-citation>(accessed on 20 October 2011)</date-in-citation>
          <comment>Available online:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ispa.cnr.it/Collection">www.ispa.cnr.it/Collection</ext-link></comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Higgins</surname>
              <given-names>D.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gibson</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>CLUSTAL W: Improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title>
          <source>Nucl. Acids Res.</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>4673</fpage>
          <lpage>4680</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tamura</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dudley</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nei</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0.</article-title>
          <source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>1596</fpage>
          <lpage>1599</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488738</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msm092</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Felsenstein</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Confidence limits on phylogenies: An approach using the bootstrap.</article-title>
          <source>Evolution</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>783</fpage>
          <lpage>791</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>NCBI Home Page</article-title>
          <date-in-citation>(accessed on 20 October 2011)</date-in-citation>
          <comment>Available online:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link></comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geiser</surname>
              <given-names>D.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>del Mar Jimenez-Gasco</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kang</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Makalowska</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Veeraraghavan</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuldau</surname>
              <given-names>G.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>FUSARIUM-ID v.1.0: A DNA sequence database for identifying <italic>Fusarium</italic></article-title>
          <source>Eur. J. Plant Pathol.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>473</fpage>
          <lpage>480</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:EJPP.0000032386.75915.a0</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gagkaeva</surname>
              <given-names>T.Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yli-Mattila</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic Diversity of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> in Europe and Asia.</article-title>
          <source>Eur. J. Plant Pathol.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>551</fpage>
          <lpage>562</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:EJPP.0000032395.11246.d0</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clear</surname>
              <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rooney</surname>
              <given-names>A.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gaba</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patrick</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Starkey</surname>
              <given-names>D.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilbert</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geiger</surname>
              <given-names>D.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nowicki</surname>
              <given-names>T.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An adaptive evolutionary shift in <italic>Fusarium</italic> head blight pathogen populations is driving the rapid spread of more toxigenic <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> in North America.</article-title>
          <source>Fungal Genet. Biol.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>473</fpage>
          <lpage>484</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18035565</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fgb.2007.10.003</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Monds</surname>
              <given-names>R.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cromey</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lauren</surname>
              <given-names>D.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>di Menna</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marshall</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fusarium gramineraum, F cortaderiae and F pseudogramineraum in New Zealand: Molecular phylogenetic analysis, mycotoxin chemotypes and co-existence of specie</article-title>
          <source>Mycol. Res.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>410</fpage>
          <lpage>420</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15912928</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Qu</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>H.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>J.B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>A.B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>C.S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caarter</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicholson</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liao</surname>
              <given-names>Y.C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Geographic distribution and genetic diversity of <italic>Fusarium gramineraum</italic> and <italic>F. asiaticum</italic> on wheat spikes throughout China</article-title>
          <source>Plant Pathol.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>15</fpage>
          <lpage>24</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gale</surname>
              <given-names>L.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>L.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hernick</surname>
              <given-names>C.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katamura</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kistler</surname>
              <given-names>H.C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Population analysis of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> from wheat fields in Eastern China.</article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>1315</fpage>
          <lpage>1322</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18943886</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO.2002.92.12.1315</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39-toxins-03-01294">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schmale</surname>
              <given-names>D.G.</given-names>
              <suffix>III</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leslie</surname>
              <given-names>J.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zeller</surname>
              <given-names>K.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saleh</surname>
              <given-names>A.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shields</surname>
              <given-names>E.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bergstrom</surname>
              <given-names>G.C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic structure of athmospheric populations of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>
          <source>Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>96</volume>
          <fpage>1021</fpage>
          <lpage>1026</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944058</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-96-1021</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
