<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?properties no_embargo?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2639029</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ern259</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18953072</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Papers</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Overexpression of <italic>TiERF1</italic> enhances resistance to sharp eyespot in transgenic wheat</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Liang</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>ZengYan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>HongXia</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>HongXia</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Du</surname>
            <given-names>LiPu</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>Huijun</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xin</surname>
            <given-names>Zhiyong</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>National Key Facility for Crop Gene Resources and Genetic Improvement, Institute of Crop Science, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing 100081, PR China</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>zhangzy@mail.caas.net.cn</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated  by PMC from publisher pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>59</volume>
      <issue>15</issue>
      <fpage>4195</fpage>
      <lpage>4204</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2008 The Author(s).</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p>
          <p>This paper is available online free of all access charges (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html">http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html</ext-link> for further details)</p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wheat sharp eyespot, primarily caused by a soil-borne fungus <italic>Rhizoctonia cerealis</italic>, has become one of the most serious diseases of wheat in China. In this study, an ethylene response factor (ERF) gene from a wheat relative <italic>Thinopyrum intermedium</italic>, <italic>TiERF1</italic>, was characterized further, transgenic wheat lines expressing <italic>TiERF1</italic> were developed, and the resistance of the transgenic wheat lines against <italic>R. cerealis</italic> was investigated. Southern blotting analysis indicated that at least two copies of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene exist in the <italic>T. intermedium</italic> genome. Yeast one-hybrid assay indicated that the activation domain of TiERF1 is essential for activating the transcript of the reporter gene with the GCC-box <italic>cis</italic>-element. The <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene was introduced into a Chinese wheat cultivar, Yangmai12, by biolistic bombardment. Results of PCR and Southern blotting analyses indicated that <italic>TiERF1</italic> was successfully integrated into the genome of the transgenic wheat, where it can be passed down from the T<sub>0</sub> to T<sub>4</sub> generations. Quantitative reverse transcription-PCR analysis demonstrated that <italic>TiERF1</italic> could be overexpressed in the stable transgenic plants, in which the expression levels of wheat pathogenesis-related (PR) genes primarily in the ethylene-dependent signal pathway, such as a chitinase gene and a &#x3B2;-1,3-glucanase gene, were increased dramatically. Disease tests indicated that the overexpression of <italic>TiERF1</italic> conferred enhanced resistance to sharp eyespot in the transgenic wheat lines compared with the wild-type and silenced <italic>TiERF1</italic> plants. These results suggested that the overexpression of <italic>TiERF1</italic> enhances resistance to sharp eyespot in transgenic wheat lines by activating PR genes primarily in the ethylene-dependent pathway.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Defence-related gene</kwd>
        <kwd>ethylene response factor (ERF)</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Rhizoctonia cerealis</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>sharp eyespot</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Thinopyrum intermedium</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>transgenic wheat plants</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Wheat sharp eyespot, mainly caused by <italic>Rhizoctonia cerealis</italic>, has become one of the most serious diseases of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) in China since the 1980s. In infected wheat plants, <italic>R. cerealis</italic> may destroy the transport tissues and other tissues in stems and sheaths of host plants, leading to a block in the transportation of substances required for nutrition, to lodging, and even to dead spikes. In China, wheat production, with &gt;6.00 million ha each year, was subjected to a sharp eyespot threat from 2005 to 2008, resulting in economic losses of &gt;&#xA5;1 billion.</p>
      <p>Breeding wheat varieties with resistance to sharp eyespot is the most promising and reliable means of wheat sharp eyespot control. However, there is very little basic theoretical research on wheat defence against <italic>R. cerealis</italic>, and no reliably resistant cultivars in different environment conditions have been developed by traditional breeding to date. Therefore, it is necessary and urgent for effective control of sharp eyespot to strengthen research on wheat defence mechanisms against <italic>R. cerealis</italic> and to develop genetic engineering to increase the disease resistance in wheat.</p>
      <p>Plants have evolved a complex battery of defence mechanisms against attacks of various pathogens. The key to understanding plant defence responses lies in the elucidation of the signalling pathways involved in their regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">McGrath <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). In the model plant <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), the salicylic acid (SA)-dependent systemic acquired resistance (SAR) pathway, and jasmonic acid (JA) and ethylene (ET)-induced resistance pathways are well recognized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Thomma <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Hammond-Kosack and Parker, 2003</xref>). SA, JA, and ET are each involved in the regulation of defence against different pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Thomma <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Qiu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Resistance to biotrophic pathogens is primarily regulated by an SA-dependent pathway, whereas resistance against necrotrophic pathogens and insects is usually regulated by a JA/ET-dependent pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Thomma <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">McGrath <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). However, SA- and JA-/ET-dependent defence signals interact with each other, either synergistically or antagonistically (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Durrant and Dong, 2004</xref>).</p>
      <p>Transcription factors (TFs) are believed to play a crucial role in the transmission of pathogen-derived defence signals to either activate or suppress expression of downstream defence genes as well as in the regulation of cross-talk between different signalling pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Lorenzo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">McGrath <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). There is accumulating evidence to show that activator-type ethylene-responsive factors (ERFs) of TFs positively regulated the defence responses to a range of pathogens in various plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Zhou <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Park <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Berrocal-Lobo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Gu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Yi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">McGrath <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Cao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; O&#x148;ate-S&#xE1;nchez and Singh, 2007). For instance, constitutive expression of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ERF1 confers host resistance to several necrotrophic and soil-borne pathogens via activating expression of downstream PR genes in the JA- and ET-dependent pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Berrocal-Lobo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Lorenzo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; Berrocal-Lobo and Monila, 2004). Accordingly, in many instances, genes encoding TFs that are involved in plant defence signalling are also transcriptionally regulated by pathogen challenge and treatment with defence elicitors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">McGrath <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>).</p>
      <p>In a previous study, <italic>Thinopyrum intermedium</italic> [Barkworth and Dewey=<italic>Agropyron intermedium</italic> (Host) Beauvoir], a wheat wild relative with resistance to <italic>R. cerealis</italic>, was used to isolate a pathogen-induced ERF gene, <italic>TiERF1</italic>, whose expression was induced by <italic>R. cerealis</italic> challenge based on quantitative reverse transcription-PCR (Q-RT-PCR) analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Liang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). That study suggested that TiERF1 may be involved in the plant defence response to <italic>R. cerealis</italic> infection. To unravel whether and how TiERF1 functions in defence against <italic>R. cerealis</italic>, the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene was introduced into a susceptible wheat cultivar.</p>
      <p>In the present report, <italic>TiERF1</italic> was further characterized, transgenic wheat lines overexpressing the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene were developed, and the resistance to <italic>R. cerealis</italic> of the transgenic wheat lines and the expression of a subset of wheat PR genes were investigated.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Plant materials and treatments</title>
        <p>The wheat cultivar (cv.) Yangmai12 was provided by Senior Researcher Shunhe Cheng from the Lixiahe Agricultural Institute of Jiangsu. The <italic>T. intermedium</italic> cv. Z1146 was kindly provided by Professor Lihui Li in our institute. Seeds of Yangmai12 and Z1146 were germinated and grown in a greenhouse with 16&#x2009;h light at 23&#x2009;&#xB0;C/8&#x2009;h darkness at 16&#x2009;&#xB0;C. Seedlings at the two- to three-leaf stage were treated with 1&#x2009;mM SA, 0.2&#x2009;mM methyl jasmonate (MeJA), ET released from 0.25&#x2009;mM ethephon, MeJA plus ET at the above concentration, and 0.1&#x2009;mM CoCl<sub>2</sub> (an inhibitor of ET synthesis), as well as water (mock) according to the method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref>. Leaves from the treatments mentioned above were harvested at the indicated times, then quickly frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x2013;80&#x2009;&#xB0;C until use.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Transactivation activity assay of <italic>TiERF1</italic> in yeast cells</title>
        <p>The reporter constructs, pGCC-LacZ and pmGCC-LacZ, were prepared according to the protocol of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref>. These constructs contain three copies of the GCC box (3&#xD7;GCC) or mutant GCC (3&#xD7;mGCC), respectively, fused to the <italic>Lac</italic>Z reporter gene in the vector pLacZi (Clontech). The effector vectors pYTiERF1, containing the full open reading frame (ORF) sequence of <italic>TiERF1</italic> (GenBank accession no. EF570121), and pYTiERF1&#x394;AD, in which the putative activation domain (from amino acid 51 to 75) in pYTiERF1 is deleted, were also prepared. All of these constructs possess activation and binding domains derived from TiERF1 rather than yeast, and can be expressed in yeast cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>).</p>
        <p>Using the methodology provided in the yeast one-hybrid manual (Clontech), the effector and reporter constructs were transformed into competent cells of the yeast strain YM4271 to form four kinds of combinations, namely Y-pYTiERF1/pGCC-LacZ, Y-pYTiERF1/pmGCC-LacZ, Y-pYTiERF1&#x394;AD/pGCC-LacZ, and Y-pYTiERF1/pLacZi. The transformants were selected by growth on SD medium minus Ura and Trp. Subsequently, a filter-lift assay on &#x3B2;-galactosidase (encoded by <italic>LacZ</italic>) activity was performed to determine the transcription activation character of the TiERF1 protein and TiERF1&#x394;AD protein according to the manual (Clontech).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Plant transformation vector and wheat transformation</title>
        <p>The pAHC25 plasmid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Christensen and Quail, 1996</xref>; a gift from Dr Peter Quail, USDA-ARS, Albany, CA, USA) contains the <italic>uidA</italic> [encoding the &#x3B2;-glucuronidase (GUS)] and <italic>bar</italic> [encoding the phosphinothricin acetyltransferase (PAT)] genes, respectively, driven by the maize <italic>ubiquitin</italic> (<italic>Ubi</italic>) promoter and terminated by the 3&#x2032;-non-transcribed region of the <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens nopaline synthase</italic> (<italic>nos</italic>) gene. PAT activity confers resistance to phoshinothricin-containing herbicides, such as Bialaphos.</p>
        <p>The full ORF sequence of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene with <italic>Sma</italic>I and <italic>Sac</italic>I was cloned into the <italic>Sma</italic>I and <italic>Sac</italic>I sites of pAHC25 to form the transformation vector pAHCTiERF1, in which the <italic>TiERF1</italic> replaced the <italic>uidA</italic> gene of the original pAHC25 vector (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). The orientation and the ORF integrity of <italic>TiERF1</italic> in the construct were confirmed by sequence analysis.</p>
        <p>The wheat cv. Yangmai12 was used as the host of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> transformation. All aspects of the transformation protocols were conducted according to the protocol described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Xu <italic>et al.</italic> (2001)</xref>. Briefly, the immature embryos of Yangmai12 were incubated to form embryogenic calli. The plasmid DNA (20&#x2009;&#x3BC;g) of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> expression vector pAHCTiERF1 was packed onto gold powder particles (10&#x2009;mg) of 110&#x2009;&#x3BC;m diameter and then introduced into embryogenic calli with a particle inflow gun (PDS1000/He, Bio-Rad) at 1100&#x2009;psi bombardment pressure, a 25&#x2009;pA vacuum, and a bombardment distance of 6&#x2009;cm. The bombarded wheat calli were regenerated and selected using Bialaphos. When the plantlets had grown to 7&#x2013;8&#x2009;cm, the seedlings with roots were transferred to soil pots and grown in an environmentally controlled greenhouse at &#x223C;70% relative humidity for 16&#x2009;h in the light at 23&#x2013;25&#x2009;&#xB0;C and 8&#x2009;h in the dark at &#x223C;13&#x2013;16&#x2009;&#xB0;C.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>PCR detection of TiERF1 in the trangenic wheat plants</title>
        <p>The presence of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene in the transgenic wheat plants was monitored by PCR using the gene-specific primers TiE-406F (GAGGCCACGGCGTTCATG) and TiE-746R (GACCCGGACGAGGAGGAG). The PCR was performed in a total volume of 25&#x2009;&#x3BC;l containing 1&#xD7; GC buffer I (TaKaRa), 100&#x2013;200&#x2009;ng of genomic DNA, 187.5&#x2009;&#x3BC;M of each dNTP (TaKaRa), 0.25&#x2009;&#x3BC;M of each primer, and 1&#x2009;U of <italic>Taq</italic> polymerase (TaKaRa), and subjected to a program of initial denaturation at 94&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 4&#x2009;min, followed by 10 cycles of 45&#x2009;s at 94&#x2009;&#xB0;C, 45&#x2009;s at 62&#x2009;&#xB0;C, and 1&#x2009;min at 72 &#xB0;C, then 25 cycles of 45&#x2009;s at 94&#x2009;&#xB0;C, 45&#x2009;s at 58&#x2013;60&#x2009;&#xB0;C, and 1&#x2009;min at 72&#x2009;&#xB0;C, and a final extension at 72&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 10&#x2009;min. The amplified product (341&#x2009;bp) specific to the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene was resolved on a 1% (w/v) agarose gel and visualized by ethidium bromide staining.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Southern blotting analysis</title>
        <p>Total genomic DNAs were isolated according to the extraction protocol reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). Southern blotting was conducted according to the modified protocol of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Sharp <italic>et al.</italic> (1989)</xref>. The genomic DNAs (&#x223C;20&#x2009;&#x3BC;g each) of <italic>T. intermedium</italic> and wheat cv. Yangmai12, digested by the restriction enzymes <italic>Bgl</italic>II, <italic>Eco</italic>RV, <italic>Hin</italic>dIII, and <italic>Bam</italic>HI, or 20&#x2009;pg of pAHCTiERRF1 plasmid DNA (positive control) were resolved on a 0.8% agarose gel, and then were depurinated in 0.25&#x2009;M HCl, and transferred to a nylon membrane (Hybond N+, Amersham BioScience) using alkalinity transfer buffer (0.4&#x2009;M NaOH plus 1&#x2009;M NaCl). A specific fragment of <italic>TiERF1</italic> (nucleotides 406&#x2013;746) labelled by [&#x3B1;-<sup>32</sup>P]dCTP was used as the probe. Hybridization was carried out at 65&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 16&#x2009;h in Denhardt's buffer (5&#xD7; SSC, 5&#xD7; Denhardt's solution, 0.1% SDS). The hybridized membrane was washed twice (2&#xD7; SSC, 0.1% SDS) at 65&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 5&#x2009;min, twice (1&#xD7; SSC, 0.1% SDS) at 65&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 5&#x2009;min, and then in 0.1&#xD7; SSC, 0.1% SDS at 65&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 5&#x2009;min 2&#x2013;4 times based on the radioactivity intensity. Blots were exposed on a phosphor screen (Kodak-K) for 2&#x2009;d, and the signals were captured using a Molecular Imager FX System (Bio-Rad).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>RNA extraction and transcript analysis</title>
        <p>Total RNA of each sample was extracted using the TRIZOL reagent according to the manufacturer's protocol (Invitrogen). A 2&#x2009;&#x3BC;g aliquot of RNA per sample was used to synthesize the first-strand cDNA using an RNA PCR Kit (TaKaRa).</p>
        <p>In the transgenic and wild-type wheat plants, and wild-type <italic>T. intermedium</italic> plants, the expression levels of <italic>TiERF1</italic> and defence-related genes, including PR genes, a <italic>PR3-chitinase I</italic> gene (<italic>ChiI</italic>), a <italic>PR2 &#x3B2;-1,3-glucanase gene</italic> (<italic>D-GLU</italic>), <italic>PR10</italic>, and <italic>PR1</italic>, were investigated using RT-PCR and Q-RT-PCR methods with the specific primers listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>. Q-RT-PCR was performed with SYBR<sup>&#xAE;</sup> Green I dye (TaKaRa) using an ABI PRISM<sup>&#xAE;</sup> 7000 sequence detection system, where reactions were subjected to the following program: 95&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 1&#x2009;min, 41 cycles of 95&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 10&#x2009;s, and 60&#x2009;&#xB0;C for 31&#x2009;s. For each sample, the Ct value of each target gene was normalized to the Ct value of the <italic>actin</italic> gene. The relative value of gene expression was derived from 2<sup>&#x2013;&#x394;&#x394;CT</sup> <bold>(</bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Livak and Schmittgen, 2001</xref>). The relative expression of the target gene in the transgenic wheat plants was present relative to average wild-type levels.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Sequences of the gene-specific primer pairs used in the study</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank accession no.</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward and reverse primers</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fragment size (bp)</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>TiERF1</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF570121</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: 5&#x2032;-GAGGCCACGGCGTTCATG-3&#x2032;</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">341</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: 5&#x2032;-GACCCGGACGAGGAGGAG-3&#x2032;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>actin</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BE425627</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: 5&#x2032;-CACTGGAATGGTCAAGGCTG-3&#x2032;</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">211</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: 5&#x2032;-CTCCATGTCATCCCAGTTG-3&#x2032;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>ChiI</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK207575</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: 5&#x2032;-ACCTCCTTGGCGTCAGCT-3&#x2032;</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">173</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: 5&#x2032;-TCGCACCATTATTCCCTT-3&#x2032;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>D</italic>-<italic>GLU</italic></td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DQ090946</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: 5&#x2032;-GCGTGAAGGTGGTGATTT-3&#x2032;</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">352</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: 5&#x2032;-GTGCCCGTTACACTTGGAT-3&#x2032;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>PR10</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CV778999</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: 5&#x2032;-ACGGAGCGGATGTGGAAG-3&#x2032;</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">269</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: 5&#x2032;-GCCACCTGCGACTTGAGC-3&#x2032;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>PR1</italic>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF384143</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: 5&#x2032;-ATAACCTCGGCGTCTTCATC-3&#x2032;</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: 5&#x2032;-GCTTATTACGGCATTCCTTTT-3&#x2032;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Inoculation with R. cerealis and the disease rating in wheat</title>
        <p>At peak tillering stage, the bases of the first to second sheaths of the wheat plants were inoculated with small toothpick fragments harbouring the well-developed mycelia of <italic>R. cerealis</italic> according to the cultured toothpick method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Cai <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref>. The disease ratings of wheat plants were evaluated and photographed at the maturation stage of wheat following the scoring standard described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Cai <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref>, where infection type 1 (IT:1) indicates a mini-lesion (&lt;1%) on the first&#x2013;second sheaths rather than stems; IT:2 indicates that the width of a disease lesion is less than half that of the infected stem perimeter; IT:3 indicates that the width of a disease lesion is more than half that of the infected stem perimeter; IT:4 indicates that the width of the disease lesion is &gt;75% that of the infected stem perimeter; and IT:0 indicates no disease symptom on the sheath and stem. The disease index=&#x3A3;(<italic>d<sub>i</sub></italic>&#xD7;<italic>l<sub>i</sub></italic>)&#xD7;100/(<italic>L</italic>&#xD7;<italic>d</italic><sub>i</sub>max), where <italic>d</italic><sub>i</sub> indicates the infection type, <italic>l</italic><sub>i</sub> indicates the plant numbers of each infection type, and <italic>L</italic> indicates the total numbers of plants in the disease investigation. Plants with a disease index of 0 were considered as immune, those with a disease index &lt;20.0% as having high resistance, those with a disease index of 20.01&#x2013;40.00% as being resistant, those with a disease index of 60.01&#x2013;80.00% as susceptible, and those with a disease index of 80.01&#x2013;100.00% as highly susceptible.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>At least two copies of TiERF1 exist in the T. intermedium genome</title>
        <p>Southern blotting analysis is necessary to identify the size of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> family since the genome of <italic>T. intermedium</italic> has not been sequenced. The result of Southern hybridization with the specific <italic>TiERF1</italic> sequence showed that two clear hybridization bands were present in <italic>T. intermedium</italic> genomic DNA digested by <italic>Bgl</italic>II, <italic>Eco</italic>RV, <italic>Hin</italic>dIII, and <italic>Bam</italic>HI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), indicating that at least two copies of <italic>TiERF1</italic> should exist in the <italic>T. intermedium</italic> genome since the sequence of <italic>TiERF1</italic> corresponding to the probe does not contain the above enzyme sites. One clear hybridization band was present in the genomic DNA of wheat Yangmai12 digested by <italic>Bgl</italic>II, and a weak hybridization band was present in the wheat genomic DNA digested by <italic>Bam</italic>HI and <italic>Eco</italic>RV, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), suggesting that the wheat genome contained at least one homologous sequence of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene.</p>
        <fig id="fig1" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Southern blotting analysis of genomic DNAs from <italic>T. intermedium</italic> (1) and wheat cv. Yangmai12 (2) digested with <italic>Bgl</italic>II, <italic>Eco</italic>RV, <italic>Hin</italic>dIII, and <italic>Bam</italic>HI. Fragments were hybridized with an [&#x3B1;- <sup>2</sup>P]dCTP-labelled probe from the <italic>TiERF1</italic>-specific fragment (nucleotides 407&#x2013;747).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexbotern259f01_ht"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>TiERF1 harbours a transactivation domain functioning as a transcriptional activator</title>
        <p>Sequence analysis revealed that the TiERF1 protein contains a putative transcriptional activation domain (AD) in the N-terminus (from amino acids 51 to 75) of <italic>TiERF1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Liang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). The yeast one-hybrid assay was used to investigate the function of the putative AD domain of TiERF1. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, significant activity of &#x3B2;-galactosidase (encoded by <italic>LacZ</italic>) could be detected only in the yeast cells containing the wild-type TiERF1 effector plus the pGCC-LacZ reporter, Y-pYTiERF1/pGCC-LacZ, but no activity of &#x3B2;-galactosidase was present in the other combinations, Y-pYTiERF1&#x394;AD/pGCC-LacZ, Y-pYTiERF1/pmGCC-LacZ, and Y-pYTiERF1/pLacZi. The results demonstrated that the putative transcription AD functions as a transactivation domain, which is essential for TiERF1 activating the transcription of the reporter gene <italic>LacZ</italic>.</p>
        <fig id="fig2" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The transcriptional activation activity of TiERF1. (A) Scheme of the reporter and effector constructs. GAP, the promoter of the glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase gene. (B) Yhe yeast cells selected in SD-Ura-Trp medium (plate) and quality assay of the &#x3B2;-galactosidase activity (lifted-filter) for four kinds of reporter and effector combinations. 1, Y-pYTiERF1/pGCC-LacZ; 2, Y-pYTiERF1/pLacZi; 3, Y-pYTiERF1/pmGCC-LacZ; 4, Y-pYTiERF1&#x394;AD/pGCC-LacZ. (This figure is available in colour at <italic>JXB</italic> online.)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexbotern259f02_3c"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Transgenic wheat plants expressing TiERF1</title>
        <p>To elucidate if <italic>TiERF1</italic> confers enhanced resistance of the transgenic wheat to <italic>R. cerealis</italic>, the wheat cv. Yangmai12, which is susceptible to <italic>R. cerealis</italic>, was used to generate <italic>TiERF1</italic> transgenic wheat plants. Based on detection of the positive <italic>TiERF1</italic> transgenic wheat plants from the T<sub>0</sub>&#x2013;T<sub>4</sub> generations by PCR analysis, stable inheritance of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene was detected in these progeny derived from 13 lines, i.e. E111, E117, E199, E231, E259, E314, E319, E334, E348, E512, E765, E767, and E787 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig3" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>(A) Scheme of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> transformation vector pAHCTiERF1. (B) PCR analysis of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene in T<sub>3</sub> plants of the transgenic lines. M, 100 bp ladders; P, pAHCTiERF1 plasmid; W, WT Yangmai12; 1&#x2013;7, positive plants from the transgenic lines E111, E117, E199, E512, E765, E767, and E787; 8, silenced transgenic plant E314-3-3; 9, undetected transgenic plant E503-4-1. (C) Southern blotting of three positive PCR transgenic wheat lines. Genomic DNAs of T<sub>3</sub> plants from the transgenic lines E199, E767, and E787, and the wild-type Yangmai12 digested with <italic>Bgl</italic>II, <italic>Eco</italic>RV, and <italic>Hin</italic>dIII, were hybridized with the <italic>TiERF1</italic>-specific probe. M, &#x3BB;DNA/<italic>Hin</italic>dIII; P, pAHCTiERF1 plasmid. (D) RT-PCR analysis on <italic>TiERF1</italic> expression in T<sub>3</sub> plants from the transgenic lines E111, E199, E765, E767, and E787, the silenced transgenic plant E314-3-3, and the wild-type Yangmai12. (E) Q-RT-PCR analysis on <italic>TiERF1</italic> expression in T<sub>4</sub> plants from the transgenic lines E111, E117, E199, E231, E259, E334, E348, E512, E765, E767, E787, E314-3-3, and wild-type Yangmai12. The relative expression of the target gene is presented relative to average wild-type levels. The average and SE of three technical replicates are presented.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexbotern259f03_ht"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The result of Southern blotting analysis showed that one hybridization band with a different pattern was present in each transgenic line E199, E767, and E787 digested with <italic>Eco</italic>RV and <italic>Hin</italic>dIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>), indicating that the transgenic <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene was integrated into the wheat genome with a single copy, and these three lines were independently derived. When the genomic DNAs were digested by <italic>Bgl</italic>II, one strong and one weak hybridization bands were present, respectively, in the each transgenic line; two weak bands were present in the genomic DNA of wild-type wheat cv. Yangmai12, indicating further that the wheat genome contained at least one homologous sequence of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene.</p>
        <p>RT-PCR analysis indicated that the <italic>TiERF1</italic> transcript was overexpressed in the positive transgenic plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3D</xref>), such as T<sub>3</sub> progeny plants of lines E111, E117, E199, E231, E259, E319, E334, E348, E512, E765, E767, and E787 showing resistance to sharp eyespot, but there was no detectable <italic>TiERF1</italic> expression in the T<sub>3</sub> plants of E314-3-3 with susceptibility to sharp eyespot, presumably resulting from silencing of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene. Q-RT-PCR analysis indicated that <italic>TiERF1</italic> was still overexpressed in the T<sub>4</sub> progeny plants of the transgenic lines E111, E117, E199, E231, E259, E319, E334, E348, E512, E765, E767, and E787, all of which contained the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene and showed resistance to sharp eyespot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3E</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Overexpression of TiERF1 enhances resistance to R. cerealis</title>
        <p>The results of the sharp eyespot test demonstrated that the transgenic wheat lines overexpressing <italic>TiERF1</italic> showed enhanced resistance (ITs: 0&#x2013;1), whereas the non-transgenic wheat Yangmai 12 showed susceptibility to <italic>R. cerealis</italic> (ITs: 3&#x2013;4) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). From T<sub>1</sub>&#x2013;T<sub>4</sub> plants, high resistance to sharp eyespot was present in the <italic>TiERF1</italic>-expressing plants, but not in the segregated plants lacking the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene or in the silenced transgenic plants, such as E314-3-3. The results suggested that the enhanced resistance in the transgenic lines overexpressing <italic>TiERF1</italic> could be stably inherited, and was associated with accumulation of <italic>TiERF1</italic> transcript.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float">
          <label>Table 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The disease resistance in <italic>TiERF1</italic> transgenic and wild-type wheat plants</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Lines</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">PCR detection</td>
                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">RT-PCR detection</td>
                <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Sharp eyespot<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IT</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disease index</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resistance rating</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E111</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E117</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.71</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E199</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.38</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E231</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.16</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E259</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.64</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E314</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.00</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E319</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E334</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.09</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E348</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.95</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E512</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.50</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E765</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.22</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E767</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.76</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E787</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.98</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yangmai12</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2212;</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td>
                <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.50</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HS</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>Note: HR, highly resistant; HS, highly sensitive; I, immune.; S, sensitive.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <fig id="fig4" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Sharp eyespot resistance of a <italic>TiERF1</italic> transgenic wheat line E111 compared with wild-type Yangmai12. (This figure is available in colour at <italic>JXB</italic> online.)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexbotern259f04_3c"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Overexpression of TiERF1 activates the transcript of some PR genes</title>
        <p>Q-RT-PCR was used to investigate the expression of wheat PR genes in the transgenic wheat lines expressing <italic>TiERF1</italic> and the wild-type Yangmai12. The results showed that overexpression of <italic>TiERF1</italic> in wheat dramatically increased the transcript levels of <italic>ChiI</italic> 1200- to 1800-fold and those of <italic>D-GLU</italic> 800- to 1200-fold over those in the wild-type wheat parent Yangmai12, and increased the transcript abundance of <italic>PR10</italic>, 12- to 20-fold over that in the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>), but did not noticeably change the transcript level of <italic>PR1</italic> (data not shown) in the transgenic plants compared with the wild-type plants. However, the transcript levels of <italic>TiERF1</italic>, <italic>ChiI</italic>, <italic>D-GLU</italic>, and <italic>PR10</italic> in the silenced transgenic plant E314-3-3 were similar to those in the wild-type Yangmai12.</p>
        <fig id="fig5" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 5.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Q-RT-PCR analysis of the expression of the PR genes <italic>ChiI</italic> (A), <italic>D-GLU</italic> (B), and <italic>PR10</italic> (C) in T<sub>4</sub> progeny from the transgenic lines E199, E231, E259, E348, E765, E767, E787, and E314, and wild-type Yangmai12. The relative expression of the target gene is presented relative to average wild-type levels. The average and SE of three technical replicates are presented.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexbotern259f05_lw"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Expression characteristics of PR genes in wheat and T. intermedium</title>
        <p>To establish the expression characteristics of <italic>ChiI</italic>, <italic>D-GLU</italic>, <italic>PR10</italic>, and <italic>PR1</italic> genes, Q-RT-PCR analysis was used to investigate the effects of SA, JA, ET, JA+ET, and the ET synthesis inhibitor (CoCl<sub>2</sub>) on the transcript levels of the above PR genes in wild-type Yangmai12 and <italic>T. intermedium</italic>. The results of these experiments are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figs 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>. The transcript abundances of <italic>ChiI</italic> and <italic>D-GLU</italic> were dramatically increased by ET treatment, and increased by JA treatment, but could not be detected after CoCl<sub>2</sub> treatment, suggesting that <italic>ChiI</italic> and <italic>D-GLU</italic> are downstream PR genes primarily in the ET-dependent pathway. The transcript abundance of <italic>PR10</italic> was significantly increased by JA treatment, increased by ET treatment, and not affected by CoCl<sub>2</sub> treatment, suggesting that wheat <italic>PR10</italic> is a downstream PR gene primarily in the JA-dependent pathway. The transcript abundance of <italic>PR1</italic> was significantly increased by SA treatment, but not obviously affected by ET, JA, and CoCl<sub>2</sub> treatments, suggesting that wheat <italic>PR1</italic> is a downstream defence-related gene primarily in the SA-dependent pathway. These results indicated that these PR genes in <italic>T. intermedium</italic> were regulated through similar signal pathways of wheat.</p>
        <fig id="fig6" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 6.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Q-RT-PCR analysis of the expression of the wheat <italic>ChiI</italic> (A), <italic>D-GLU</italic> (B), <italic>PR10</italic> (C), and <italic>PR1</italic> (D) genes in response to exogenous hormones. Seedlings of Yangmai12 were treated with ET, MeJA, ET plus MeJA, SA, CoCl<sub>2</sub> (an inhibitor of ET synthesis), and water (mock) for 24&#x2009;h. The expression of the target gene is presented relative to average mock levels. The average and SE of three technical replicates are presented.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexbotern259f06_lw"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="fig7" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 7.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Q-RT-PCR analysis of the expression of <italic>TiERF1</italic> (A), <italic>ChiI</italic> (B), <italic>D-GLU</italic> (C), <italic>PR10</italic> (D), and <italic>PR1</italic> (E) genes in <italic>T. intermedium</italic> in response to exogenous hormones. Seedlings of <italic>T. intermedium</italic> Z1146 were treated with ET, MeJA, SA, and water (mock) for 24&#x2009;h. The expression of the target gene is presented relative to average mock levels. The average and SE of three technical replicates are presented.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jexbotern259f07_lw"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Wheat sharp eyespot has been becoming a devastating disease of wheat in China. It is urgent to elucidate the host defence mechanism against the pathogen, a typical soil-borne fungus <italic>R. cerealis</italic>. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ERF1 and AtERF2 have been shown to play an important modulated role in mediating resistance to several necrotrophic fungi and a soil-borne fungus <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Berrocal-Lobo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Berrocal-Lobo and Molina, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">McGrath <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Therefore, ERFs in wheat and its relative <italic>T. intermedium</italic> were used as the starting point to study host defence against <italic>R. cerealis</italic>.</p>
      <p>In a previous study, an ERF gene in <italic>T. intermedium</italic>, <italic>TiERF1</italic>, was isolated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Liang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), which could be induced by <italic>R. cerealis</italic> challenge, and played a positively modulating role in certain defence responses of transgenic tobacco plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Liang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). TiERF1 belongs to the B3 subgroup of the ERF family. Several ERF proteins in the B3 subgroup were shown to regulate the plant defence response positively through activating PR genes with a GCC-box <italic>ci</italic>s-element, such as <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ERF1, AtERF2, and AtERF14, tomato Pti4 and TSRF1, tobacco OPBP1, and rice OsBIERF3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Berrocal-Lobo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Gu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>, 2004; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Berrocal-Lobo and Molina, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">McGrath <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Cao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; O&#x148;ate-S&#xE1;nchez and Singh, 2007). In this study, further yeast one-hybrid analysis confirmed that the putative transcriptional AD of TiERF1 is a transactivation domain essential for TiERF1 as a transcriptional activator following binding to the GCC-box, suggesting that TiERF1 should play modulating roles in the defence response through activating transcripts of PR genes with a GCC-box. These findings gave rise to the hypothesis that overexpression of <italic>TiERF1</italic> may positively regulate the host defence against <italic>R. cerealis.</italic> This report confirmed the hypothesis.</p>
      <p>In this study, since the genome of <italic>T. intermedium</italic> has not yet been sequenced, Southern blotting was used to analyse the copy number of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene in the <italic>T. intermedium</italic> genome. The Southern blotting results suggested that at least two copies of <italic>TiERF1</italic> exist in the <italic>T. intermedium</italic> genome. One clear hybridization band was present in the genomic DNA of wheat Yangmai12 digested by <italic>Bgl</italic>II, and a weak hybridization band was present in the wheat genomic DNA digested by <italic>Bam</italic>HI and <italic>Eco</italic>RV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), suggesting that the wheat genome contained at least one homologous sequence of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene. Sequence alignment analysis indicated that the probe of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> sequence shares 87% identity with the corresponding sequence of a wheat ERF gene <italic>TaERF3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), supporting the Southern blotting results with <italic>Bgl</italic> II. The highly specific <italic>TiERF1</italic> hybridization in <italic>Bam</italic>HI and <italic>Eco</italic>RV digestions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3C</xref>) may result from the high stringency for hybridization, blot washing, or the restriction sites in wheat genome.</p>
      <p>To unravel the roles of <italic>TiERF1</italic> in the host defence mechanism against <italic>R. cerealis</italic>, overexpressing and silencing lines of the gene should be developed and investigated. Because the transformation system of <italic>T. intermedium</italic> has not been established, transgenic wheat lines expressing <italic>TiERF1</italic> were developed in this study. Based on PCR detection results on <italic>TiERF1</italic> present in T<sub>0</sub>&#x2013;T<sub>4</sub> individuals, stable inheritance of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene was detected in these progeny derived from 13 lines. Southern analysis results indicated that a different pattern of <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene integration was detected in stable inheritance lines, such as E199, E765, and E767. The transgenic wheat lines with different integration patterns show the genetic independence of transgenic lines, like the transgenic wheat plants expressing <italic>AtNPR1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Ragiba <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), demonstrating further the transformation randomness in micro-projectile bombardment. Stable integration and inheritance of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene were confirmed in the five examined generations (from T<sub>0</sub> to T<sub>4</sub>). Results of RT-PCR, Q-RT-PCR, and the disease resistance assays indicated the stable overexpression of the <italic>TiERF1</italic> gene in most of the transgenic lines which showed enhanced resistance to sharp eyespot. However, the progeny of a few lines had no detectable <italic>TiERF1</italic> expression, leading to susceptibility to sharp eyespot. The reason behind the non-expression of the transgenic plants is not clear, but presumably results from silencing at the transcript level of the introduced genes. Similar silencing transgenic events occurred in other transgenic wheat plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Anand <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Ragiba <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Furthermore, the transgenic wheat lines overexpressing <italic>TiERF1</italic> showed enhanced resistance to sharp eyespot compared with non-transgenic wheat Yangmai12 and the silenced transgenic wheat E314 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>), indicating that the enhanced resistance of the transgenic plants was associated with accumulation of <italic>TiERF1</italic> transcript, and overexpression of <italic>TiERF1</italic> conferred the enhanced resistance to sharp eyespot in transgenic wheat plants.</p>
      <p>To elucidate if TiERF1 plays positive regulatory roles in defence against <italic>R. cerealis</italic> through up-regulating the expression of some downstream PR genes, the expression of some PR genes with a GCC-box <italic>cis</italic>-element in transgenic wheat plants overexpressing <italic>TiERF1</italic> should be analysed. However, there is a lack of information regarding the promoter sequence of known wheat PR genes. Based on our analysis of a PR gene (<italic>D-GLU</italic>) involved in wheat defence against <italic>R. cerealis</italic> (unpublished data) and other reports about some PR genes in wheat and rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Kong <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Qiu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), expression of some wheat defence-related genes (<italic>ChiI</italic>, <italic>D-GLU</italic>, <italic>PR10</italic>, and <italic>PR1</italic>), which may be regulated by different signallings, was investigated in the transgenic wheat lines. The Q-RT-PCR analysis of expression of the targeting genes showed that overexpression of <italic>TiERF1</italic> in the transgenic wheat lines dramatically increased the transcript levels of wheat <italic>ChiI</italic> and <italic>D-GLU</italic>, and also activated the expression of <italic>PR10</italic> compared with the silenced transgenic wheat and wild-type Yangmai12 plants, but did not noticeably change the transcript level of the wheat <italic>PR1</italic> gene. As expected, the disease resistance of the <italic>TiERF1</italic>-expressing wheat plants was associated with higher transcript levels of the wheat PR genes. Although the expression characteristics of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> PR genes are well documented, this information is not available for the wheat PR genes assayed in the analyses of the transgenic wheat plants described above. To understand further in which signal pathway the PR genes regulated by TiERF1 are involved, in this study the effects of ET, CoCl<sub>2</sub>, JA, ET+JA, and SA on the expression of the above wheat PR genes in wheat and <italic>T. intermedium</italic> were investigated by Q-RT-PCR analysis. Here, the results indicated that <italic>ChiI</italic> and <italic>D-GLU</italic> are downstream defence-related genes primarily in the ET-dependent pathway; wheat <italic>PR10</italic> is a downstream defence-related gene primarily in the JA-dependent pathway; and wheat <italic>PR1</italic> is a downstream defence-related gene primarily in the SA-dependent pathway. The expression characteristics of the defence-related genes in <italic>T. intermedium</italic> are the same as those in wheat. These results indicated that <italic>TiERF1</italic> overexpression may activate primarily the PR genes (<italic>ChiI</italic> and <italic>D-GLU</italic>) in the ET-dependent pathway, and may up-regulate the PR gene (<italic>PR10</italic>) in the JA-dependent pathway, leading to enhanced resistance to sharp eyespot. It was also found that the transgenic wheat overexpressing <italic>D-GLU</italic> improved resistance to sharp eyespot (unpublished result). The above results suggested that <italic>TiERF1</italic>, and <italic>ChiI</italic> and <italic>D-GLU</italic> may participate positively in wheat resistance against <italic>R. cerealis</italic>. These results support the view on ERFs as important components of the ET signal pathway for regulating PR genes with or without a GCC-box (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Solano <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; Chakravarthy <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Guo and Ecker, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Mazarei <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; O&#x148;ate-S&#xE1;nchez and Singh, 2007), and may provide evidence to bridge the gap between the transgenic <italic>TiERF1</italic>, <italic>ChiI</italic>, and <italic>D-GLU</italic> genes and transgenic resistance, and these three genes may be allocated to the ET-dependent pathway.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, all the results supported the hypothesis that overexpression of <italic>TiERF1</italic> could confer enhanced resistance to <italic>R. cerealis</italic> infection in transgenic wheat plants without a major resistance gene background. TiERF1 was a positive regulator of wheat resistance against <italic>R. cerealis</italic> through activating the transcript of PR genes mainly in the ET-dependent pathway. Genetic engineering with <italic>TiERF1</italic> provides an effective strategy for developing wheat germplasm with resistance to sharp eyespot. To our knowledge, this is the first report about the roles of an ERF and wheat PR genes in the ET-dependent pathway in wheat defence against <italic>R. cerealis</italic> infection. This study provides new insights into wheat defence mechanisms against <italic>R. cerealis</italic>.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors are grateful to the anonymous reviewers for constructive comments on the manuscript. This research was funded by the <grant-sponsor>National Natural Science Foundation of China</grant-sponsor> (grant no. <grant-num>30671292</grant-num>) and the <grant-sponsor>National &#x2018;Hi-Tech&#x2019; project</grant-sponsor> (grant no.<grant-num>2006AA10A104</grant-num> and grant no. <grant-num>2008ZX08002-001</grant-num>).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Anand</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trick</surname>
              <given-names>HN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bockus</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muthukrishnan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Greenhouse and field testing of transgenic wheat plants stably expressing genes for thaumatin-like protein, chitinase and glucanase against <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>1101</fpage>
          <lpage>1111</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12598580</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berrocal-Lobo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Molina</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ETHYLENE RESPONSE FACTOR 1 mediates Arabidopsis resistance to the soil-borne fungus <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic></article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant-Microbe Interactions</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>763</fpage>
          <lpage>770</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15242170</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berrocal-Lobo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Molina</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Solano</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Constitutive expression of ETHYLENE-RESPONSE-FACTOR1 in Arabidopsis confers resistance to several necrotrophic fungi</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Journal</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          <lpage>32</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12060224</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cai</surname>
              <given-names>SB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ren</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>JZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>HG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>XY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Germplasm development and mapping of resistance to sharp eyespot (<italic>Rhizoctonia cerealis</italic>) in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Scientia Agricultura Sinica</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>928</fpage>
          <lpage>934</lpage>
          <comment>(in Chinese)</comment>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cao</surname>
              <given-names>YF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>YF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Overexpression of the rice EREBP-like gene OsBIERF3 enhances disease resistance and salt tolerance in transgenic tobacco</article-title>
          <source>Physiological and Molecular Plant Pathology</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>202</fpage>
          <lpage>211</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chakravarthy</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Touri</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D'Ascenzo</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fobert</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Despres</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The tomato transcription factor Pti4 regulates defense-related gene expression via GCC box and non-GCC box <italic>cis</italic>-elements</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>3033</fpage>
          <lpage>3050</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14630974</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Christensen</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quail</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ubiquitin promoter-based vectors for high-level expression of selectable and/or screenable marker genes in monocotyledonous plants</article-title>
          <source>Transgenic Research</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>213</fpage>
          <lpage>218</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8673150</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Durrant</surname>
              <given-names>WE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Systemic acquired resistance</article-title>
          <source>Annual Review of Phytopathology</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>185</fpage>
          <lpage>209</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gu</surname>
              <given-names>YQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wildermuth</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chakravarthy</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loh</surname>
              <given-names>YT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>XH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tomato transcription factors Pti4, Pti5, and Pti6 activate defense responses when expressed in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>817</fpage>
          <lpage>831</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11971137</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
              <given-names>ZJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>XJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>XL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ling</surname>
              <given-names>JQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Overexpression of the AP2/EREBP transcription factor OPBP1 enhances disease resistance and salt tolerance in tobacco</article-title>
          <source>Plant Molecualr Biology</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>607</fpage>
          <lpage>618</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
              <given-names>HW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ecker</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The ethylene signaling pathway: new insights</article-title>
          <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>40</fpage>
          <lpage>49</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14732440</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parker</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Deciphering plant&#x2013;pathogen communication: fresh perspectives for molecular resistance breeding</article-title>
          <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>177</fpage>
          <lpage>193</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kong</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohm</surname>
              <given-names>HW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Induction of wheat defense and stress-related genes in response to <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>
          <source>Genome</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>29</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15729394</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liang</surname>
              <given-names>HX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>HX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>FD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xin</surname>
              <given-names>ZY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>ZY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel activator-type ERF of <italic>Thinopyrum intermedium</italic>, TiERF1, positively regulates defence responses</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>3111</fpage>
          <lpage>3120</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18611911</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Livak</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmittgen</surname>
              <given-names>TD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2<sup>&#x2013;&#x394;&#x394;CT</sup> method</article-title>
          <source>Methods</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>402</fpage>
          <lpage>408</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lorenzo</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Piqueras</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanchez-Serrano</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Solano</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ETHYLENE RESPONSE FACTOR1 integrates signals from ethylene and jasmonate pathways in plant defense</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>165</fpage>
          <lpage>178</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12509529</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mazarei</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elling</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maier</surname>
              <given-names>TR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Puthoff</surname>
              <given-names>DP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baum</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>GmEREBP1 is a transcription factor activating defense genes in soybean and Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant-Microbe Interactions</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>107</fpage>
          <lpage>119</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17313162</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McGrath</surname>
              <given-names>KC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dombrecht</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manners</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schenk</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edgar</surname>
              <given-names>CI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maclean</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scheible</surname>
              <given-names>WR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Udvardi</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kazan</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Repressor- and activator-type ethylene response factors functioning in jasmonate signaling and disease resistance identified via a genome-wide screen of Arabidopsis transcription factor gene expression</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>139</volume>
          <fpage>949</fpage>
          <lpage>959</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16183832</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x148;ate-S&#xE1;nchez</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jonathan</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Young</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>KB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>AtERF14, a member of the ERF family of transcription factors, plays a nonredundant role in plant defense</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>143</volume>
          <fpage>400</fpage>
          <lpage>409</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17114278</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ham</surname>
              <given-names>BK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shin</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peak</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Overexpression of the tobacco <italic>Tsi1</italic> gene encoding an EREBP/AP2-type transcription factor enhances resistance against pathogen attack and osmotic stress in tobacco</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Cell</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>49</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Qiu</surname>
              <given-names>DY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xiao</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ding</surname>
              <given-names>XH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xiong</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cai</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cao</surname>
              <given-names>YL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>XH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>CG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>OsWRKY13 mediates rice disease resistance by regulating defense-related genes in salicylate- and jasmonate-dependent signaling</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant-Microbe Interactions</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>492</fpage>
          <lpage>499</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17506327</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ragiba</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Juliane</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Melissa</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harold</surname>
              <given-names>NT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jyoti</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetically engineered resistance to Fusarium head blight in wheat by expression of Arabidopsis NPR1</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Plant-Microbe Interactions</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>123</fpage>
          <lpage>129</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16529374</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharp</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chao</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Desai</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gale</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The isolation, characterization and application in the Triticeae of a set of wheat RFLP probes identifying each homoeologous chromosome arm</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>342</fpage>
          <lpage>348</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Solano</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stepanova</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chao</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ecker</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nuclear events in ethylene signaling: a transcriptional cascade mediated by ETHYLENE-INSENSITIVE 3 and ETHYLENE-RESPONSE-FACTOR 1</article-title>
          <source>Genes and Development</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>3703</fpage>
          <lpage>3714</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9851977</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thomma</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eggermont</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Penninckx</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mauch-Mani</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vogelsang</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cammue</surname>
              <given-names>BPA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Broekaert</surname>
              <given-names>WF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Separate jasmonate-dependent and salicylate-dependent defense-response pathways in Arabidopsis are essential for resistance to distinct microbial pathogens</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <fpage>15107</fpage>
          <lpage>15111</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pang</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ye</surname>
              <given-names>XG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Study on the gene transferring Nib8 into wheat for its resistance to the yellow mosaic virus by bombardment</article-title>
          <source>Acta Agronomica Sinica</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>14</fpage>
          <lpage>20</lpage>
          <comment>(in Chinese)</comment>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yi</surname>
              <given-names>SY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Joung</surname>
              <given-names>YH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>WT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The pepper transcription factor CaPF1 confers pathogen and freezing tolerance in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>136</volume>
          <fpage>2862</fpage>
          <lpage>2874</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15347795</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>HB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>DB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chan</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>YH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>ZJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>XC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tomato stress-responsive factor TSRF1 interacts with ethylene responsive element GCC box and regulates pathogen resistance to <italic>Ralatonia solanacearum</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>825</fpage>
          <lpage>834</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15604719</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib29">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>ZY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xin</surname>
              <given-names>ZY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>YZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>QF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>ZS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mapping of a BYDV resistance gene from <italic>Thinopyrum intermedium</italic> in wheat background by molecular markers</article-title>
          <source>Science in China (Series C)</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>663</fpage>
          <lpage>668</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18726490</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib30">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>ZY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yao</surname>
              <given-names>WL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liang</surname>
              <given-names>HX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>HX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel ERF transcription activator in wheat and its induction kinetics after pathogen and hormone treatments</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>2993</fpage>
          <lpage>3003</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17728298</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib31">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Pto kinase conferring resistance to tomato bacterial speck disease interacts with proteins that bind a <italic>cis</italic>-element of pathogenesis-related genes</article-title>
          <source>EMBO Journal</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>3207</fpage>
          <lpage>3218</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9214637</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
