<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Bot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann. Bot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">annbot</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">annbot</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Annals of Botany</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0305-7364</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1095-8290</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3936580</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mct283</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">mct283</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
          <subject>1</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Comparative analysis of the cold acclimation and freezing tolerance capacities of seven diploid <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> accessions</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Colton-Gagnon</surname>
            <given-names>Katia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ali-Benali</surname>
            <given-names>Mohamed Ali</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mayer</surname>
            <given-names>Boris F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dionne</surname>
            <given-names>Rachel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bertrand</surname>
            <given-names>Annick</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Do Carmo</surname>
            <given-names>Sonia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Charron</surname>
            <given-names>Jean-Benoit</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="af1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>McGill University, Department of Plant Science, 21,111 Lakeshore, Sainte-Anne-de-Bellevue, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="af2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Agriculture and Agri-food Canada, Soil and Crops Research and Development Centre, 2560 Hochelaga Blvd, Quebec, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="af3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>McGill University, Department of Pharmacology and Therapeutics, 3655 Promenade Sir-William-Osler, Montreal, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>For correspondence. E-mail <email>jean-benoit.charron@mcgill.ca</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>8</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>8</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>113</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>681</fpage>
      <lpage>693</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-request">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Annals of Botany Company.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="mct283.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background and Aims</title>
          <p>Cold is a major constraint for cereal cultivation under temperate climates. Winter-hardy plants interpret seasonal changes and can acquire the ability to resist sub-zero temperatures. This cold acclimation process is associated with physiological, biochemical and molecular alterations in cereals. <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> is considered a powerful model system to study the response of temperate cereals to adverse environmental conditions. To date, little is known about the cold acclimation and freezing tolerance capacities of <italic>Brachypodium</italic>. The main objective of this study was to evaluate the cold hardiness of seven diploid <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>An integrated approach, involving monitoring of phenological indicators along with expression profiling of the major vernalization regulator <italic>VRN1</italic> orthologue, was followed. In parallel, soluble sugars and proline contents were determined along with expression profiles of two <italic>COR</italic> genes in plants exposed to low temperatures. Finally, whole-plant freezing tests were performed to evaluate the freezing tolerance capacity of <italic>Brachypodium</italic>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Key Results</title>
          <p>Cold treatment accelerated the transition from the vegetative to the reproductive phase in all diploid <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions tested. In addition, low temperature exposure triggered the gradual accumulation of <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> transcripts in all accessions tested. These accessions exhibited a clear cold acclimation response by progressively accumulating proline, sugars and <italic>COR</italic> gene transcripts. However, whole-plant freezing tests revealed that these seven diploid accessions only have a limited capacity to develop freezing tolerance when compared with winter varieties of temperate cereals such as wheat and barley. Furthermore, little difference in terms of survival was observed among the accessions tested despite their previous classification as either spring or winter genotypes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>This study is the first to characterize the freezing tolerance capacities of <italic>B. distachyon</italic> and provides strong evidence that some diploid accessions such as Bd21 have a facultative growth habit.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>cold acclimation</kwd>
        <kwd><italic>COR</italic>413</kwd>
        <kwd>flowering</kwd>
        <kwd>freezing tolerance</kwd>
        <kwd>ice recrystallization inhibition</kwd>
        <kwd>fructans</kwd>
        <kwd>phenological development</kwd>
        <kwd>proline</kwd>
        <kwd>vernalization</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>VRN1</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>winter hardiness</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="14"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Cold is one of the major constraints restricting cereal cultivation under temperate climates (<xref rid="MCT283C37" ref-type="bibr">Kosova <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Freezing temperatures encountered late in spring, early in autumn and during winter severely alter plant survival and thus represent a significant impediment for yield improvement. To circumvent some of the limitations imposed by freezing temperatures, hardy cereals efficiently interpret and respond in a co-ordinated manner to environmental cues that signal seasonal changes. As a consequence, winter genotypes can acquire the ability to resist freezing temperatures, whereas spring genotypes will remain limited in their ability to resist freezing (<xref rid="MCT283C42" ref-type="bibr">Limin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Freezing tolerance in plants is thus not a constitutive trait and is expressed following exposure to low non-freezing temperatures, a process known as cold acclimation (<xref rid="MCT283C24" ref-type="bibr">Guy, 1990</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C57" ref-type="bibr">Thomashow, 1999</xref>). Numerous studies have characterized in depth the cold acclimation process in cereals and other plants such as <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and have established that this process is associated with numerous physiological, biochemical and molecular alterations (<xref rid="MCT283C26" ref-type="bibr">Houde <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C10" ref-type="bibr">Danyluk <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C9" ref-type="bibr">Crosatti <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C41" ref-type="bibr">Limin <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C54" ref-type="bibr">Stockinger <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C23" ref-type="bibr">Grossi <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C31" ref-type="bibr">Jaglo-Ottosen <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C57" ref-type="bibr">Thomashow, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C48" ref-type="bibr">NDong <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C63" ref-type="bibr">Vogel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C62" ref-type="bibr">Van Buskirk and Thomashow, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C3" ref-type="bibr">Badawi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C20" ref-type="bibr">Galiba <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). These alterations are regulated by a complex multigenic system that revolves around the induced expression of several cold-regulated (<italic>COR</italic>) genes (<xref rid="MCT283C58" ref-type="bibr">Thomashow, 2001</xref>). This transcriptional response is thus essential for the development of freezing tolerance and will ultimately promote self-adaptive features, such as increased levels of carbohydrates, soluble proteins, proline and organic acids, photosynthetic adjustments, appearance of new enzyme isoforms, and modifications in the lipid membrane composition, necessary for the plant to protect critical cell structures and vital physiological processes (<xref rid="MCT283C27" ref-type="bibr">Hughes and Dunn, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C28" ref-type="bibr">H&#xFC;ner <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C47" ref-type="bibr">McNeil <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C57" ref-type="bibr">Thomashow, 1999</xref>).</p>
      <p>Despite these self-adaptive features, sub-zero temperatures remain fatal to the sensitive floral meristems. Hardy cereals thus have a vernalization requirement that delays the transition from the vegetative to the reproductive phase. Exposure to a period of low non-freezing temperatures modulates the expression of specialized vernalization genes, which in turn promotes flowering only in the milder conditions of spring. Vernalization is thus initiated within the same time frame as the induction of the cold acclimation pathway. Despite this temporal overlap, no direct molecular link has been clearly established between vernalization and the cold acclimation processes. Nonetheless, several studies have pointed out that the characterization of the vernalization requirements of a cereal provides key information about its freezing tolerance capacity by showing that the transition from the vegetative to the reproductive phase is associated with the downregulation of <italic>COR</italic> genes and the upregulation of the vernalization gene <italic>VRN-1</italic> (<xref rid="MCT283C17" ref-type="bibr">Fowler <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="MCT283C18" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C45" ref-type="bibr">Mahfoozi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="MCT283C46" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C13" ref-type="bibr">Dhillon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). As a result, full expression of cold hardiness genes only occurs in the vegetative phase, and plants in the reproductive phase have a limited ability to accumulate <italic>COR</italic> gene transcripts and to cold acclimate. In addition, plants that are still in the vegetative phase have the ability to re-acclimate even after periods of exposure to warm temperatures, whereas plants in the reproductive phase only have a poor ability to re-acclimate (<xref rid="MCT283C45" ref-type="bibr">Mahfoozi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001<italic>a</italic></xref>).</p>
      <p>In the context of increasing demand on crops for food and biofuel production, breeding for cold tolerance holds promises for enhanced yield and extended cultivation seasons. It is thus important to gain in-depth knowledge about the cold response mechanisms of cereal plants and the intricate molecular circuitry involved. In order to support research initiatives, it is crucial to have a model plant which, in addition to possessing a small physical size, rapid life cycle and undemanding growth requirements, can make it amenable to perform high-throughput screening routines, functional analyses and transformation procedures (<xref rid="MCT283C14" ref-type="bibr">Draper <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>).</p>
      <p>With its status of a major staple food and its compact genome of 441 Mbp (<xref rid="MCT283C5" ref-type="bibr">Bennett <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>), rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) was initially proposed as such a model for cereal plants. However, its use as a model organism for temperate cereals and forages has remained a matter of debate despite extensive international efforts that have led to the development of comprehensive genetic maps and imposing expressed sequence tag (EST) and germplasm collections. Nevertheless, the lack of microsynteny conservation, the presence of multiple small rearrangements and the fact that rice does not necessarily exhibit all the traits relevant to temperate cereal crops such as freezing tolerance and vernalization have considerably hampered the initial interest in this plant (<xref rid="MCT283C14" ref-type="bibr">Draper <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C15" ref-type="bibr">Faricelli <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p>
      <p><italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> is an annual temperate wild grass that originates from Mediterranean and Middle East countries where sub-zero temperatures are frequently observed (<xref rid="MCT283C50" ref-type="bibr">Opanowicz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C65" ref-type="bibr">Vogel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). It has many appealing biological attributes including self-fertility, small stature, short generation time and efficient transformation (<xref rid="MCT283C22" ref-type="bibr">Garvin, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C2" ref-type="bibr">Alves <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C64" ref-type="bibr">Vogel and Bragg, 2009</xref>). Moreover, <italic>Brachypodium</italic> has a small sequenced genome (272 Mbp), and spring and winter diploid accessions have been classified according to the capacity to flower with or without cold exposure (<xref rid="MCT283C65" ref-type="bibr">Vogel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). There is strong chromosomal synteny between <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and other temperate cereals, and about 77 % of the genes retrieve significant matches in <italic>Triticeae</italic> EST databases (<xref rid="MCT283C29" ref-type="bibr">Huo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). This body of evidence has led researchers to propose <italic>Brachypodium</italic> as an appropriate model to study the response of temperate cereals to their environment. As a result, the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> model has proved its value in a number of biotic and abiotic stress tolerance studies (<xref rid="MCT283C53" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C44" ref-type="bibr">Luo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C51" ref-type="bibr">Peraldi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), clearly demonstrating its potential for understanding and ultimately improving abiotic stress tolerance in temperate cereals.</p>
      <p>To date, little is known about the capacities of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> to cold acclimate and develop freezing tolerance. A recent study by <xref rid="MCT283C40" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> has demonstrated that <italic>Brachypodium</italic> has the molecular circuitry necessary to activate <italic>COR</italic> gene expression. Despite this leap forward, the extent of <italic>Brachypodium</italic>'s capacity to resist freezing is still unknown. In this study, we investigated the cold hardiness capacity of <italic>Brachypodium.</italic> To achieve this goal, an integrated approach involving the monitoring of double-ridge (DR) formation and final leaf number (FLN) was used to verify the growth habit classification of seven diploid <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions. In addition, the cellular concentration of soluble sugars and proline were determined, along with the transcript accumulation profiles of orthologues of the major vernalization regulator <italic>VRN1</italic> and two <italic>COR</italic> genes at different stages of cold acclimation. Finally, whole-plant freezing tests (WPFTs) were performed in order to characterize fully the freezing tolerance capacity of <italic>Brachypodium</italic>. This study is thus critical to evaluate the potential contribution of <italic>B. distachyon</italic> to cold hardiness research.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Plant material and growth conditions</title>
        <p>Seeds of <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> spring accessions Bd2-3, Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd30-1, and winter accessions Bd1-1, Bd18-1 and Bd29-1 were soaked for 2 h in sterile distilled water at room temperature, after which the lemma was removed. The seeds were then sterilized in 70 % ethanol, rinsed with sterile distilled water and sterilized again in 1&#xB7;3 % sodium hypochlorite solution according to <xref rid="MCT283C61" ref-type="bibr">Vain <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> and <xref rid="MCT283C2" ref-type="bibr">Alves <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref>. The seeds were placed between two sterile filter papers imbibed with sterile distilled water in a Petri dish at 4 &#xB0;C in the dark for 1 week. This stratification treatment is essential for the synchronization of germination of all <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions. Seeds were sown in pots containing Agro Mix<sup>&#xAE;</sup> (Plant Products Co. Ltd) and grown until the three-leaf stage (approx. 10 d) at 20 &#xB0;C with a 16 h photoperiod and a photosynthetic photon flux density of 150 &#xB5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. At the end of this period, control non-acclimated plants were harvested (NA0) or maintained under the same light and temperature conditions for 5 (NA5), 7 (NA7), 21 (NA21) and 45 d (NA45) to provide adequate controls for the different cold acclimation (CA) time points. Cold acclimation was performed by subjecting plants at the three-leaf stage to a temperature of 4 &#xB1; 1 &#xB0;C under either an 8 h photoperiod [short day (SD)] or a 16 h photoperiod [long day (LD)] at a photosynthetic photon flux density of 150 &#xB5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> for different periods of time as specified for each experiment. Deacclimated plants (DA1) were exposed to cold for 28 d (sugar and proline assays) or 42 d [quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR)] and returned to 20 &#xB0;C under a 16 h photoperiod for 1 d. All plant samples were collected at the same time of day, 4 h after the beginning of the light period.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Double-ridge formation</title>
        <p>A dissection of the crown and an analysis of the shoot apex development identified the DR stage (<xref rid="MCT283C35" ref-type="bibr">Kirby and Appleyard, 1987</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C36" ref-type="bibr">Kirby, 1990</xref>). Three-leaf stage plants were maintained under control conditions or exposed to 4 &#xB0;C for the specified periods of time. After each treatment, plants were returned to 20 &#xB0;C under a 16 h photoperiod until DR formation. An average of ten plants per accession were dissected at each of the ten low temperature (LT) treatments, and the mean number of days required to achieve DR formation was recorded to determine the influence of the LT treatment on the rate of phenological development. The experiment was repeated three times with independent biological replicates.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Final leaf number measurements</title>
        <p>Leaves on the main shoot were numbered and the plants were grown until the flag leaf emerged and the FLN could be determined (<xref rid="MCT283C66" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>). Vernalization saturation was reached once the LT treatment no longer reduced the FLN. A minimum of ten plants was used at each of the ten LT treatments under both SD and LD conditions. The experiment was repeated three times with independent biological replicates.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Whole-plant freezing test</title>
        <p>For the WPFTs, 21 seedlings (three of each of the seven <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions tested) were grown until the three-leaf stage in a circular pattern in 4 inch round pots at 20 &#xB0;C. Plants were either kept under the same conditions for an additional 5 d (NA5 plants) or cold acclimated at 4 &#xB0;C for 28 d (CA28). Following acclimation, WPFTs were performed in a programmable Percival low-temperature chamber (LT-36VL) specifically designed to measure cold hardiness in plants. After a 4 h equilibration period at &#x2013;2 &#xB0;C during which plants were seeded with ice chips to initiate freezing (<xref rid="MCT283C8" ref-type="bibr">Charron <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), the temperature was lowered by 1 &#xB0;C h<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, the temperature being decreased in the first 5 min followed by a 55 min plateau. Plants were tested between &#x2013;7 and &#x2013;12 &#xB0;C. At the end of each temperature plateau, three randomly selected pots of NA and CA plants were withdrawn from the chambers for a total of six pots per plateau. To minimize light stress effects after the freezing treatment, plants were thawed at 4 &#xB0;C for 24 h in the dark before returning to normal growth conditions. After 2 weeks, survival counts were taken and the 50 % lethal temperature (LT<sub>50</sub>) calculated. A total of nine plants per accession, per treatment, per plateau, per experiment were removed from the incubator. The experiment was repeated four times with independent biological replicates.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Proline and water-soluble sugar assays</title>
        <p>For free proline and water-soluble sugar (WSS) content assays, the aerial parts of nine plants for each accession were used at each of the seven LT treatments. The experiment was repeated three times with nine independent biological replicates.</p>
        <p>Free proline content was analysed using a colorimetric assay (<xref rid="MCT283C1" ref-type="bibr">&#xC1;brah&#xE1;m <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Proline was extracted by grinding 100 mg of dried plant material with 500 &#xB5;L of 3 % (w/v) sulfosalicylic acid. The extract was centrifuged at 13 000 rpm for 5 min at room temperature. A 0&#xB7;1 mL aliquot of the extract was mixed with 0&#xB7;5 mL of a solution of acidic ninhydrin [40 % acidic ninhydrin (8&#xB7;8 &#xB5;<sc>m</sc> nihydrin, 10&#xB7;5 <sc>m</sc> glacial acetic acid, 2&#xB7;4 <sc>m</sc> orthophosphoric acid), 40 % glacial acetic acid and 20 % of 3 % sulfosalicylic acid]. The samples were incubated for 60 min at 96 &#xB0;C and the reaction was terminated by incubating the samples on ice for 5 min. The samples were then extracted by adding 1 mL of toluene and vortexing for 20 s. The absorbance at 520 nm was measured using toluene as a reference. The standard curve was made using <sc>l</sc>-proline in a range of 0&#x2013;57&#xB7;5 &#xB5;g mL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. Free proline content [&#x3BC;mol g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> fresh weight (f. wt)] was calculated according to <xref rid="MCT283C4" ref-type="bibr">Bates <italic>et al.</italic> (1973)</xref>:
<disp-formula id="MCT283M1"><label>(1)</label><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\eqalign{{\rm Free \ proline}= \, ({\rm \mu g} \ {\rm proline} \ {\rm mL}^{-1}\times {\rm mL} \ {\rm toluene}) \cr / 115 \! \cdot \! 5\,{\rm \mu g} \ {\rm\mu mol}^{-1}/({\rm g} \ {\rm sample}/5)}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p>
        <p>Total WSS content was assessed according to <xref rid="MCT283C44" ref-type="bibr">Luo <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> with modifications to allow the data to be collected using a microplate reader (<xref rid="MCT283C21" ref-type="bibr">Galicia <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Total WSS was extracted from 5 mg of plant dry tissues with 1 mL of distilled water by vortexing. The extract was incubated at 70 &#xB0;C for 45 min, vortexed every 15 min and centrifuged at 13 000 rpm for 20 min at room temperature. The supernatant was diluted 1:10 and 50 &#xB5;L of this sample was mixed with 100 &#xB5;L of anthrone solution [100 mg of anthrone in 100 mL of 95 % (w/w) H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>] in a 96-well microplate. The microplates were shaken at 150 rpm for 10 min at room temperature and incubated at 100 &#xB0;C for 4 min. After cooling, the absorbance at 630 nm was measured. The standard curve was made using sucrose in a range of 0&#x2013;200 &#xB5;g mL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. The WSS content in mg of sucrose g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> of dry plant material was calculated as:
<disp-formula id="MCT283M2"><label>(2)</label><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$ \eqalignno{{\rm WSS}= \, ({\rm mg \ of \ sucrose/mg \ of \ starting \ dry \ plant \ material}) \cr \times {\rm dilution \ factor}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Quantification of fructans</title>
        <p>Dried ground material (100&#x2013;200 mg) was incubated in 6 mL of deionized H<sub>2</sub>O at 80 &#xB0;C for 20 min. The extracts were then incubated overnight at 4 &#xB0;C and were subsequently centrifuged for 10 min at 1500 <italic>g</italic>. A 1 mL sub-sample of the supernatant was collected for quantification of fructans. High degree of polymerization (HDP, from DP 15 to DP 200) fructans and LDP (DP 10) fructans were analysed using a Waters HPLC analytical system controlled by the Empower II software. Samples were kept at 4 &#xB0;C throughout the analysis within the Waters 717<sup>plus</sup> autosampler. The HDP fructans were separated on a Shodex KS-804 column preceded by a Shodex KS-G pre-column (Shodex, Tokyo, Japan) eluted isocratically at 50 &#xB0;C with deionized water at a flow rate of 1&#xB7;0 mL min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, and were detected on a refractive index detector (Model 2410, Waters). The DP of HDP fructans was estimated by reference to a standard curve established with seven polymaltotriose pullulan standards (Shodex Standard P-82) ranging from a molecular weight of 0&#xB7;58 &#xD7; 10<sup>4</sup> to 85&#xB7;3 &#xD7; 10<sup>4</sup>. The retention time on the Shodex column is a function of the log of the molecular weight of pullulan molecules. The concentrations of both HDP and LDP fructans are expressed on an equivalent fructose basis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>RNA extraction, cDNA synthesis and quantitative real-time PCR analysis</title>
        <p>Total RNA was isolated from the aerial parts of plants (<italic>n</italic> = 3 plants per time point) using the RNeasy plant mini kit (Qiagen). All RNAs were treated with DNase I (Qiagen) to remove genomic DNA. RNA integrity was visually assessed with agarose gel electrophoresis. A 2 &#xB5;g aliquot of total RNA was then reverse transcribed using the AffinityScript QPCR cDNA Synthesis Kit (Agilent Technologies) according to the manufacturer's recommendations. Parallel reactions were run for each RNA sample in the absence of AffinityScript reverse transcriptase (no reverse transcriptase control) to assess any genomic DNA contamination. The cDNA products were diluted in water to 400 ng &#x3BC;L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> and stored at &#x2013;20 &#xB0;C.</p>
        <p>Quantitative PCR assays were conducted in triplicate in an Mx3000 real-time thermal cycler (Agilent Technologies) with Brilliant III Ultra-Fast SYBR<sup>&#xAE;</sup> Green QPCR master mix (Agilent Technologies). First-strand cDNA was used as template for PCR amplification using gene-specific primers (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="MCT283TB1">1</xref>). Amplification of the 18S rRNA gene was used as an internal standard. Amplification was performed in a 15 &#xB5;L reaction containing 1&#xD7; SYBR Green master mix, 350 n<sc>m</sc> of each primer, 30 n<sc>m</sc> reference dye ROX and 80 ng of cDNA template. The PCR thermal cycling parameters were 95 &#xB0;C for 2 min followed by 40 cycles of 95 &#xB0;C for 5 s and 60 &#xB0;C for 20 s. Three technical replicates were used, and the experiment was repeated three times with different biological replicates. Controls without template were included for all primer pairs.
<table-wrap id="MCT283TB1" position="float"><label>Table&#xA0;1.</label><caption><p>List of primers used in this study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer name</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer sequence (5&#x2032; to 3&#x2032;)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplicon size (bp)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BradiVRN1-F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x2032;-CAGATCCAGAAAGAACCAGCTAA-3&#x2032;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">220</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BradiVRN1-R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x2032;-GCGATTACTGATATTTGTTGTTGG-3&#x2032;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BradiCOR413-F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x2032;-AGGTTGGTTGCTGGATTGCGTTC-3&#x2032;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BradiCOR413-R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x2032;-TCCAGCCAATCAGGAAAGTGGCG-3&#x2032;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BradiIRI-F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x2032;-AACTGGCAACAACAACGCCGTG-3&#x2032;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BradiIRI-R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x2032;-ACGATGTGGTTGCTCCCGGATAC-3&#x2032;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi18S-F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x2032;-GAAGTTTGAGGCAATAACAGGTCT-3&#x2032;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradi18S-R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x2032;-ATCACGATGAATTTCCCAAGATTAC-3&#x2032;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Raw fluorescent data (background-subtracted data) provided by the Mx-Pro QPCR software (Agilent Technologies) were analysed using the PCR Miner program (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://miner.ewindup.info/miner">http://miner.ewindup.info/miner</uri>; <xref rid="MCT283C69" ref-type="bibr">Zhao and Fernald, 2005</xref>). For each LT treatment, data were expressed as a ratio of gene of interest expression to 18S expression.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>Unless stated otherwise, all the experiments were carried out three times in a complete randomized design with a minimum of three replicates. All data were subjected to an analysis of variance (ANOVA) using the general linear model (GLM) procedure in SAS (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA) to identify significant treatment effects. Comparisons between means were made using least significant differences (LSDs) at a 0&#xB7;05 probability level when ANOVA indicated model and treatment significances.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="s3">
      <title>RESULTS</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Phenological development</title>
        <p>Molecular and physiological studies aimed at understanding the mechanism of freezing tolerance in cereals have revealed that this process is closely associated with the vernalization response (<xref rid="MCT283C17" ref-type="bibr">Fowler <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C12" ref-type="bibr">Danyluk <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C13" ref-type="bibr">Dhillon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Thus, with the goal of unravelling the cold acclimation pattern of seven <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions, we initially opted for a classical approach by determining the effects of low non-freezing temperatures on their phenological development. As a first step, we tested the effects of cold exposure on the FLN of different accessions under SD and LD conditions. In all <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions tested in the current study, exposure to cold and SD conditions had noticeable effects on their FLN. The FLN of the four accessions able to flower without being exposed to LT clearly decreased following the cold treatment under SD conditions (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F1">1</xref>A). Their FLN declined from 11&#x2013;13 leaves under normal conditions to 7&#x2013;8 leaves after 28 d of cold treatment. Exposure to cold for periods &gt;28 d did not further reduce the FLNs of accessions Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd30-1.
<fig id="MCT283F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Final leaf number of seven diploid <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> accessions in response to cold exposure. Final leaf number was compiled for <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions previously shown to have spring (left panel) or winter (right panel) growth habits when cold acclimated under (A and B) SD and (C and D) LD conditions. Time points where plants did not flower during the course of the experiment are indicated by an asterisk. Statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0&#xB7;05) in final leaf number were observed until 28 d for Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd30-1, until 35 d for Bd2-3, until 49 d for Bd29-1 and until 56 d for accessions Bd1-1 and Bd18-1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mct28301"/></fig></p>
        <p>The three winter accessions did not transition from the vegetative to the reproductive phase in the time frame of the experiment unless they were cold treated under SD conditions for a minimum of 28 d. At this time point, these accessions showed elevated FLN (15&#x2013;18 leaves), and a steady decrease in the FLN was observed during the cold treatment until no noticeable changes (7&#x2013;10 leaves) were observed for exposure longer than 49&#x2013;56 d (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F1">1</xref>B).</p>
        <p>We initially chose to perform cold treatment under SDs as this experimental set-up resembles the natural conditions observed during the autumn and is known to promote strong cold acclimation responses in temperate cereals (<xref rid="MCT283C19" ref-type="bibr">Fowler <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). However, this experimental design introduces an obvious confounding factor by simultaneously varying the temperature and the photoperiod. Thus, to determine the respective contributions of LT and daylength reduction to the FLN changes observed in Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F1">1</xref>A and B, we monitored fluctuations in the FLNs of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions cold treated under LD conditions. Under these conditions, we observed a significant FLN reduction in two <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions able to flower without being exposed to LT (Bd3-1 and Bd21; Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F1">1</xref>C). The FLNs of these accessions declined, respectively, from 11 and 13 leaves under normal conditions to six and seven leaves after only 14 d of cold treatment. Interestingly, LD conditions significantly delayed the flowering transition of winter accessions since these accessions only formed spikes after spending a minimum of 49 d at 4 &#xB0;C. At this time point, the winter accessions tested (Bd1-1 and Bd18-1) had FLNs of eight and 13, respectively, and prolonged LT exposure up to 63 d further reduced their FLNs to seven and eight (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F1">1</xref>D). Together, the results presented in Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F1">1</xref> demonstrate that a LT treatment reduces the FLN of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions in both SD and LD conditions and that the rate of this reduction is photoperiod dependent.</p>
        <p>In order to expand our phenological characterization, we monitored at different stages of cold exposure under SDs the formation of the DR structure, a well-known indicator of the transition from the vegetative to the reproductive stages in grasses (<xref rid="MCT283C34" ref-type="bibr">Kirby, 2002</xref>). As expected, dissection of the shoot apices established that four of the accessions, Bd2-3, Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd30-1, entered the reproductive phase when grown at 20 &#xB0;C for their complete life cycle. This observation confirms that those accessions do not require a cold treatment in order to flower (point 0 day; Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F2">2</xref>A). The days of growth required until DR formation (from the end of the vernalization treatment to the DR formation) varied markedly among those accessions, clearly indicating natural genetic variation. Indeed, accession Bd2-3 needed the most days to reach the DR stage, in contrast to accessions Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd30-1 that presented very similar profiles when maintained under control conditions (point 0 day; Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F2">2</xref>A). Interestingly, a cold treatment under SD conditions reduced the numbers of days required until DR formation following LT treatment in these four accessions (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F2">2</xref>A).
<fig id="MCT283F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Apical development of seven diploid <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> accessions exposed to cold (4 &#xB0;C) for the indicated time. Double-ridge formation was compiled for <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions previously shown to have (A) spring or (B) winter growth habits. Time points where plants never formed the double-ridge structure during the course of the experiment are indicated by an asterisk. Statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0&#xB7;05) in days to double-ridge values were observed until 28 d for Bd21 and Bd 30-1, until 42 d for Bd2-3 and Bd 3-1 and until 49 d of treatment for Bd1-1, Bd18-1 and Bd29-1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mct28302"/></fig></p>
        <p>Contrasting results were obtained with the three other accessions tested (Bd1-1, Bd18-1 and Bd29-1; Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F2">2</xref>B). Under SD conditions, these accessions only formed the DR structure after spending a minimum of 28 d at 4 &#xB0;C, indicating that unlike accessions Bd2-3, Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd30-1 (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F2">2</xref>A), they have a strong vernalization requirement and are true winter accessions. For these accessions, vernalization saturation was reached after a cold treatment of 49 d (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F2">2</xref>B).</p>
        <p>The results presented in Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F2">2</xref> also indicate that a cold treatment under SD conditions can promote the formation of the DR structure earlier in the development of most <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions with no absolute vernalization requirement. Indeed, by adding the number of days of growth before the vernalization treatment (14 d), the duration of the vernalization treatment at a given time point and the corresponding number of days needed to observe the DR structure once the plants are returned to normal conditions, it is possible to estimate whether an LT treatment under SD conditions can stimulate early flowering in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> plants. In comparison with untreated plants, 21 d of exposure to LT and SD conditions accelerated the DR formation in accessions Bd3-1 and Bd21 by 6 and 11 d, respectively, while 28 and 35 d exposures accelerated the flowering transition of accession Bd3-1 by 23 and 24 d. On the other hand, accession Bd30-1 did not develop the DR structure earlier following the nine LT treatments.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Molecular response to low temperatures</title>
        <p>In order to substantiate our phenological development observations and further to highlight the link between the vernalization and the cold acclimation responses in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, we opted to juxtapose the expression profiles of orthologues of the vernalization regulator <italic>VRN1</italic> and of two <italic>COR</italic> genes already shown to be differentially expressed in response to cold in monocots (<xref rid="MCT283C7" ref-type="bibr">Breton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C59" ref-type="bibr">Tremblay <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C40" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).</p>
        <p>In agreement with <xref rid="MCT283C25" ref-type="bibr">Higgins <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref>, <italic>Bradi1g08340&#xB7;1</italic>, hereafter named <italic>BradiVRN1</italic>, was selected for this study because of its high level of sequence homology to the wheat <italic>VRN1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aob.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aob/mct283/-/DC1">Supplementary Data Fig. S1</ext-link>). The protein encoded by <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> shares high homology with <italic>Triticum monococcum VRN1</italic> (<xref rid="MCT283C52" ref-type="bibr">Pidal <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) (89 % identity and 92 % similarity) and <italic>Triticum aestivum VRT-1</italic> (<xref rid="MCT283C12" ref-type="bibr">Danyluk <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>) (84 % identity and 89 % similarity; Fig. S1). Like most MADS box transcription factors, the protein encoded by <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> contains the usual three conserved regions (MADS, I and K domains) and a C-terminal domain. As expected, lower sequence similarity is observed in the C-terminal region since this region was shown to diverge substantially between MADS box orthologues (<xref rid="MCT283C56" ref-type="bibr">Theissen <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>). Sequence analysis further revealed that <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> possesses a bipartite nuclear targeting domain that is conserved in all the MADS box transcription factors as well as conserved phosphorylation sites in the C-terminal region (Fig. S1; <xref rid="MCT283C12" ref-type="bibr">Danyluk <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>).</p>
        <p><italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions Bd1-1, Bd2-3, Bd3-1, Bd18-1 and Bd21 were selected to highlight variations in transcript accumulation of <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> in response to cold exposure because of their contrasting differences in phenological development. Non-acclimated (NA0 and NA7) plants and plants cold acclimated for 1 and 7 d (CA1 and CA7) showed minimal <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> transcript accumulation, whereas progressively longer cold exposure led to a gradual accumulation of the transcript in all accessions tested (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F3">3</xref>A&#x2013;E). Maximum accumulation was reached after 42 d, and transcript levels remained elevated after 1 d of deacclimation in all accessions (DA1; Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F3">3</xref>A&#x2013;E). The fold change values in <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> transcripts varied greatly among accessions, with overall differences ranging from 100-fold (Bd3-1) to 1500-fold (Bd1-1) increases after 42 d of cold treatment. No obvious correlation was observed between the magnitude of the variations in <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> transcripts and the growth habits of the accessions tested (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F3">3</xref>A&#x2013;E). Interestingly, increased accumulation of <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> transcripts is also observed in ageing Bd21 plants never exposed to 4 &#xB0;C, whereas the level of this transcript remains low and stable in ageing Bd18-1 plants (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F3">3</xref>F).
<fig id="MCT283F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Expression analysis of <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> in response to low temperatures. (A&#x2013;C) Relative transcript accumulation of <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions Bd2-3, Bd3-1 and Bd21. (D and E) Relative transcript accumulation of <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> in winter <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions Bd1-1 and Bd18-1. (F) Relative transcript accumulation of <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> in Bd21 and Bd18-1 plants not exposed to 4 &#xB0;C. Letters above bars represent statistical significance (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0&#xB7;05); different letters indicate statistically different fold expression.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mct28303"/></fig></p>
        <p>Variations in the expression of <italic>COR</italic> genes can be correlated to the level of freezing tolerance in cereals (<xref rid="MCT283C26" ref-type="bibr">Houde <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C10" ref-type="bibr">Danyluk <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C17" ref-type="bibr">Fowler <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C41" ref-type="bibr">Limin <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C11" ref-type="bibr">Danyluk <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C7" ref-type="bibr">Breton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). In this study, we thus explored the possibility of using <italic>BradiIRI</italic> (Bradi5g27350&#xB7;1) and <italic>Bradicor413</italic> (Bradi1g07440&#xB7;1) as potential markers for freezing tolerance in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>. As expected, the accumulation of <italic>BradiIRI</italic> increased following cold exposure in accessions Bd2-3 and Bd18-1 (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F4">4</xref>A, C). In Bd2-3, maximum transcript accumulation was reached after 7 d at 4 &#xB0;C, after which a steady decrease in accumulation was observed. In Bd18-1, the level of <italic>BradiIRI</italic> transcripts gradually increased until 14 d of cold exposure, after which a decrease in accumulation was also observed. The level of <italic>BradiIRI</italic> transcripts returned to control levels in both accessions after 1 d of deacclimation (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F4">4</xref>A, C).
<fig id="MCT283F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Accumulation of <italic>COR</italic> gene transcripts during cold acclimation in <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>. Relative transcript accumulation of (A, B) <italic>BradiIRI</italic> and (C, D) <italic>BradiCOR413</italic> in Bd2-3 and Bd18-1 plants exposed to LT for up to 42 d. Relative transcript accumulation in above-ground tissues was measured by quantitative real-time PCR and normalized to 18S rRNA transcript levels. Letters above bars represent statistical significance (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0&#xB7;05); different letters indicate statistically different fold expression.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mct28304"/></fig></p>
        <p>The <italic>cold-regulated 413</italic> gene was first identified in wheat and arabidopsis where the accumulation of its transcripts was correlated with the capacity of the plant to develop freezing tolerance (<xref rid="MCT283C7" ref-type="bibr">Breton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). Sequence homology searches allowed us to identify <italic>Bradi1g07440&#xB7;1</italic> as the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> orthologue of <italic>COR413</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aob.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aob/mct283/-/DC1">Supplementary Data Fig. S2</ext-link>). A clear accumulation of <italic>BradiCOR413</italic> transcripts was observed after 1 d of cold treatment in both accessions tested (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F4">4</xref>B, D). In Bd2-3, the maximum accumulation was observed after 7 d of cold exposure. Following that point, a gradual decrease in transcript abundance was observed until 21 d of cold treatment, after which the levels remained constant until the end of the cold treatment (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F4">4</xref>B, D). In Bd18-1, <italic>BradiCOR413</italic> transcripts levels remained high during the first 3 weeks of cold treatment, after which a slight decrease in transcript levels was noticed (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F4">4</xref>B, D). Upon deacclimation, <italic>BradiCOR413</italic> levels returned to control levels in both accessions (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F4">4</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Freezing tolerance determination</title>
        <p>In order to determine the freezing tolerance capacities of the seven diploid <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions used in this study, WPFTs were conducted with plants grown under normal conditions (NA5) and plants that were cold acclimated for 28 d (CA28; Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F5">5</xref>A). The 28 d time point was selected based on our phenological development observations and gene accumulation data (Figs&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F2"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F3"/>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F4">4</xref>), as well as on reported distinctive variation in freezing tolerance between spring and winter wheat varieties observed after 4 weeks of cold exposure (<xref rid="MCT283C16" ref-type="bibr">Fowler and Limin, 2004</xref>). Furthermore, preliminary tests performed with control plants and plants exposed to cold for 7 and 14 d did not reveal significant differences in freezing tolerance between NA and CA <italic>Brachypodium</italic> plants (data not shown). Prior to WPFTs, no noticeable morphological differences that could explain variations in freezing tolerance were apparent between NA5 and CA28 <italic>Brachypodium</italic> plants. Following WPFTs, plants that did not survive the procedure were heavily damaged and evidently dead. A survival rate of 50 % was obtained for NA5 plants at temperatures ranging from &#x2013;7&#xB7;6 &#xB0;C (Bd21) to &#x2013;8&#xB7;8 &#xB0;C (Bd18-1). A 28 d period of cold exposure allowed an approx. 2 &#xB0;C decrease in the LT<sub>50</sub> values for all accessions, with survival rates of 50 % observed at temperatures ranging from &#x2013;10&#xB7;3 &#xB0;C (Bd3-1) to &#x2013;10&#xB7;6 &#xB0;C (Bd18-1). Overall, no obvious difference in freezing tolerance was observed between the group of accessions that do not require vernalization to flower (Bd2-3, Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd30-1) and the winter type accessions (Bd1-1, Bd18-1 and Bd29-1; Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F5">5</xref>A).
<fig id="MCT283F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Freezing temperature tolerance (LT<sub>50</sub>) of seven diploid <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> accessions. (A) Plants at the three-leaf stage were either kept under normal conditions (non-acclimated) for 5 d (NA5) or cold acclimated for 28 d (CA28) before being subjected to WPFTs. After 2 weeks in normal growth conditions, survival counts were taken and the LT<sub>50</sub> was calculated. The experiment was repeated four times, and error bars indicate the standard deviation of the mean. (B and C) Relative transcript abundance of <italic>BradiIRI</italic> (B) and <italic>BradiCOR413</italic> (C) in NA5 and CA28 plants used for WPFTs of seven diploid <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions. Letters above bars represent statistical significance (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0&#xB7;05); different letters indicate statistically different fold expression.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mct28305"/></fig></p>
        <p>The observed homogeneity in freezing tolerance levels between the seven <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions tested suggests similar <italic>COR</italic> gene transcripts levels after 28 d of cold acclimation. The accumulation levels of <italic>BradiIRI</italic> and <italic>BradiCOR413</italic> transcripts were thus monitored in NA5 and CA28 samples taken prior to the WPFTs. The accumulation levels of <italic>BradiIRI</italic> transcripts did not reflect the WPFT observations since pronounced variations in <italic>BradiIRI</italic> transcript levels were observed among the different accessions (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F5">5</xref>B). After 28 d of cold acclimation, the strongest accumulation of <italic>BradiIRI</italic> transcripts was detected in Bd18-1, while 20 times fewer transcripts were detected in Bd3-1. On the other hand, <italic>BradiCOR413</italic> transcript accumulation was relatively stable among CA28 plants of all accessions, which better reflects their homogenous freezing tolerance capacities (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F5">5</xref>C).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Metabolic adjustments in response to low temperatures</title>
        <p>In order to characterize further the freezing tolerance of <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, we determined the effect of prolonged cold exposure on the content of WSS. Non-acclimated <italic>Brachypodium</italic> tissues contained minimum values of WSS, ranging from 43 &#xB5;g mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> dry weight (d. wt) (Bd1-1) to 57 &#xB5;g mg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> d. wt (Bd30-1; Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F6">6</xref>A, C). A significant increase in the WSS concentration was noticed in all accessions when the plants were exposed to cold temperatures (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F6">6</xref>A, C). After a 1 d de-acclimation period under normal growth conditions, a clear reduction of the WSS concentration was observed in all accessions (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F6">6</xref>A, C). Interestingly, the WSS content was high in all <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions at the 28 d time point. However, these values varied greatly among accessions, which could suggest that a global assessment of WSS does not have the specificity needed to estimate precisely the freezing tolerance capacity of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> plants. To circumvent this limitation, we opted to measure fructans, a well-characterized group of storage carbohydrates known to accumulate during cold acclimation in temperate grasses (<xref rid="MCT283C43" ref-type="bibr">Livingston <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). The chromatographic characterization of fructans revealed that both LDP and HDP fructans are present in above-ground tissues of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> plants (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="MCT283TB2">2</xref>). In all accessions tested, LDP and HDP fructans were found to increase in response to LT treatment. In comparison with LDP fructans, higher concentrations of HDP fructans were observed in the seven <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions tested (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="MCT283TB2">2</xref>). Furthermore, HDP fructan values in cold-acclimated plants did not show any significant variation among the different accessions, which suggest that this measurement could potentially be used as a freezing tolerance indicator for the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> model.
<fig id="MCT283F6" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Water-soluble sugar and proline concentration in leaves of seven diploid <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> accessions exposed to cold. (A and C) WSS and (B and D) proline concentration of non-acclimated plants (NA0 and NA5), cold-acclimated plants (CA7, CA14, CA21 and CA28) and de-acclimated plants (DA1) of accessions previously shown to have a spring growth habit (left) or winter growth habit (right). The error bars indicate standard deviation of the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mct28306"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="MCT283TB2" position="float"><label>TABLE&#xA0;2.</label><caption><p>Changes in LDP and HDP fructans in above-ground tissues of seven diploid <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> accessions in response to cold acclimation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accession</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth habit</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDP (mg g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> d. wt)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDP (mg g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> d. wt)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">NA5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd2-3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#xB7;16 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;02<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#xB7;05 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;08<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd3-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#xB7;11 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;03<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#xB7;10 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;10<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#xB7;06 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;02<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#xB7;12 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;09<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd30-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#xB7;08 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;02<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#xB7;51 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;13<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd1-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Winter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#xB7;04 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;02<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#xB7;80 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;06<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd18-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Winter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#xB7;05 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;01<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#xB7;04 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;04<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd29-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Winter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#xB7;08 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;01<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#xB7;29 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;05<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">CA28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd2-3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#xB7;13 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;09<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#xB7;66 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;21<sup>ab</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd3-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#xB7;31 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;22<sup>f</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#xB7;45 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;62<sup>bc</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#xB7;57 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;11<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#xB7;96 &#xB1; 2&#xB7;90<sup>bc</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd30-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#xB7;22 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;11<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#xB7;95 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;43<sup>bc</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd1-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Winter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#xB7;99 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;13<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#xB7;55 &#xB1; 2&#xB7;79<sup>bc</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd18-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Winter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#xB7;62 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;05<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#xB7;97 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;09<sup>bc</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bd29-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Winter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#xB7;38 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;09<sup>be</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#xB7;74 &#xB1; 0&#xB7;64<sup>c</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Different letters indicate significant differences between means (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0&#xB7;05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>We also wanted to determine if proline could be used as an indicator of the freezing tolerance level of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions. Under control conditions, similar basal proline contents were observed in all accessions (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F6">6</xref>B, D). As observed in the case of WSS, an elevated proline content was observed in all accessions throughout the cold treatment. Winter accessions Bd18-1 and Bd29-1 displayed the most robust proline profile throughout the cold treatment (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F6">6</xref>B, D), whereas the lowest pool of proline was observed in winter accession Bd1-1. A decrease in proline concentration was observed in all accessions when plants were returned to normal conditions for 1 d (DA1). However, proline levels remained elevated in DA1 plants of accessions Bd18-1, Bd29-1 and Bd30-1, whereas levels returned close to control values in accession Bd1-1, Bd2-3, Bd3-1 and Bd21 (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F6">6</xref>B, D).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>As part of our long-term objective of complete characterization of the freezing tolerance components of <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>, we devised a classical approach involving the monitoring of phenological, molecular and metabolic indicators. Temperate cereal germplasms can be divided into three broad growth habit classifications &#x2013; winter, facultative and spring. Winter varieties are freezing tolerant and require vernalization. In contrast, spring varieties barely tolerate freezing temperatures and do not require vernalization. The facultative growth habit lacks a clear definition and is considered by some as a sub-class of the winter growth habit. The facultative habit genotypes are usually freezing tolerant like winter varieties but lack vernalization requirements (<xref rid="MCT283C70" ref-type="bibr">von Zitzewitz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>).</p>
      <p>The <italic>B. distachyon</italic> diploid inbred lines used in this study were previously classified as either spring (Bd2-3, Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd30-1) or winter genotypes (Bd1-1, Bd18-1 and Bd29-1) according to their capacity to flower or not without prior exposure to cold (<xref rid="MCT283C53" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Our results, obtained from the monitoring of phenological indicators and the profiling of <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> transcript accumulation, corroborate the winter habit classification of accessions Bd1-1, Bd18-1 and Bd29-1. These accessions did not flower without being previously exposed to 4 &#xB0;C for a minimum of 28 d under SD conditions (Figs.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F1">1</xref>, 2). Non-acclimated winter accession plants were eventually grown for &gt;200 d without any signs of flowering (data not shown), clearly highlighting their absolute vernalization requirement. The fact that sharp decreases in FLN and in the number of days to DR formation are observed for theses accessions is in agreement with reports on wheat and rye winter varieties (Limin <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996<italic>b</italic>). On the other hand, the trend observed for these two phenological indicators in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> &#x2018;spring&#x2019; accessions did not exhibit the stable characteristic profiles generally observed in rye and wheat spring varieties (<xref rid="MCT283C17" ref-type="bibr">Fowler <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="MCT283C18" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>). A closer examination of the profiles obtained for the two phenological indicators used in this study revealed a closer match to facultative cereal varieties where a small but significant acceleration of the phenological development is usually observed when plants are exposed to cold. The acceleration in response to LT of the phenological development of accessions Bd2-3, Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd30-1 observed during this study was unexpected, and implies that these accessions are facultative genotypes since this type of behaviour is uncommon for spring genotypes. At first sight, these results do not agree with the study of <xref rid="MCT283C53" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> that reported no significant effect of vernalization (in terms of number of days) on the vegetative to reproductive phase transition in accessions Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd30-1. However, this discrepancy can most probably be explained by the age difference of the plant material used in both studies. Indeed, <xref rid="MCT283C53" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> used plants that were closer to the transition point before performing the vernalization treatment (4-week-old plants grown under a 20 h light/4 h dark photoperiod), wheras <italic>Brachypodium</italic> plants at the three-leaf stage (approx. 14 d old) were exposed to cold in the current study.</p>
      <p>The genome of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> has been reported to contain multiple orthologues of the temperate cereal gene <italic>VRN1</italic>. On one hand, <xref rid="MCT283C53" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> proposed that two genes (Bradi1g08340&#xB7;1 and Bradi1g59250&#xB7;1) could potentially be considered as <italic>VRN1</italic> orthologues, while another study clearly identified Bradi1g08340&#xB7;1 as the only <italic>VRN1</italic> candidate in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (<xref rid="MCT283C25" ref-type="bibr">Higgins <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). For this study, Bradi1g08340&#xB7;1 was selected based on its close sequence identity to wheat <italic>VRN1</italic>. Although further work is needed to confirm <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> (Bradi1g08340&#xB7;1) as <italic>VRN1</italic>, the expression profiles presented in this study undoubtedly revealed several key characteristics that establish this gene as a vernalization gene (<xref rid="MCT283C67" ref-type="bibr">Yan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). The transcript accumulation patterns observed among accessions Bd1-1, Bd2-3, Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd18-1 over a period of 42 d of cold exposure are consistent with profiles commonly observed in winter wheat varieties. These winter varieties generally express <italic>VRN1</italic> at low levels during the early stages of cold exposure, and progressively higher levels of this transcript can be detected until the 49&#x2013;56 d mark, where a distinctive plateau is usually reached (<xref rid="MCT283C32" ref-type="bibr">Kane <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Furthermore, the abundance of this transcript remains elevated upon deacclimation after 42 d of cold treatment. While this expression pattern was expected for winter habit genotypes Bd1-1 and Bd18-1, it does not support the &#x2018;spring habit&#x2019; classification of Bd2-3, Bd3-1 and Bd21 accessions. Spring cereal genotypes such as Manitou (wheat) and Morex (barley) constitutively express <italic>VRN1</italic> regardless of their vernalization status (<xref rid="MCT283C12" ref-type="bibr">Danyluk <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C32" ref-type="bibr">Kane <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C70" ref-type="bibr">von Zitzewitz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Surprisingly, the transcript accumulation pattern of <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> in accessions Bd2-3, Bd3-1 and Bd21 (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F3">3</xref>A, B, C) resembles the profiles observed in winter cereal varieties and is a very close match to the <italic>VRN1</italic> profile observed in the facultative barley variety Dicktoo (<xref rid="MCT283C12" ref-type="bibr">Danyluk <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C32" ref-type="bibr">Kane <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C70" ref-type="bibr">von Zitzewitz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). In addition, the present study demonstrates that LT is not necessarily the only determinant responsible for the increased accumulation of <italic>VRN1</italic> in facultative accessions, since this transcript accumulates at late developmental stages in accession Bd21 grown under control conditions (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F3">3</xref>F). This observation, together with our DR and FLN data (Figs&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F1">1</xref>, 2), clearly suggests that accession Bd21 has a facultative growth habit.</p>
      <p>The possibility that no spring habit <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accession can be found in the group of diploid accessions tested is further substantiated by our WPFT observations. Even if a cold acclimation period of 28 d only resulted in a modest 2 &#xB0;C gain in freezing tolerance in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, the fact that this gain is similarly observed among all accessions is another good indication that these accessions can be classified as facultative or winter habits. In addition, the LT<sub>50</sub> values observed for non-acclimated plants are relatively low in comparison with values previously obtained for barley (approx. &#x2013;2 &#xB0;C; <xref rid="MCT283C42" ref-type="bibr">Limin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) and winter wheat varieties (approx. &#x2013;4 &#xB0;C; <xref rid="MCT283C16" ref-type="bibr">Fowler and Limin, 2004</xref>) grown under similar conditions. This suggests that <italic>B. distachyon</italic> has stronger constitutive freezing tolerance mechanisms compared with modern cultivated cereal varieties that rely on inducible mechanisms to develop freezing tolerance.</p>
      <p>The <italic>BradiIRI</italic> and <italic>BradiCOR413</italic> transcript abundance analyses reported here provide additional evidence that some of the molecular mechanisms of freezing tolerance observed in hardy grasses are present in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>. Furthermore, the differential transcript accumulation patterns observed for both <italic>COR</italic> genes emphasizes the possibility that accessions Bd2-3, Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd30-1 have facultative growth habits. Facultative genotypes, like winter types, are known to rely on induced <italic>COR</italic> gene expression to induce their freezing tolerance capacities but lack an absolute vernalization requirement (<xref rid="MCT283C33" ref-type="bibr">Karsai <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). In addition, the decline observed in <italic>BradiIRI</italic> and <italic>BradiCOR413</italic> transcript accumulation in Bd2-3 and Bd18-1 (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F4">4</xref>) is negatively correlated with the increase in <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> transcript levels (Fig.&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F3">3</xref>A, E). This suggests that <italic>COR</italic> gene transcripts become less abundant when the floral transition is about to be reached in these accessions. However, our results suggest that <italic>BradiIRI</italic> is not a reliable freezing tolerance indicator/marker for <italic>Brachypodium</italic>. This observation agrees well with results reported in <xref rid="MCT283C40" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref>, where 7-week-old cold-acclimated <italic>Brachypodium</italic> plants of accessions Bd1-1, Bd21-1 and Bd29-1 were shown to accumulate various levels of <italic>BradiIRI</italic> transcripts. On the other hand, <italic>COR413</italic> accumulation has been tightly correlated to the plant's capacity to develop freezing tolerance in wheat (<xref rid="MCT283C7" ref-type="bibr">Breton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>), and our observations suggest that this gene could potentially be used as a freezing tolerance indicator for <italic>Brachypodium</italic> as well. Nevertheless, accessions or eventually transformants with clear phenotypic variations for freezing tolerance will have to be investigated either to support or to refute this assertion.</p>
      <p>Several metabolites have been reported to give instantaneous snapshots of the physiology of a plant cell (<xref rid="MCT283C39" ref-type="bibr">Levitt, 1980</xref>). This is best exemplified by the existence of positive correlations between the level of freezing tolerance of cereals and their capacities to accumulate compatible solutes such as proline and WSS (<xref rid="MCT283C49" ref-type="bibr">Olien and Clark, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C30" ref-type="bibr">Hurry <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C68" ref-type="bibr">Yoshida <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C60" ref-type="bibr">V&#xE1;g&#xFA;jfalvi <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). The distinctive difference in WSS concentration generally observed between spring and winter cereal genotypes was not observed among the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> diploid accessions tested. Again, this can probably be explained by the facultative behaviour displayed by accessions Bd2-3, Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd30-1 throughout this study. Nonetheless, the lack of a clear trend among the WSS profiles observed in this study might just be a characteristic that sets apart the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> model, since <xref rid="MCT283C44" ref-type="bibr">Luo <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> did not find a distinctive difference in WSS among <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions even if clear differences in drought tolerance capacities were observed. However, our study provides evidence that the characterization of HDP fructans could serve as an alternative to the broad characterization of WSS in order to evaluate the freezing tolerance capacities of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions. Our results revealed that <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions with similar freezing tolerance capacities accumulate HDP fructans at very comparable levels after 28 d of cold treatment. This finding does not seem to be limited to the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> model since similar correlations have been established in winter wheat, triticale and rye cultivars (<xref rid="MCT283C55" ref-type="bibr">Suzuki and Nass, 1988</xref>). However, while HDP fructans do accumulate in response to cold in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, it is worth noting that the overall concentration values of HDP and LDP fructans remain low in comparison with values observed in cold-hardy grasses such as winter wheat varieties and annual bluegrass genotypes that can accumulate up to 100 mg g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> d. wt under similar conditions (<xref rid="MCT283C55" ref-type="bibr">Suzuki and Nass, 1988</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C68" ref-type="bibr">Yoshida <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="MCT283C6" ref-type="bibr">Bertrand <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>).</p>
      <p>Our results also indicate that although exposure to cold temperatures triggers the accumulation of proline in <italic>Brachypodium</italic>, the size of the proline pool of a given accession cannot be used to predict its freezing tolerance behaviour accurately since accessions with markedly different proline levels such as Bd29-1 and Bd1-1 exhibited very similar LT<sub>50</sub> values (Figs&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="MCT283F5">5</xref>, 6). This observation agrees well with the fact that no correlation could be established between variations in the proline pool during cold exposure and the level of freezing tolerance for arabidopsis and <italic>Thellungiella</italic> sp. (<xref rid="MCT283C38" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).</p>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <p>This study demonstrates that cold acclimation and freezing tolerance mechanisms exist in <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>. In response to LT, <italic>Brachypodium</italic> plants were able to accumulate <italic>COR</italic> gene transcripts and increase their pools of osmoprotectants. These changes are most probably responsible for the decrease in the LT<sub>50</sub> values observed in all <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions tested and support our findings that cold acclimation modestly increases the freezing tolerance capacity of the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> model. Together with earlier findings that the <italic>CBF</italic> gene family is present in the genome of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and that <italic>BradiCBF1</italic> is regulated by LT (<xref rid="MCT283C40" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), the results presented here demonstrate that <italic>Brachypodium</italic> is able to acclimate to LT and to develop freezing tolerance.</p>
        <p>This study also demonstrates that little to no natural genetic variation in terms of freezing tolerance exists among the <italic>Brachypodium</italic> diploid accessions tested and is the first to demonstrate that some <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions that do not necessitate a cold treatment in order to flower possess a facultative growth habit. We demonstrated that <italic>Brachypodium</italic> accessions Bd2-3, Bd3-1, Bd21 and Bd30-1 advanced to DR formation more rapidly and progressively reduced their FLN when exposed to cold for several days. Furthermore, a gradual accumulation of <italic>BradiVRN1</italic> transcripts and a synchronized decrease in the level of <italic>COR</italic> gene transcript were also observed in these accessions during cold acclimation.</p>
        <p>Taken together, this study is the first to characterize the freezing tolerance capacities of the model plant <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and to demonstrate that the widely used Bd21 accession has a facultative growth habit.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title>
      <p>
        <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aob.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aob/mct283/-/DC1">Supplementary data are available online at www.oab.oxfordjournals.org and consist of the following. Figure S1: alignment of the deduced amino acid sequences of <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> VRN1-related proteins. Figure S2: alignment of the deduced amino acid sequences of <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> COR413 with related proteins.</ext-link>
      </p>
      <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Data</title>
        </caption>
        <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_113_4_681__index.html"/>
        <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_mct283_mct283supp.pdf"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
      <p>The authors are grateful to Thomas Nicole, Lisa Rosenberger, Purva Karia and Philippe Seguin for their help during the course of the experiments. We also thank David F. Garvin for providing <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> seeds. K.C.G. was supported by an Alexander-Graham-Bell scholarship from the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council (NSERC). The authors also acknowledge the support from the Centre SEVE. This work was supported by the NSERC of Canada [Discovery grant 386537 to J.B.C].</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>LITERATURE CITED</title>
      <ref id="MCT283C1">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>&#xC1;brah&#xE1;m</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hourton-Cabassa</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Erdei</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szabados</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Methods for determination of proline in plants</article-title>
          <source>Methods in Molecular Biology</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>639</volume>
          <fpage>317</fpage>
          <lpage>331</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20387056</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C2">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alves</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Worland</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thole</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Snape</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bevan</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vain</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A protocol for <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> community standard line Bd21</article-title>
          <source>Nature Protocols</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>638</fpage>
          <lpage>649</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C3">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Badawi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Danyluk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boucho</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Houde</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarhan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The <italic>CBF</italic> gene family in hexaploid wheat and its relationship to the phylogenetic complexity of cereal <italic>CBF</italic>s</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Genetics and Genomics</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>277</volume>
          <fpage>533</fpage>
          <lpage>554</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17285309</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C4">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bates</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waldren</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Teare</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rapid determination of free proline for water-stress studies</article-title>
          <source>Plant and Soil</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>205</fpage>
          <lpage>207</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C5">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhandol</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leitch</surname>
              <given-names>IJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nuclear DNA amounts in angiosperms and their modern uses &#x2013; 807 new estimates</article-title>
          <source>Annals of Botany</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <fpage>859</fpage>
          <lpage>909</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C6">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bertrand</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castonguay</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azaiez</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsiang</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dionne</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cold-induced responses in annual bluegrass genotypes with differential resistance to pink snow mold (<italic>Microdochium nivale</italic>)</article-title>
          <source>Plant Science</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>180</volume>
          <fpage>111</fpage>
          <lpage>119</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21421353</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C7">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Breton</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Danyluk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Charron</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarhan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Expression profiling and bioinformatic analyses of a novel stress-regulated multispanning transmembrane protein family from cereals and Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>132</volume>
          <fpage>64</fpage>
          <lpage>74</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12746512</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C8">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Charron</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ouellet</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Houde</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarhan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The plant Apolipoprotein D ortholog protects <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> against oxidative stress</article-title>
          <source>BMC Plant Biology</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>86</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18671872</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C9">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Crosatti</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nevo</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stanca</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cattivelli</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic analysis of the accumulation of COR14 proteins in wild (<italic>Hordeum spontaneum</italic>) and cultivated (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>) barley</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>975</fpage>
          <lpage>981</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24162433</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C10">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Danyluk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Houde</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rassart</surname>
              <given-names>&#xC9;</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarhan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differential expression of a gene encoding an acidic dehydrin in chilling sensitive and freezing tolerant gramineae species</article-title>
          <source>FEBS Letters</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>344</volume>
          <fpage>20</fpage>
          <lpage>24</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7910142</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C11">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Danyluk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perron</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Houde</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Accumulation of an acidic dehydrin in the vicinity of the plasma membrane during cold acclimation of wheat</article-title>
          <source>The Plant Cell</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>623</fpage>
          <lpage>638</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9548987</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C12">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Danyluk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kane</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Breton</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Limin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fowler</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarhan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>TaVRT-1, a putative transcription factor associated with vegetative to reproductive transition in cereals</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>132</volume>
          <fpage>1849</fpage>
          <lpage>1860</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12913142</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C13">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dhillon</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pearce</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stockinger</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of freezing tolerance and flowering in temperate cereals: the <italic>VRN-1</italic> connection</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>153</volume>
          <fpage>1846</fpage>
          <lpage>1858</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20571115</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C14">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Draper</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mur</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jenkins</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Brachypodium distachyon A new model system for functional genomics in grasses</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>127</volume>
          <fpage>1539</fpage>
          <lpage>55</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11743099</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C15">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Faricelli</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valarik</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Control of flowering time and spike development in cereals: the earliness per se Eps-1 region in wheat, rice, and Brachypodium</article-title>
          <source>Functional and Integrative Genomics</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>293</fpage>
          <lpage>306</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19851796</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C16">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fowler</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Limin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Interactions among factors regulating phenological development and acclimation rate determine low-temperature tolerance in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Annals of Botany</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>717</fpage>
          <lpage>724</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15374834</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C17">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fowler</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chauvin</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Limin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarhan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The regulatory role of vernalization in the expression of low-temperature-induced genes in wheat and rye</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>1996a</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>554</fpage>
          <lpage>559</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24162347</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C18">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fowler</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Limin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relationship between low-temperature tolerance and vernalization response in wheat and rye</article-title>
          <source>Canadian Journal of Plant Science</source>
          <year>1996b</year>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>42</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C19">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fowler</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Breton</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Limin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahfoozi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarhan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Photoperiod and temperature interactions regulate low-temperature-induced gene expression in barley</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>127</volume>
          <fpage>1676</fpage>
          <lpage>1681</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11743112</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C20">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Galiba</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>V&#xE1;g&#xFA;jfalvi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Solt&#xE9;sz</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulatory genes involved in the determination of frost tolerance in temperate cereals</article-title>
          <source>Plant Science</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>176</volume>
          <fpage>12</fpage>
          <lpage>19</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C21">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Galicia</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nurit</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosales</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Palacios-Rojas</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Laboratory protocols 2009: maize nutrition quality and plant tissue analysis laboratory</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <publisher-loc>Mexioc, D.F</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>CIMMYT</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C22">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Garvin</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Varshney</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koebner</surname>
              <given-names>RMD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>: a new model system for structural and functional analysis of grass genomes</article-title>
          <source>Model plants and crop improvement.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, CRC</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher-name>
          <fpage>109</fpage>
          <lpage>123</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C23">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grossi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giorni</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rizza</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stanca</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cattivelli</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wild and cultivated barleys show differences in the expression pattern of a cold-regulated gene family under different light and temperature conditions</article-title>
          <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>1061</fpage>
          <lpage>1069</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9869412</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C24">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guy</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cold acclimation and freezing stress tolerance: role of protein metabolism</article-title>
          <source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>187</fpage>
          <lpage>223</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C25">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Higgins</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bailey</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laurie</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparative genomics of flowering time pathways using <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> as a model for the temperate grasses</article-title>
          <source>PLoS One</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <comment>e10065</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C26">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Houde</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dhindsa</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarhan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A molecular marker to select for freezing tolerance in Gramineae</article-title>
          <source>Molecular and General Genetics</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>234</volume>
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1495483</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C27">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hughes</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dunn</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The molecular biology of plant acclimation to low temperature</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>291</fpage>
          <lpage>305</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C28">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>H&#xFC;ner</surname>
              <given-names>NPA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>&#xD6;quist</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarhan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Energy balance and acclimation to light and cold</article-title>
          <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>224</fpage>
          <lpage>230</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C29">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huo</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vogel</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lazo</surname>
              <given-names>GR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Structural characterization of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> genome and its syntenic relationship with rice and wheat</article-title>
          <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          <lpage>61</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19184460</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C30">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hurry</surname>
              <given-names>VM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strand</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tobiaeson</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gardestrom</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oquist</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cold hardening of spring and winter wheat and rape results in differential effects on growth, carbon metabolism, and carbohydrate content</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>697</fpage>
          <lpage>706</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228623</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C31">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jaglo-Ottosen</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilmour</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zarka</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schabenberger</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomashow</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis CBF1</italic> overexpression induces <italic>COR</italic> genes and enhances freezing tolerance</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>280</volume>
          <fpage>104</fpage>
          <lpage>106</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9525853</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C32">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kane</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Danyluk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tardif</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>TaVRT-2</italic>, a member of the <italic>St</italic>MADS-11 clade of flowering repressors, is regulated by vernalization and photoperiod in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>138</volume>
          <fpage>2354</fpage>
          <lpage>2363</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16024692</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C33">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Karsai</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sz&#x171;cs</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meszaros</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The <italic>Vrn-H2</italic> locus is a major determinant of flowering time in a facultative&#xD7;winter growth habit barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L.) mapping population</article-title>
          <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>1458</fpage>
          <lpage>1466</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15834697</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C34">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kirby</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Curtis</surname>
              <given-names>BC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rajaram</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>G&#xF3;mez Macpherson</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Botany of the wheat plant</article-title>
          <source>FAO Plant Production and Protection Series.</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <publisher-name>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO)</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C35">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kirby</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Appleyard</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Cereal development guide</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <publisher-loc>Warwickshire, UK</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Arable Unit National Agricultural Centre</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C36">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kirby</surname>
              <given-names>EJM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Co-ordination of leaf emergence and leaf and spikelet primordium initiation in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Field Crops Research</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>253</fpage>
          <lpage>264</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C37">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kosova</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vitamvas</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasil</surname>
              <given-names>IT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Expression of dehydrins in wheat and barley under different temperatures</article-title>
          <source>Plant Science</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>180</volume>
          <fpage>46</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21421346</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C38">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>YP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Babakov</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Boer</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zuther</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hincha</surname>
              <given-names>DK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparison of freezing tolerance, compatible solutes and polyamines in geographically diverse collections of <italic>Thellungiella sp.</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> accessions</article-title>
          <source>BMC Plant Biology</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>131</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22863402</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C39">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Levitt</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Responses of plants to environmental stresses: chilling, freezing and high temperature stresses.</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C40">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rudi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stockinger</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparative analyses reveal potential uses of Brachypodium distachyon as a model for cold stress responses in temperate grasses</article-title>
          <source>BMC Plant Biology</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <comment>65</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C41">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Limin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Danyluk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chauvin</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fowler</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarhan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chromosome mapping of low-temperature induced <italic>Wcs120</italic> family genes and regulation of cold-tolerance expression in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Molecular and General Genetics</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>253</volume>
          <fpage>720</fpage>
          <lpage>727</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9079883</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C42">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Limin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corey</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayes</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fowler</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Low-temperature acclimation of barley cultivars used as parents in mapping populations: response to photoperiod, vernalization and phenological development</article-title>
          <source>Planta</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>226</volume>
          <fpage>139</fpage>
          <lpage>146</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17245568</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C43">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Livingston</surname>
              <given-names>DP</given-names>
              <suffix>3rd</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hincha</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heyer</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fructan and its relationship to abiotic stress tolerance in plants</article-title>
          <source>Cell and Molecular Life Sciences</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>2007</fpage>
          <lpage>2023</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C44">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Natural variation of drought response in <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic></article-title>
          <source>Physiologia Plantarum</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>141</volume>
          <fpage>19</fpage>
          <lpage>29</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20875057</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C45">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahfoozi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Limin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fowler</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Developmental regulation of low-temperature tolerance in winter wheat</article-title>
          <source>Annals of Botany</source>
          <year>2001a</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>751</fpage>
          <lpage>757</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C46">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahfoozi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Limin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fowler</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Influence of vernalization and photoperiod responses on cold hardiness in winter cereals</article-title>
          <source>Crop Science</source>
          <year>2001b</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>1006</fpage>
          <lpage>1011</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C47">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McNeil</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nuccio</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanson</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Betaines and related osmoprotectants. Targets for metabolic engineering of stress resistance</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <fpage>945</fpage>
          <lpage>949</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10444077</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C48">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>NDong</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Danyluk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pocock</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huner</surname>
              <given-names>NPA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarhan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cold-regulated cereal chloroplast late embryogenesis abundant-like proteins: molecular characterization and functional analyses</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>129</volume>
          <fpage>1368</fpage>
          <lpage>1381</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12114590</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C49">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Olien</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clark</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Changes in soluble carbohydrate composition of barley, wheat, and rye during winter</article-title>
          <source>Agronomy Journal</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <fpage>21</fpage>
          <lpage>21</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C50">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Opanowicz</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vain</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Draper</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parker</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doonan</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>: making hay with a wild grass</article-title>
          <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>172</fpage>
          <lpage>177</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18343709</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C51">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peraldi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beccari</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steed</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicholson</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>: a new pathosystem to study Fusarium head blight and other <italic>Fusarium</italic> diseases of wheat</article-title>
          <source>BMC Plant Biology</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <comment>100</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C52">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pidal</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fu</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tranquilli</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The CArG-box located upstream from the transcriptional start of wheat vernalization gene <italic>VRN1</italic> is not necessary for the vernalization response</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Heredity</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <comment>355</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C53">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schwartz</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doyle</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manzaneda</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rey</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitchell-Olds</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amasino</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Natural variation of flowering time and vernalization responsiveness in <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic></article-title>
          <source>BioEnergy Research</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>38</fpage>
          <lpage>46</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C54">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stockinger</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilmour</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomashow</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana CBF1</italic> encodes an AP2 domain-containing transcriptional activator that binds to the C-repeat/DRE, a cis-acting DNA regulatory element that stimulates transcription in response to low temperature and water deficit</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>1035</fpage>
          <lpage>1040</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C55">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Suzuki</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nass</surname>
              <given-names>HG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fructan in winter wheat, triticale and fall rye cultivars of varying cold hardiness</article-title>
          <source>Canadian Journal of Botany</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>1723</fpage>
          <lpage>1728</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C56">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Theissen</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saedler</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Classification and phylogeny of the MADS-box multigene family suggest defined roles of MADS-box gene subfamilies in the morphological evolution of eukaryotes</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Molecular Evolution</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>484</fpage>
          <lpage>516</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8875863</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C57">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thomashow</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Plant cold acclimation: freezing tolerance genes and regulatory mechanisms</article-title>
          <source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology and Plant Molecular Biology</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>571</fpage>
          <lpage>599</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C58">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thomashow</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>So what's new in the field of plant cold acclimation? Lots!</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiology</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>125</volume>
          <fpage>89</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11154304</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C59">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tremblay</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ouellet</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fournier</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Danyluk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarhan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular characterization and origin of novel bipartite cold-regulated ice recrystallization inhibition proteins from cereals</article-title>
          <source>Plant and Cell Physiology</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>884</fpage>
          <lpage>891</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15792959</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C60">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>V&#xE1;g&#xFA;jfalvi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kerepesi</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galiba</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tischner</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sutka</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Frost hardiness depending on carbohydrate changes during cold acclimation in wheat</article-title>
          <source>Plant Science</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>144</volume>
          <fpage>85</fpage>
          <lpage>92</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C61">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vain</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Worland</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thole</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of the temperate grass <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> (genotype Bd21) for T-DNA insertional mutagenesis</article-title>
          <source>Plant Biotechnology Journal</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>236</fpage>
          <lpage>245</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18004984</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C62">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Van Buskirk</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomashow</surname>
              <given-names>MF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> transcription factors regulating cold acclimation</article-title>
          <source>Physiologia Plantarum</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>126</volume>
          <fpage>72</fpage>
          <lpage>80</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C63">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vogel</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zarka</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Buskirk</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fowler</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomashow</surname>
              <given-names>MF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Roles of the CBF2 and ZAT12 transcription factors in configuring the low temperature transcriptome of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>
          <source>The Plant Journal</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>195</fpage>
          <lpage>211</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15634197</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C64">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vogel</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bragg</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Feuillet</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muehlbauer</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>, a new model for the Triticeae</article-title>
          <source>Genetics and genomics of the Triticeae (Plant genetics and genomics: crops and models).</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
          <fpage>427</fpage>
          <lpage>449</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C65">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vogel</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garvin</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mockler</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genome sequencing and analysis of the model grass <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic></article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>463</volume>
          <fpage>763</fpage>
          <lpage>768</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20148030</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C66">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ritchie</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fischer</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schulthess</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Vernalization in wheat I. A model based on the interchangeability of plant age and vernalization duration</article-title>
          <source>Field Crops Research</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <lpage>100</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C67">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loukoianov</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tranquilli</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Helguera</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fahima</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Positional cloning of the wheat vernalization gene <italic>VRN1</italic></article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <comment>6263</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C68">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yoshida</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abe</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moriyama</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuwabara</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Carbohydrate levels among winter wheat cultivars varying in freezing tolerance and snow mold resistance during autumn and winter</article-title>
          <source>Physiologia Plantarum</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>8</fpage>
          <lpage>16</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C69">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fernald</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comprehensive algorithm for quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Computational Biology</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>1047</fpage>
          <lpage>1064</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16241897</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="MCT283C70">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>von Zitzewitz</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szucs</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubcovsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular and structural characterization of barley vernalization genes</article-title>
          <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>449</fpage>
          <lpage>467</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16235110</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
