<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3983115</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-02315</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094359</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Agriculture</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Crops</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genetics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Gene Expression</subject>
              <subject>Gene Function</subject>
              <subject>Mutation</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Microbiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Medical Microbiology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Microbial Pathogens</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Mycology</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>MYT3, A Myb-Like Transcription Factor, Affects Fungal Development and Pathogenicity of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Functional Studies of MYT3 in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Yongsoo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Hun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Son</surname>
            <given-names>Hokyoung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>Gyung Ja</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Jin-Cheol</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Yin-Won</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Agricultural Biotechnology and Center for Fungal Pathogenesis, Seoul National University, Seoul, Republic of Korea</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Eco-friendly New Materials Research Group, Research Center for Biobased Chemistry, Division of Convergence Chemistry, Korea Research Institute of Chemical Technology, Daejeon, Republic of Korea</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>Jae-Hyuk</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>University of Wisconsin &#x2013; Madison, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>lee2443@snu.ac.kr</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: YK HK HS YWL. Performed the experiments: YK HK HS GJC JCK YWL. Analyzed the data: YK HK HS GJC JCK YWL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: GJC JCK YWL. Wrote the paper: YK HK HS YWL.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <elocation-id>e94359</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Kim et al</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We previously characterized members of the Myb protein family, MYT1 and MYT2, in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>. MYT1 and MYT2 are involved in female fertility and perithecium size, respectively. To expand knowledge of Myb proteins in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, in this study, we characterized the functions of the <italic>MYT3</italic> gene, which encodes a putative Myb-like transcription factor containing two Myb DNA-binding domains and is conserved in the subphylum Pezizomycotina of Ascomycota. MYT3 proteins were localized in nuclei during most developmental stages, suggesting the role of MYT3 as a transcriptional regulator. Deletion of <italic>MYT3</italic> resulted in impairment of conidiation, germination, and vegetative growth compared to the wild type, whereas complementation of <italic>MYT3</italic> restored the wild-type phenotype. Additionally, the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain grew poorly on nitrogen-limited media; however, the mutant grew robustly on minimal media supplemented with ammonium. Moreover, expression level of nitrate reductase gene in the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain was decreased in comparison to the wild type and complemented strain. On flowering wheat heads, the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain exhibited reduced pathogenicity, which corresponded with significant reductions in trichothecene production and transcript levels of trichothecene biosynthetic genes. When the mutant was selfed, mated as a female, or mated as a male for sexual development, perithecia were not observed on the cultures, indicating that the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain lost both male and female fertility. Taken together, these results demonstrate that MYT3 is required for pathogenesis and sexual development in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, and will provide a robust foundation to establish the regulatory networks for all Myb-like proteins in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This research was supported by the Basic Science Research Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by Ministry of Science, ICT &amp; Future Planning (No. 2008-0061897). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The homothallic ascomycete fungus <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> is a prominent plant pathogen that causes Fusarium head blight (FHB) on cereal crops and ear rot on maize <xref rid="pone.0094359-Goswami1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Guenther1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, resulting in a severe reduction of crop yield and production of mycotoxins (e.g., trichothecenes and zearalenone) that are dangerous to animals and humans <xref rid="pone.0094359-Desjardins1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. In particular, sexual spores (ascospores) of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> are believed to be the primary inocula for FHB epidemics in cereal crops <xref rid="pone.0094359-Sutton1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. The spores overwinter within a fruiting body (perithecium) on plant debris, and are forcibly discharged into the air under milder temperatures and moderate moisture <xref rid="pone.0094359-Sutton1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Paulitz1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. To date, several genes related to sexual development have been studied in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, and those genes are known to be closely related to disease development <xref rid="pone.0094359-Hou1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Shim1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Urban1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Yu1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> genome, 19 transcription factors encoding Myb-like proteins were identified at a previous work <xref rid="pone.0094359-Son1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Of these Myb-like proteins, we found that MYT1 and MYT2 transcription factors are involved in female fertility and perithecium size, respectively <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lin2" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Furthermore, several deletion mutants of putative Myb transcription factors, including FGSG_01915, FGSG_02719, and FGSG_12781, in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> exhibited abnormality in sexual development <xref rid="pone.0094359-Son1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. These data suggest that the Myb transcription factors are required for normal sexual development of <italic>F. graminearum</italic>.</p>
      <p>Transcription factors that contain the Myb DNA-binding domain are involved in various cellular processes in eukaryotes, including cell proliferation, apoptosis, differentiation, metabolism, and stress responses <xref rid="pone.0094359-Dubos1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Oh1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Ramsay1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Ravaglia1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. The v-Myb DNA-binding domain was originally identified from avian myeloblastosis virus (AMV) as a truncated version of a cellular progenitor c-Myb that contains three Myb DNA-binding domains, which are referred to as R1, R2, and R3 <xref rid="pone.0094359-Beug1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Gonda1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. The Myb DNA-binding domains identified from vertebrates, plants, and oomycetes are relatively conserved between species, and most Myb proteins contain one to three variants of the Myb DNA-binding domain, such as R1, R2R3, and R1R2R3 <xref rid="pone.0094359-Dubos1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lipsick1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Xiang1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Each Myb DNA-binding domain spans approximately 52 amino acids arranged as tandem repeats of a helix-turn-helix motif <xref rid="pone.0094359-Anton1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Ogata1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. This repeat region is involved in DNA-binding, and the specificity of DNA binding is known to be dependent on the third &#x3B1;-helices of R2 and R3 <xref rid="pone.0094359-Howe1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Currently, a few Myb-like proteins have been identified and characterized in fungal species. Ag<italic>BAS1,</italic> a homolog of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae BAS1</italic>, was identified in <italic>Ashbya gossypii</italic>, and the deletion mutant of Ag<italic>BAS1</italic> exhibited auxotrophy for adenine and a delay in spore germination <xref rid="pone.0094359-Mateos1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Furthermore, AgBAS1 controls the adenine-mediated regulation of the purine biosynthetic pathway by regulating the gene expression of <italic>ADE4</italic> by binding to the <italic>ADE4</italic> promoter <xref rid="pone.0094359-Mateos1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. In <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic>, a Myb transcription factor, FlbD, controls asexual and sexual differentiation <xref rid="pone.0094359-ArratiaQuijada1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Wieser1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. The <italic>flbD</italic> mutants were unable to develop the cleistothecial peridium, a specialized external tissue that differentiates during fruiting body formation, and exhibited severely defective conidiation. In addition, a Myb-like protein <italic>PsMYB1</italic> of <italic>Phytophthora sojae,</italic> which causes soybean root rot, was identified by differential expression between wild type and MAP kinase mutants, and the <italic>PsMYB1</italic> is known to be involved in zoospore-mediated pathogenicity <xref rid="pone.0094359-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In the present report, as a series of MYT1 and MYT2, we aimed to expand the current knowledge of how Myb transcription factors regulate sexual development of <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, with an emphasis on the characterization of the gene involved in the formation of perithecia and ascospores. To this end, we chose to investigate <italic>MYT3,</italic> which encodes a putative Myb-like transcription factor, and further characterized its biological function by molecular approaches. Our results demonstrate that <italic>MYT3</italic> is required for conidiation, vegetative growth, sexual development, and pathogenicity.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Fungal strains and media</title>
        <p>All strains used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0094359-t001">Table 1</xref>. The wild-type strain Z-3639 and mutants derived from the wild-type strain were maintained on complete media (CM) <xref rid="pone.0094359-Leslie1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, and stored in 20% glycerol at &#x2212;80&#xB0;C. The growth rates of the wild type and transgenic strains were measured in CM and minimal media (MM; 3 g KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.5 g MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.5 g KCl, 30 g sucrose, and 20 g agar per liter). To observe responses to nitrogen sources, the MM was modified by addition of 2 g NaNO<sub>3</sub> or 2 g (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> per liter. Conidia production was induced in carboxymethyl cellulose (CMC) medium <xref rid="pone.0094359-Cappellini1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. Minimal liquid medium supplemented with 5 mM agmatine (MMA) was used for trichothecene analysis <xref rid="pone.0094359-Gardiner1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0094359-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094359.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> strains used in this study.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0094359-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0094359.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source or reference</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z-3639</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wild type</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>myt3</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>::<italic>GEN</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HK33</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>acl2</italic>::<italic>GEN</italic>; <italic>HYG</italic>-<italic>P<sub>ZEAR</sub></italic>::ACS2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mat1r</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>mat1-1</italic>::<italic>GEN</italic>; <italic>hH1</italic>::<italic>RFP-GEN</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>mat2</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>mat1-2</italic>::<italic>GFP-HPH</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>::<italic>MYT3-HYG</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In this study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MYT3</italic>-oe</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P<sub>EF1&#x3B1;</sub></italic>::<italic>MYT3-GEN</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In this study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MYT3</italic>-gfp</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MYT3</italic>::<italic>GFP-HPH</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In this study</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MYT3</italic>-gr</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MYT3</italic>::<italic>GFP-HPH</italic>; <italic>hH1</italic>::<italic>RFP-GEN</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In this study</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Nucleic acid manipulations and protein sequence analysis</title>
        <p>Fungal strains grown in CM broth for 5 days at 25&#xB0;C were harvested and lyophilized. The procedures for isolation of genomic DNA were performed as described <xref rid="pone.0094359-Leslie1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Standard methods were followed for restriction endonuclease digestion, agarose gel electrophoresis, and Southern blotting <xref rid="pone.0094359-Sambrook1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. To measure expression level of transcripts, total RNA was extracted by using the Easy-Spin Total RNA Extraction Kit (iNtRON Biotechnology, Seongnam, Korea), and the first strand of cDNA was synthesized from the RNA by SuperScriptIII reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). PCR primers were obtained from Bionics (Seoul, Korea), listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0094359.s004">Table S1</xref>. Protein sequence alignment was performed by Clustal Omega <xref rid="pone.0094359-Sievers1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, and drawn by BOXSHADE 3.31 available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ch.embnet.org/software/BOX_form.html">http://www.ch.embnet.org/software/BOX_form.html</ext-link>. InterPro (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/</ext-link>) and Fungal Transcription Factor Database (FTFD; ftfd.snu.ac.kr) were used to search for the Myb DNA-binding domains. Automated mode of SWISS-MODEL <xref rid="pone.0094359-Arnold1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> and YASPIN <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lin3" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref> were used for the structural analysis of Myb-like DNA binding domains. Nuclear localization sequences (NLSs) were identified by cNLS Mapper <xref rid="pone.0094359-Kosugi1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Complementation and overexpression of <italic>MYT3</italic></title>
        <p>For the complementation of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain, intact copies of <italic>MYT3</italic> (FGSG_00324; <italic>Fusarium</italic> Comparative Sequencing Project at the Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org">http://www.broadinstitute.org</ext-link>) were amplified from <italic>F. graminearum</italic> wild-type Z-3639 with primer pair MYT3-5N/MYT3-3N. The selection marker, hygromycin phosphotransferase (<italic>HPH</italic>), was amplified from the HK33 strain with primer pair HPH-F/HPH-R <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lee2" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. These two fragments were co-transformed into the protoplast of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain. For fungal transformations, the methods for the preparation of protoplasts and regeneration of transformants were performed as described previously <xref rid="pone.0094359-Kim1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. Transformants were confirmed by Southern blot analysis. To generate the <italic>MYT3</italic> overexpression strains, the 5&#x2032; flanking region and ORF region of <italic>MYT3</italic> were amplified with primer pairs UP-5F/5R-GEN and MYT3-F/MYT3-R, respectively. A PCR fragment with the geneticin resistant gene (<italic>GEN</italic>) and the elongation factor 1&#x3B1; promoter (<italic>P<sub>EF1&#x3B1;</sub></italic>) was amplified from pSKGEN <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lee2" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref> using primer pair Neo-F/EF-R. These three amplicons were combined as previously described <xref rid="pone.0094359-Yu2" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. The resulting product was amplified with nested primers MYT3-5N and MYT3-RN to create a 4.3-kb product containing <italic>GEN</italic> and <italic>P<sub>EF1&#x3B1;</sub></italic> fused to the <italic>MYT3</italic> ORF. The final construct was transformed into the wild-type strain.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Cellular localization of MYT3</title>
        <p>To investigate cellular localization of MYT3, we generated a strain carrying green fluorescent protein (GFP) fused to C-terminus of MYT3. A PCR fragment including <italic>GFP</italic> and <italic>HPH</italic> was amplified from the pIGPAPA plasmid <xref rid="pone.0094359-Horwitz1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref> with primers GFP-F and HYG-F1. The 5&#x2032; flanking region, which is the <italic>MYT3</italic> C-terminus without its own terminator sequence, was amplified from the wild-type strain with primers MYT3-5F and MYT3-5R. The 3&#x2032; flanking region of <italic>MYT3</italic> was amplified by primers MYT3-3F and MYT3-3R. These three resulting PCR products were fused as described <xref rid="pone.0094359-Yu2" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. The resulting PCR product was used as a template with primers MYT3-gfpF and MYT3-gfpR for a final construct. Subsequently, the final PCR products were transformed into the wild-type strain.</p>
        <p>To observe co-localization of MYT3 with a nuclear protein, a resulting <italic>MYT3</italic>-gfp transformant was outcrossed with a mat1r strain that contains red fluorescent protein (RFP) fused to histone H1 as generated previously <xref rid="pone.0094359-Son2" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. Strains containing both <italic>MYT3</italic>::<italic>GFP</italic> and <italic>hH1</italic>::<italic>RFP</italic> were selected by antibiotic resistance and confirmed by PCR. Microscopic observation was performed by a DE/Axio Imager A1 microscope (Carl Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany) with the filter set 38HE (excitation 470/40; emission 525/50) for GFP and the filter set 15 (excitation 546/12; emission 590) for RFP.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Western blot analysis</title>
        <p>Mycelia and perithecia were harvested from carrot agar cultures, and ground by liquid nitrogen. The ground tissues (approximately 100 to 150 mg) were used for the extraction of total protein with 300 &#x3BC;l of extraction buffer [50 mM Tris-Cl, pH 8.4; 192 mM glycine; 0.1% sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS); 1 mM protease inhibitor phenylmethanesulfonylfluoride]. After centrifugation at 16000 g for 10 min, supernatant was used for the protein analysis. The samples containing 1.5 to 2.0 &#x3BC;g of total protein were separated on 5% sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gels. Preparing gels and electrophoresis were performed as previously described <xref rid="pone.0094359-Laemmli1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. Western blot analysis was performed using chemiluminescence (GE Healthcare, Little Chalfont, UK) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Primary anti-GFP (Abcam, Cambridge, UK) and anti-rabbit secondary antibody conjugated to horseradish peroxidase (GE Healthcare) were used at 1 4000 and 1 5000 dilution, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Conidiation, germination, and pathogenicity assay</title>
        <p>To measure conidiation, the same sized agar blocks of the wild type, &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>, &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com, and <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe strains grown on CM were used to inoculate 5 ml of CMC liquid medium. The conidia were counted after 5 days of incubation. To measure germination rate, conidial suspensions (10<sup>6</sup>/ml) of each strain were inoculated into 20 ml of CM and MM including NaNO<sub>3</sub>. The germinated conidia per 100 conidia were counted 0, 2, 4, 8, and 16 h after inoculation. For the pathogenicity assay, 10 &#x3BC;l of conidial suspension (10<sup>6</sup>/ml) obtained from each strain were point-inoculated into a spikelet of the wheat head at early anthesis. Infected plants were incubated in a humidity chamber for 3 days, and subsequently transferred to a green house. After 2 weeks, spikelets showing disease symptoms were counted.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Quantitative real-time (qRT)-PCR of gene expression</title>
        <p>The qRT-PCR was performed using SYBR Green Supermix (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA) and a 7500 real-time PCR system (Applied Biosystems, Foster city, CA, USA). Each reaction contained 10 &#x3BC;l of SYBR green Supermix, 500 nM of forward and reverse primers, cDNA template, and nuclease-free water to a final volume of 20 &#x3BC;l. PCR cycling conditions were 2 min at 50&#xB0;C (one cycle); 10 min at 95 &#xB0;C (one cycle); and 15 s at 95&#xB0;C followed by 1 min at 60&#xB0;C (40 cycles). Experiments were repeated two times with three replicates. Expression levels were calculated using the comparative Ct method (Applied Biosystems). <italic>CYP1</italic> gene (FGSG_07439) served as the endogenous reference for normalization.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Trichothecene analysis</title>
        <p>To analyze total trichothecene production, conidial suspensions (10<sup>4</sup>/ml) of each strain were inoculated in MMA, and the cultures were incubated for 7 days at 25&#xB0;C. The culture media was filtered with Miracloth. Trichothecenes were extracted from 150 &#x3BC;l of culture filtrates by mixing with 250 &#x3BC;l of ethyl acetate/methanol solution (4 1, v/v) <xref rid="pone.0094359-He1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Extracts were dried and derivatized with Sylon BTZ (BSA + TMCS + TMS1, 3 2 3; Supelco, Bellefonte, PA, USA). Sequentially, 200 &#x3BC;l of <italic>n</italic>-hexane and 200 &#x3BC;l of distilled water were added to the reaction products. This reaction was left standing until two layers separated. Trichothecenes in the upper layer were analyzed with a Shimadzu QP-5000 gas chromatograph-mass spectrometer (GC-MS; Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan) <xref rid="pone.0094359-Seo1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. The total trichothecene concentration was quantified based on the biomass of each strain in MMA.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2i">
        <title>Sexual crosses</title>
        <p>From strains grown on carrot agar media <xref rid="pone.0094359-Leslie1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref> for 5 days, aerial mycelia were removed with 700 &#x3BC;l of 2.5% Tween 60 solution to induce fertilization. The plates were incubated under a near-UV light for 7 to 10 days. For outcrosses, mycelia of a female strain grown on carrot agar media were fertilized with 1 ml of conidial suspension (10<sup>6</sup>/ml) obtained from male strain, which was induced in CMC. The heterothallic &#x394;<italic>mat2</italic> mutant, a deletion strain of <italic>MAT1-2</italic>, was used as a tester mutant for outcrosses <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lee3" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. Perithecia and ascospores were observed 9 days after sexual crosses.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Identification of Myb-like transcription factor MYT3</title>
        <p><italic>MYT3</italic> has an open reading frame (ORF) of 7,340 base pairs (bp) with three introns, and is predicted to encode a 2,304-amino acid protein that contains two Myb-like DNA-binding domains (residues 1,263 to 1,314 and 1,534 to 1,586; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). BLAST and phylogenetic analysis of homologous proteins in other fungi demonstrated that MYT3 is more highly conserved within species of the subphylum Pezizomycotina of the Ascomycota than in the phyla Oomycota, Basidiomycota and the subphylum Saccharomycotina (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0094359.s001">Figure S1A</xref>). Additionally, the Myb-like DNA binding domains of MYT3 showed high sequence similarities to <italic>F. oxysporum</italic> (FOXG_00743, 93%), <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> (MGG_14558, 74%), <italic>Neurospora crassa</italic> (NCU_10346, 69%), and <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> (BC1G_02829, 54%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g001">Figure 1A and S</xref>1B) although the other regions of MYT3 homolog proteins were variable. Currently, none of the MYT3 homologs has been functionally characterized. Each Myb-like DNA binding domain of MYT3 consists of 52 amino acids, forming a helix-turn-helix structure with hydrophobic residues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g001">Figure 1A and B</xref>). The third helix of the second domain contains residues (KN) that are implicated to be in direct contact with DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g001">Figure 1A</xref>) <xref rid="pone.0094359-Garzia1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, suggesting that MYT3 possibly functions in transcriptional regulation.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0094359-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094359.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Alignment of Myb-like DNA-binding domains of MYT3 homologs.</title>
            <p>(A) MYT3 homologs in <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> (FOXG_00743), <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> (MGG_14558), <italic>Neurospora crassa</italic> (NCU_10346), <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> (BC1G_02829) were used for this analysis. Each Myb domain contains three helices, indicated with an underline, and residues that form their hydrophobic cores, indicated by black dots above the residue. The second domain contains residues that are implicated to have direct contact with the DNA, indicated by asterisks <xref rid="pone.0094359-Xiang1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Garzia1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. (B) Ribbon diagram of Myb-like DNA binding domains in MYT3.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0094359.g001"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>MYT3 is consistently expressed in nuclei</title>
        <p>In addition to the Myb DNA-binding domains, we identified several nuclear localization sequences (NLSs) in MYT3, including mono- and bi-partite sequences (data not shown). Therefore, we next investigated whether MYT3 localizes in the nucleus. To do this, we generated a strain that has GFP fused to C-terminus of MYT3 in the wild-type strain, named by <italic>MYT3</italic>-gfp (). Thirteen transformants containing single <italic>MYT3</italic>::<italic>GFP</italic> copy were obtained, and nuclear GFP signals were observed in these strains. For further confirmation of nuclear localization of MYT3, the <italic>MYT3</italic>-gfp strain was outcrossed with a mat1r strain that contains RFP fused to histone H1 protein in <italic>MAT1-1</italic> deletion background, with expectation to observe co-localization of MYT3::GFP and hH1::RFP in nuclei. From perithecia by this outcrossing, we isolated 20 progeny resistant to both hygromycin and geneticin, and observed that all progeny expressed GFP and RFP in nucleus of the most developmental stages such as hyphae, conidia, and ascospores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g002">Figure 2</xref>), indicating that MYT3 is continuously expressed in nuclei.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0094359-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094359.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Nuclear localization of MYT3.</title>
            <p>Representative examples show co-localization of MYT3 fused with green fluorescent protein (GFP) and histone H1 fused with red fluorescent protein (RFP). A strain containing MYT3::GFP and hH1::RFP was grown on CM (hypha), YMA (conidia), and carrot agar media (ascospores) for the microscopic observation, respectively. DIC, differential interference contrast; scale bar&#x200A;=&#x200A;20 &#x3BC;m.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0094359.g002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Genetic complementation and expression of <italic>MYT3</italic></title>
        <p>To confirm the roles of <italic>MYT3</italic>, we generated a complementation strain, &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com, by co-transforming the <italic>MYT3</italic> gene and hygromycin resistance gene into the protoplast of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0094359.s003">Figure S3A</xref>). Southern blot analysis indicated that the resulting mutant, designated strain &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com, obtains a 2.3-kb band of hybridization present in the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0094359.s003">Figure S3A</xref>). To further dissect the molecular mechanism of the function of <italic>MYT3</italic>, overexpression of <italic>MYT3</italic> was achieved with a construct containing the <italic>EF1&#x3B1;</italic> promoter fused to the <italic>MYT3</italic> ORF (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0094359.s003">Figure S3B</xref>). Strain <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe, obtained by insertion of the constitutive expression construct into the wild type, was confirmed by Southern blot analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0094359.s003">Figure S3B</xref>), and the expression level of <italic>MYT3</italic> in the <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe strain was measured by qRT-PCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g003">Figure 3A</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0094359-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094359.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Transcriptional/translational expression of <italic>MYT3</italic>.</title>
            <p>(A) Transcript levels of <italic>MYT3</italic> in each strain were analyzed by qRT-PCR. Total RNA of each strain was extracted from vegetative cultures grown on carrot agar media, and from sexual cultures 3, 5, and 7 days after induction of sexual development. WT, wild-type strain Z-3639; &#x394;<italic>myt3, MYT3</italic> deletion mutant; <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe, over expression strain where <italic>MYT3</italic> expression is driven by the <italic>EF1&#x3B1;</italic> promoter. d, day; n.d., not detected. (B) Western blot analysis of <italic>MYT3</italic>-gfp stain. Lane 1, whole cell extracts were prepared from vegetative cultures grown on carrot agar media for 5 days; Lane 2&#x2013;4, whole cell extracts were from sexual cultures 3, 5, and 7 days after induction of sexual development, respectively. Top, western blotting data; bottom, coomassie blue staining used as a loading control.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0094359.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Expression of <italic>MYT3</italic> in the <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe strain was consistent at all stages of development, with approximately two- to three-fold higher expression than that of the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). The expression level of <italic>MYT3</italic> in the wild-type strain was slightly increased at 3 days after sexual induction, and decreased over time to the similar level of expression in vegetative growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). At translational level, the expected 283-kDa protein (MYT3::GFP) in a <italic>MYT3</italic>-gfp strain was detected by anti-GFP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). However, expression of MYT3 was high during sexual development with the highest level at 7 days after sexual induction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that <italic>MYT3</italic> play an important role during sexual development.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Deletion of <italic>MYT3</italic> affects fungal development in response to nitrogen</title>
        <p>The deletion mutant of <italic>MYT3</italic> exhibited a growth defect on CM in comparison to the wild type, &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com, and <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g004">Figure 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0094359-t002">Table 2</xref>). Also, the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain poorly grew on MM lacking nitrogen in comparison to the growth on CM (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0094359-t002">Table 2</xref>). With these observations, increasing expression of ESTs, corresponding to FGSG_00324 (<italic>MYT3</italic>), in nitrogen starvation condition (MIPS, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plexdb.org/">http://www.plexdb.org/</ext-link>) <xref rid="pone.0094359-Gldener1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref> gave rise to a question whether nutrient such as nitrogen sources affects fungal growth of &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain. On MM containing nitrate, the mutant grew poorly compared to the wild type, whereas fungal growth of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com and <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe strains was similar to that of the wild type (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0094359-t002">Table 2</xref>). When MM was supplemented with ammonium instead of nitrate as a nitrogen source, the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain grew better than the wild type, &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com, and <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). Additionally, expression level of nitrate reductase gene (FGSG_01947) homologous to <italic>niaD</italic> of <italic>F. fujikuroi</italic><xref rid="pone.0094359-Tudzynski1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref> was significantly decreased in the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain grown in MM + nitrate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). Although the expression of this gene from the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain grown in MM + ammonium was slightly decreased in comparison to the wild type and &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com, the magnitude of the induction was comparably low in all strains grown MM + ammonium compared to the MM + nitrate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). Together, these results indicate that MYT3 is involved in nitrogen metabolic pathway by regulating the expression of nitrate reductase gene.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0094359-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094359.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Effects of nitrogen source on fungal growth and expression of nitrate reductase gene.</title>
            <p>(A) Vegetative growth of each strain on complete media (CM), minimal media (MM) containing nitrate, and MM containing ammonium. Photographs were taken after 5 days (CM, MM + nitrate) and 7 days (MM + ammonium) of incubation. WT, wild-type strain Z-3639; &#x394;<italic>myt3, MYT3</italic> deletion mutant; &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com, complemented strain of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>; <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe, overexpressed strain of <italic>MYT3</italic>. (B) To measure expression of nitrate reductase gene, all strains were grown in CM media for 48 h and then washed with water. The resulting mycelia were transferred into MM+ nitrate or MM + ammonium, and total RNA was extracted 3 h after resuspension.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0094359.g004"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0094359-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094359.t002</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Conidiation, growth, and virulence of <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> strains.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0094359-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0094359.t002"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Fungal growth</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conidiation (&#xD7;10<sup>5</sup> spores/ml)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CM</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MM</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MM (-N)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disease index<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wild type</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7&#xB1;2.2A<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">c</xref></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76&#xB1;0.5A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79&#xB1;1.7A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57&#xB1;2.1A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0&#xB1;2.2A</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>myt3</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#xB1;0.2B</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61&#xB1;2.4B</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44&#xB1;1.1B</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#xB1;3.1B</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3&#xB1;0.5B</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1&#xB1;1.3A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75&#xB1;1.3A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77&#xB1;1.4A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59&#xB1;2.3A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3&#xB1;2.1A</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MYT3</italic>-oe</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8&#xB1;2.2A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76&#xB1;0.6A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70&#xB1;1.7C</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58&#xB1;0.6A</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0&#xB1;4.5A</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>(-N) indicates lacking of nitrogen source in MM.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label>b</label>
              <p>Mean and standard deviation of diseased spikelets per wheat head.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label>c</label>
              <p>Values with different letters within a column indicate statistical difference (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) based on Tukey's test. All experiments were repeated three times with three replicates each.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>The &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain produced approximately 50-fold less conidia compared to the wild type 5 days after inoculation into CMC media, but there was no significant difference in conidiation among the wild type, &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com, and <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe strains (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0094359-t002">Table 2</xref>). In addition, the germination rate of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain on CM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g005">Figure 5A</xref>) and MM including nitrate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g005">Figure 5B</xref>) was markedly slower than that of other strains. Taken together, these results represent that deletion of <italic>MYT3</italic> contributes to the impairment of fungal development and growth.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0094359-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094359.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Germination rate of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> strains.</title>
            <p>(A) Numbers of germinated conidia in CM were counted 0, 4, and 8 h after inoculation. (B) Numbers of germinated conidia on MM containing nitrate were counted 0, 4, 8, 16 and 24 h after inoculation. Each experiment was performed in triplicate two independent times. WT, wild-type strain Z-3639; &#x394;<italic>myt3, MYT3</italic> deletion mutant; &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com, complemented strain of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>; <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe, overexpressed strain of <italic>MYT3</italic>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0094359.g005"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title><italic>MYT3</italic> is involved in pathogenicity during infection of wheat</title>
        <p>Our observations that the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain grows slowly on CM and MM (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0094359-t002">Table 2</xref>) led us to question whether the deletion of <italic>MYT3</italic> affects <italic>F. graminearum</italic> pathogenicity during wheat infection. To evaluate pathogenicity on flowering wheat heads, conidial suspensions of each strain were point-inoculated on a spikelet and incubated in a greenhouse. The wild-type strain induced normal head blight symptoms, which manifests as discoloration, at 14 days after inoculation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). In contrast, the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain was restricted to infection sites, which were unable to spread from the rachis to reach adjacent spikelets on the head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). Consequently, the average disease index of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain was approximately 10-fold lower than the wild-type level (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0094359-t002">Table 2</xref>). The infections by &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com and <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe strains displayed the similar levels of pathogenicity to the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g006">Figure 6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0094359-t002">Table 2</xref>). Thus, our results reveal that MYT3 plays an important role in the progression of head blight after initial colonization.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0094359-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094359.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Virulence assay and trichothecene analysis.</title>
            <p>(A) Flowering wheat head were inoculated with conidia of the wild-type (WT) Z-3639, &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> mutant, complemented strain &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com, and overexpressed strain <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe, respectively. Mock indicates a negative control inoculated with 0.01% Tween 20. Wheat heads were photographed 14 days after inoculation. (B) Analysis of total trichothecenes (deoxynivalenole and 15-acetyl-deoxynivalenol) was performed on each strain grown in minimal liquid medium supplemented with 5 mM agmatine (MMA). The measured amount of trichothecenes was normalized to the biomass of each strain. (C) Expression of <italic>TRI5</italic> and <italic>TRI6</italic> in the wild type, &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>, <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe strains. Transcript levels were analyzed by qRT-PCR from cultures grown in MMA for 4 days and presented as relative transcript level compared to a control gene, <italic>CYP1</italic>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0094359.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3f">
        <title><italic>MYT3</italic> has an effect on the biosynthesis of trichothecenes</title>
        <p>To determine whether <italic>MYT3</italic> affects trichothecene biosynthesis, we measured trichothecene production by the wild type, &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>, &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com, and <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe strains grown on MMA. After normalizing to the amount of fungal biomass, the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain produced approximately 10-fold less trichothecenes compared to the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g006">Figure 6B</xref>). Furthermore, the ability to produce trichothecenes was restored in the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g006">Figure 6B</xref>). To confirm this observation, we investigated the expression of the trichothecene synthesis genes <italic>TRI5</italic> (FGSG_03537) and <italic>TRI6</italic> (FGSG_03536), which encode a trichodiene synthase and a major transcriptional regulator for trichothecene production, respectively <xref rid="pone.0094359-Seong1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. In the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain, the expression levels of <italic>TRI5</italic> and <italic>TRI6</italic> were reduced more than six-fold (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g006">Figure 6C</xref>) compared to the wild type and <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe strains. Together, these results show that the reduction in trichothecene biosynthesis is attributable to disruption of <italic>MYT3</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3g">
        <title><italic>MYT3</italic> is dispensable for male/female fertility in outcrosses</title>
        <p>Self-fertility of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain was determined from the formation of perithecia and ascospores on carrot agar media. The wild-type strain began to produce protoperithecia 3 days after sexual induction. After an additional 3- or 4-day incubation, mature perithecia were formed; the perithecia contained asci, each with eight ascospores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g007">Figure 7A</xref>). In contrast, the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain only produced mycelia and/or conidia, and never produced fruiting bodies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g007">Figure 7A</xref>). The sexual defects in the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain were recovered in the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com strain.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0094359-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094359.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain exhibits a lack of sexual development.</title>
            <p>(A) Strains grown on carrot agar media were self-fertilized. Photos were taken 9 days after sexual induction. Dissecting the perithecia showed the asci and ascospores of each strain (inset boxes). WT, wild-type strain Z-3639; &#x394;<italic>myt3, MYT3</italic> deletion mutant; &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>-com, complemented strain of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic>; <italic>MYT3</italic>-oe, overexpressed strain of <italic>MYT3</italic>. Scale bar&#x200A;=&#x200A;500 &#x3BC;m. (B) Heterozygous outcrosses. The &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain, as either a female or male strain, was outcrossed with self-sterile &#x394;<italic>mat2</italic> strain. Photos were taken 9 days after outcrossing. Scale bar&#x200A;=&#x200A;500 &#x3BC;m.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0094359.g007"/>
        </fig>
        <p>When a conidial suspension of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain was spermatized to a self-sterile &#x394;<italic>mat2</italic> strain, a deletion mutant of <italic>MAT1-2</italic>, no perithecia were formed on the outcrossed cultures, indicating that the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain lost male fertility (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g007">Figure 7B</xref>). Furthermore, when the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain was used as a female strain in outcrossing with the &#x394;<italic>mat2</italic> strain, no perithecia were found on the carrot agar media (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0094359-g007">Figure 7B</xref>). Taken together, these results show that deletion of <italic>MYT3</italic> abolishes both male and female fertility.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Previously, we reported that the Myb-like proteins MYT1 and MYT2 play important roles in female fertility and perithecium size during the sexual development of <italic>F. graminearum</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0094359-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lin2" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Specifically, deleting <italic>MYT2</italic> enhanced vegetative growth and increased the number of ascospores <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lin2" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. In addition, we observed that MYT2 displays differential expression in germinated hyphae compared to ascospores and conidia <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lin2" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. These results suggest that <italic>MYT2</italic> suppresses cell proliferation in various developmental stages, as well as critical roles for Myb-like proteins. Except with <italic>MYT1</italic> and <italic>MYT2</italic>, the <italic>F. graminearum</italic> genome has several Myb-like proteins whose biological functions remain unclear. As a series of Myb-like proteins in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, we characterized the roles of <italic>MYT3</italic> in aspects of fungal development and pathogenicity.</p>
      <p>The Myb proteins belong to a large family of transcription factors that are essential for regulating genes for cellular processes. Extensive studies of Myb-like proteins in various eukaryotes have demonstrated that the roles of Myb proteins are functionally diverse. Myb proteins are involved in proliferation, differentiation, metabolic pathways, cell fate, and stress responses <xref rid="pone.0094359-Oh1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Ramsay1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Ravaglia1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. In this study, we found that MYT3 contains two Myb-like DNA binding domains, which are likely to build a helix-turn-helix structure with hydrophobic residues and conserved in the subphylum Pezizomycotina. However, due to the low sequence similarity with comparison of other Myb proteins identified previously, we cannot conclude whether MYT3 belongs to a certain subfamily of Myb proteins (e.g., R1, R2R3, or R1R2R3). Myb proteins have diverged substantially between organisms. For examples, 4R-Myb subfamily of Myb proteins was identified in plants, and consists of four repeats; one of the repeats contain R1/R2-like repeat <xref rid="pone.0094359-Dubos1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The oomycetes <italic>P. infestans</italic> has an atypical class of Myb proteins that contain multi-domains, and neither of the tandem Myb domains resembles the R2 or R3 region of c-Myb. Additionally, several proteins with novel combinations of Myb domains were observed in this organism <xref rid="pone.0094359-Xiang1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. The <italic>F. graminearum</italic> genome is different from other eukaryotes in the total number of Myb proteins. The <italic>F. graminearum</italic> genome was reported to contain 19 Myb-like proteins <xref rid="pone.0094359-Son1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, whereas <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Oryzae sativa</italic>, and <italic>P. sojae</italic> were predicted to express 198, 183, and 68 Myb-like proteins, respectively <xref rid="pone.0094359-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Yanhui1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. In addition, most Myb proteins of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> have either one or two Myb-like DNA binding domains without the presence of a signature sequence, such as SHAQKY (data not shown) <xref rid="pone.0094359-Ehrenkaufer1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>. Taken together, Myb-like proteins in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> seem to be highly divergent within this species.</p>
      <p>The regulatory functions of Myb proteins in response to nutritional stimuli, such as nitrogen and carbon, have been studied in other fungi. The deletion mutant of <italic>flbD</italic>, a Myb transcription factor, in <italic>A. nidulans</italic> showed an impaired ability to produce conidia under nitrogen starvation conditions <xref rid="pone.0094359-ArratiaQuijada1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. In <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic>, the Myb-type DNA binding protein Reb1 regulates the transcription of the <italic>ste9+</italic> gene by binding its promoter, which is involved in G1 cell cycle arrest and sexual differentiation in response to nitrogen starvation <xref rid="pone.0094359-RodrguezSnchez1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. Similar to the fungi, it was reported that CmMYB1, an R2R3-type MYB transcription factor, is responsible for the expression of nitrogen assimilation genes in a unicellular red alga <italic>Cyanidioschyzon merolae</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0094359-Imamura1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. <italic>CmMYB1</italic> expression was induced by nitrogen depletion, and the <italic>CmMYB1</italic> mutant showed decreased cell viability after exposure to nitrogen-depleted conditions compared to the parental strain <xref rid="pone.0094359-Imamura1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. CmMYB1 specifically occupies the promoters of nitrogen assimilation genes only under nitrogen-depleted conditions, indicating that CmMYB1 is a central nitrogen regulator in <italic>C. merolae</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0094359-Imamura1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Related with the regulation of nitrogen metabolism, the mechanism mediated by global regulators AreA/Nit2 has been extensively studied in filamentous fungi <xref rid="pone.0094359-Kudla1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Mihlan1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Todd1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. The transcriptional regulator AreA activates the expression of nitrogen assimilatory genes such as nitrate reductase gene by binding its promoter when favored nitrogen sources, such as glutamine and ammonium, are not available <xref rid="pone.0094359-Arst1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Marzluf1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>. In this study, with our observations that growth defect of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain on MM and MM containing nitrate as a nitrogen source, we measured that expression of <italic>FgniaD</italic>, which encodes a nitrate reductase, was decreased in the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain grown on MM + nitrate compared to the wild type. These observations gave rise to the hypothesis that MYT3 is involved in nitrogen assimilatory pathway. This hypothesis is supported by our observation that <italic>FgniaD</italic> has two putative Myb DNA-binding sequences at &#x2212;47 and &#x2212;227 bp upstream of the start codon, based on the binding sequences of 5&#x2032;-Y(T/C)AACK(G/T)G-3&#x2032; as previously described <xref rid="pone.0094359-Garzia1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. This binding motif was shown to be responding to the Lys1575 and Asn1576 residues in the second Myb-like domain of MYT3, which has been implicated to participate in direct contact with DNA <xref rid="pone.0094359-Garzia1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Tahirov1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>. However, further studies are needed to clarify whether Myb DNA-binding domains of MYT3 in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> bind to the <italic>FgniaD</italic> promoter.</p>
      <p>Considering that MYT3 is conserved in species of the subphylum Pezizomycotina of the Ascomycota, and that transcriptional/translational expression of <italic>MYT3</italic> is increased during sexual development, we hypothesized that MYT3 plays an important role in sexual development. Most <italic>F. graminearum</italic> deletion mutants that have a sexual development defect exhibit an impairment in female fertility, but retain male fertility; for example, <italic>ZIF1</italic> (b-ZIP transcription factor), <italic>FgVelB</italic> (velvet regulator), and <italic>FgflbA</italic> (regulator of G protein signaling) <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Park1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. A <italic>MYT1</italic> deletion mutant also resulted in a defect in female fertility, but retained male fertility <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Interestingly, the <italic>MYT3</italic> deletion mutant lost both female and male fertility, and a complemented strain recovered all of the defects. To dissect these observations, we investigated whether deletion of <italic>MYT3</italic> has an effect on vegetative compatibility. In this study, we generated <italic>nit1</italic> and <italic>nitM</italic> mutants derived from the wild type and &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strains (data not shown), respectively, and tested their ability to form heterokaryon by hyphal fusion from the pairing combinations (WT <italic>nitM</italic> &#xD7; &#x394;<italic>myt3 nit1</italic>, WT <italic>nit1</italic> &#xD7; &#x394;<italic>myt3 nitM</italic>, and &#x394;<italic>myt3 nit1</italic> &#xD7; &#x394;<italic>myt3 nitM</italic>). However, all combinations produced fungal colonies (data not shown), indicating that the <italic>nit</italic> strains used in this study were in same vegetative compatibility group, and deletion of <italic>MYT3</italic> did not cause vegetative incompatibility. Thus, these results suggest that <italic>MYT3</italic> is not involved in heterokaryon formation through hyphal fusion.</p>
      <p>We demonstrated that <italic>MYT3</italic> plays an important role in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> on wheat heads. As previously mentioned, <italic>PsMYB1</italic> is also involved in <italic>P. sojae</italic> pathogenesis of soybean, which silencing of <italic>PsMYB1</italic> resulted in the impairment of zoosporogenesis and zoospore development <xref rid="pone.0094359-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. In plants, several Myb transcription factors (e.g., <italic>AtMYB30</italic>, <italic>TaPIMP1</italic>, <italic>JAmyb</italic>, and <italic>BOS1</italic>) are involved in host resistance to pathogens and abiotic stress, which involves signaling pathways for plant defense molecules, such as jasmonate, salicylic acid, and abscisic acid <xref rid="pone.0094359-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Lee4" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Mengiste1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0094359-Vailleau1" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>. Our results also showed that the disease index of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain was approximately 10-fold less than the wild-type level, resulting from an inability of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain to spread from an inoculated spikelet to other spikelets. In addition, trichothecene production and <italic>TRI5</italic> and <italic>TRI6</italic> gene transcript levels were remarkably reduced in the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain. This finding may also contribute to the reduced progression of plant disease because trichothecenes are an important virulence factor in <italic>F. graminearum</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0094359-Proctor1" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>. Furthermore, we cannot exclude the possibility that MYT3 is required to respond to an environmental cue from the host that helps regulate pathogenesis: this possibility is supported by our observations of different growth pattern of the &#x394;<italic>myt3</italic> strain to specific nitrogen source. Thus, considering involvement of MYT3 in pathogenesis, identification of target genes regulated by MYT3 will contribute critical information to help understand regulatory mechanisms of <italic>F. graminearum</italic> pathogenesis.</p>
      <p>In summary, we examined the biological functions of MYT3, a Myb-like protein in <italic>F. graminearum</italic> that contains two Myb DNA-binding domains. Our results showed that MYT3 is localized in nuclei during developmental stages, affects various aspects of fungal development, such as conidiation, germination, and male/female fertility, and contributes to pathogenicity by either directly or indirectly influencing trichothecene biosynthesis. Our identification of these functions for <italic>MYT3</italic> sheds further light on the complex roles of Myb-like proteins in fungal development and pathogenicity of <italic>F. graminearum</italic>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0094359.s001">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Distribution and phylogenetic analysis of MYT3 homologs in fungi.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0094359.s001.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0094359.s002">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Strategy for fusion of </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>GFP</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> to </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>MYT3</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0094359.s002.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0094359.s003">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Strategies for complementation and overexpression of </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>MYT3</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0094359.s003.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0094359.s004">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Primers used in this study.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0094359.s004.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Goswami1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Heading for disaster: <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> on cereal crops</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Pathol</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>515</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20565626</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Guenther1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guenther</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trail</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The development and differentiation of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic> (anamorph: <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>) during colonization of wheat</article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source><volume>97</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16389974</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Desjardins1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Desjardins AE (2006) <italic>Fusarium</italic> mycotoxins chemistry, genetics, and biology. AE Desjardins, ed. editor. St. Paul, MN: APS Press. </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Sutton1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Epidemiology of wheat head blight and maize ear rot caused by <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Can J Plant Pathol</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>209</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Paulitz1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paulitz</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Diurnal release of ascospores by <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic> in inoculated wheat plots</article-title>. <source>Plant Dis</source><volume>80</volume>: <fpage>674</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>678</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Hou1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A mitogen-activated protein kinase gene (<italic>MGV1</italic>) in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> is required for female fertility, heterokaryon formation, and plant infection</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1119</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12423017</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Lee1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Myong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H-K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title><italic>FgVelB</italic> globally regulates sexual reproduction, mycotoxin production and pathogenicity in the cereal pathogen <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source><volume>158</volume>: <fpage>1723</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22516221</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Shim1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>W-B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sagaram</surname><given-names>US</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>So</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>FSR1 is essential for virulence and female fertility in <italic>Fusarium verticillioides</italic> and <italic>F. graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>725</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16838785</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Urban1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mott</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Farley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Fusarium graminearum MAP1</italic> gene is essential for pathogenicity and development of perithecia</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Pathol</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>347</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20569395</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Yu1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>J-A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>W-B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Functional analyses of heterotrimeric G protein G<italic>&#x3B1;</italic> and G<italic>&#x3B2;</italic> subunits in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source><volume>154</volume>: <fpage>392</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18227243</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Son1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A phenome-based functional analysis of transcription factors in the cereal head blight fungus, <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002310</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22028654</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Lin1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A putative transcription factor MYT1 is required for female fertility in the ascomycete <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e25586</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21984921</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Lin2">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A putative transcription factor MYT2 regulates perithecium size in the ascomycete <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e37859</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22649560</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Dubos1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dubos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stracke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grotewold</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weisshaar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>MYB transcription factors in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source><volume>15</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20674465</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Oh1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The <italic>myb</italic> gene family in cell growth, differentiation and apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source><volume>18</volume>: <fpage>3017</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10378697</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Ramsay1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonda</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>MYB function in normal and cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18574464</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Ravaglia1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ravaglia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Espley</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henry-Kirk</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andreotti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ziosi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional regulation of flavonoid biosynthesis in nectarine (<italic>Prunus persica</italic>) by a set of R2R3 MYB transcription factors</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source><volume>13</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23617716</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Beug1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beug</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Kirchbach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doderlein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Conscience</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Chicken hematopoietic cells transformed by seven strains of defective avian leukemia viruses display three distinct phenotypes of differentiation</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>18</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">227607</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Gonda1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gonda</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gough</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Blaquiere</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Nucleotide sequence of cDNA clones of the murine <italic>myb</italic> proto-oncogene</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>2003</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2998780</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Lipsick1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lipsick</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>One billion years of Myb</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source><volume>12</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8710361</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Xiang1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Judelson</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Myb transcription factors in the oomycete <italic>Phytophthora</italic> with novel diversified DNA-binding domains and developmental stage-specific expression</article-title>. <source>Gene</source><volume>453</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20060444</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Anton1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anton</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frampton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Tryptophans in <italic>myb</italic> proteins</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>336</volume>: <fpage>719</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3060725</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Ogata1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sekikawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Solution structure of a specific DNA complex of the Myb DNA-binding domain with cooperative recognition helices</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>79</volume>: <fpage>639</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7954830</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Howe1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reakes</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Characterization of the sequence-specific interaction of mouse c-<italic>myb</italic> protein with DNA</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source><volume>9</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2403925</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Mateos1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mateos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Revuelta</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Purine biosynthesis, riboflavin production, and trophic-phase span are controlled by a Myb-related transcription factor in the fungus <italic>Ashbya gossypii</italic></article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>72</volume>: <fpage>5052</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5060</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16820505</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-ArratiaQuijada1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arratia-Quijada</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>S&#xE1;nchez</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scazzocchio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>FlbD, a Myb transcription factor of <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic>, is uniquely involved in both asexual and sexual differentiation</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>132</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>142</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Wieser1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wieser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>FlbD encodes a Myb-like DNA-binding protein that coordinates initiation of <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic> conidiophore development</article-title>. <source>Gene Dev</source><volume>9</volume>: <fpage>491</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7883170</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Zhang1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A Myb transcription factor of <italic>Phytophthora sojae</italic>, regulated by MAP kinase PsSAK1, is required for zoospore development</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e40246</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22768262</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Leslie1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leslie JF, Summerell BA (2006) The <italic>Fusarium</italic> laboratory manual. Ames, IA: Blackwell Pub.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Cappellini1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cappellini</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>1965</year>) <article-title>Macroconidium formation in submerged cultures by a non-sporulating strain of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Mycologia</source><volume>57</volume>: <fpage>962</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>966</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Gardiner1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Nutrient profiling reveals potent inducers of trichothecene biosynthesis in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>46</volume>: <fpage>604</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19406250</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Sambrook1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sambrook J, Russell DW (2001) Molecular cloning: a laboratory manual, 2nd ed. Cold Spring Harbor, NY: Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Sievers1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dineen</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karplus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Fast, scalable generation of high-quality protein multiple sequence alignments using Clustal Omega</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>539</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21988835</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Arnold1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bordoli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schwede</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The SWISS-MODEL Workspace: A web-based environment for protein structure homology modelling</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>22</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16301204</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Lin3">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simossis</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heringa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A simple and fast secondary structure prediction algorithm using hidden neural networks</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>21</volume>: <fpage>152</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15377504</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Kosugi1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kosugi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hasebe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Systematic identification of yeast cell cycle-dependent nucleocytoplasmic shuttling proteins by prediction of composite motifs</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>106</volume>: <fpage>10171</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19520826</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Lee2">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Functional analyses of two acetyl coenzyme A synthetases in the ascomycete <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1043</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21666077</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Kim1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Putative polyketide synthase and laccase genes for biosynthesis of aurofusarin in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1701</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15811992</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Yu2">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamari</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>J-A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reyes-Dominguez</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Double-joint PCR: a PCR-based molecular tool for gene manipulations in filamentous fungi</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>973</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15465386</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Horwitz1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Horwitz</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ritter</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sandrock</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>A G protein alpha subunit from <italic>Cochliobolus heterostrophus</italic> involved in mating and appressorium formation</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>26</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10072317</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Son2">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y-W</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>ATP citrate lyase is required for normal sexual and asexual development in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>48</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21237280</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Laemmli1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Laemmli</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name> (<year>1970</year>) <article-title>Cleavage of structural proteins during the assembly of the head of bacteriophage T4</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>227</volume>: <fpage>680</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5432063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-He1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Purification of deoxynivalenol from <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> rice culture and mouldy corn by high-speed counter-current chromatography</article-title>. <source>J Chromatogr A</source><volume>1151</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17306807</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Seo1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>J-A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y-W</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Variation in 8-ketotrichothecenes and zearalenone production by <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> isolates from corn and barley in Korea</article-title>. <source>Mycopathologia</source><volume>134</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20882466</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Lee3">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y-W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turgeon</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Shifting fungal reproductive mode by manipulation of mating type genes: obligatory heterothallism of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>50</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14507370</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Garzia1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Garzia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Etxebeste</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herrero-Garcia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ugalde</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Espeso</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The concerted action of bZip and cMyb transcription factors FlbB and FlbD induces <italic>brlA</italic> expression and asexual development in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>75</volume>: <fpage>1314</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20132447</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Gldener1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>G&#xFC;ldener</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seong</surname><given-names>K-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boddu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trail</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Development of a <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> Affymetrix GeneChip for profiling fungal gene expression in vitro and in planta</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>43</volume>: <fpage>316</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16531083</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Tudzynski1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tudzynski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mende</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weltring</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kinghorn</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Unkles</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Gibberella fujikuroi niaD</italic> gene encoding nitrate reductase: isolation, sequence, homologous transformation and electrophoretic karyotype location</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source><volume>142</volume>: <fpage>533</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8868428</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Seong1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seong</surname><given-names>K-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pasquali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hilburn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Global gene regulation by <italic>Fusarium</italic> transcription factors Tri6 and Tri10 reveals adaptations for toxin biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>72</volume>: <fpage>354</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19320833</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Yanhui1">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yanhui</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiaoyuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meihua</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jigang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The MYB transcription factor superfamily of Arabidopsis: expression analysis and phylogenetic comparison with the rice MYB family</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source><volume>60</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16463103</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Ehrenkaufer1">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ehrenkaufer</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hackney</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A developmentally regulated Myb domain protein regulates expression of a subset of stage-specific genes in <italic>Entamoeba histolytica</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell Microbiol</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>898</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>910</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19239479</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-RodrguezSnchez1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodr&#xED;guez-S&#xE1;nchez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodr&#xED;guez-L&#xF3;pez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garc&#xED;a</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tenorio-G&#xF3;mez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schvartzman</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The fission yeast rDNA-binding protein Reb1 regulates G1 phase under nutritional stress</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source><volume>124</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21118960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Imamura1">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Imamura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanesaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ohnuma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inouye</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sekine</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>R2R3-type MYB transcription factor, CmMYB1, is a central nitrogen assimilation regulator in <italic>Cyanidioschyzon merolae</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>106</volume>: <fpage>12548</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>12553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19592510</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Kudla1">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kudla</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caddik</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Langdon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martinez-Rossi</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>The regulatory gene <italic>areA</italic> mediation nitrogen metabolite repression in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic>. Mutations affecting specificity of gene activation alter a loop residue of a putative zinc finger</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source><volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1355</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1970293</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Mihlan1">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mihlan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Homann</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tudzynski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>AREA directly mediates nitrogen regulation of gibberellin biosynthesis in <italic>Gibberella fujikuroi</italic>, but its activity is not affected by NMR</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>47</volume>: <fpage>975</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12581353</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Todd1">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hynes</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Nuclear accumulation of the GATA factor AreA in response to complete nitrogen starvation by regulation of nuclear export</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1646</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16215172</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Arst1">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arst</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cove</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Nitrogen metabolite repression in <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source><volume>126</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4591376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Marzluf1">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marzluf</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Genetic regulation of nitrogen metabolism in the fungi</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><volume>61</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9106362</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Tahirov1">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tahirov</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ichikawa-Iwata</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inoue-Bungo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Mechanism of c-Myb-C/EBP beta cooperation from separated sites on a promoter</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>108</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11792321</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Wang1">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A novel transcriptional factor important for pathogenesis and ascosporogenesis in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>24</volume>: <fpage>118</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20795857</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Park1">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>A-R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>J-A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Functional analyses of regulators of G protein signaling in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><volume>49</volume>: <fpage>511</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22634273</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Lee4">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A novel jasmonic acid-inducible rice <italic>myb</italic> gene associates with fungal infection and host cell death</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>527</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11310740</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Mengiste1">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mengiste</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salmeron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The <italic>BOTRYTIS SUSCEPTIBLE1</italic> gene encodes an R2R3MYB transcription factor protein that is required for biotic and abiotic stress responses in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2551</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14555693</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Vailleau1">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vailleau</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tronchet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montillet</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Triantaphylides</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A R2R3-MYB gene, <italic>AtMYB30</italic>, acts as a positive regulator of the hypersensitive cell death program in plants in response to pathogen attack</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>99</volume>: <fpage>10179</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12119395</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Proctor1">
        <label>65</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hohn</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Reduced virulence of <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic> caused by disruption of a trichthecene toxin biosynthetic gene</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>593</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8589414</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0094359-Bowden1">
        <label>66</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Sexual recombination in <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Phytopathology</source><volume>89</volume>: <fpage>182</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944794</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
