<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4607432</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26468648</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140524</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-33353</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title><italic>W3</italic> Is a New Wax Locus That Is Essential for Biosynthesis of &#x3B2;-Diketone, Development of Glaucousness, and Reduction of Cuticle Permeability in Common Wheat</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Cuticular Wax and Wheat Tolerance to Abiotic Stress</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Zhengzhi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>Wenjie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>Huilan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Challa</surname>
            <given-names>Ghana S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bi</surname>
            <given-names>Caili</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="currentaff001">
            <sup>&#xA4;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Trick</surname>
            <given-names>Harold N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Wanlong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff001">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Biology and Microbiology, South Dakota State University, Brookings, South Dakota, 57007, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff002">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Plant Pathology, Kansas State University, Manhattan, Kansas, 66506, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Jin-Song</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, CHINA</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
          <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: WL. Performed the experiments: ZZ WL WW HZ GSC. Analyzed the data: WL ZZ WW HZ GSC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CB HNT. Wrote the paper: WL.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="currentaff001">
          <label>&#xA4;</label>
          <p>Current address: Department of Biology, Hebei Normal University, Shijiazhuang, Hebei, 050024, China</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>wanlong.li@sdstate.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>10</issue>
      <elocation-id>e0140524</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Zhang et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0140524.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>The cuticle plays important roles in plant development, growth and defense against biotic and abiotic attacks. Crystallized epicuticular wax, the outermost layer of cuticle, is visible as white-bluish glaucousness. In crops like barley and wheat, glaucousness is trait of adaption to the dry and hot cultivation conditions, and hentriacontane-14,16-dione (&#x3B2;-diketone) and its hydroxy derivatives are the major and unique components of cuticular wax in the upper parts of adult plants. But their biosynthetic pathway and physiological role largely remain unknown. In the present research, we identified a novel wax mutant in wheat cultivar Bobwhite. The mutation is not allelic to the known wax production gene loci <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic>, and designated as <italic>W</italic>3 accordingly. Genetic analysis localized <italic>W3</italic> on chromosome arm 2BS. The <italic>w3</italic> mutation reduced 99% of &#x3B2;-diketones, which account for 63.3% of the total wax load of the wild-type. <italic>W3</italic> is necessary for &#x3B2;-diketone synthesis, but has a different effect on &#x3B2;-diketone hydroxylation because the hydroxy-&#x3B2;-diketones to &#x3B2;-diketone ratio increased 11-fold in the <italic>w3</italic> mutant. Loss of &#x3B2;-diketones caused failure to form glaucousness and significant increase of cuticle permeability in terms of water loss and chlorophyll efflux in the <italic>w3</italic> mutant. Transcription of 23 cuticle genes from five functional groups was altered in the <italic>w3</italic> mutant, 19 down-regulated and four up-regulated, suggesting a possibility that <italic>W3</italic> encodes a transcription regulator coordinating expression of cuticle genes. Biosynthesis of &#x3B2;-diketones in wheat and their implications in glaucousness formation and drought and heat tolerance were discussed.</p>
        <sec id="sec001">
          <title>Key Message</title>
          <p><italic>W3</italic> is essential for &#x3B2;-diketone biosynthesis but suppresses its hydroxylation. Loss-of-function mutation <italic>w3</italic> significantly increased cuticle permeability in terms of water loss and chlorophyll efflux.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was partly supported by the USDA/DOE Feedstock Genomics Program, South Dakota Agricultural Experimental Station (Brookings, SD) and South Dakota Wheat Commission (Pierre, SD).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="9"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <page-count count="21"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta id="data-availability">
          <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
          <meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information file.</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability</title>
      <p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information file.</p>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec002">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>During transition from water to land colonization, plants developed an array of mechanisms for adaptation to the desiccation environment. One of these mechanisms is deposition of cuticle, a hydrophobic coat, to cover the aerial organ surfaces. In addition to function in protecting water loss, cuticle, as the interface between the sessile plants and their environment, plays important roles in plant defense against heat, UV radiation, pathogen and insect attacks [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Cuticle consists of the fundamental framework of cutin and intracuticular wax inserted in it and epicuticular wax overlaid on them. Cutin is the cell wall-bounded ester polymer of hydroxy fatty acids [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], and waxes are the very long chain fatty acids (VLCFAs) and their derivatives including alcohols, aldehydes, alkanes, ketones and wax esters [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Variation in epicuticular wax composition causes changes in plant appearance: glaucous or nonglaucous. Glaucousness, the bluish-white look, is the visible form of densely arrayed wax crystals.</p>
      <p>In wax biosynthesis, <italic>de novo</italic> C<sub>16</sub> and C<sub>18</sub> fatty acids, the precursors, are first elongated into VLCFAs (C<sub>20</sub> to C<sub>34</sub>) by fatty acyl elongase (FAE) complex. The VLCFAs can be converted to primary alcohols and further esterified with the C<sub>16</sub> fatty acids into wax esters via the acyl reduction pathway [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and converted to alkanes, aldehydes, secondary alcohols and ketones through decarbonylation pathway [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. All the wax species are synthesized in epidermal cells, transported extracellular and deposited to cuticle. Wax synthesis and export are under tight developmental and environmental regulations. Molecular identification of the genes coding for the wax biosynthetic enzymes, wax transporters and wax regulators in the model plant Arabidopsis provided genetic and molecular supports to the VLCFA and associated pathways (reviewed in [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p>
      <p>The VLCFA and associated pathways are conserved in higher plants, and many of their components of these pathways have also been identified in the grass genomes. Maize wax genes <italic>GLOSSY1</italic> (<italic>GL1</italic>) [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], <italic>GL2</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], <italic>GL4</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] and <italic>GL8</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] are homologous to <italic>ECERIFERUM3</italic> (<italic>CER3</italic>), <italic>CER2</italic>, <italic>CER6</italic> and <italic>&#x3B2;-keto acyl-CoA reductase 1</italic> (<italic>KCR1</italic>) of Arabidopsis, respectively. A T-DNA insertion mutant in a <italic>CER6</italic> homolog reduced leaf wax crystal density in rice [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Maize AP2 transcription factor GL15 involves in the transition from juvenile to adult leaf identity including wax composition [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and HD-ZIP IV family transcription factor OCL1 regulates cuticular wax biosynthesis by activation of a fatty acyl-CoA reductase (FAR) and a putative wax transporter [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p>
      <p>In addition to the VLCFA and associated pathways, a diverse of plants, including barley and wheat (<italic>Triticum</italic> L.), employ another parallel wax biosynthetic pathway for biosynthesis of hentriacontane-14,16-dione (also known as &#x3B2;-diketone) and its derivatives. In wheat, the VLCFA pathways are active in the vegetative stage, but the &#x3B2;-diketone pathway predominates in the reproductive stage [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. It is believed that &#x3B2;-diketone is synthesized using C<sub>14</sub> and C<sub>16</sub> fatty acids as precursors [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Wax profiling of barley mutants suggests that <italic>cer-q</italic>, <italic>cer-c</italic> and <italic>cer-u</italic> mutants respectively define the initial condensing reaction, subsequent chain extensions and hydroxylation [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], but little is known about the genetic components of this pathway. In common wheat (<italic>T</italic>. <italic>aestivum</italic> L., genomes AABBDD), two wax inhibitors and two wax production genes underlie the glaucousness variations: <italic>Iw1</italic> on chromosome arm 2BS [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], <italic>Iw2</italic> on 2DS [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], <italic>W1</italic> on 2BS [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and <italic>W2</italic> on 2DS [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In durum wheat (<italic>T</italic>. <italic>turgidum</italic> subsp. <italic>durum</italic>, genomes AABB), a third wax inhibitor <italic>Iw3</italic> is located in the distal region of chromosome arm 1BS [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. We previously characterized a set of wheat near isogenic lines (NILs) differing at <italic>W1</italic>, <italic>W2</italic>, <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> loci and durum NILs differing at the <italic>Iw3</italic> locus, and found that loss of both functional alleles of the <italic>W</italic> genes or presence of either <italic>Iw</italic> gene causes depletion of &#x3B2;-diketones and nonglaucous phenotype. While elimination of &#x3B2;-diketones is compensated by increase of aldehydes and primary alcohols in the <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> NILs [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], <italic>Iw3</italic> inhibits &#x3B2;-diketone, reduces primary alcohols but increase aldehyde and alkanes in the glume wax [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Although expression of a <italic>FAR1</italic> homolog was maintained at high level in the <italic>Iw</italic> NILs, no match was found between expression of 72 wax genes and &#x3B2;-diketone distribution pattern [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. All this suggests that &#x3B2;-diketones are synthesized through a not-yet-identified pathway.</p>
      <p>We recently identified a nonglaucous (NG) mutant in Bobwhite (BW) wheat. Compared to the wild type BW, the mutant lost 63% of total wax load and almost all of the &#x3B2;-diketones, and showed a significant increase of water loss. Genetic and molecular analyses indicated that the mutant gene is not allelic to either <italic>W1</italic> or <italic>W2</italic> and expression of numerous cuticle genes of five different pathways was significantly down regulated. Here we report the results and their implications in Triticeae cuticle biosynthesis and drought tolerance.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="sec003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="sec004">
        <title>Genetic Analysis of the Wax Mutant</title>
        <p>During intercrossing BW transgenic plants to combine the different RNAi transgenes, a NG plant was found in a small T<sub>1</sub> population of the transgenic line #056 in the spring of 2010. It dried out prematurely (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A</xref>). We recovered two NG plants, NG1 and NG2, from the T<sub>2</sub> populations derived from the glaucous T<sub>1</sub> plants of the same pot. These NG plants had much lower level of glaucousness in leaves, sheaths, peduncle, and spikes as compared to the wild type BW (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>). The mutant plants died prematurely again in the late spring of 2011 although they were well watered (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1C</xref>) probably due to the high temperature.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0140524.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140524.g001</object-id>
          <label>Fig 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Phenotype of the nonglaucous mutant.</title>
            <p>(<bold><italic>A</italic></bold>) The mutant was found in a small F<sub>2</sub> population derived from a cross between two RNAi transgenic plants in BW background due to premature drying out. (<bold><italic>B</italic></bold>) Adult plants of BW (left) and the nonglaucous mutant (right) at anthesis. (<bold><italic>C</italic></bold>) Adult plants of BW (left) and the nonglaucous mutant (right) at grain-filling stage.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0140524.g001"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We started genetic analysis of this presumable NG mutant by crossing it with the wild type BW. The F<sub>1</sub> plants were glaucous but their glaucousness level was intermediate between BW and the NG mutant (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2A</xref>). A population of 361 F<sub>2</sub> individuals segregated into 265 glaucous and 96 nonglaucous, which fits the 3 (glaucous) to 1 (nonglaucous) ratio (<italic>P</italic> = 0.38812; <xref rid="pone.0140524.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), indicating that a single-gene mutation underlies the nonglaucous phenotype. To test if the mutation was due to transgene insertion, we screened 38 nonglaucous F<sub>2</sub> individuals derived from the cross between NG1 and BW for the transformation selection marker <italic>bar</italic> gene and RNAi transgene constructs [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] by targeting at the <italic>Ubq-bar</italic> and <italic>gus-nos</italic> junctions, respectively. Result showed that eight plants were negative for both the <italic>Ubq-bar</italic> and <italic>gus-nos</italic> junctions, and 7 additional plants were negative for the <italic>gus-nos</italic> junction. Furthermore, NG2 contained neither <italic>Ubq-bar</italic> nor <italic>gus-nos</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0140524.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). These data indicate that one <italic>bar</italic> locus was not linked with the RNAi locus in NG1 and that the nonglaucous mutation is independent of the transgene insertions.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0140524.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140524.g002</object-id>
          <label>Fig 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Genetic analysis of <italic>w3</italic> mutant.</title>
            <p>(<bold><italic>A</italic></bold>) The F<sub>1</sub> hybrid between BW and the nonglaucous mutant is intermediate between its parents in glaucousness intensity. (<bold><italic>B</italic></bold>) The F<sub>1</sub> hybrid between the mutant and <italic>w1w2</italic> double recessive line was glaucous. The scale bars indicate 1 cm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0140524.g002"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pone.0140524.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140524.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Phenotypes and segregations of glaucousness in hybrids and their progenies.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone.0140524.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0140524.t001"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crosses</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># of F<sub>1</sub></th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>1</sub> Plant</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>2</sub> segregation</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> values</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> values</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> values</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> values</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">plants</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">phenotype</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(gl : ng)<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3 : 1)</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15 : 1)</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9 : 7)</th>
                  <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1 : 1)</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>w3</italic> x BW</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glaucous</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106:38</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70032</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 x 10<sup>&#x2212;23</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 x 10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 x 10<sup>&#x2212;10</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>w3</italic> x CS-TDIC 2B</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glaucous</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265:96</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38812</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 x 10<sup>&#x2212;56</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9 x 10<sup>&#x2212;11</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 x 10<sup>&#x2212;18</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>w1w2</italic> x <italic>w3</italic></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glaucous</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141:129</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 x 10<sup>&#x2212;18</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 x 10&#x2212;<sup>175</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18217</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46477</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>w1w2</italic> x BW</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glaucous</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133:11</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 x 10<sup>&#x2212;6</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49112</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 x 10<sup>&#x2212;24</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 x 10<sup>&#x2212;81</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>w3</italic> x CS 2BS-1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nonglaucous</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0:71</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 x 10<sup>&#x2212;48</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 x 10<sup>&#x2212;233</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 x 10<sup>&#x2212;21</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 x 10<sup>&#x2212;17</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>w3</italic> x CS 2BS-2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nonglaucous</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0:71</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 x 10<sup>&#x2212;48</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 x 10<sup>&#x2212;233</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 x 10<sup>&#x2212;21</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 x 10<sup>&#x2212;17</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>w3</italic> x CS 2BS-3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nonglaucous</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0:72</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7 x 10<sup>&#x2212;49</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 x 10<sup>&#x2212;237</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 x 10<sup>&#x2212;22</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 x 10<sup>&#x2212;17</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>w3</italic> x CS 2BS-5</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nonglaucous</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0:68</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8 x 10<sup>&#x2212;46</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1x 10<sup>&#x2212;224</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7 x 10<sup>&#x2212;21</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 x 10<sup>&#x2212;16</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>w3</italic> x CS 2BS-10</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nonglaucous</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0:72</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7 x 10<sup>&#x2212;49</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 x 10<sup>&#x2212;237</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 x 10<sup>&#x2212;22</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 x 10<sup>&#x2212;17</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>w3</italic> x CS 2BS-14</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nonglaucous</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0:35</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 x 10<sup>&#x2212;34</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 x 10<sup>&#x2212;116</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 x 10<sup>&#x2212;11</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3 x 10<sup>&#x2212;9</sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t001fn001">
              <p>*gl, glaucous; ng, nonglaucous.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>To test if the nonglaucous mutation is allelic to the known wax production genes in wheat, we crossed S-615 <italic>w1w2</italic> near isogenic line (NIL), which is nonglaucous due to loss-of-function at the functionally redundant <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic> loci [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], with BW and the NG2 mutant line. The F<sub>2</sub> population derived from the cross between S615-<italic>w1w2</italic> and BW segregated into 133 glaucous and 11 nonglaucous plants, well-fitting the 15 to 1 ratio (<italic>P</italic> = 0.49112; <xref rid="pone.0140524.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) and indicating that BW carries both <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic> functional alleles. The F<sub>1</sub> hybrid plants between S615-<italic>w1w2</italic> and NG2 carry glaucousness at low intensity (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2B</xref>), indicating that the nonglaucous mutation in BW is not allelic to either <italic>W1</italic> or <italic>W2</italic>, but its wild type allele in S615-<italic>w1w2</italic> complements to the functional alleles of the <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic> loci carried by BW. According to the recommended rules for gene symbolization in wheat [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], we designated this new wax gene locus as <italic>W3</italic> and the mutant as <italic>w</italic>3. A population of 270 F<sub>2</sub> plants derived from the cross between the <italic>w3</italic> mutant and the <italic>w1w2</italic> NIL segregated into 141 glaucous and 129 nonglaucous, which fits a 1 to 1 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.46477) or 9 to 7 ratio (<italic>P</italic> = 0.18217; <xref rid="pone.0140524.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) and is more similar to the two-locus segregation ratios than a three-locus segregation. These results corroborate that <italic>W3</italic> is not homologous to the known wax gene loci <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic> and suggested that <italic>W3</italic> is most probably linked with the <italic>W1</italic> or <italic>W2</italic> locus. To identify the chromosomal location of the <italic>W3</italic> locus, we developed a mapping population from a cross between the <italic>w3</italic> mutant and Chinese Spring (CS)-<italic>T</italic>. <italic>turgidum</italic> subsp. <italic>dicoccoides</italic> 2B substitution line (CS-TDIC 2B) and genotyped the 82 NG F<sub>2</sub> individuals (168 gametes) using 2BS and 2DS SSR markers for detection of marker-<italic>W3</italic> linkage. The result showed that <italic>W3</italic> is linked with the 2BS SSR markers and 5.5 cM proximal to the marker loci <italic>Xwmc770</italic> and <italic>Xgwm148</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3A</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0140524.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140524.g003</object-id>
          <label>Fig 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Chromosomal localization of the <italic>W3</italic> locus.</title>
            <p>(<bold><italic>A</italic></bold>) Molecular mapping of the <italic>W3</italic> locus on the chromosome arm 2BS. The markers are listed at the right side of the map, and genetic distances (cM) between the marker loci are indicated at the left side of the map. The <italic>W3</italic> locus is indicated in bold. The top of the map is towards the telomere and the bottom is towards the centromere. (<bold><italic>B</italic></bold>) The peduncles of CS N2B-T2D (1), F<sub>1</sub> hybrids of NG2 with N2B-T2D (2), with deletion line 2BS-1 (3), with 2BS-2 (4), with 2BS-3 (5), with 2BS-5 (6), with 2BS-10 (7) and with 2BS-14 (8). All the flag-leaf sheaths are nonglaucous. The scale bar indicate 1 cm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0140524.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We also crossed the <italic>w3</italic> mutant with CS 2BS deletion lines (2BS-1, -2, -3, -5, -10 and -14). All these deletion lines and nullisomic 2B-tetrasomic 2D (N2B-T2D), in which lack of one pair of chromosome 2B is compensated by two pairs of chromosome 2D, are nonglaucous due to missing the <italic>W1</italic> locus. The F<sub>1</sub> hybrid plants between the <italic>w3</italic> mutant and the 2BS deletion lines were nonglaucous similar to N2B-T2D, or carried nearly undetectable glaucousness (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3B</xref>). No glaucous individuals were observed in their F<sub>2</sub> populations (<xref rid="pone.0140524.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). This result corroborates that the <italic>W3</italic> locus is located in the distal region of chromosome arm 2BS.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, we genotyped BW and the <italic>w3</italic> mutant using SSR markers located in the distal regions of the 42 wheat chromosome arms on wheat genetic maps. All 42 SSR markers were positive and detected monomorphism (<xref rid="pone.0140524.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). This indicated BW and the <italic>w3</italic> mutant shares the same genetic background.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec005">
        <title>Wax Morphology</title>
        <p>At stage F10.5.1, wheat plants are flowering, and glaucousness is fully developed. We inspected the cuticle surfaces of flag leaf sheaths of BW and <italic>w3</italic> mutant under a scanning electron microscope (SEM) at this developmental stage. The electron micrographs showed clear differences between BW and <italic>w3</italic> mutant (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). In BW, cuticle surface was covered with thick meshwork of long wax crystal tubes (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A</xref>). In contrast, short wax bodies were appressed to the leaf cuticle surface of <italic>w3</italic> mutant at low density (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4B</xref>). This result indicated that the <italic>W3</italic> locus has a major effect on cuticle, epicuticular wax in particular, development. Considering that the great contrast in wax crystal morphology and density between BW and <italic>w3</italic> mutant was found in the flag leaf sheath, we used this tissue for measuring cuticle permeability, profiling composition of the cuticular waxes and quantifying transcription of cuticle genes.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0140524.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140524.g004</object-id>
          <label>Fig 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>SEM micrographs of cuticle surfaces of flag leaf sheaths.</title>
            <p>(<bold><italic>A</italic></bold>) BW and (<bold><italic>B</italic></bold>) <italic>w3</italic> mutant. The scale bars indicated 1 &#x3BC;m.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0140524.g004"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec006">
        <title>Cuticle Permeability</title>
        <p>We measured the cuticle permeability in two experiments using the flag-leaf sheath: water loss in air and chlorophyll leaching in 80% ethanol. In the first experiment, significantly higher water loss rate was observed in the <italic>w3</italic> mutant 1 h after detachment (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.03303) and incremented throughout the time course (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>). We inspected stomata, and no significant difference was found in stomata density between BW and <italic>w3</italic> mutant, ~60 stomata in one view field of 10x20 magnification under microscope. The stomata were closed within one hour after detachment. This suggests that the difference in water loss rate is attributed to cuticle permeability. In the second experiment, <italic>w3</italic> mutant showed significantly higher chlorophyll efflux rate from the sixth to eighth hour of treatment (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.02491; <xref rid="pone.0140524.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>). Both lines were similar in total chlorophyll content after 48-hour extraction (<italic>P</italic> = 0.80435). This corroborates the conclusion from the water loss experiment that change of wax crystal morphology and density led to increase of cuticle permeability in <italic>w3</italic> mutant.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0140524.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140524.g005</object-id>
          <label>Fig 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Analysis of cuticle permeability of BW and <italic>w3</italic> mutant.</title>
            <p>Cuticle permeability was evaluated by air drying at room temperature (<bold><italic>A</italic></bold>) and by chlorophyll leaching in 80% ethanol (<bold><italic>B</italic></bold>). The numbers on the x-axes represent hours of treatment. Water loss or chlorophyll leaching at each time point is represented on the y-axes as percentages of the total water content or total chlorophyll content in the tissue. Measurements taken from six individuals were averaged.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0140524.g005"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Difference in water-loss rate was also found in spikes in relation to glaucousness. Six hours after detachment, top awns of the <italic>w3</italic> mutant started to dry (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6B</xref>). Twelve hours after detachment, spike of <italic>w3</italic> mutant completely discolored and dried out; awns of <italic>w1w2</italic> double recessive line were twisted and some glumes discolored, but BW and F<sub>1</sub> between <italic>w3</italic> mutant and <italic>w1w2</italic> stayed in normal shape (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6C</xref>). This indicates that <italic>W3</italic> played an important role in preventing non-stomatal transpiration.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0140524.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140524.g006</object-id>
          <label>Fig 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Spikes responses to dehydration.</title>
            <p>Spike of BW (<italic>W1W1W2W2W3W3</italic>), <italic>w3</italic> mutant (<italic>W1W1W2W2w3w3</italic>), <italic>w1w2</italic> double recessive line (<italic>w1w1w2w2W3W3</italic>), and the F<sub>1</sub> hybrid between <italic>w3</italic> and <italic>w1w2</italic> (<italic>W1w1W2w2W3w3</italic>) at 0 (<bold><italic>A</italic></bold>), 6 (<bold><italic>B</italic></bold>) and 12 h of dehydration (<bold><italic>C</italic></bold>). The designations are indicated on the top. The scale bars indicate 1 cm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0140524.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec007">
        <title>Wax Composition</title>
        <p>We extracted wax from the flag-leaf sheath at stage F10.5.1 and comparatively profiled the wax composition of BW and the <italic>w3</italic> mutant by GC-MS. Ninety-two wax molecules were identified, two thirds of which were trace and could not find a match in the National Institute of Standards and Technology database. These minors and unknowns account for ~10% total wax extract in BW, which had similar abundance in <italic>w3</italic> mutant.</p>
        <p>We analyzed the distribution patterns of major wax species in BW and <italic>w3</italic> mutant. In BW, two major wax components, diketones and alkanes account for 63.3% and 34.0% of the total wax load, respectively. Remaining 2.7% are wax esters (1.0%), fatty acids (0.8%), primary alcohols (0.7%) and aldehydes (0.2%). Dramatic differences were found in total wax load and wax composition between BW and <italic>w3</italic> mutant (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref>). Compared to BW, <italic>w3</italic> mutant lost 64% of the total wax (<italic>P</italic> = 5 x 10<sup>&#x2212;7</sup>; <xref rid="pone.0140524.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref>). While alkanes were maintained unchanged (<italic>P</italic> = 0.68113; <xref rid="pone.0140524.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref>), &#x3B2;-diketones reduced to 1% in <italic>w3</italic> mutant (<italic>P</italic> = 1 x 10<sup>&#x2212;8</sup>; <xref rid="pone.0140524.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref>). As a result, alkanes account for over 90% of the total wax load of <italic>w3</italic> mutant (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref>). Two types of diketones, &#x3B2;-diketone and hydroxy-&#x3B2;-diketones, were detected. Hydroxy-&#x3B2;-diketones account for 8.5% of the total &#x3B2;-diketones in BW. As a result, BW had a hydroxy-&#x3B2;-diketones to &#x3B2;-diketone ratio (OH-D/&#x3B2;-D) of 0.0925. In <italic>w3</italic> mutant, &#x3B2;-diketone and hydroxy-&#x3B2;-diketones did not reduce proportionally: 181-fold reduction in &#x3B2;-diketone (<italic>P</italic> = 1 x 10<sup>&#x2212;7</sup>), but 16-fold reduction in hydroxy-&#x3B2;-diketones (<italic>P</italic> = 0.00002; <xref rid="pone.0140524.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>). Two hydroxy-&#x3B2;-diketone isomers, 8- and 9-hydroxy hentriatane-14,16-dione, were detected. The 8-isomer reduced ~14-fold (<italic>P</italic> = 2 x 10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup>) and the 9-isomer reduced ~22-fold (<italic>P</italic> = 0.00001) in <italic>w3</italic> mutant. Therefore, the hydroxy-&#x3B2;-diketones content was roughly equal to that of &#x3B2;-diketone in <italic>w3</italic> mutant with an OH-D/&#x3B2;-D of 1.014 (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>), indicating a ~11-fold increase as compared to BW (<italic>P</italic> = 0.00695). This suggests a differential effect of the <italic>w3</italic> mutation on biosynthesis of &#x3B2;-diketone and its hydroxylation.</p>
        <fig id="pone.0140524.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140524.g007</object-id>
          <label>Fig 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Wax composition of BW and <italic>w3</italic> mutant.</title>
            <p>Total wax load and content of alkanes, &#x3B2;-diketones, primary alcohols (alkan-1-ols), aldehydes, wax esters, and fatty acids of the flag leaf sheaths were measured by GC-MS. The numbers on the y-axes indicate average content expressed as &#x3BC;g per g dried tissue (dry weight, DW). The error bars indicate standard deviation of the mean estimated from five biological replicates.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0140524.g007"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone.0140524.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140524.g008</object-id>
          <label>Fig 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Variation of wax homologues between BW and <italic>w3</italic> mutant.</title>
            <p>Carbon atom numbers of alkanes, &#x3B2;-diketones, primary alcohols (alkan-1-ols), fatty acids, wax esters, and aldehydes are indicated on the x-axes. Their contents are indicated on y-axes as &#x3BC;g per g dried tissue (dry weight, DW). The error bars indicate standard deviation of the mean calculated from five biological replicates. &#x3B2;-D, &#x3B2;-diketone; and OH-&#x3B2;, hydroxy-&#x3B2;-diketones.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0140524.g008"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In addition to &#x3B2;-diketones, wax ester content, especially octadecanoic acid octadecyl ester (C<sub>36</sub>), was significantly decreased in <italic>w3</italic> mutant (<italic>P</italic> = 0.00002; Figs <xref rid="pone.0140524.g007" ref-type="fig">7</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0140524.g008" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). Contrary to diketones and wax esters, total aldehyde was significantly increased in <italic>w3</italic> mutant (<italic>P</italic> = 0.01026; <xref rid="pone.0140524.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref>). With regard to specific carbon length homologues of aldehydes, significant increase of C<sub>28</sub> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.00309) and C<sub>32</sub> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.00008) homologues and significant reduction of C<sub>26</sub> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.00485) and C<sub>30</sub> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.00008) homologues was observed in <italic>w3</italic> mutant (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>). Although no significant difference was found between BW and <italic>w3</italic> mutant in the total primary alcohol and alkane content (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref>), changes were detected in some homologues of these wax species: C<sub>20</sub> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.01215) alcohol was reduced in <italic>w3</italic> mutant, but C<sub>22</sub>, C<sub>26</sub> and C<sub>28</sub> alcohols (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.00036) and C<sub>33</sub> alkane (<italic>P</italic> = 0.02579) were significantly increased in <italic>w3</italic> mutant (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec008">
        <title>Transcription of Cuticle Genes</title>
        <p>To gain insights into the <italic>W3</italic>-dependent genetic pathways, we profiled expression of 72 wheat wax candidate genes belonging to six categories [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] in the flag-leaf sheath of BW and <italic>w3</italic>-BW by qPCR. Of these 72 wax genes, five are responsible for cutin biosynthesis, 17 for fatty acyl elongation, 17 for VLCFA reduction and wax esterification, 21 for VLCFA decarbonylation, seven for wax transport and five for wax regulation (<xref rid="pone.0140524.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). Result showed that expression of 19 genes was significantly down regulated and four up regulated (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>). Of these 19 down-regulated genes, nine genes were down regulated more than twofold. These include five <italic>CER1</italic> members, <italic>FAR5</italic>, <italic>KCR2</italic>, <italic>KCS-3</italic> and <italic>LTP</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>). Of the five down-regulated <italic>CER1</italic> genes, <italic>CER1-1</italic> showed greatest fold change, <italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. 3.4-fold down-regulation. Expression of four <italic>CER3</italic> genes reduced only ~1.5-fold though they may also be involved in decarbonylation via interaction with <italic>CER1</italic> gene products. By contrast, expression of <italic>CER4-3</italic>, <italic>CER4-12</italic>, <italic>MAH1-5</italic> and <italic>WSD1</italic> increased ~1.5-fold (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone.0140524.g009" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140524.g009</object-id>
          <label>Fig 9</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Transcriptional changes of wax genes in <italic>w3</italic> mutant against BW.</title>
            <p>Genes with significant fold changes are depicted. The error bars represent standard deviation of the mean fold-change of mRNA levels calculated from four biological replicates. Asterisks indicate that the difference is significant at <italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.05 (*) or at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 (**). Expression data for all genes analyzed are listed in <xref rid="pone.0140524.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0140524.g009"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec009">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Glaucousness is one of the most eye-catching traits and has been used as a morphological marker in wheat genetic studies for ~80 years (reviewed in [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]). Its adaptive value in improving crop tolerance to drought and heat was recognized in 1980s [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], and the climate change resumed interest in this trait more recently [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Nevertheless, basic research of glaucousness in wheat lagged behind compared to other cereal crops, such as barley, a distant relative of wheat. One of the major reasons for this is lack of nonglaucous mutants in polyploid wheat. In this study, we identified a new &#x3B2;-diketone-deficit wax mutation <italic>w3</italic> and investigated the function of &#x3B2;-diketone as a major wax component in drought tolerance. Molecular characterization of <italic>w3</italic> mutant also shed light on diketone biosynthesis.</p>
      <sec id="sec010">
        <title>Wax Loci</title>
        <p>In barley, a diploid species, 79 wax loci have been identified by 1,580 induced <italic>eceriferum</italic> mutants [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], of which 53 mutant loci were localized to the all 7 chromosomes [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Chromosome 2H, which is homoeologous to wheat chromosomes 2A, 2B and 2D, carries 11 wax loci, of which <italic>cer-c</italic>, <italic>cer-q</italic>, <italic>cer-u</italic>, <italic>cer-v</italic> and <italic>cer-zt</italic> are located on the short arm and <italic>cer-g</italic>, <italic>cer-n</italic>, <italic>cer-yb</italic> and <italic>gsh5</italic> (<italic>cer-s</italic>) on the long arm. In contrast, only four wax loci, <italic>W1</italic>, <italic>W2</italic>, <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> have been identified in hexaploid wheat with <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>Iw1</italic> located on 2BS and <italic>W2</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> on 2DS [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In polyploid wheat, mutation rate are 5- to 10-fold higher than diploid species due to genetic redundancy [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], but the mutant phenotypes are often masked by the wild type alleles of the homoeologous loci. The <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic> genes are functionally redundant in forming glaucousness, but they differ in chromosomal locations [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] and expression profiles [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], suggesting a possibility that they are paralogous and their orthologs in the homoeologous chromosomes are silenced, deleted, neo- or sub-functionalized, which is an important feature of polyploid evolution [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. In the present research, we showed <italic>W3</italic> is located on chromosome arm 2BS and complements with <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic> for &#x3B2;-diketone production. Different from <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic>, homoeologs of <italic>W3</italic> in the A and D genomes of polyploid wheat lost their function in glaucousness formation. This makes <italic>W3</italic> more tractable for genetic manipulation and molecular study of wheat wax.</p>
        <p>In addition to BW, a single functional <italic>W3</italic> locus is present in CS-TDIC 2B (<xref rid="pone.0140524.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), probably also in CS. But it was previously not detected in the CS aneuploids, including nullisomics, nulli-tetrasomics (NT) and deletion lines. This failure was because <italic>W3</italic> is linked with <italic>W1</italic>. Deletion of either one causes the nonglaucous phenotype and prevents identification of another wax locus supposing that CS does not carry the <italic>W2</italic> allele. We examined the 42 NT lines and found that only N2B-T2A and N2B-T2D were nonglaucous. We also examined all eight homozygous deletion lines available for chromosome arm 2BS (2BS-1, -2, -3, -5, -6, -10,-12 and -14) and found that all of them were nonglaucous. These results confirmed that <italic>W1</italic> is located in the distal region of the chromosome arm [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], which prevents to identify additional wax loci on same chromosome arm although several wax loci located on homoeologous chromosome arm 2HS of barley [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. No segregation in the F<sub>2</sub> populations derived from the crosses between the <italic>w3</italic> mutant and 2BS deletion lines suggests that both <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W3</italic> are located in the distal bin. The <italic>w3</italic> mutants may already exist in other wheat cultivars besides BW, but they are assumed to be the <italic>w1</italic> mutant. Therefore, allelism test is essential for identifying new wax gene loci in addition to marker linkage mapping. We are mapping the <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W3</italic> loci, and the closely linked molecular markers will provide more detailed information on the organization of these wax loci on 2BS.</p>
        <p>The <italic>w3</italic> mutation is independent of transgene insertions (<xref rid="pone.0140524.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>), suggesting that it could have been induced by tissue culture process during transformation. It is well known that <italic>in vitro</italic> tissue culture generates genomic stress, reprograms cell development and causes genetic and epigenetic changes [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Some of these changes inherit as morphological or physiological mutants. Spontaneous mutation of other origin, however, cannot be excluded because we recently identified several other morphological mutants in BW, which did not go through tissue culture.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec011">
        <title><italic>W3</italic> Effect on Biosynthesis of &#x3B2;-Diketones</title>
        <p>Like the wax genes <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], <italic>W3</italic> is essential for biosynthesis of &#x3B2;-diketones, but had little effect on biosynthesis of alkanes. This supports the proposal that &#x3B2;-diketones are synthesized through a genetic pathway different from VLCFA synthesis and associated alkane-forming decarbonylation pathways although both &#x3B2;-diketones and alkanes are odd-carbon waxes [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Two biosynthetic pathways have been proposed for &#x3B2;-diketone biosynthesis: condensation of two C<sub>16</sub> &#x3B2;-ketoesters via a &#x201C;biological Claisen reaction&#x201D; [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] and a modified elongation reaction on a selectively protected &#x3B2;-keto acid precursor [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Both proposals lack molecular evidence although the latter was based on biochemical analysis of the substrate and inhibitor specificity [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], wax metabolite profiling and genetic analysis of the barley <italic>cer-c</italic>, <italic>cer-q</italic> and <italic>cer-u</italic> mutants [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. In the both proposed models, a decarboxylative reaction was included. The <italic>cer-q</italic> and <italic>cer-c</italic> mutations impair the keto-protected chain elongation and lead to C<sub>13</sub> and C<sub>15</sub> alkan-2-ol formation [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. These secondary alcohols, products of &#x3B2;-keto fatty acid decarbonylation, were not detected either in <italic>w1w2</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] or the <italic>w3</italic> mutant in this research, suggesting that these wheat wax production genes act in upstream of the pathway or &#x3B2;-diketone is synthesized through the &#x201C;biological Claisen reaction&#x201D; in wheat [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. qPCR assays showed that transcription of three FAE genes, five <italic>CER1</italic> and four <italic>CER3</italic> homologs was significantly down-regulated in <italic>w3</italic> mutant (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0140524.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). In Arabidopsis, CER1 and CER3 are involved in VLCFA decarbonylation [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Because alkane content remained at the same level in <italic>w3</italic> mutant as in the wild type, these decarbonylation genes were not involved in alkane synthesis, but probably participated in the &#x3B2;-diketone-forming decarboxylative reaction. Considering that decarbonylation is the last step of &#x3B2;-diketone synthesis, transcription of these <italic>CER1</italic> and <italic>CER3</italic> homologs is possibly regulated either directly by <italic>W3</italic> or by a substrate-mediated feed-forward loop.</p>
        <p>The hydroxy &#x3B2;-diketone isomers are derived from &#x3B2;-diketone by hydroxylation [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], hence their changes in <italic>w3</italic> mutant are expected to be proportional. Contrary to this expectation, <italic>w3</italic> mutant had a much higher HO-D/&#x3B2;-D ratio compared to BW. This result suggests that hydroxylation reaction enzymes in the BW background are less sensitive to depletion of the substrate, i.e. &#x3B2;-diketone, or <italic>W3</italic> promotes synthesis of &#x3B2;-diketone but suppresses its hydroxylation. In agreement with the latter hypothesis, expression of <italic>MAH1-7</italic>, a homolog of <italic>MAH1</italic> that is responsible for midchain alkane hydroxylation in Arabidopsis [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], increased 1.5-fold in the <italic>w3</italic> mutant (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0140524.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). In another research, we found that interaction between wax production genes <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic> is required for biosynthesis of hydroxy-&#x3B2;-diketones and that up-regulation of <italic>MAH1-8</italic> paralleled with &#x3B2;-diketone hydroxylation in the <italic>W1W2</italic> double dominant genotype [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. It would be interesting to see if <italic>W3</italic> interacts with <italic>W1</italic> and <italic>W2</italic> by combining their loss-of-function mutations in the same genetic background and measuring their effect on the hydroxy &#x3B2;-diketone isomers.</p>
        <p>In addition to FAE, decarbonylation and hydroxylase genes, expression of three cutin biosynthetic genes, <italic>FAR5</italic> and the putative wax transporter <italic>LTP</italic> was also down regulated in the <italic>w3</italic> mutant (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0140524.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). It is hard to imagine how a single-gene mutation affects expression of genes functioning in five cuticle pathways. In the model plant Arabidopsis, mutation in wax regulator <italic>SHN</italic> of the AP2/EREBP family altered property of both wax and cutin and expression of genes in multiple pathways [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. We measured expression of five known wax regulator genes, but none of them changed significantly (<xref rid="pone.0140524.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). Accordingly, one possibility would be that <italic>W3</italic> encodes a wax regulator that orchestrates transcription of the biosynthetic and transporter genes and those acting at the upstream of &#x3B2;-diketone pathway. This may explain the mutant effect on other wax species, such as wax esters, C<sub>33</sub> alkane, C<sub>22</sub>, C<sub>26</sub> and C<sub>28</sub> alcohol, and aldehydes (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>). An alternative and less likely scenario would be that <italic>W3</italic> targets on the initial step of diketone biosynthesis and the expression of these 20 genes are regulated by substrate-mediated feed-forward loops or secondary responses as discussed earlier. In either case, our results suggest a possibility that &#x3B2;-diketone pathway in Triticeae uses some <italic>CER1</italic> and <italic>CER3</italic> homologs for decarbonylation and <italic>MAH1</italic> homologs for hydroxylation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec012">
        <title>&#x3B2;-Diketones and Glaucousness</title>
        <p>Cuticular waxes from the upper parts of adult Triticeae plants can be divided into two types according to their major constituents: primary alcohol-rich and &#x3B2;-diketone-rich wax. The diploid wheat <italic>T</italic>. <italic>monococcum</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>urartu</italic> belong to the former and polyploid wheat <italic>T</italic>. <italic>turgidum</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>timopheevii</italic> to the latter type [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Analyses of NG mutants of barley [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and wheat [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] indicated that &#x3B2;-diketones play an important role in glaucousness development. Wax profiling of the wheat wax gene NILs identified three types of waxes from the flag leaf sheaths: &#x3B2;-diketone-rich wax from the glaucous NILs carrying <italic>W1w2</italic>, <italic>w1W2</italic> or <italic>W1W2</italic>, alkane-rich wax from the nonglaucous NIL <italic>w1w2</italic>, and alcohol-rich wax from the nonglaucous NILs carrying the wax inhibitor <italic>Iw1</italic> or <italic>Iw2</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In BW, &#x3B2;-diketone and hydroxy-&#x3B2;-diketones account for 63% of the total wax load. In the <italic>w3</italic> mutant, &#x3B2;-diketones reduced ~100-fold. At the same time, wax crystal tubes were almost invisible in the flag-leaf sheath (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4B</xref>). This confirms the role of &#x3B2;-diketones in glaucousness determination.</p>
        <p>Next to &#x3B2;-diketones, alkanes, mainly C<sub>29</sub> and C<sub>31</sub> homologues, constitute the second major wax component, accounting for 34% of the total wax in BW. Although only significant net change was found in C<sub>33</sub> alkane (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>), proportion of the whole alkanes was increased to 90% due to depletion of the &#x3B2;-diketones. Significant differences were also observed between BW and <italic>w3</italic> mutant in aldehydes, primary alcohols, and wax esters, but they had very low abundance, less than 3% of total wax in BW, suggesting that they are less likely to contribute to the mutant phenotype.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec013">
        <title>&#x3B2;-Diketones and Abiotic Stress</title>
        <p>Early physiological studies in cereal crops showed that glaucousness increased grain yield by &gt;7% in barley [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] and wheat [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0140524.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. More recent experiments performed in Mexico, where no rainfall was received during the growing cycle, showed glaucousness significantly contributed to grain yield even in irrigated condition [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p>
        <p>Our recent research using the <italic>W1</italic>, <italic>W2</italic>, <italic>Iw1</italic> and <italic>Iw2</italic> NILs indicated that glaucousness significantly reduced cuticle permeability expressed as water loss and chlorophyll efflux. Difference in cuticle permeability was also found among the glaucous NILs, which differed in the hydroxy-&#x3B2;-diketones, and suggested a role of these hydroxy isoforms in drought tolerance [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In the present research, we showed that the <italic>w3</italic> mutation impairs the biosynthesis of &#x3B2;-diketone and further deplete the hydroxy forms. At the same time, the <italic>w3</italic> mutation significantly increased water loss and chlorophyll leaching (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>). In the spike, <italic>w3</italic> mutant showed even faster water loss than the <italic>w1w2</italic> double recessive plant (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>). One explanation is that the <italic>w3</italic> mutant lost 99% of &#x3B2;-diketones (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref>), but they reduced 92% in the <italic>w1w2</italic> NIL [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In addition to cuticular waxes, cutin proper plays an even greater role in protecting the non-controllable water loss as recently demonstrated in Arabidopsis [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] and barley [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. In the <italic>w3</italic> mutant, three of the five cutin genes assayed showed ~1.5-fold down-regulation (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0140524.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). Transmission electron microscopic inspection of cutin organization in BW and <italic>w3</italic> mutant may provide more insights into the effect of the <italic>w3</italic> mutation on cutin foundation organization.</p>
        <p>Another important function of glaucousness is to reflect extra irradiation [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In this respect, &#x3B2;-diketones greatly contribute to heat tolerance. The glaucousness can reduced the photosynthetic temperature by up to 0.7&#xB0;C in the drought-stressed field [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. We observed that well-watered <italic>w3</italic> mutant plants died prematurely in the later spring seasons of 2010 and 2011 in a temperature poorly-controlled greenhouse room (<xref rid="pone.0140524.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1C</xref>). This did not occur in the fall and winter seasons, suggesting that loss of &#x3B2;-diketones in <italic>w3</italic> mutant increased its susceptibility to the high temperature. Preliminary result from field experiment in 2014 showed that <italic>w3</italic> mutation significantly reduced 1000-kernel weight (Wanlong Li and Karl Glover, unpublished data). Detailed physiological experiments need to be conducted using growth chambers with well-controlled temperatures and relative humidity to shed light on how the <italic>w3</italic> mutation affects the thermal characteristics of adult wheat plants.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec014">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="sec015">
        <title>Plant Materials and Growing Conditions</title>
        <p>Transgenic plant #056 was generated in BW by bombardment transformation of RNAi construct pVGS193 (Bi C, Trick HN, Gill BS and Li W, unpublished), which was developed using pANDA, a Gateway-based RNAi vector [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Other plant materials are listed in <xref rid="pone.0140524.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref> with their accession numbers, wax genotypes, wax phenotypes and sources of seeds. The crosses were made by manual emasculation and pollination. All the plants were grown in 4&#x201D;x4&#x201D; pots containing Sunshine<sup>&#xAE;</sup> potting mix #3 (Sun Gro Horticulture, Agawam, MA, USA) supplemented with Multicote<sup>&#xAE;</sup>8 Controlled-Release Fertilizer (Haifa, Altamonte, FL, USA) in a greenhouse. Temperature in the greenhouse was set as 22&#xB0; at day and 17&#xB0; at night, and day length was 16 h.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec016">
        <title>Markers Genotyping and Linkage Mapping</title>
        <p>Genomic DNA was isolated following the procedure described by [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was conducted in 10 &#x3BC;l containing ~40 ng genomic DNA, 250 &#x3BC;M dNTPs, 200 nM primers, 0.5 unit of Taq polymerase, and 1&#xD7; Green Go-Taq Reaction Buffer (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) and implemented on 9700 dual thermocyclers (ABI), which were programmed as 94&#xB0;C for 5 min, then 40 cycles of 94&#xB0;C 20 s, 55&#x2013;60&#xB0;C 30 s and 72&#xB0;C 1 min 20 s, and finally 7 min at 72&#xB0;C. The PCR products were separated by 1.5% agarose or 6% polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis.</p>
        <p>We used MAPMAKER3.0 [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] for determining the order of marker and gene loci and the Kosambi mapping function for converting the recombination into genetic distance in terms of centi-Morgan (cM) [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. An LOD score of 3.0 is applied to all marker loci.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec017">
        <title>Microscopy</title>
        <p>For stoma counting and aperture observations, both sides of flag leaf sheaths were coated with 10% cellulose acetate dissolved in acetone using a paint brush. Air-dried for 5 min, the cellulose film was carefully peeled and the imprinted slides were observed under a light microscope at a magnification of 10x20. The fresh cuticle samples of flag leaf sheaths were sputtered with gold powder using the CrC-150 Sputtering System and inspected using a Hitachi S-3400N SEM (Hitachi, Tokyo, Japan).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec018">
        <title>Cuticle Trait Measurements</title>
        <p>At Feekes&#x2019; stage 10.5.1 (F10.5.1) when wheat plants flower, flag leaf sheathes were detached and immersed in 30 ml 80% ethanol in a 50-ml falcon tube. The capped tube was agitated at 50 rpm on an orbital shaker. A 150-&#x3BC;l aliquot was removed at a two-hour time interval for measuring the absorbance at 648 nm and 664 nm on Synergy 2 Multi-Mode Microplate Reader (Biotek, Winooski, VT, USA). The sample was returned to the same tube after measurement. Six replicates of extraction were conducted each from an individual of the same line. Two measurements were performed for each extraction and their values were averaged for subsequent calculation. The sheaths were also subjected to air-drying at room temperature with 45% relative humidity. Their weight was measured at a one-hour time interval for 12 consecutive hours to evaluate the water loss rate using an AB54-S/FACT analytical balance (Mettler Toledo, Columbus, OH, USA) with an accuracy of &#xB1;0. 0001 g.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec019">
        <title>Wax Extraction and Metabolite Analysis</title>
        <p>One flag leaf sheath was detached at stage F10.5.1 and immersed in 10 ml HPLC-grade chloroform containing 2 &#x3BC;g tetracosane as an internal reference, which is not present in plant wax, and gently agitated for 1 min, the tissue was rinsed in another tube containing 5 ml chloroform. Two extracts were merged and purified by filtration with Iso-Disc PTFE-13-2 filter (Sigma, St Louis, MO, USA). For each line, five biological replicates were extracted separately. Purified wax extract was dried under a nitrogen stream. Wax silylation, gas chromatography&#x2013;mass spectrometry (GC-MS) profiling, and substance identification were performed at the W.M. Keck Metabolomics Research Laboratory of Iowa State University (Ames, IA, USA) on a fee-for-service basis. In brief, the dried wax extract was dissolved in 100 &#x3BC;l of BSTFA+TCMS (N,O-Bis(trimethylsilyl)trifluoroacetamide with 1% trimethylchlorosilane) and derivatized at 80&#xB0;C for 30 minutes. The solution is dried under a stream of nitrogen and the residue is reconstituted in 50 &#x3BC;l chloroform and subjected to GC-MS analysis. GC-MS analysis was performed with an Agilent 6890 GC interfaced to a 5973 mass spectrometer. The HP-5ms column (30 m x 0.25 mm i.d. coated with a 0.25 &#x3BC;m film, Agilent Technologies) was used, and temperature gradient was programmed from 150 to 320&#xB0;C at 5&#xB0;C/min with helium flow rate at 1.0 ml/min. Operating parameters for MS were set to 70 eV of ionization voltage and 280&#xB0;C of interface temperature.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec020">
        <title>Quantitative RT-PCR</title>
        <p>Of the 72 quantitative RT-PCR (qPCR) primer pairs used, 64 were adopted from Zhang et al [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] and eight pairs from Kosma et al. [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] together with their gene name designations. At stage F9.0 when the flag leaf is fully emerged from the whorl and flag leaf sheath is rapidly elongating, the flag leaf sheath was collected and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and used for RNA isolation using Trizol reagent (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Waltham, MA, USA) following the manufacturer&#x2019;s instruction. Four biological replicates were used. After evaluating RNA integrity in agarose gel and quantification with Nanodrop ND-1000 (Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA), 1 &#x3BC;g total RNA was used for reverse transcription using QuantiTect Reverse Transcription Kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA, USA). Approximately 5 ng cDNA was used as template for qPCR, which was performed on ABI 7900HT High-Throughput Real-Time Thermocycler (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc.) using the iTaq&#x2122; SYBR<sup>&#xAE;</sup> Green Supermix with ROX (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). Two technical replicates were included for each biological replicate. Melt curve analysis was conducted to determine the amplified specificity of PCR products. <italic>TaRPII36</italic> was used as the internal reference [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] and relative transcript abundance in the RNA samples was quantified using the 2<sup>-&#x394;&#x394;Ct</sup> method as described by [<xref rid="pone.0140524.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec021">
        <title>Data Analysis and Statistics</title>
        <p>Wax load, components, chlorophyll efflux, water loss, and wax gene transcription were measured from four or more biological replicates. The means, standard deviations and <italic>P</italic> values were estimated using Microsoft<sup>&#xAE;</sup> Excel functions. Student&#x2019;s t-tests were performed to evaluate statistical significance of the differences between BW and the NG mutant. Pearson's chi-squared test was calculated for the deviation of F<sub>2</sub> segregation from the expected ratios. The cut-off for statistical significance was set to <italic>P</italic>-value &#x2264; 0.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec022">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0140524.s001">
        <label>S1 Fig</label>
        <caption>
          <title>PCR screening of transgenes in the nonglaucous F<sub>2</sub> segregants.</title>
          <p>The upper band (arrow) was detected using a primer pair targeting on <italic>gus-nos</italic> junction <monospace>(5&#x2019;- CATGAAGATGCGGACTTACG-3&#x2019; and 5&#x2019;- GCGCGCTATATTTTGTTTTC-3&#x2019;)</monospace>. The lower band (arrow) was detected using a primer pair targeting on <italic>Ubq-bar</italic> junction <monospace>(5&#x2019;- GAAGTCCAGCTGCCAGAAAC-3&#x2019; and 5&#x2019;- GCACCATCGTCAACCACTAC-3&#x2019;)</monospace>. The designation of plant lines are indicated above the picture. BW, Bobwhite; NG1, nonglaucous mutant line 1; NG2, nonglaucous mutant line 2; CS, Chinese Spring. NG1, the female parent of the F<sub>2</sub> population, carries the bar and RNAi transgene; NG2 is negative for either of them. BW and CS are the negative controls.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0140524.s001.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0140524.s002">
        <label>S1 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Genotyping of Bobwhite and w3 mutant line NG2 with SSR markers located in distal end of wheat chromosome arms</title>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0140524.s002.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0140524.s003">
        <label>S2 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Expression of wax genes in the w3 mutant against BW.</title>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0140524.s003.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0140524.s004">
        <label>S3 Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>A list of plant materials used.</title>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0140524.s004.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Drs. Bikram S. Gill (Kansas State University, Manhattan, KS, USA) and Koichiro Tsunewaki (Fukui Prefectural University, Fukui, Japan) for providing seeds.</p>
    </ack>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>BW</term>
          <def>
            <p>Bobwhite</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CS</term>
          <def>
            <p>Chinese Spring</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CS-TDIC 2B</term>
          <def>
            <p>Chinese Spring-<italic>T</italic>. <italic>turgidum</italic> subsp. <italic>dicoccoides</italic> 2B substitution line</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>&#x3B2;-D</term>
          <def>
            <p>&#x3B2;-diketone</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CER</term>
          <def>
            <p>ECERIFERUM</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>FAE</term>
          <def>
            <p>fatty acyl elongase</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>FAR</term>
          <def>
            <p>fatty acyl-CoA reductase</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>GL</term>
          <def>
            <p>GLOSSY</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>KCR</term>
          <def>
            <p>&#x3B2;-keto acyl-CoA reductase</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>KCS</term>
          <def>
            <p>&#x3B2;-keto acyl-CoA synthases</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>LTP</term>
          <def>
            <p>lipid transfer protein</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>MAH</term>
          <def>
            <p>midchain alkane hydroxylase</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>NIL</term>
          <def>
            <p>near isogenic line</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>NG</term>
          <def>
            <p>nonglaucous</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>NT</term>
          <def>
            <p>nulli-tetrasomic</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>OH-&#x3B2;</term>
          <def>
            <p>hydroxy &#x3B2;-diketone</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>qPCR</term>
          <def>
            <p>quantitative real time PCR</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>SEM</term>
          <def>
            <p>scanning electron microscope</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>VLCFA</term>
          <def>
            <p>very long chain fatty acid</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>WSD</term>
          <def>
            <p>Wax Ester Synthase/Acyl-Coenzyme A:Diacylglycerol Acyltransferase</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref001">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wynne Griffiths</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effects of stress on plant cuticular waxes</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>171</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>469</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>99</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2006.01826.x">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2006.01826.x</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 16866954?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16866954</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref002">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kolattukudy</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biopolyester membranes of plants: cutin and suberin</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>208</volume>(<issue>4447</issue>):<fpage>990</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1000</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17779010?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17779010</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref003">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nawrath</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>The biopolymers cutin and suberin</article-title>. <source>Arabidopsis Book</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>e0021</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1199/tab.0021">10.1199/tab.0021</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3243382.<?supplied-pmid 22303198?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22303198</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref004">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beisson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ohlrogge</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Building lipid barriers: biosynthesis of cutin and suberin</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>236</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>46</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tplants.2008.03.003">10.1016/j.tplants.2008.03.003</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18440267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18440267</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref005">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kolattukudy</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Plant waxes</article-title>. <source>Lipids</source>. <year>1970</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>259</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref006">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vioque</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kolattukudy</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Resolution and purification of an aldehyde-generating and an alcohol-generating fatty acyl-coa reductase from pea leaves (Pisum sativum L.)</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>340</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>64</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>72</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 9126278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9126278</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref007">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hepworth</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jetter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>CER4 encodes an alcohol-forming fatty acyl-coenzyme A reductase involved in cuticular wax production in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>142</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>866</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>77</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.106.086785">10.1104/pp.106.086785</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC1630741.<?supplied-pmid 16980563?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16980563</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref008">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Identification of the wax ester synthase/acyl-coenzyme A: diacylglycerol acyltransferase WSD1 required for stem wax ester biosynthesis in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>148</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>107</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.108.123471">10.1104/pp.108.123471</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2528131.<?supplied-pmid 18621978?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18621978</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref009">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cheesbrough</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kolattukudy</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Alkane biosynthesis by decarbonylation of aldehydes catalyzed by a particulate preparation from <italic>Pisum sativum</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>6613</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 6593720?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6593720</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref010">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>The cytochrome P450 enzyme CYP96A15 is the midchain alkane hydroxylase responsible for formation of secondary alcohols and ketones in stem cuticular wax of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>145</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>653</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>67</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.107.107300">10.1104/pp.107.107300</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2048791.<?supplied-pmid 17905869?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17905869</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref011">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Domergue</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pascal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jetter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Renne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Reconstitution of plant alkane biosynthesis in yeast demonstrates that Arabidopsis ECERIFERUM1 and ECERIFERUM3 are core components of a very-long-chain alkane synthesis complex</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>3106</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>18</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.112.099796">10.1105/tpc.112.099796</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3426135.<?supplied-pmid 22773744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22773744</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref012">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jetter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sealing plant surfaces: cuticular wax formation by epidermal cells</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>683</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>707</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.arplant.59.103006.093219">10.1146/annurev.arplant.59.103006.093219</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 18251711?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18251711</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref013">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joub&#xE8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Arabidopsis cuticular waxes: advances in synthesis, export and regulation</article-title>. <source>Prog Lipid Res</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>110</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>29</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.plipres.2012.10.002">10.1016/j.plipres.2012.10.002</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 23103356?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23103356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref014">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Recent advances in cuticular wax biosynthesis and its regulation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>246</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/mp/sss159">10.1093/mp/sss159</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 23253604?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23253604</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref015">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pyee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kolattukudy</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>The GLOSSY1 locus of maize and an epidermis-specific cDNA from Kleinia odora define a class of receptor-like proteins required for the normal accumulation of cuticular waxes</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>1091</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>100</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 9112770?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9112770</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref016">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sturaro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hartings</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmelzer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salamini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Motto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cloning and characterization of GLOSSY1, a maize gene involved in cuticle membrane and wax production</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>478</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>89</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.104.058164">10.1104/pp.104.058164</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC1104201.<?supplied-pmid 15849306?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15849306</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref017">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tacke</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Korfhage</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maddaloni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Motto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lanzini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Transposon tagging of the maize Glossy2 locus with the transposable element En/Spm</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>907</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>17</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8580961?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8580961</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref018">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schnable</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>. <article-title>DLA-based strategies for cloning insertion mutants: cloning the gl4 locus of maize using Mu transposon tagged alleles</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>183</volume>:<fpage>1215</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1534/genetics.109.108936">10.1534/genetics.109.108936</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 19805815?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19805815</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref019">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>D Yandeau-Nelson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meeley</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nikolau</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schnable</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Characterization of two GL8 paralogs reveals that the 3-ketoacyl reductase component of fatty acid elongase is essential for maize (Zea mays L.) development</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>844</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15941398?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15941398</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref020">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delledonne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nikolau</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schnable</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sequence analysis of the cloned glossy8 gene of maize suggests that it may code for a beta-ketoacyl reductase required for the biosynthesis of cuticular waxes</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>501</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 9342868?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9342868</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref021">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ranathunge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Wax Crystal-Sparse Leaf1 encodes a beta-ketoacyl CoA synthase involved in biosynthesis of cuticular waxes on rice leaf</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>228</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>675</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00425-008-0770-9">10.1007/s00425-008-0770-9</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 18574592?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18574592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref022">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moose</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sisco</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Glossy15, an APETALA2-like gene from maize that regulates leaf epidermal cell identity</article-title>. <source>Genes &amp; Development</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>3018</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8957002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref023">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Javelle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vernoud</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Depege-Fargeix</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arnould</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oursel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Domergue</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Overexpression of the epidermis-specific homeodomain-leucine zipper IV transcription factor Outer Cell Layer1 in maize identifies target genes involved in lipid metabolism and cuticle biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>154</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>86</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.109.150540">10.1104/pp.109.150540</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2938141.<?supplied-pmid 20605912?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20605912</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref024">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Javelle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klein-Cosson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vernoud</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boltz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Timmermans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Genome-wide characterization of the HD-ZIP IV transcription factor family in maize: preferential expression in the epidermis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>790</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>803</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.111.182147">10.1104/pp.111.182147</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3192571.<?supplied-pmid 21825105?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21825105</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref025">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tulloch</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Composition of leaf surface waxes of <italic>Triticum</italic> species: Variation with age and tissue</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>. <year>1973</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>2225</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref026">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effects of inhibitors on the biosynthesis of the long chain lipids with even carbon numbers in barley spike epicuticular wax</article-title>. <source>Carlsberg Res Commun</source>. <year>1978</year>; <volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>15</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref027">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>von Wettstein-Knowles</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genetic control of &#x3B2;-diketone and hydroxyl-&#x3B2;-diketone synthesis in epicuticular waxes of barley</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>. <year>1972</year>; <volume>06</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24477953</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref028">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adamski</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mugford</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>The Inhibitor of wax 1 locus (Iw1) prevents formation of beta- and OH-beta-diketones in wheat cuticular waxes and maps to a sub-cM interval on chromosome arm 2BS</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>989</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1002</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/tpj.12185">10.1111/tpj.12185</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 23551421?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23551421</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref029">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leverington-Waite</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snape</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mapping of a gene (Vir) for a non-glaucous, viridescent phenotype in bread wheat derived from Triticum dicoccoides, and its association with yield variation</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>159</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>333</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10681-007-9514-3">10.1007/s10681-007-9514-3</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref030">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tsunewaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ebana</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Production of near-isogenic lines of common wheat for glaucousness and genetic basis of this trait clarified by their use</article-title>. <source>Genes Genet Syst</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref031">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Comparative high-resolution mapping of the wax inhibitors Iw1 and Iw2 in hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e84691</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0084691">10.1371/journal.pone.0084691</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3871689.<?supplied-pmid 24376835?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24376835</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref032">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deynze</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Autrique</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Merlino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Molecular mapping of wheat. Homoeologous group 2</article-title>. <source>Genome</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>516</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 18470185?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18470185</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref033">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular mapping of a dominant non-glaucousness gene from synthetic hexaploid wheat (Triticum aestivum L.)</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>155</volume>(<issue>1&#x2013;2</issue>):<fpage>71</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10681-006-9302-5">10.1007/s10681-006-9302-5</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref034">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Comparative fine mapping of the Wax 1 (W1) locus in hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>128</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1595</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>603</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00122-015-2534-9">10.1007/s00122-015-2534-9</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 25957646?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25957646</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref035">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dubcovsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Echaide</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giancola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rousset</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joppa</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Seed-storage-protein loci in RFLP maps of diploid, tetraploid, and hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>1169</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref036">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fine mapping and metabolic and physiological characterization of the glume glaucousness inhibitor locus Iw3 derived from wild wheat</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>127</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>831</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00122-014-2260-8">10.1007/s00122-014-2260-8</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 24522723?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24522723</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref037">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genetic interactions underlying the biosynthesis and inhibition of beta-diketones in wheat and their impact on glaucousness and cuticle permeability</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e54129</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0054129">10.1371/journal.pone.0054129</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3547958.<?supplied-pmid 23349804?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23349804</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref038">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Simple RNAi vectors for stable and transient suppression of gene function in rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>490</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15111724?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15111724</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref039">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dubcovsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>, editors. <source>Catalogue of gene symbols for wheat 11th International Wheat Genetics Symposium</source>; <year>2008</year>; <publisher-loc>Brisbane Qld Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sidney University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref040">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Yield, water relations, gas exchange, and surface reflectances of near-isogenic wheat lines differing in glaucousness</article-title>. <source>Crop Sci</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>318</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref041">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rawson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Glaucousness in wheat: Its development and effect on water-use efficiency, gas exchange and photosynthetic tissue temperature</article-title>. <source>Aust J Plant Physiol</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>465</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>73</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref042">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Monneveux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonz&#xE1;lez-Santoyo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pe&#xF1;a</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zapata</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Relationships between grain yield, flag leaf morphology, carbon isotope discrimination and ash content in irrigated wheat</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agronomy and Crop Science</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>190</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>395</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>401</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1439-037X.2004.00116.x">10.1111/j.1439-037X.2004.00116.x</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref043">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Izanloo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuchel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chalmers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tester</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Identification of novel quantitative trait loci for days to ear emergence and flag leaf glaucousness in a bread wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) population adapted to southern Australian conditions</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>124</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>697</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>711</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00122-011-1740-3">10.1007/s00122-011-1740-3</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 22045047?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22045047</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref044">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lundqvist</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lundqvist</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mutagen specificity in barley for 1580 eceriferum mutants localized to 79 loci</article-title>. <source>Hereditas</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref045">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Franckowiak</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lundqvist</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>. <article-title>Descriptions of barley genetic stocks for 2011</article-title>. <source>Barley Genetics Newsletter</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>202</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref046">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slade</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fuerstenberg</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loeffler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steine</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Facciotti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>A reverse genetic, nontransgenic approach to wheat crop improvement by TILLING</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>81</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15580263?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15580263</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref047">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Uauy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paraiso</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colasuonno</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berardi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A modified TILLING approach to detect induced mutations in tetraploid and hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage><comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-9-115">10.1186/1471-2229-9-115</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 19712486?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19712486</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref048">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Polyploidy and genome evolution in plants</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pbi.2005.01.001">10.1016/j.pbi.2005.01.001</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 15752992?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15752992</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref049">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Neelakandan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Recent progress in the understanding of tissue culture-induced genome level changes in plants and potential applications</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Rep</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>597</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>620</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00299-011-1202-z">10.1007/s00299-011-1202-z</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 22179259?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22179259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref050">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Plant waxes</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Waxes: chemistry, molecular biology and functions</source>. <publisher-loc>Dundee, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Oily Press</publisher-name>; <year>1995</year> p. <fpage>175</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref051">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>von Wettstein-Knowles</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Biosynthesis and genetics of waxes</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Waxes: chemistry, molecular biology and functions</source>. <publisher-loc>Dundee, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Oily Press</publisher-name>
<year>1995</year> p. <fpage>91</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>129</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref052">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>von Wettstein-Knowles</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Plant Waxes</chapter-title><source>eLS</source>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year> p. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref053">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aharoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dixit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jetter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thoenes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Arkel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The SHINE clade of AP2 domain transcription factors activates wax biosynthesis, alters cuticle properties, and confers drought tolerance when overexpressed in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2463</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.104.022897">10.1105/tpc.104.022897</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC520946.<?supplied-pmid 15319479?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15319479</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref054">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Broun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poindexter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>CZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riechmann</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>. <article-title>WIN1, a transcriptional activator of epidermal wax accumulation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>4706</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0305574101">10.1073/pnas.0305574101</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC384811.<?supplied-pmid 15070782?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15070782</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref055">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kannangara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Branigan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Penfield</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mouille</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>The transcription factor WIN1/SHN1 regulates Cutin biosynthesis in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1278</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>94</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.106.047076">10.1105/tpc.106.047076</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC1913754.<?supplied-pmid 17449808?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17449808</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref056">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tulloch</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Leaf wax of <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic></article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>. <year>1973</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>2217</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref057">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tulloch</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>. <article-title>A survey of epicuticular waxes among genera of Triticeae. 2. Chemistry</article-title>. <source>Can J Bot</source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>2602</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref058">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Netting</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chemical genetics of &#x3B2;-diketone formation in wheat</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>. <year>1968</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>2089</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref059">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Figini</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>. <article-title>Epicuticular waxes of glaucous and nonglaucous durum wheat lines</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>1986</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>429</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref060">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baenziger</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wesenberg</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sicher</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effects of genes controlling barley leaf and sheath waxes on agronomic performance in irrigated and dryland environments</article-title>. <source>Crop Sci</source>. <year>1983</year>; <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>116</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref061">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>L&#xFC;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Des Marais</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Arabidopsis ECERIFERUM9 involvement in cuticle formation and maintenance of plant water status</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>159</volume>:<fpage>930</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.112.198697">10.1104/pp.112.198697</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 22635115?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22635115</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref062">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Komatsuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nawrath</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pourkheirandish</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tagiri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>An ATP-binding cassette subfamily G full transporter is essential for the retention of leaf water in both wild barley and rice</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>30</issue>):<fpage>12354</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1108444108">10.1073/pnas.1108444108</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3145689.<?supplied-pmid 21737747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21737747</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref063">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Recurrent deletions of puroindoline genes at the grain hardness locus in four independent lineages of polyploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant physiology</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>146</volume>:<fpage>200</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 18024553?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18024553</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref064">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abrahamson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lincoln</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>MAPMAKER: an interactive computer package for constructing primary genetic linkage maps of experimental and natural populations</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>174</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>81</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 3692487?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3692487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref065">
        <label>65</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kosambi</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>. <article-title>The estimation of map distances from recombination values</article-title>. <source>Ann Eugen</source>. <year>1944</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>172</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref066">
        <label>66</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kosma</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nemacheck</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jenks</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Changes in properties of wheat leaf cuticle during interactions with Hessian fly</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>43</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04229.x">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04229.x</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 20409001?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20409001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0140524.ref067">
        <label>67</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>402</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/meth.2001.1262">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 11846609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
