<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?>
  <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>
  <?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?>
  <?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?>
  <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?>
  <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4740857</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep20309</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep20309</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Precocious leaf senescence by functional loss of <italic>PROTEIN S-ACYL TRANSFERASE14</italic> involves the NPR1-dependent salicylic acid signaling</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Xin-Ying</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Jia-Gang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Song</surname>
            <given-names>Shi-Jian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Qun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kang</surname>
            <given-names>Hui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Yan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Sha</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">b</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>State Key Laboratory of Crop Biology, College of Life Sciences, Shandong Agricultural University</institution>, Tai&#x2019;an, 271018, <country>China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1">
          <label>a</label>
          <email>yzhang@sdau.edu.cn</email>
        </corresp>
        <corresp id="c2">
          <label>b</label>
          <email>shali@sdau.edu.cn</email>
        </corresp>
        <fn id="n1">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>04</day>
        <month>02</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <elocation-id>20309</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>09</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2016, Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-holder>
        <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <!--author-paid-->
          <license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x2019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We report here that Arabidopsis PROTEIN S-ACYL TRANSFERASE14 (PAT14), through its palmitate transferase activity, acts at the vacuolar trafficking route to repress salicylic acid (SA) signaling, thus mediating age-dependent but not carbon starvation-induced leaf senescence. Functional loss of <italic>PAT14</italic> resulted in precocious leaf senescence and its transcriptomic analysis revealed that senescence was dependent on salicylic acid. Overexpressing <italic>PAT14</italic> suppressed the expression of SA responsive genes. Introducing the SA deficient mutants, <italic>npr1-5</italic> and <italic>NahG</italic>, but not other hormonal mutants, completely suppressed the precocious leaf senescence of <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function, further supporting the epistatic relation between <italic>PAT14</italic> and the SA pathway. By confocal fluorescence microscopy, we showed that PAT14 is localized at the Golgi, the <italic>trans</italic>-Golg network/early endosome, and prevacuolar compartments, indicating its roles through vacuolar trafficking. By reporter analysis and real time PCRs, we showed that the expression <italic>PAT14</italic>, unlike most of the senescence associated genes, is not developmentally regulated, suggesting post-transcriptional regulatory mechanisms on its functionality. We further showed that the maize and wheat homologs of <italic>PAT14</italic> fully rescued the precocious leaf senescence of <italic>pat14-2</italic>, demonstrating that the role of <italic>PAT14</italic> in suppressing SA signaling during age-dependent leaf senescence is evolutionarily conserved between dicots and monocots.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Leaf senescence is a developmentally programmed dismantling process by which leaf longevity is limited while nutrients are remobilized into seeds as in annual plants or other storage tissues as in perennial plants<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. Leaf senescence starts with an initiation stage during which photosynthetic activities gradually decrease, followed by a degenerative phase when cellular components disassemble while macromolecules degrade, and culminated with a terminal phase when cells die<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. The onset and progression of senescence affects fitness, yield, and grain quality<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>, thus is under complex control.</p>
    <p>Senescence integrates developmental and environmental cues into age-dependent changes in which phytohormones play key roles<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>. Salicylic acid (SA), jasmonates (JA), and ethylene promote leaf senescence<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref> while auxin and cytokinins (CK) delay leaf senescence<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>. Common execution events downstream of hormone-controlled leaf senescence were postulated<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref> whereas different hormones may influence leaf senescence by changing the age status of plants, by transcriptional changes, or by integrating environmental responses<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>.</p>
    <p>Senescence associates with tremendous transcriptional changes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>. Therefore, transcription factors, such as NAC, MYB, bZIP, and WRKY, were most noted for their roles in senescence, whose activities resulted in transcriptional changes of senescence associated genes (<italic>SAG</italic>s)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. Despite the extensive studies on transcriptional controls of senescence, important knowledge gaps remain. Senescence by itself is a process of nutrient remobilization from senescing organs to newly initiated leaves or developing grains<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. Components involved in the dismantling of source tissues and nutrient remobilization to sink tissues are yet to be identified.</p>
    <p>We report here the identification of a novel component positively regulating leaf longevity by suppressing SA biosynthesis and signaling. PROTEIN S-ACYL TRANSFERASE14 (PAT14) is one of the 24 Arabidopsis PATs catalyzing the addition of a long chain fatty acid, usually C16 palmitate, to Cys residues thus changing the subcellular localization, activity, or turnover of substrate proteins<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>. Functional loss of <italic>PAT14</italic> resulted in precocious leaf senescence that was suppressed by the expression of the wild-type PAT14 but not by its catalytically inactive mutant, suggesting that PAT14 functions through substrate palmitoylation. Transcriptomic studies revealed that <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function accelerated natural senescence without affecting developmental program. In addition, genes involved in SA biosynthesis or signaling were significantly over-represented in the group of upregulated transcripts comparing <italic>pat14</italic> to wild type. Indeed, reducing SA levels or disrupting SA signaling suppressed precocious leaf senescence of <italic>pat14</italic> during development, suggesting that <italic>PAT14</italic> negatively regulates SA biosynthesis or signaling. We further showed that the positive role of PAT14 in leaf longevity is evolutionarily conserved because its maize and wheat homologs fully rescued the mutant phenotype. By using fluorescence probes and pharmacological treatments, we showed that PAT14s are localized at endomembrane compartments along vacuolar trafficking route, namely, the Golgi, the <italic>trans</italic>-Golgi network/early endosome (TGN/EE), and prevacuolar compartments/multivesicular bodies (PVC/MVB), suggesting a key role of vacuole-mediated processes in leaf senescence.</p>
    <sec disp-level="1">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Functional loss of <italic>PAT14</italic> results in precocious leaf senescence</title>
        <p>Using a reverse genetic approach, we isolated and characterized two T-DNA insertion alleles for <italic>PAT14</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1A</xref>), named as <italic>pat14-1</italic> (SALK_026159) and <italic>pat14-2</italic> (GABI-KAT153A10). Transcript analysis showed that both alleles were null mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1B</xref>). The <italic>pat14</italic> mutants did not differ from wild type during vegetative growth under long day (LD) condition (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 1</xref>). However, at approximately 4 weeks after germination (4WAG) when both wild type and mutants bolted, <italic>pat14</italic> mutants showed rapid leaf chlorosis while wild type stayed green for a more extended period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 1</xref>). A green fluorescence protein (GFP) translational fusion of the <italic>PAT14</italic> genomic fragment driven by its own promoter (<italic>PAT14g-GFP</italic>) fully restored the mutant phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Because <italic>pat14-2</italic> is a GABI-KAT insertion line that allows easier selection on plates, it was used for further analyses unless noted otherwise.</p>
        <p>We carried out detailed analyses comparing <italic>pat14-2</italic> with wild type on several physiological parameters reflecting the senescing status of plants, such as ion leakage and chlorophyll contents<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>. The 4<sup>th</sup> pair of true leaves was chosen for these analyses because of their close association with developmental programs as reported by others<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>. Ion leakage slightly increased from 3-week-old (W3) to 5-week-old (W5) in wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1D</xref>). By contrast, ion leakage of <italic>pat14-2</italic> leaves increased substantially over time, especially from W4, after plants have bolted and was significantly higher than wild type at W4 and W5 but not before (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1D</xref>). Consistent with the fact that wild type stayed green for an extended period after floral transition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Supplemental Fig. 1</xref>), contents of chlorophyll did not decrease from W3 to W5 in wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1E</xref>). In stark contrast, chlorophyll levels began to drop from W4 in <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1E</xref>). Accumulation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) and occurrence of cell death were increased in <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
        <p>Both the onset and progression of senescence were earlier in <italic>pat14-2</italic> than in wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1F</xref>). To exclude the possibility that early senescence of <italic>pat14-2</italic> was due to altered developmental programs such as early flowering<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>, we analyzed flowering time based on the number of days to bolting and the number of rosette leaves upon floral transition because the two parameters faithfully reflect the developmental timing. No significant difference was detected between <italic>pat14-2</italic> and wild type either on the days to bolting or the number of rosette leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1G,H</xref>). Because <italic>pat14</italic> mutants showed accelerated leaf senescence under LD condition only after floral transition, we wondered whether its function was induced by floral induction or just age related. To distinguish the two possibilities, we grew wild type, <italic>pat14-2</italic>, and <italic>PAT14g-GFP;pat14-2</italic> plants under short day (SD) condition. Two-month-old <italic>pat14-2</italic> showed accelerated leaf chlorosis than wild type or <italic>PAT14g-GFP;pat14-2</italic> plants under SD condition when phase transition was yet to occur (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 3</xref>). These results indicated that functional loss of <italic>PAT14</italic> specifically promoted senescence in an age-dependent manner without affecting the developmental timing.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Functional loss of <italic>PAT14</italic> causes transcriptomic changes indicative of precocious leaf senescence</title>
        <p>To provide more evidence that <italic>PAT14</italic> functional loss resulted in early senescence and also to gain insights into the molecular basis of the underlying mechanisms, we performed microarray analyses to compare transcriptomic changes during natural senescence versus by <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function. RNAs were extracted from the 4<sup>th</sup> pair of leaves from wild type (WT) or <italic>pat14-2</italic> (MU) at 21 DAG (W3) or 35 DAG (W5). Because flowering occurs around W4 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 1</xref>), the 4<sup>th</sup> pair of true leaves from W3 and W5 represent sink and source tissues respectively, two opposite statuses regarding nutrient remobilization<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. In addition, qPCRs showed that several senescence associated genes, such as <italic>SAG13</italic> and <italic>SAG21</italic>, were hardly detectable at W3 but high in W5 in wild-type leaves (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 4</xref>), indicating a significant difference between the two time-points regarding natural senescence.</p>
        <p>Arabidopsis Affymetrix GeneChip arrays were probed. In WT3, MU3, or WT5 samples, approximately 60% of the 24000 genes on the GeneChip showed detectable expression. Because <italic>pat14-2</italic> was significantly senesced at 5 WAG, which could have an overall impact on transcriptomes due to cellular dismantling, we did not include MU5 in the experiment. Using a twofold change of transcript abundance as the cutoff, 1458 or 2396 genes were upregulated or downregulated in WT5 v.s. in WT3 while only 623 or 487 genes were upregulated or downregulated in MU3 v.s. in WT3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Dataset 1</xref>). Because transcriptomic changes in WT5 v.s in WT3 encompass both senescence-related and developmentally regulated transcriptional changes while mutations at <italic>PAT14</italic> did not affect developmental programs, it was not a surprise that a much larger number of genes were transcriptionally changed in WT5 v.s. WT3 than in MU3 v.s. WT3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2A</xref>). A large percentage of genes showing different transcript abundance by <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function (MU3 v.s. WT3) fall into natural senescence-induced and developmentally regulated transcriptomic changes in wild type (WT5 v.s. WT3) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2A</xref> and Dataset S1). We verified results from microarray analyses by using qPCRs to test transcript abundance of representative genes whose upregulation or downregulation reflects senescence status (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S4</xref>). Few Gene Ontology (GO) terms were over-represented among genes downregulated by <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function (MU3 v.s. WT3), within which most related to organ morphogenesis and development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Dataset 1</xref>). By contrast, GO terms including defense response, cell death, hormone signaling, transport, intracellular trafficking, ROS signaling, responses to stresses, and cellular signaling are over-represented among genes upregulated by <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Dataset 2</xref>). Among hormone-related functional categories, genes involved in SA biosynthesis and signaling were over-represented (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2B</xref>), indicating enhanced SA pathways by <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title><italic>PAT14</italic> suppresses age-dependent leaf senescence by repressing SA biosynthesis and signaling</title>
        <p>The over-representation of SA biosynthetic and signaling pathways in <italic>pat14-2</italic> before the onset of senescence suggested that precocious leaf senescence during development by <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function depended on SA biosynthesis and signaling. To test this hypothesis, we crossed <italic>npr1-5</italic>, a null mutant of <italic>NONEXPRESSER OF PATHOGEN RELATED GENE1</italic> (<italic>NPR1</italic>) impaired in most SA responses<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>, and <italic>NahG</italic> that encodes an SA hydroxylase to deplete endogenous SA<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>, with <italic>pat14-2</italic>. Under green house conditions, the SA deficient mutant <italic>npr1-5</italic> and <italic>NahG</italic> were undistinguishable from wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3</xref>). However, introducing <italic>npr1-5</italic> or <italic>NahG</italic> into <italic>pat14-2</italic> substantially delayed the precocious leaf senescence either at 4 WAG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3A</xref>) or 5 WAG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3B</xref>), suggesting that precocious leaf senescence of <italic>pat14-2</italic> relies on intact SA biosynthesis and signaling.</p>
        <p>To determine the senescence status of these mutants molecularly, we analyzed the expression of genes encoding senescence associated proteins and SA signaling proteins at 4 WAG and 5 WAG by quantitative real time PCRs. Consistent with its precocious leaf senescence, the <italic>pat14-2</italic> plants showed significantly higher expression of <italic>SAG</italic>s, such as <italic>SAG12, SAG13</italic> and <italic>SAG21</italic>, which were suppressed by the introduced <italic>npr1-5</italic> or <italic>NahG</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Genes responding to SA signaling, such as <italic>PAD4, PR1</italic>, and <italic>SID2</italic>, were significantly induced by <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Similar to that of <italic>SAG</italic>s, their induction in <italic>pat14-2</italic> was also suppressed by <italic>npr1-5</italic> or <italic>NahG</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4B</xref>). These results provided molecular evidence supporting the SA-dependent effect of <italic>PAT14</italic> on age-dependent leaf senescence.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Overexpressing <italic>PAT14</italic> suppresses SA biosynthesis and signaling but is not sufficient to extend leaf longevity</title>
        <p>To further verify that <italic>PAT14</italic> suppressed SA biosynthesis and signaling and to determine whether PAT14 gain-of-function had an opposite phenotype to that of mutants, i.e. extended leaf longevity, we generated a construct overexpressing <italic>PAT14</italic> using the <italic>Pro</italic><sub><italic>35S</italic></sub> promoter. More than twenty <italic>Pro</italic><sub><italic>35S</italic></sub>:<italic>PAT14</italic> transgenic lines were obtained. However, no substantial difference was observed at the onset and progress of natural senescence between wild type and <italic>PAT14</italic> overexpression lines (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 5</xref>), suggesting that at least <italic>PAT14</italic> overexpression alone could not extend leaf longevity under regular growth conditions. However, we found that overexpressing <italic>PAT14</italic> significantly suppressed the expression of SA biosynthetic and signaling genes, such as <italic>PR1, PAD4</italic>, and <italic>SID2</italic>, at an extent correlating with the transcriptional levels of <italic>PAT14</italic> in different transgenic lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref>). These results indicated that PAT14 indeed suppresses SA biosynthesis and signaling, which alone, however, is not sufficient to extend leaf longevity during age-dependent leaf senescence.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Precocious leaf senescence of <italic>pat14-2</italic> was not dependent on other hormonal signaling</title>
        <p>Other hormones also play promoting or inhibiting roles in leaf senescence; the former including ethylene and JA while the latter including auxin and CK<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>. To determine whether <italic>PAT14</italic> controls leaf senescence also through other hormonal pathways, we introduced corresponding mutants or transgenic overexpression lines into <italic>pat14-2</italic> for their potential genetic interactions. Introducing <italic>ein2-1</italic>, an <italic>ETHYLENE-INSENSITIVE2</italic> (<italic>EIN2</italic>) mutant insensitive to ethylene<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, or <italic>coi1-2</italic>, a <italic>CORONATINE-INSENSITIVE1</italic> (<italic>COI1</italic>) mutant insensitive to JA<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref> did not suppress the precocious leaf senescence of <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Fig. 6A,B</xref>). On the other hand, overexpressing <italic>YUC6</italic> to increase auxin biosynthesis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref> or introducing <italic>gin2-1</italic> in which cytokinin signaling was enhanced<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref> did not suppress the precocious leaf senescence of <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Fig. 6A,B</xref>). These results indicated that <italic>PAT14</italic> regulates age-dependent leaf longevity specifically through the SA pathway.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title><italic>PAT14</italic> is not involved in carbon starvation-induced leaf senescence</title>
        <p>Because leaf senescence is also induced by carbon starvation, we wondered whether <italic>PAT14</italic> was involved in carbon starvation-induced leaf senescence. To test that, we placed wild-type and <italic>pat14-2</italic> plants of 3 WAG in the dark for a certain period. Wild-type and <italic>pat14-2</italic> plants growing under LD condition in nutrient rich soil were comparable at 3 WAG (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 6</xref>). Dark treatment for 3 days (D3 - C) resulted in leaf chlorosis comparably between <italic>pat14-2</italic> and wild type (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 6</xref>). No substantial differences regarding leaf chlorosis were observed for <italic>PAT14</italic> overexpressing lines or the SA deficient mutant <italic>npr1-5</italic> or <italic>NahG</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 6</xref>). The result suggested that PAT14 is not involved in leaf senescence induced by carbon starvation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title><italic>PAT14</italic> is constitutively expressed</title>
        <p>Because senescence associates with tremendous transcriptional changes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>, the specific phenotype of <italic>pat14</italic> mutants prompted us to test whether <italic>PAT14</italic> was transcriptionally regulated during senescence. We generated a <italic>PAT14g-GUS</italic> that fully restored leaf longevity when introduced in <italic>pat14-2</italic> as did <italic>PAT14g-GFP</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>). By histochemical analysis of <italic>PAT14g-GUS</italic>;<italic>pat14-2</italic>, we found that <italic>PAT14</italic> was constitutively expressed in various tissues, such as seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Fig. 7A</xref>), leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Fig. 7B</xref>), lateral and primary roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Fig. 7C,D</xref>), stems (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Fig. 7G</xref>), and inflorescences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Fig. 7H</xref>). Expression of <italic>PAT14</italic> was also detected in specific cell types, such as guard cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Fig. 7E</xref>). <italic>PAT14</italic> was expressed most prominently in vascular tissues, specifically in the phloem (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Fig. 7F,G</xref>).</p>
        <p>We tested whether <italic>PAT14</italic> was regulated by senescence during development, by carbon starvation, or by SA through analyzing GUS signals of <italic>PAT14g-GUS;pat14-2</italic> transgenic plants of different ages, upon dark treatment, or upon treatment with an SA agonist, benzo (1,2,3) thiadizaole-7-carbothioic acid (BTH), respectively. GUS signals were not detectably different in leaves from W3 to W5 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 7</xref>). Indeed, no senescence-associated transcriptional change was identified for <italic>PAT14</italic> based on microarray studies of natural senescence<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>. Histochemical analysis on <italic>PAT14g-GUS;pat14-2</italic> seedlings did not show signal enhancement upon dark treatment or by BTH treatment (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 7</xref>). To confirm the constitutive expression of <italic>PAT14</italic>, we performed quantitative real-time PCRs (qPCRs) on wild-type plants at W3, W4, and W5. Results obtained by qPCRs were consistent with the GUS data such that no significant difference was detected during development for the expression of <italic>PAT14</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 7</xref>), in contrast with many senescence-associated genes (<italic>SAG</italic>s) whose expression increased significantly when plants age (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 4</xref>). Because <italic>PAT14</italic> is constitutively expressed, its roles in leaf senescence during plants aging could be regulated at the post-transcriptional level such as by post-translational modifications.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>PAT14 is localized at the Golgi, the <italic>trans</italic>-Golgi network/early endosome, and prevacuolar compartment</title>
        <p>PATs are multi-span transmembrane proteins whose subcellular localization plays a key role in their functional specificity<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>. The <italic>PAT14g-GFP</italic> transgene fully restored leaf longevity after floral transition in <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1C</xref>), indicating that the GFP fusion did not disturb its function and thus would reflect its native subcellular localization. In <italic>PAT14g-GFP</italic>;<italic>pat14-2</italic>, GFP signals were present in vesicular structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Fig. 8A</xref>). To determine the identity of these vesicles, we applied fluorescence colabeling by using the lipophilic fluorescence dye FM4-64 that is internalized to several endomembrane compartments through endocytic trafficking<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>. FM4-64 was detected at punctuate vesicles as early as 5 min after pulse labeling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Fig. 8A</xref>), which represent the <italic>trans</italic>-Golgi network/early endosome (TGN/EE). A portion of GFP signals overlapped with the internalized FM4-64 signals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Fig. 8A</xref>), indicating its localization at the TGN/EE. We then applied the fungal toxin Brefeldin A (BFA) at the presence of cycloheximide (CHX). BFA interferes with post-Golgi trafficking, and thus results in membrane aggregates called the &#x201C;BFA compartments&#x201D; that contain TGN/EE cores and surrounding Golgi stacks<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref> while CHX inhibits <italic>de novo</italic> protein synthesis. BFA treatment caused FM4-64-positive signals to form so-called BFA compartments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Fig. 8A</xref>). Under such treatment, a subset of PAT14-positive signals colocalized with FM4-64 in the &#x201C;core&#x201D; of BFA compartments while another subset surrounded the FM4-64-core (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Fig. 8A</xref>), indicating that PAT14 is present both at the Golgi and the TGN/EE. Beside its localization at the Golgi and the TGN/EE, a portion of GFP signals was insensitive to even prolonged BFA treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Fig. 8A</xref>). To determine the identity of these vesicles, we applied Wortmannin (WM) after BFA treatment. WM is mostly noted for its inhibitory role on vacuolar fusion of prevacuolar compartments/multivesicular bodies (PVC/MVB) and thus resulted in ring-shaped vesicles of PVC/MVB identity<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. Application of WM resulted in the fusion of the remaining punctate vesicles into ring-shaped compartments unassociated with the BFA-induced aggregates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Fig. 8A</xref>), indicative of PVC/MVB. Thus, we concluded that PAT14 is localized at several endomembrane compartments including the Golgi, the TGN/EE, and the PVC/MVB.</p>
        <p>To gain more evidence for the subcellular localization of PAT14, we also introduced <italic>PAT14g-GFP</italic> into various transgenic lines expressing RFP-fused subcellular markers, including the Golgi marker WAVE22R<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>, the TGN/EE marker HAP13-RFP<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref> and the PVC/MVB marker VSR2-RFP<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>. Partial co-localization of PAT14 with all three markers again demonstrated its localization at these endomembrane compartments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Fig. 8B</xref>).</p>
        <p>Compared to the fully restored leaf longevity of <italic>pat14-2</italic> by <italic>PAT14g-GFP</italic>, a mutation that disrupted the key catalytic Cys within its DHHC motif (PAT14gC157S) thus potentially abolished its palmitoylation activity<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref> failed to rescue the early senescence phenotype of <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1C</xref>). This result suggested that the function of PAT14 during senescence was due to palmitoylation of its substrate(s). However, it was also possible that the point mutation altered its subcellular localization or stability, resulting in the failure of complementation. To exclude this possibility, we used confocal fluorescence microscopy to image the localization of <italic>PAT14gC157S-GFP</italic>;<italic>pat14-2</italic> by the same fluorescence colabeling and pharmacological treatments. Our results clearly showed that the C157S point-mutation did not interfere with the native localization or stability of PAT14 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 8</xref>). Thus, we concluded that PAT14 promotes leaf longevity through its substrate palmitoylation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Evolutionarily conserved function of PAT14</title>
        <p>PATs are encoded by multi-gene families in all eukaryotes, including plants. PATs from a given plant species are quite diverse in sequences outside their catalytic DHHC motifs, implying neo-functionalization during evolution after genome duplications<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref>. However, proteins sharing high sequence identity with PAT14 were identified from various plant species ranging from the unicellular Chlamydomonas to various higher plant species (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 9</xref>), suggesting that functional diversification of <italic>PAT14</italic> occurred early and was retained during evolution.</p>
        <p>To determine whether the function of <italic>PAT14</italic> was conserved during evolution, we isolated PAT14 homologs from two major crops, maize and wheat, for which proper timing of leaf senescence is crucial for increasing seed yield. Sequence alignment showed that the central hydrophilic loop containing the DHHC motif of PAT14s are highly conserved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9">Fig. 9A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 9</xref>), presumably important for the recognition of specific cargos. In addition to the catalytic domain, both the C-terminal cytoplasmic tails and the N-terminal hydrophilic region are also highly conserved among PAT14 homologs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9">Fig. 9A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 9</xref>), suggesting key regulatory function by non-catalytic domains. We thus generated constructs containing <italic>Pro</italic><sub><italic>35S</italic></sub>-driven GFP-fused ZmPAT14 and TaPAT14 and introduced the transgenes into <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9">Fig. 9B</xref>). The fact that the expression of <italic>ZmPAT14-GFP</italic> and <italic>TaPAT14-GFP</italic> fully restored leaf longevity of <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9">Fig. 9C,D</xref>) indicates functional conservation.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="1">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>We show in this study the identification and characterization of a novel component involved in leaf senescence during development. The <italic>pat14</italic> mutants behaved similarly to wild type until floral induction when accelerated cell death occurred in the mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Figs 1 and 2</xref>). However, the function of <italic>PAT14</italic> during leaf senescence is not dependent on floral induction because <italic>pat14</italic> under SD condition also senesced earlier before floral transition was yet to occur (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 3</xref>). In addition, functional loss of <italic>PAT14</italic> did not alter the sensitivity toward artificial carbon starvation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 6</xref>), indicating its specific involvement in age-dependent processes.</p>
      <p>Transcriptomic analysis revealed the possible involvement of SA signaling in <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>). This was confirmed molecularly by analyzing the relative expression of SA responsive genes, which showed elevated expression in <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 4</xref>) but reduced expression by <italic>PAT14</italic> overexpression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref>). The SA-dependency was further verified by genetic analysis. Introducing <italic>NahG</italic> to reduce SA accumulation suppressed the leaf chlorosis and elevated expression of <italic>SAG</italic>s of <italic>pat14-2</italic> during development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figs 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">4</xref>). Although it was shown that some SA-inducible genes were not dependent on NPR1 and thus suggesting other components downstream of SA<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>, we showed genetically and molecularly that <italic>npr1-5</italic> fully suppressed the precocious leaf senescence of <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figs 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">4</xref>), suggesting that <italic>PAT14</italic> mediates SA signaling in an NPR1-dependent way. On the other hand, manipulating other hormonal signals by using corresponding mutants or overexpressors did not affect the precocious leaf senescence of <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Fig. 6</xref>). Previous transcriptomic and genetic studies suggested that SA signaling is specifically involved in natural but not starvation-induced leaf senescence<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>. Thus, the NPR1-dependent SA signaling explains well the phenotype of <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function.</p>
      <p>Unlike most genes involved in senescence, <italic>PAT14</italic> is not transcriptionally induced during leaf senescence or by carbon starvation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 7</xref>). In fact, although overexpressing <italic>PAT14</italic> did suppress the expression of SA responsive genes, it did not significantly promote leaf longevity by itself (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 5</xref>). Both results indicate that PAT14 is regulated post-transcriptionally during senescence. However, despite its constitutive expression, <italic>PAT14</italic> is prominent in the phloem of root and aerial parts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Fig. 7</xref>). Precocious cell death in <italic>pat14-2</italic> leaves occurred mostly proximal to leaf veins rather than spreading all over the old leaves (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 2</xref>). Phloem plays a key role in nutrient remobilization from sources to sinks. Because nutrient remobilization is an important issue to be addressed during floral induction and carbon starvation when developing seeds or newly initiated leaves become new sinks, the failure to satisfy the need due to <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function may be partially compensated by the accelerated cell death of old leaves. This is certainly an interesting possibility to be investigated in the future. In addition, SA migrates from the site of infection to other parts of plants through phloem, which is critical for systemic acquired resistance during pathogen infection<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>. Considering the enhanced SA signaling on site in <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function and the enriched expression of <italic>PAT14</italic> in phloem, the intriguing possibility that <italic>PAT14</italic> facilitates long-distance SA transport is certainly worthy of future exploration.</p>
      <p>The C157S mutation potentially disrupting the catalytic activity of PAT14<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref> abolished its ability to rescue <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>), suggesting that substrate palmitoylation is responsible for the functionality of PAT14 during natural senescence. Currently, it is still a technical challenge to pinpoint substrates of a given PAT. A biotin switch isobaric tagging approach was developed, which theoretically can identify differentially palmitolyated proteins by comparing palmitoyl-proteomics of wild type and those of <italic>PAT</italic> mutants<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref>. However, a recent attempt using this approach to identify substrates of Arabidopsis TIP GROWTH DEFECTIVE 1/PAT24 (TIP1)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref> resulted in over a hundred proteins that are significantly under-palmitoylated by <italic>TIP1</italic> loss-of-function<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref>. Even if the substrates of TIP1 are among the pool, it will be an unfathomable task to pinpoint them.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, the localization of PAT14 will help to reveal the identity of its substrates. The localization of PAT14 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Fig. 8</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 8</xref>) indicates that it is involved in vacuolar trafficking. Earlier studies indicated that vacuolar trafficking may play a key role in chlorophyll degradation processes during senescence<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">42</xref>. Recently, several studies showed that disrupting molecular components critical for vacuolar trafficking resulted in precocious leaf senescence. Functional loss of <italic>AMSH1</italic> and <italic>VACUOLAR PROTEIN SORTING2.1</italic> (<italic>VPS2.1</italic>), encoding proteins regulating vacuolar trafficking, resulted in early senescence and hypersensitivity to artificial carbon starvation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>. Genetic interference of a few other genes encoding vacuolar trafficking regulators, such as VPS and Rab GTPases, also resulted in precocious leaf senescence<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">44</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">45</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref>. Indeed, microarray data indicated that vacuolar activities are among the most over-represented intracellular activities enhanced during natural senescence<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>. Thus, it is likely that PAT14 regulates the membrane association and activities of protein factors whose activity is important for vacuolar function specifically during senescence. Potential candidates are SNAREs, a large number of which are likely subjected to palmitoylation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref> and critical for the specificity of membrane fusion<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">47</xref>. Arabidopsis genome encodes a large number of SNAREs<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">47</xref> that are localized differentially at Golgi and post-Golgi compartments<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">48</xref>. Cytological, genetic, as well as phenotypic analyses of SNAREs will help reveal the factors responsible for PAT14-mediated leaf senescence.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="1">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Plant materials, growth conditions, and histochemical analyses</title>
        <p>The Arabidopsis T-DNA insertion lines, SALK_026159 (<italic>pat14-1</italic>) and GABI-KAT153A10 (<italic>pat14-2</italic>) were obtained from ABRC (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.Arabidopsis.org">http://www.Arabidopsis.org</ext-link>). <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Columbia-0 ecotype was used as the wild type. Arabidopsis plants were grown as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>. Stable transgenic plants were selected on half-strength MS supplemented with 30 &#x3BC;g/ml Basta salts or 7.5 mg/ml sulfadiazine (Sigma, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sigmaaldrich.com">http://www.sigmaaldrich.com</ext-link>). The allelic mutant <italic>pat14-2</italic> was used to generate double mutants with <italic>npr1-5, NahG, ein2-1, coi1-2, gin2-1</italic>, and <italic>YUC6</italic> overexpression lines by crosses. GUS histochemical analyses were performed as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>. DAB staining for H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and tryphan blue staining for cell death were performed as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>PCR, RT-PCR, and qPCR</title>
        <p>Mutants of <italic>PAT14</italic> were analyzed by genotyping PCR using the following primers: ZP1147/ZP1771 for <italic>PAT14</italic>, LB1/ZP1771 for <italic>pat14-1</italic>, ZP8/ZP1203 for <italic>pat14-2.</italic> For RT-PCR and quantitative real-time PCR analyses, total RNAs were extracted using the RNeasy Plant miniprep kit according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions (Qiagen). Reverse transcriptions were performed using Superscript<sup>TM</sup> III Reverse Transcriptase with on-column DNase-I treatment (Invitrogen). The following primer pairs were used in RT-PCRs to characterize mutants or complemented mutants: F1/R1 for endogenous <italic>PAT14</italic>, ZP1599/ZP1600 for exogenous <italic>PAT14</italic> or <italic>PAT14-C157S</italic>, ZP1506/ZP11 for <italic>ZmPAT14</italic>, and ZP1628/ZP2682 for <italic>TaPAT14</italic>. Arabidopsis <italic>ACTIN2</italic> was used as the internal control for RT-PCRs<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49">49</xref>. The qPCR analyses were performed as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>. Primers in qRT-PCR analyses are as followed: ZP1581/ZP1582 for <italic>SAG13</italic>, ZP3139/ZP3140 for <italic>SAG12</italic>, ZP1498/ZP1499 for <italic>SAG21</italic>, ZP2190/ZP2191 for <italic>PAD4</italic>, ZP2319/ZP2320 for <italic>SID2</italic>, ZP2304/ZP2305 for <italic>PDF1.2</italic>, and ZP1583/ZP1584 for <italic>PR1</italic>. Primers are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S1</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Plasmid construction</title>
        <p>All constructs were generated using the Gateway<sup>TM</sup> technology (Invitrogen). Entry vectors for the coding sequences of genes were generated in the pENTRY/SD/D-TOPO vector (Invitrogen). Primers for generating entry vectors containing corresponding coding sequences are as followed: ZP1399/ZP1400 for <italic>YUC6</italic>, ZP1506/ZP1509 for <italic>ZmPAT14</italic>, and ZP2681/ZP2682 for <italic>TaPAT14</italic>. The destination vector for <italic>Pro</italic><sub><italic>35S</italic></sub>:<italic>YUC6</italic> and <italic>Pro</italic><sub><italic>35S</italic></sub>:<italic>PAT14-GFP</italic> was described earlier<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">50</xref>. The entry vector for the <italic>PAT14</italic> genomic sequence together with the 1305 base pair sequence upstream of its start codon (<italic>PAT14g</italic>) was generated by using the primer pair ZP1262/ZP1263. A C157S mutation was generated by site-directed mutagenesis from the <italic>PAT14g</italic> entry vector. The destination vector for <italic>PAT14g-</italic>GFP and <italic>PAT14gC157S</italic>-GFP translational fusion constructs was described earlier<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>. The destination vector for the <italic>PAT14g</italic>-GUS translation fusion construct was obtained from ABRC<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51">51</xref>. The destination vector for constitutively expressing ZmPAT14- and TaPAT14-GFP was described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">50</xref>. Expression vectors were generated by LR reactions using LR Clonase (Invitrogen). Primers are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Table 1</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Quantification of Chlorophyll contents and ion leakage</title>
        <p>To measure the Chlorophyll contents and ion leakage, the 4<sup>th</sup> pair of rosette leaves from 21 DAG (week 3), 28 DAG (week 4) or 35 DAG (week 5) plants were used. Chlorophyll was extracted and measured as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>. For ionic leakage measurement, the leaf discs without the major veins were collected and infiltrated in 10 ml deionized water with vacuum till the leaf discs were immersed in the water. Conductivity of the solution was measured after gentle agitation at root temperature for 1 hr. Total ionic strength was measured after the solution was heated in 100&#x2009;&#xB0;C water bath for 10 min and cooled to root temperature. The leaked ions were represented as the percentage of the initial conductivity versus the total conductivity.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>Pharmacological treatment and confocal microscopy</title>
        <p>FM4-64 uptake, BFA treatments, and laser scanning confocal fluorescence imaging were performed as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref>. For the combined BFA and WM treatment, 4 DAG seedlings were first pulse-labeled with 4 &#x3BC;M FM4-64 for 5 min. After three times of washing, seedlings were incubated in 1/2 MS supplemented with 50 &#x3BC;M BFA for 50 min. Seedlings were then incubated in fresh 1/2 MS supplemented with 50 &#x3BC;M BFA and 33 &#x3BC;M WM for 1 hr before being examined. BTH dissolved in water (100 &#x3BC;M) was sprayed on 1-week-old seedlings (for GUS histochemical analysis) or 3-week-old plants (for qPCRs). Materials were collected at designated time points (12 hrs&#x2013;48 hrs) after spray for analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec disp-level="2">
        <title>DNA microarray and data analyses</title>
        <p>Three independently derived sets of wild-type (WT) or <italic>pat14-2</italic> (MU) plant materials either at W3 (WT3 or MU3) or at W5 (WT5 or MU5) were used for microarray analyses using the Affymetrix GeneChip&#xAE; Arabidopsis ATH1 Genome Array, which was performed by Shanghai Biotechnology Co., Ltd. (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebioservice.com">www.ebioservice.com</ext-link>). Total RNAs were extracted using TRIZOL Reagent (Life technologies) following the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions and RNA integrity was inspected by an Agilent Bioanalyzer 2100 (Agilent technologies). Qualified total RNA was further purified by RNeasy micro kit (QIAGEN) and RNase-Free DNase Set (QIAGEN). Total RNAs were amplified, labeled and purified by using GeneChip 3&#x2019;IVT Express Kit (Affymetrix) followed the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions to obtain biotin labeled cRNAs. Array hybridization and wash was performed using GeneChip&#xAE; Hybridization, Wash and Stain Kit (Affymetrix) in Hybridization Oven 645 (Affymetrix) and Fluidics Station 450 (Affymetrix) followed the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. Slides were scanned by GeneChip&#xAE; Scanner 3000 (Affymetrix) and Command Console Software 3.1 (Affymetrix) with default settings. Raw data were normalized by MAS 5.0 algorithm, Gene Spring Software 11.0 (Agilent technologies). GO classification of genes exhibiting at least twofold changes in transcript levels was conducted using AmiGO online tool (version 1.8) with default settings<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52">52</xref>. Analyses were based on May 24<sup>th</sup>, 2014 release of GO database. Gene IDs and their putative functions were assigned using TAIR as the database filter. The expected ratio indicates the percentage of genes of the designed GO term within all genes represented on the GeneChip array.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="1">
      <title>Additional Information</title>
      <p><bold>Accession Numbers</bold>: Sequence data from this article can be found in the GenBank databases under the following accession numbers: At3g60800 for PAT14, At5g25620Z for YUC6, At5g45900 for ATG7, At1g64280 for NPR1, At2g39940 for COI1, At4g29130 for GIN2, At2g29350 for SAG13, At5g45890 for SAG12, At4g02380 for SAG21, At3g52430 for PAD4, At1g74710 for SID2, At5g44420 for PDF1.2, and At2g14610 for PR1.</p>
      <p><bold>How to cite this article</bold>: Zhao, X.-Y. <italic>et al.</italic> Precocious leaf senescence by functional loss of <italic>PROTEIN S-ACYL TRANSFERASE14</italic> involves the NPR1-dependent salicylic acid signaling. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>6</bold>, 20309; doi: 10.1038/srep20309 (2016).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e28" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Information</title>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep20309-s1.pdf"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e31" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Dataset 1</title>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep20309-s2.xls"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="d33e34" content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Dataset 2</title>
        </caption>
        <media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep20309-s3.xls"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Drs. Chuan-You Li, Yvon Jaillais, Yu-Jin Hao and Zhao-Hui Chu for sharing published plant materials, Dr. Xian Sheng Zhang for access to microscopy facilities, and the ABRC for mutant seeds. This research was supported by Shandong Provincial Natural Science Foundation (ZR2014CM027 to S.L.), by a grant from Natural Science Foundation of China (31261160490 to Y.Z.), by Shandong Provincial Funds for Outstanding Young Scientists (to Y.Z.), by National Key Laboratory of Plant Molecular Genetics (to S.L.), and by the Tai-Shan Scholar program from Shandong Provincial Government.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="b1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>P. O.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Molecular genetics of leaf senescence in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>272</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>278</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12818661</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jibran</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Dijkwel</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Hormonal regulation of leaf senescence through integration of developmental and stress signals</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>547</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>561</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23504405</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><article-title>Senescence, ageing and death of the whole plant</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source><volume>197</volume>, <fpage>696</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>711</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23176101</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Himelblau</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Nutrients mobilized from leaves of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> during leaf senescence</article-title>. <source>J Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>158</volume>, <fpage>1317</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1323</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Convergence and divergence in gene expression profiles induced by leaf senescence and 27 senescence-promoting hormonal, pathological and environmental stress treatments</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>644</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>655</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21988545</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grbi&#x107;</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Bleecker</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Ethylene regulates the timing of leaf senescence in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>595</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>602</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fukushige</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Evidence supporting a role of jasmonic acid in Arabidopsis leaf senescence</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>128</volume>, <fpage>876</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>884</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11891244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sturre</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hille</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Dijkwel</surname><given-names>P. P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Arabidopsis onset of leaf death mutants identify a regulatory pathway controlling leaf senescence</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>51</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>63</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12366800</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Trifurcate feed-forward regulation of age-dependent cell death involving <italic>miR164</italic></article-title> In <source>Arabidopsis. Science</source>
<volume>323</volume>, <fpage>1053</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1057</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19229035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<article-title><italic>ETHYLENE-INSENSITIVE3</italic> is a senescence-associated gene that accelerates age-dependent leaf senescence by directly repressing <italic>miR164</italic> transcription in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>3311</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3328</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24064769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Salicylic acid has a role in regulating gene expression during leaf senescence</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>23</volume>, <fpage>677</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>685</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10972893</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Halitschke</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Salicylic acid 3-hydroxylase regulates <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> leaf longevity by mediating salicylic acid catabolism</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>110</volume>, <fpage>14807</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>14812</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23959884</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>P. O.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Auxin response factor 2 (ARF2) plays a major role in regulating auxin-mediated leaf longevity</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source><volume>61</volume>, <fpage>1419</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1430</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20164142</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Inhibition of leaf senescence by autoregulated production of cytokinin</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>270</volume>, <fpage>1986</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1988</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8592746</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title><italic>YUCCA6</italic> over-expression demonstrates auxin function in delaying leaf senescence in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source><volume>62</volume>, <fpage>3981</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3992</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21511905</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Breeze</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>High-resolution temporal profiling of transcripts during <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> leaf senescence reveals a distinct chronology of processes and regulation</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>23</volume>, <fpage>873</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>894</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21447789</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Buchanan-Wollaston</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Comparative transcriptome analysis reveals significant differences in gene expression and signalling pathways between developmental and dark/starvation-induced senescence in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>42</volume>, <fpage>567</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>585</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15860015</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Transcriptome of Arabidopsis leaf senescence</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>521</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>549</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van der Graaff</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Transcription analysis of Arabidopsis membrane transporters and hormone pathways during developmental and induced leaf senescence</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>141</volume>, <fpage>776</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>792</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16603661</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Balazadeh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riano-Pachon</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Mueller-Roeber</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Transcription factors regulating leaf senescence in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Biol (Stuttg)</source>
<volume>10</volume> Suppl 1, <fpage>63</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>75</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18721312</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baekkeskov</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Kanaani</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Palmitoylation cycles and regulation of protein function (Review)</article-title>. <source>Mol Membr Biol</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>42</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>54</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19169934</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Greaves</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Chamberlain</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>DHHC palmitoyl transferases: substrate interactions and (patho)physiology</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>245</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>253</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21388813</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hemsley</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Grierson</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Multiple roles for protein palmitoylation in plants</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>302</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18501662</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Overexpression of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> acyl-CoA binding protein ACBP3 promotes starvation-induced and age-dependent leaf senescence</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1463</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1482</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20442372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kachroo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Klessig</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The Arabidopsis <italic>ssi1</italic> mutation restores pathogenesis-related gene expression in <italic>npr1</italic> plants and renders defensin gene expression salicylic acid dependent</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>191</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>206</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9927638</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vernooij</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaffney</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Ryals</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Characterization of tobacco plants expressing a bacterial salicylate hydroxylase gene</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>959</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>968</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8555459</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>COS1: An Arabidopsis <italic>coronatine insensitive1</italic> suppressor essential for regulation of jasmonate-mediated plant defense and senescence</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>16</volume>, <fpage>1132</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1142</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15075400</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Role of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> glucose sensor HXK1 in nutrient, light, and hormonal signaling</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>300</volume>, <fpage>332</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>336</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12690200</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bolte</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>FM-dyes as experimental probes for dissecting vesicle trafficking in living plant cells</article-title>. <source>J Microsc</source><volume>214</volume>, <fpage>159</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>173</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15102063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>BFA-induced compartments from the Golgi apparatus and <italic>trans</italic>-Golgi network/early endosome are distinct in plant cells</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>60</volume>, <fpage>865</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>881</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19709389</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Identification of multivesicular bodies as prevacuolar compartments in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> BY-2 cells</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>16</volume>, <fpage>672</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>693</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14973159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Geldner</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Rapid, combinatorial analysis of membrane compartments in intact plants with a multicolor marker set</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source><volume>59</volume>, <fpage>169</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>178</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19309456</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>HAPLESS13, the Arabidopsis mu1 adaptin, is essential for protein sorting at the trans-Golgi network/early endosome</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>162</volume>, <fpage>1897</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1910</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23766365</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Katsiarimpa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>The deubiquitinating enzyme AMSH1 and the ESCRT-III subunit VPS2.1 are required for autophagic degradation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>25</volume>, <fpage>2236</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2252</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23800962</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hemsley</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Grierson</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The TIP GROWTH DEFECTIVE1 S-acyl transferase regulates plant cell growth in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>2554</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2563</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16100337</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L.-Z.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>PROTEIN S-ACYL TRANSFERASE10 is critical for development and salt tolerance in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1093</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1107</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23482856</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Batistic</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><article-title>Genomics and localization of the Arabidopsis DHHC-CRD <italic>S</italic>-acyltransferase protein family</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.1112.203968</pub-id> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kihara</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Igarashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Intracellular localization and tissue-specific distribution of human and yeast DHHC cysteine-rich domain-containing proteins</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1761</volume>, <fpage>474</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>483</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16647879</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Bouteau</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Crosstalk between intracellular and extracellular salicylic acid signaling events leading to long-distance spread of signals</article-title>. <source>Plant cell reports</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>1125</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1138</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23689257</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hannoush</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The chemical toolbox for monitoring protein fatty acylation and prenylation</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>498</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>506</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20559317</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b41">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hemsley</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weimar</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dupree</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Grierson</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A proteomic approach identifies many novel palmitoylated proteins in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>
<volume>197</volume>, <fpage>805</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>814</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23252521</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b42">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Matile</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hortensteiner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Chlorophyll Degradation</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>95</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012204</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b43">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Role of an <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Rab GTPase RabG3b in pathogen response and leaf senescence</article-title>. <source>J Plant Biol</source><volume>52</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>87</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b44">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Surpin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>The VTI family of SNARE proteins is necessary for plant viability and mediates different protein transport pathways</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>15</volume>, <fpage>2885</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2899</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14615598</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b45">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Qa-SNAREs localized to the <italic>trans</italic>-Golgi network regulate multiple transport pathways and extracellular disease resistance in plants</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>109</volume>, <fpage>1784</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1789</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22307646</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b46">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> VPS35, a retromer component, is required for vacuolar protein sorting and involved in plant growth and leaf senescence</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><volume>49</volume>, <fpage>142</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>156</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18222962</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b47">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bassham</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandizzi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Otegui</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Sanderfoot</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The secretory system of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Arabidopsis Book</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e0116</fpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22303241</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b48">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Systematic analysis of SNARE molecules in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>: dissection of the post-Golgi network in plant cells</article-title>. <source>Cell structure and function</source><volume>29</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>65</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15342965</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b49">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A distinct mechanism regulating a pollen-specific guanine nucleotide exchange factor for the small GTPase Rop in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>104</volume>, <fpage>18830</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>18835</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18000057</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b50">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inze</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Depicker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>GATEWAY vectors for <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated plant transformation</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>195</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11992820</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b51">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A gateway cloning vector set for high-throughput functional analysis of genes in planta</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>133</volume>, <fpage>462</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>469</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14555774</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b52">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Carbon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>AmiGO: online access to ontology and annotation data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume>, <fpage>288</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>289</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19033274</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p><bold>Author Contributions</bold> X.-Y.Z., J-G.W., S.-J.S., Q.W. and H.K. performed the experiments; S.L. initiated the project, conducted microarrays and analyzed transcriptomic data; S.L. and Y.Z. designed the experiments and wrote the article.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f1">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Functional loss of Arabidopsis <italic>PAT14</italic> resulted in early senescence.</title>
        <p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic illustration of the <italic>PAT14</italic> genomic locus and the two T-DNA insertion sites. Arrows indicate primer binding sites for RT-PCR analyses. (<bold>B</bold>) Transcript analysis of <italic>PAT14</italic> in wild type (WT), <italic>pat14-1, pat14-2, PAT14g-GFP</italic> in <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<italic>PAT14g-GFP;pat14-2</italic>) and <italic>PAT14gC157S -GFP</italic> in <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<italic>mPAT14g-GFP;pat14-2</italic>). <italic>ACT2, ACTIN2</italic>, was used as the internal control. (<bold>C</bold>) A representative plant at 40 days after germination (DAG) under long day (LD) condition from the corresponding genetic backgrounds shown in (<bold>B</bold>). (<bold>D,E</bold>) Electrolyte leakage (<bold>D</bold>) and relative chlorophyll contents (<bold>E</bold>) of wild type and <italic>pat14-2</italic> at W3, W4, and W5 were measured by using the 4<sup>th</sup> pair of true leaves. Results are given as means&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;standard deviation (SD), N&#x2009;=&#x2009;30. * and *** indicate significant difference (Students&#x2019; <italic>t</italic>-test, P&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05 or P&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001 respectively). (<bold>F</bold>) Onset and progression of leaf senescence in LD-grown wild type and <italic>pat14-2</italic>. Green bars indicate days from leaf emergence to visible yellowing at the leaf tip (onset) while yellow bars indicate the time period (days) it takes from the first visible yellowing at the leaf tip to the leaf petiole (progression). The 4<sup>th</sup> pair of true leaves was chosen for this measurement. Results shown are given as means&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD, N&#x2009;=&#x2009;30. (<bold>G,H</bold>) Number of rosette leaves at floral transition (<bold>G</bold>) and number of days to bolting (<bold>H</bold>). Data were collected from 30 LD-grown plants for each genetic background. Results are given as means&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;standard deviation (SD). No significant difference was detected (<italic>t</italic>-test, P&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;0.05).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep20309-f1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f2">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Functional loss of <italic>PAT14</italic> caused transcriptomic changes indicative of precocious leaf senescence.</title>
        <p>(<bold>A</bold>) Venn diagrams to illustrate the number of genes significantly upregulated or downregulated in wild type during development (WT5 v.s WT3) or by <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function (MU3-WT3). The groups only include genes that show at least twofold upregulation or downregulation in the relevant experiments. Detailed gene lists are included in Dataset S1. (<bold>B</bold>) Functional categories overrepresented in the 623 upregulated genes by <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function (MU3 v.s. WT3) according to GO Term analysis. All categories shown are significantly overrepresented (Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic>-test, P&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.01).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep20309-f2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f3">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Mutations at SA biosynthesis and signaling suppressed age-dependent precocious leaf senescence by <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function.</title>
        <p>(<bold>A,B</bold>) Representative images of wild type (WT), <italic>npr1-5, NahG, pat14-2, pat14-2 npr1-5</italic>, and <italic>pat14-2 NahG</italic> at 28 DAG (Week 4, A) or 35 DAG (Week 5, B).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep20309-f3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f4">
      <label>Figure 4</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Mutations at SA biosynthesis and signaling suppressed age-dependent precocious leaf senescence by <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function.</title>
        <p>(<bold>A,B</bold>) Relative transcript abundance of <italic>SAG</italic>s (<italic>SAG12, SAG13</italic> and <italic>SAG21</italic>) as well as SA responsive genes (<italic>PAD4, PR1</italic>, and <italic>SID2</italic>) in wild type, <italic>npr1-5, NahG, pat14-2, pat14-2 npr1-5</italic>, and <italic>pat14-2 NahG</italic> at week 4 (W4, <bold>A</bold>) or week 5 (W5, <bold>B</bold>) by qRT-PCRs. The 4<sup>th</sup> pair of true leaves was used for RNA extractions. Results are given as means&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD of one out of three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate significant difference from either of the other samples (<italic>t</italic>-test, P&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.01).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep20309-f4"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f5">
      <label>Figure 5</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Overexpression of <italic>PAT14</italic> suppressed the expression of SA biosynthetic and signaling genes.</title>
        <p>Relative transcript abundance of SA responsive genes (<italic>PAD4, SID2</italic>, and <italic>PR1</italic>), two <italic>SAG</italic>s (<italic>SAG13</italic> and <italic>SAG21</italic>), and <italic>PAT14</italic> in wild type and two lines of <italic>PAT14OX</italic> at week 3 by qRT-PCRs. The 4<sup>th</sup> pair of true leaves was used for RNA extractions. Results are given as means&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SEM, N&#x2009;=&#x2009;3. Means with different letters are significantly different (<italic>t</italic>-test, P&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.01).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep20309-f5"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f6">
      <label>Figure 6</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Disrupted ethylene or JA signaling as well as enhanced auxin or cytokinin signaling did not suppress the early senescence of <italic>PAT14</italic> loss-of-function.</title>
        <p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative images of plants from the given genotypes at 5 weeks after germination (Week 5). (<bold>B</bold>) Relative transcript abundance of SA responsive genes (<italic>PAD4</italic> and <italic>PR1</italic>) and senescence-associated genes (<italic>SAG13</italic> and <italic>SAG21</italic>) in given genotypes at week 5 by qRT-PCRs. The 4<sup>th</sup> pair of true leaves was used for RNA extraction. Results are given as means&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SEM, N&#x2009;=&#x2009;3. Means with different letters for each genetic background are significantly different (<italic>t</italic>-test, P&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.01).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep20309-f6"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f7">
      <label>Figure 7</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Expression of <italic>PAT14</italic> by histochemical analyses of <italic>PAT14g-</italic>GUS; <italic>pat14-2</italic> transgenic lines.</title>
        <p>(<bold>A&#x2013;H</bold>) GUS signals are detected in seedlings (<bold>A</bold>), leaves especially veins (<bold>B</bold>), root vascular tissues (<bold>C,D</bold>) and lateral root primordial (<bold>C</bold>), guard cells (<bold>E</bold>), phloem tissues in roots (<bold>F</bold>) and stems (<bold>G</bold>), inflorescence (<bold>H</bold>) and floral organ abscission zone (H arrow). In total, 26 individual transgenic lines were analyzed and representative expression patterns are shown. Bars&#x2009;=&#x2009;500&#x2009;&#x3BC;m for (<bold>A,B,E,H</bold>); 50&#x2009;&#x3BC;m for (<bold>C,D,F</bold>,<bold>G</bold>).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep20309-f7"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f8">
      <label>Figure 8</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Arabidopsis PAT14 is localized at the Golgi, the TGN/EE, and PVC/MVB.</title>
        <p>(<bold>A</bold>) Confocal fluorescence imaging of <italic>PAT14g-GFP</italic> in <italic>pat14-2</italic> (<italic>PAT14g-GFP;pat14-2</italic>) stained with FM4-64. Arrows indicate BFA compartments in which both FM4-64 and PAT14-positive TGN/EE accumulates in the center surrounded by PAT14-positive Golgi stacks. Arrowheads indicate ring-shaped PVC/MVB labeled by PAT14 upon wortmannin treatment. (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>PAT14g-GFP</italic> was introduced in transgenic plants expressing RFP-fused markers for Golgi (WAVE22R), TGN/EE (HAP13), and PVC/MVB (VSR2). Partial co-localization was observed for all combinations. Bars&#x2009;=&#x2009;7.5&#x2009;&#x3BC;m for (<bold>A</bold>); 5&#x2009;&#x3BC;m for (<bold>B</bold>).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep20309-f8"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f9">
      <label>Figure 9</label>
      <caption>
        <title><italic><bold>P</bold>AT14</italic> homologs from maize and wheat suppressed the precocious leaf senescence of pat14-2.</title>
        <p>(<bold>A</bold>) Sequence alignment of Arabidopsis PAT14 and its homologs from maize (ZmPAT14) and wheat (TaPAT14). Yellow residues are consensus residues while blue or green residues represent residues replaced with other residues of similar characteristics. Sequence alignment was performed with Vector NTI (Invitrogen). UNIPROT accession number for ZmPAT14 is CPOBY3 and for TaPAT14 is W5B4H0. (<bold>B</bold>) Transcript analysis of Zm<italic>PAT14</italic> or <italic>TaPAT14</italic> in <italic>pat14-2. ACT2</italic> was used as the internal control. (<bold>C</bold>) Representative complemented plants at reproductive stage corresponding to the genotypes showing in (<bold>B</bold>).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep20309-f9"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
